  <page>
    <title>Ankleshwar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>588265</id>
    <revision>
      <id>920363996</id>
      <parentid>919700145</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-09T09:07:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Reyk</username>
        <id>378651</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>missing word</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use Indian English|date=September 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2016}}
&lt;!-- See [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Indian cities]] for details --&gt;
'''Ankleshwar''', (sometimes written '''Anklesvar''')  is a city and a [[municipality]] in the [[Bharuch district]] of the state of [[Gujarat]], [[India]]. The city is located fourteen kilometres from [[Bharuch]].
AiA-Ankleshwar Industrial Association is the largest organisation in GiDC where over 2000 industries are registered. This Notified Area is also under the AiA board, and MCM is the controller in the Authority. Polluters are punished by AiA, which is resulting in lower levels of pollution.

== Economy ==
{{unreferenced section|date = May 2013}}
The town is known for its industrial township called [[Gujarat Industrial Development Corporation|GIDC]] (Gujarat Industrial Development Corporation). Ankleshwar has an office of the [[ONGC]] (Oil and Natural Gas Corporation Limited). Ankleshwar has over 1500 chemical plants, producing products such as pesticides, pharmaceuticals, chemicals and paints. GIDC has started organising Trade fair and Industrial expo occasionally to attract large number of industries all over from India. It also helps to get customers on large basis.

== Demographics ==
{{As of|2011}} India [[census]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.censusindia.net/results/town.php?stad=A&amp;state5=999|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040616075334/http://www.censusindia.net/results/town.php?stad=A&amp;state5=999|archivedate=16 June 2004|title= Census of India 2001: Data from the 2001 Census, including cities, villages and towns  (Provisional)|accessdate=1 November 2008|work= |publisher= Census Commission of India}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ankleshwar had a population of 140,839. Males constitute 53% of th population and females 47%. 13% of the population is under 6 years of age.

== Transport ==
'''Ankleshwar''' is connected by [[Indian National Highway 8]] ([[Mumbai]] to [[New Delhi]]) and by the Western Railway Division of [[Indian Railways]]. The railway division runs the [[broad gauge]] train services to [[Rajpipla]]. The 136-year-old (2018) [[Golden Bridge]] built in (1881) connects Ankleshwar to Bharuch across the [[Narmada River|Narmada]] on the station front while a new bridge connects the highway, the other bridge made by L&amp;T on the highway is now ready to use.

[[Ankleshwar railway station]] is centrally located at the intersection of NH8 &amp; Station Road.

Ankleshwar City Bus stand is located on Station Road (i.e. located in the City, the western section).

Development project of [[Ankleshwar Airport]] &amp; City Bus are in pipe line in last stage.

== Education ==
Ankleshwar is an educated city. It has an average literacy rate of 79%, higher than the national average of 74.04%; with 82.14% of the males and 65% of females literate.

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Articles containing potentially dated statements from 2001]]
[[Category:All articles containing potentially dated statements]]
[[Category:Cities and towns in Bharuch district]]
[[Category:Ankleshwar|Ankleshwar]]</text>
      <sha1>421qa4oa6bs5ia97wpkjyt46n1zgw8u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
