  <page>
    <title>Aperlae</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22769436</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932844456</id>
      <parentid>932844427</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-28T14:54:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cplakidas</username>
        <id>613068</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Populated places of the Byzantine Empire]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--{{Infobox_ancient_site
  |name =  
  |native_name =
  |alternate_name = 
  |image = 
  |alt = 
  |caption = 
  |map =
  |map_caption =
  |map_type = 
  |map_alt = 
  |latitude = 
  |longitude = 
  |map_size = 
  |location = 
  |region = 
  |coordinates = 
  |type = 
  |part_of = 
  |length = 
  |width = 
  |area = 
  |height = 
  |builder = 
  |material = 
  |built = 
  |abandoned = 
  |epochs = 
  |cultures = 
  |dependency_of = 
  |occupants = 
  |event = 
  |excavations = 
  |archaeologists = 
  |condition = 
  |ownership = 
  |management = 
  |public_access = 
  |website = 
  |notes = 
}}--&gt;
'''Aperlae''' or '''Aperlai''' ({{lang-grc|Ἄπερλαι|Aperlai}}) was a city on the southern coast of [[ancient Lycia]] and former bishopric. It did not play any significant role in history or politics, yet its lifespan of 1,300 years is worth note. Harsh terrain made it difficult to survive, but like other towns along the coast, it thrived on the production of [[Tyrian dye]].

== Location and name ==
The town's position is fixed by the ''[[Stadiasmus Maris Magni|Stadiasmus]]'' at 60 ''[[stadion (unit)|stadia]]'' west of Somena, and 64 stadia west of [[Andriace]]. Leake (''Asia Minor'', p.&amp;nbsp;188) supposes Somena to be the ''Simena'' of [[Pliny the Elder|Pliny]] (v. 27). Aperlae, which is written in the text of [[Claudius Ptolemy]] ''Aperrae'', and in [[Pliny the Elder|Pliny]] ''Apyrae'', is proved to be a genuine name by an inscription found by Cockerell, at the head of Hassar bay, with the ethnic name Ἀπερλειτων on it. But there are also coins of [[Gordian III]] with the ethnic name Ἀπερραιτων. The confusion between the &quot;l&quot; and the &quot;r&quot; in the name of a small place is nothing remarkable.

=== Geography ===
Aperlae is situated near a bay and had harsh conditions all around. The sea in this region was unreliable in a storm and the bay offered near no protection from weather. It was directly between the mountains and the coast, the city's fortifications didn't encompass the arable terraced part of the mountains. There were no reliable sources of fresh water, but numerous cisterns located around the town indicated a heavy reliance on rain water. Aperlae was near a faultline leading to the seaside district of Aperlae sinking due to slow slumping over time. The most defining feature of the Aperlae landscape was the vast amount of Murex snail shells. There were two distinct parts of town where they were dumped covering altogether 1,600 square meters (at an unknown depth until the Turkish government allows archeologists to dig), they were discovered in the mortar and concrete of the buildings of the city, and they were found in large quantities dumped into the ocean.

== History ==
Aperlae was founded sometime between the late 4th and early 3rd century BCE and sustained a long lifespan of about 1,300 years until the end of the 7th century AD.
 
With the start of the [[Muslim conquests]], security of the coast failed and Aperlae was abandoned due to the threat of pirate raids and Arab corsairs. Though with the evidence of some late repairs on a church suggest that there was possibly a small settlement of squatters or stragglers after it was left, Aperlae was never rebuilt and resettled.

== Economy ==
The economy was built around the production of [[Tyrian dye]], a deep and costly [[purple]] which is gleaned from the hypobroncial gland of the ''Murex trunculus'' (which has been reclassified as [[Hexaplex trunculus]]), said to have cost 20 times its weight in gold. Experiments conducted in 1909 concluded that it would take 12,000 snails to produce 1.4&amp;nbsp;grams or 0.05 oz. Three ceramic lined vats found in the sunken district are suggested to have been holding tanks for the live snails until there were enough to be processed. Evidence of the presence of other mollusks in these piles indicates that the Murex were collected using nets and not by hand.
 
Though there was a rudimentary harbor with a jetty but not a breakwater, it is evident from the opulence presented by the city that there were more than enough resources to make one if they wanted. The city boasted four churches, a great number of tombstones and good fortifications which indicate an affluence of that time.

== Ecclesiastical history ==
Since it was in the [[Roman province]] of Lycia, the [[bishopric]] of Aperlae was a [[suffragan]] of the [[metropolitan see]] of [[Myra]], the province's capital, and was among the most important of the suffragan sees, being mentioned in fifth place in the ''[[Notitiae Episcopatuum]]'' of Pseudo-Epiphanius, composed under [[Byzantine Emperor]] [[Heraclius]] in about 640.&lt;ref&gt;Heinrich Gelzer, [https://archive.org/stream/abhandlungenbay06klasgoog#page/n578/mode/1up ''Ungedruckte und ungenügend veröffentlichte Texte der Notitiae episcopatuum''], in: Abhandlungen der philosophisch-historische classe der bayerische Akademie der Wissenschaften, 1901, p. 539, nº 258.&lt;/ref&gt; No name of any of its [[bishop]]s was identified by [[Le Quien]] in his ''Oriens christianus in quatuor Patriarchatus digestus''.

=== Titular see ===
No longer a residential bishopric, Aperlae is today listed by the [[Catholic Church]] as a [[titular see]],&lt;ref&gt;''Annuario Pontificio 2013'' (Libreria Editrice Vaticana 2013 {{ISBN|978-88-209-9070-1}}), p. 835&lt;/ref&gt; as the diocese was nominally restored in 1933, the curiate Italian name version being '''Aperle'''.

It is vacant since decades, having had only the following incumbents, both of the lowest (episcopal) rank :
* Ferdinando Baldelli (1959.07.22 – 1963.07.20), President of [[Caritas Internationalis]] (1951 – 1962)
* Felicissimus Alphonse Raeymaeckers, [[Capuchin Franciscans]] (O.F.M. Cap.) (1963.08.05 – 1967.03.12) as Auxiliary Bishop of [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Lahore|Lahore]] (1963.08.05 – 1966) and next [[Coadjutor Bishop]] of Lahore (1966 – 1967.03.12), later succeeding as Bishop (12 March 1967 Succeeded - 10 July 1975 Resigned)

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Works cited ==
* {{SmithDGRG|title=Aperlae}}
* Carter, R.S.. &quot;The Submerged Seaport of Aperlae.&quot; ''International Journal of Nautical Archeology'' '''7'''(1978): 177-85. Print.
* Hohlfelder, Robert L.; Vann, Robert L. &quot;Cabotage at Aperlae in Ancient Lycia.&quot; ''International Journal of Nautical Archeology'' '''29'''(2000): 126-135. Print.
* Hohlfelder, Robert L.; Vann, Robert L. &quot;Uncovering the Maritime Secrets of Aperlae, a Coastal Settlement of Ancient Lycia.&quot; ''Near Eastern Archeology'' '''61'''(1998): 26-37. Print.

==External links==
* [http://www.gcatholic.org/dioceses/former/t0154.htm GigaCatholic with titular incumbent biography links]

{{coord|36.1586|N|29.7836|E|source:dewiki_region:TR_type:city|format=dms|display=title}}

{{Former settlements in Turkey}}

[[Category:Catholic titular sees in Asia]]
[[Category:Populated places in ancient Lycia]]
[[Category:Former populated places in Turkey]]
[[Category:Defunct dioceses of the Ecumenical Patriarchate of Constantinople]]
[[Category:Populated places of the Byzantine Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>nob1xpxdi3a31lszcpsii9jerzotcjk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
