  <page>
    <title>Assur</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>612945</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934060555</id>
      <parentid>932450920</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-04T14:46:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mugsalot</username>
        <id>20521343</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>-[[Category:Assyria]]; -[[Category:Assyrian geography]]; -[[Category:Levant]]; -[[Category:Former populated places in Iraq]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]] removed parent categories</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Archaeological site in Iraq}}
{{Other uses2|Ashur}}
{{Infobox ancient site
| name           = Ashur
| native_name    = Aššur &lt;br /&gt; {{lang|syr|ܐܫܘܪ}} &lt;br /&gt; {{lang|fa|آشور}}
| alternate_name =
| image          = Flickr - The U.S. Army - www.Army.mil (218).jpg
| alt            =
| caption        = American soldiers on guard at the ruins of Ashur in 2008
| map_type       = Iraq
| map_alt        =
| map_size       =
| relief         =
| coordinates    = {{coord|35|27|24|N|43|15|45|E|display=inline,title}}
| location       = [[Saladin Governorate]], [[Iraq]]
| region         = [[Mesopotamia]]
| type           = Settlement
| part_of        =
| length         =
| width          =
| area           =
| height         =
| builder        =
| material       =
| built          = Approximately 2500 BC
| abandoned      = 14th century AD
| epochs         = Early [[Bronze Age]] to ?
| cultures       =
| dependency_of  =
| occupants      =
| event          =
| excavations    =
| archaeologists =
| condition      =
| ownership      =
| management     =
| public_access  = Inaccessible (in a war zone)
| website        = &lt;!-- {{URL|example.com}} --&gt;
| notes          =
| designation1            = WHS
| designation1_offname    = Ashur (Qal'at Sherqat)
| designation1_type       = Cultural
| designation1_criteria   = iii, iv
| designation1_date       = 2003 (27th [[World Heritage Committee|session]])
| designation1_number     = [https://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1130 1130]
| designation1_free1name  = Region
| designation1_free1value = [[List of World Heritage Sites in the Arab States|Arab States]]
| designation1_free2name  = [[List of World Heritage in Danger|Endangered]]
| designation1_free2value = 2003–present
}}

'''Aššur''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|æ|s|ʊər}}; [[Akkadian language|Akkadian]]; {{lang-syr|ܐܫܘܪ}} ''Āšūr''; [[Old Persian]] {{Script/Cuneiform|peo|𐎠𐎰𐎢𐎼}} ''Aθur'', {{lang-fa|آشور}}: ''Āšūr''; {{lang-he-n|אַשּׁוּר}}: ''{{transl|he|Aššûr}}'', {{lang-ar|اشور}}), also known as '''Ashur''' and '''Qal'at Sherqat''', was the capital of the [[Old Assyrian Empire]] (2025–1750 BC), the [[Middle Assyrian Empire]] (1365–1050 BC), and for a time, of the [[Neo-Assyrian Empire]] (911–608 BC). The remains of the city lie on the western bank of the [[Tigris River]], north of the confluence with its tributary, the [[Little Zab]], in what is now [[Iraq]], more precisely in the [[al-Shirqat District]] of the [[Saladin Governorate]].

Occupation of the city itself continued for approximately 4,000 years, from c. 2600 BC&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=La Boda|first=Sharon|title=International Dictionary of Historic Places: Middle East and Africa|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=R44VRnNCzAYC&amp;pg=PA89|year=1994|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-1-884964-03-9|page=89}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.britannica.com/place/Ashur-ancient-city-Iraq ''Encyclopædia Britannica'': &quot;Ashur (ancient city, Iraq)&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; to the mid-14th century AD, when the forces of [[Timur]] massacred its population. The site is a [[World Heritage Site]], having been added to that organisation's list of sites in danger in 2003 following the conflict that erupted following the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]] and as a result of a proposed dam which would flood some of the site. Assur lies {{convert|65|km}} south of the site of [[Nimrud]] and 100&amp;nbsp;km (60&amp;nbsp;mi) south of [[Nineveh]].

==History of research==
Exploration of the site of Assur began in 1898 by German archaeologists. Excavations began in 1900 by [[Friedrich Delitzsch]], and were continued in 1903–1913 by a team from the [[Deutsche Orient-Gesellschaft]] led initially by [[Robert Koldewey]] and later by [[Walter Andrae]].&lt;ref&gt;Walter Andrae, Der Anu-Adad-Tempel in Assur, JC Hinrichs, 1909, (1984 reprint {{ISBN|3-7648-1805-0}})&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Walter Andrae, Die Stelenreihen in Assur, JC Hinrichs, 1913, (1972 reprint {{ISBN|3-535-00587-6}})&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Walter Andrae, Die archaischen Ischtar-Tempel in Assur, JC Hinrichs, 1922, (1970 reprint {{ISBN|3-7648-1806-9}})&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Walter Andrae, Hethitische Inschriften auf Bleistreifen aus Assur, JC Hinrichs, 1924&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Walter Andrae, Das wiedererstandene Assur, 1938, JC Hinrichs, (1977 reprint {{ISBN|3-406-02947-7}})&lt;/ref&gt; More than 16,000 [[clay tablet]]s with [[cuneiform]] texts were discovered. Many of the objects found made their way to the [[Pergamon Museum]] in Berlin.

More recently, Ashur was excavated by B. Hrouda for the [[Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich]] and the Bavarian Ministry of Culture in 1990.&lt;ref&gt;Excavations in Iraq 1989–1990, Iraq, vol. 53, pp. 169-182, 1991&lt;/ref&gt; During the same period, in 1988 and 1989, the site was being worked by R. Dittmann on behalf of the [[Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft]].&lt;ref&gt;R. Dittmann, Ausgrabungen der Freien Universitat Berlin in Ashur und Kar-Tukulti-Ninurta in den Jahren 1986-1989, [[:de:MDPG|MDOG]], vol. 122, pp. 157–171, 1990&lt;/ref&gt;

==Name==
{{main|Name of Syria}}
''{{lang|akk-Latn|Aššur}}'' is the name of the city, of the land ruled by the city, and of its [[Ashur (god)|tutelary deity]] from which the natives took their name, as did the entire nation of [[Assyria]] which encompassed what is today northern Iraq, north east Syria and south east Turkey. Today the Assyrians are still found throughout the Middle East, particularly in [[Iraq]], [[Iran]], [[Syria]], [[Turkey]], and the Diaspora in the western world. Assur is also the origin of the names [[Syria]] and [[terms for Syriac Christians]], these being originally [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European]] derivations of Assyria, and for many centuries applying only to Assyria and the Assyrians (see [[Etymology of Syria]]) before also being applied to the [[Levant]] and its inhabitants by the [[Seleucid Empire]] in the 3rd century BC.

==Early Bronze Age==
Archaeology reveals the site of the city was occupied by the middle of the 3rd millennium BC. This was still the [[History of Sumer|Sumerian period]], before [[Assyria]] emerged in the 25th to 21st century BC.  The oldest remains of the city were discovered in the foundations of the [[Ishtar]] temple, as well as at the Old Palace. In the subsequent period, the city was ruled by kings from the [[Akkadian Empire]].  During the [[Third Dynasty of Ur]], the city was ruled by Assyrian  governors subject to the [[Sumerian people|Sumerians]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ancient.eu/ashur/|title=Ashur|author=Joshua J. Mark}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Old and Middle Assyrian Empire==
[[File:Meso2mil-English.JPG|left|thumb|[[Mesopotamia]] in 2nd millennium BC]]
[[File:AthurMdinta.jpg|thumb|right|Layout and expansion of the city over the centuries]]

By the time the Neo-Sumerian Ur-III dynasty collapsed at the hands of the [[Elam]]ites around the end of the 21st century BC according to the Middle Chronology and mid-20th century according to the Short Chronology following increasing raids by [[Gutians]] and [[Amorites]]. The native Akkadian-speaking Assyrian kings were now free while Sumer fell under the yoke of the [[Amorites]]. The Assyrian king [[Ushpia]] who reigned around the 21st century BC is credited with dedicating the first temple of the god Ashur in his home city, although this comes from a later inscription from [[Shalmaneser I]] in the 13th century. The temple likely dates to the original settlement of the site when the people of Ashur established their nation under the patronage of the city's god. Soon after in around 2000 BC, [[Puzur-Ashur I]] founded a new dynasty, with his successors such as [[Ilushuma]], [[Erishum I]] and [[Sargon I]] leaving inscriptions regarding the building of temples to [[Ashur (god)|Ashur]], [[Adad]] and [[Ishtar]] in the city. Prosperity and independence produced the first significant fortifications in this period. As the region enjoyed relative peace and stability, trade between [[Mesopotamia]] and [[Anatolia]] increased, and the city of Ashur greatly benefited from its strategic location. Merchants would dispatch their merchandise via caravan into Anatolia and trade primarily at Assyrian colonies in Anatolia, the primary one being at Karum Kanesh ([[Kültepe]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ancient.eu/ashur/|title=Ashur|author=Joshua J. Mark}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With [[Shamshi-Adad I]]'s (1813–1781 BC) capital at Assur, he magnified the city's power and influence beyond the Tigris river valley, establishing what some regard as the first Assyrian Empire. In this era, the Great Royal Palace was built, and the temple of Assur was expanded and enlarged with a [[ziggurat]]. However, this empire met its end when [[Hammurabi]], the [[Amorite]] king of [[Babylon]] conquered and incorporated the city into his short lived empire following the death of [[Ishme-Dagan I]] around 1756 BC, while the next three Assyrian kings were viewed as vassals. Not long after, the native king [[Adasi]] expelled the [[Babylonia]]ns and Amorites from Assur and Assyria as a whole around 1720 BC, although little is known of his successors. Evidence of further building activity is known from a few centuries later, during the reign of a native king [[Puzur-Ashur III]], when the city was refortified and the southern districts incorporated into the main city defenses. Temples to the moon god [[Sin]] ([[Sin (mythology)|Nanna]]) and the sun god [[Shamash]] were built and dedicated through the 15th century BC. The city was subsequently subjugated by the king of [[Mitanni]], [[Shaushtatar]] in the late 15th century, taking the gold and silver doors of the temple to his capital, [[Washukanni]], as spoils.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ancient.eu/ashur/|title=Ashur|author=Joshua J. Mark}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ashur-uballit I]] emulated his ancestor Adasi and overthrew the Mitanni empire in 1365 BC. The Assyrians reaped the benefits of this triumph by taking control of the eastern portion of the Mitanni Empire, and later also annexing [[Hittites|Hittite]], [[Babylonia]]n, [[Amorite]] and [[Hurrian]] territory. The following centuries witnessed the restoration of the old temples and palaces of Assur, and the city once more became the throne of a magnanimous empire from 1365 BC to 1076 BC. [[Tukulti-Ninurta I]] (1244–1208 BC) also constructed a new temple to the goddess [[Ishtar]]. The [[Anu]]-[[Adad]] temple was established later during the reign of [[Tiglath-Pileser I]] (1115–1075 BC). The walled area of the city in the Middle Assyrian period made up some {{convert|1.2|km2|acre}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ancient.eu/ashur/|title=Ashur|author=Joshua J. Mark}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Neo-Assyrian Empire==
[[File:Unfinished basalt statue of Shalmaneser III. From Assur, Iraq. 858-824 BCE. Ancient Orient Museum, Istanbul.jpg|left|thumb|Unfinished basalt statue of Shalmaneser III. From Assur, Iraq. 858–824 BCE. Ancient Orient Museum, Istanbul]]
[[File:Statue of the god Kidudu, guardian spirit of the wall of the city of Ashur. Circa 835 BCE. From Ashur, Iraq. The British Mueum, London.jpg|thumb|Statue of the god Kidudu, guardian spirit of the wall of the city of Ashur. Circa 835 BC. From Ashur, Iraq. The British Museum, London]]
[[File:Map of Assyria.png|thumb|right|Map of Assyria]]
[[File:Ashurnasipal with official.jpg|thumb|right|Ashurnasipal with official]]

In the [[Neo-Assyrian Empire]] (912–605 BC), the royal residence was transferred to other Assyrian cities. [[Ashur-nasir-pal II]] (884–859 BC) moved the capital from Assur to Kalhu ([[Calah]]/[[Nimrud]]) following a series of successful campaigns and produced some of the greatest artworks in the form of colossal [[lamassu]] statues and low-relief depictions of the royal court as well as battles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ancient.eu/ashur/|title=Kalhu|author=Joshua J. Mark}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the reign of [[Sargon II]] (722–705 BC), a new capital began to rise. [[Dur-Sharrukin]] (Fortress of [[Sargon II|Sargon]]) on a scale set to surpass that of Ashurnasirpal's.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ancient.eu/ashur/|title=Dur-Sharrukin|author=Joshua J. Mark}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, he died in battle and his son and successor [[Sennacherib]] (705–682 BC) abandoned the city, choosing to magnify Niniveh as his royal capital. However, the city of Ashur remained the religious center of the empire and continued to be revered as the holy crown of the empire, due to its temple of the national god [[Ashur (god)|Ashur]]. In the reign of [[Sennacherib]] (705–682 BC), the House of the New Year, ''Akitu'', was built, and the festivities celebrated in the city. Many of the kings were also buried beneath the Old Palace while some queens were buried in the other capitals such as the wife of Sargon, Ataliya. The city was sacked and largely destroyed during the decisive [[Fall of Assur|battle of Assur]], a major confrontation between the [[Neo-Assyrian Empire|Assyrian]] and [[Medes|Median]] armies.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.fr/books?id=P5q7DDqMbF0C&amp;pg=PA854&amp;lpg=PA854&amp;dq=fall+of+assur+614+BC&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=jkZfUmr0o8&amp;sig=Rhx269A-xlDAcIErwjh94Scv0w0&amp;hl=fr&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwj0l8SB_cHaAhVPalAKHROHBZ84ChDoATACegQICBAB#v=onepage&amp;q=fall%20of%20assur%20614%20BC&amp;f=true/ A Companion to the Archaeology of the Ancient Near East] &quot;In 614 BC Assur was conquered by the Medes under king Cyaxares (625-585 BC)&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.fr/books?id=78nRWgb-rp8C&amp;pg=PA18&amp;lpg=PA18&amp;dq=fall+of+nimrud+medes&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=GXv9WjYvo5&amp;sig=TrdBe6iJy6DgKZ-D3XfEfi2oues&amp;hl=fr&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwifm5eU1dbaAhUQYVAKHSobBbcQ6AEIdDAL#v=onepage&amp;q=fall%20of%20nimrud%20medes&amp;f=false/ The Fall and Rise of Jerusalem: Judah Under Babylonian Rule] &quot;the Medes left Arrapha, attacked Kalhu (Nimrud) and Ninuwa (Nineveh), and continued rapidly northward to capture the nearby city of Tarbisu. Afterward, they went back down the Tigris and laid siege to the city of Assur. The Babylonian army came to the aid of the Medes only after the Medes had begun the decisive offensive against the city, capturing it, killing many of its residents, and taking many others captive.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Achaemenid Empire==
After the Medes were overthrown by the [[Persian people|Persians]] as the dominant force in ancient Iran, Assyria was ruled by the [[Persia]]n [[Achaemenid Empire]] (as [[Athura]]) from 549 BC to 330 BC (see [[Achaemenid Assyria]]). The Assyrians of Mada ([[Media (region)|Media]]) and [[Athura]] (Assyria) had been responsible for gold and glazing works of the palace and for providing Lebanese cedar timber, respectively. The city and region of Ashur had once more gained a degree of militaristic and economic strength. Along with the Assyrians in Mada, a revolt took place in 520 BC but ultimately failed. Assyria seems to have recovered dramatically, and flourished during this period. It became a major agricultural and administrative centre of the Achaemenid Empire, and its soldiers were a mainstay of the Persian Army.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nineveh.com/Assyrians%20after%20Assyria.html |title=Assyrians after Assyria|publisher=Nineveh.com |date=4 September 1999 |accessdate=19 June 2011| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20110714183623/http://www.nineveh.com/Assyrians%20after%20Assyria.html| archivedate= 14 July 2011 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Parthian Empire==
[[File:Assur temple.jpg|thumb|120px|Parthian temple in Assur.]]
The city revived during the [[Parthian Empire]] period, particularly between 150 BC and 270 AD, being resettled and becoming an administrative centre of Parthian-ruled [[Assuristan]]. Assyriologists [[Simo Parpola]] and [[Patricia Crone]] suggest Assur may have had outright independence in this period. Other polities such as [[Beth Garmai]], [[Beth Nuhadra]] and [[Adiabene]] also flourished due to the fact that the Parthians exercised only loose or intermittent control of Assyria. New administrative buildings were erected to the north of the old city, and a palace to the south. The old temple dedicated to the national god of the Assyrians Assur ([[Ashur]]) was rebuilt, as were temples to other Assyrian gods.

Assyrian [[Eastern Aramaic]] inscriptions from the remains of Ashur have yielded insight into the Parthian-era city with Assyria having its own Aramaic [[Syriac alphabet|Syriac]] script, which was the same in terms of grammar and syntax as that found at [[Edessa]] and elsewhere in the state of [[Osroene]].

German archaeologist Klaus Beyer published over 600 inscriptions from Mesopotamian towns and cities including Ashur, [[Dura-Europos]], [[Hatra]], [[Gaddala]], [[Tikrit]] and [[Tur Abdin]]. Given that Christianity had begun to spread amongst the Assyrians throughout the Parthian era, the original Assyrian culture and religion persisted for some time, as proven by the inscriptions that include invocations to the gods [[Ashur]], [[Nergal]], [[Sin]], [[Ishtar]] and [[Shamash]], as well as mentions of citizens having compound names that refer to Assyrian gods, such as ʾAssur-ḥēl (Ashur [is] my strength), ʾAssur-emar (Ashur decreed/commanded), ʾAssur-ntan (Ashur gave [a son]), and ʾAssur-šma' (Ashur has heard; cf. [[Esarhaddon]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Beyer|1998|p=155}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Roman historian [[Festus (historian)|Festus]] wrote in about 370 that in AD 116 [[Trajan]] formed from his conquests east of the [[Euphrates]] the new Roman provinces of Mesopotamia and [[Assyria (Roman province)|Assyria]]. The existence of the latter Roman province is questioned by C.S. Lightfoot and F. Miller.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-roman-studies/article/trajans-parthian-war-and-the-fourthcentury-perspective/D5CCE57D517EE6E9AF24CAD504E72371 C. S. Lightfoot, &quot;Trajan's Parthian War and the Fourth-Century Perspective&quot; in ''The Journal of Roman Studies'', Vol. 80 (1990), pp. 115-126]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kettenhofen&gt;[http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/trajan Erich Kettenhofen, &quot;Trajan&quot; in ''Encyclopædia Iranica'' (2004)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/classical-quarterly/article/another-look-at-the-breviarium-of-festus/6E9C796F42187BFBC7671CC48B1A9DD8 Simon Grote, &quot;Another look at the ''Breviarium'' of Festus&quot; in ''The Classical Quarterly'', Volume 61, Issue 2 (December 2011), pp. 704-721]&lt;/ref&gt; In any case, just two years after the province's supposed creation, Trajan's successor [[Hadrian]] restored Trajan's eastern conquests to the Parthians, preferring to live with him in peace and friendship.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_gWcNAAAAQAAJ/page/n411 Theodore Mommsen, ''Römische Geschichte'' (Berlin 1885), vol. V (''Die Provinzen von Caesar bis Diocletian''), p. 403]&lt;/ref&gt;
 
There were later Roman incursions into Mesopotamia under [[Lucius Verus]] and under [[Septimius Severus]], who set up the Roman provinces of [[Mesopotamia (Roman province)|Mesopotamia]] and [[Osroene]].

The Persian [[Shapur I]] (241–272) captured and sacked the city in 257 AD after doing the same to [[Osroene]], [[Adiabene]], [[Beth Nuhadra]], [[Beth Garmai]] and  [[Hatra]], incorporating them into the [[Sassanid Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com.au/books?id=-9RNCgAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Iraq:+The+ancient+sites+and+Iraqi+Kurdistan&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjjvPTbrovNAhWj2qYKHTWgA4cQ6AEIHDAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Iraq%3A%20The%20ancient%20sites%20and%20Iraqi%20Kurdistan&amp;f=false|title= Iraq: The ancient sites and Iraqi Kurdistan|author=Geoff Hann|page=246|year=2015|isbn=9781841624884}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/place/Hatra|title=Hatra|work=Encyclopædia Britannica}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though destroyed by Shapur I, the city remained inhabited until the 12th and 13th century, when it belonged successively to the [[Zengid dynasty]] and the [[Ilkhanate]]. It was then abandoned and in part used as a cemetery.&lt;ref name=&quot;History of the city&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.assur.de/Themen/Stadtgeschichte_Engl/body_stadtgeschichte_engl.html|title=History of the city|work=Assur.de}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Threats to Assur==
The site was put on [[UNESCO]]'s List of [[World Heritage]] in danger in 2003, at which time the site was threatened by a looming large-scale dam project that would have submerged the ancient archaeological site.&lt;ref&gt;[https://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1130/threats/ UNESCO World Heritage in Danger 2003]&lt;/ref&gt;  The dam project was put on hold shortly after the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]].

The territory around the ancient site was occupied by the [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]] (ISIL) in 2015. Since ISIL had [[Destruction of cultural heritage by ISIL|destroyed]] a number of ancient Assyrian sites, including the cities of [[Hatra]], [[Khorsabad]], and [[Nimrud]], fears rose that Assur would be destroyed too. According to some sources, the citadel of Assur was destroyed or badly damaged in May 2015 by members of IS using [[improvised explosive device]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Mezzofiore |first1=Gianluca |last2=Limam |first2=Arij|title=Iraq: Isis 'blows up Unesco world heritage Assyrian site of Ashur' near Tikrit|url=http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/isis-blows-unesco-world-heritage-assyrian-site-ashur-near-tikrit-1503367|accessdate=24 August 2015|work=[[International Business Times]]|date=28 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; An [[Associated Press|AP]] report from December 2016 after the Iraqi forces had retaken the area, said that the militants tried to destroy the city's grand entrance arches, but they remained standing and a local historian described the damage as &quot;minor&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.aparchive.com/metadata/youtube/5a3b876a357496bbe394f88f929e873e|title=Iraq Assur {{!}} AP Archive|date=2016-12-11|website=www.aparchive.com|access-date=2019-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of February 2017, the group no longer controls the site; however, it is not secure enough for archaeological experts to evaluate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.cbsnews.com/news/iraqis-seek-funds-to-rebuild-cultural-artifacts-controlled-by-isis/|title=Iraqis seek funds to restore cultural artifacts recovered from ISIS|work=Associated Press|publisher=CBS News|date=February 24, 2017|accessdate=October 8, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Ashurism]]
* [[Chronology of the ancient Near East]]
* [[Cities of the ancient Near East]]
* [[Kings of Assyria]]
* [[Short chronology timeline]]
* [[World Heritage Sites in Danger]]
* [[Assyrian homeland]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* Klaus Beyer: Die aramäischen Inschriften aus Assur, Hatra und dem übrigen Ostmesopotamien, Germany 1998.
* [[Walter Andrae]]: Babylon. Die versunkene Weltstadt und ihr Ausgräber Robert Koldewey. de Gruyter, Berlin 1952.
* [[Stefan Heidemann]]: [https://web.archive.org/web/20110515233802/http://www.uni-jena.de/unijenamedia/Downloads/faculties/phil/iskvo/Heidemann_Texte/Heidemann_Continuity_1996_Assur.pdf ''Al-'Aqr, das islamische Assur. Ein Beitrag zur historischen Topographie Nordmesopotamiens.''] In: Karin Bartl and Stefan hauser et al. (eds.): ''Berliner Beiträge zum Vorderen Orient. Seminar fur Altorientalische Philologie und Seminar für Vorderasiatische Altertumskunde der Freien Universität Berlin, Fachbereich Altertumswissenschaften.'' Dietrich Reimer Verlag, Berlin 1996, pp.&amp;nbsp;259–285
* Eva Cancik-Kirschbaum: Die Assyrer. Geschichte, Gesellschaft, Kultur. C.H.Beck Wissen, München 2003. {{ISBN|3-406-50828-6}}
* Olaf Matthes: Zur Vorgeschichte der Ausgrabungen in Assur 1898-1903/05. MDOG Berlin 129, 1997, 9-27. ISSN 0342-118X
* Peter A. Miglus: Das Wohngebiet von Assur, Stratigraphie und Architektur. Berlin 1996. {{ISBN|3-7861-1731-4}}
* Susan L. Marchand: Down from Olympus. Archaeology and Philhellenism in Germany 1750-1970. Princeton University Press, Princeton 1996. {{ISBN|0-691-04393-0}}
* Conrad Preusser: Die Paläste in Assur. Gebr. Mann, Berlin 1955, 1996. {{ISBN|3-7861-2004-8}}
* Friedhelm Pedde, The Assur-Project. An old excavation newly analyzed, in: J.M. Córdoba et al. (Ed.), Proceedings of the 5th International Congress on the Archaeology of the Ancient Near East, Madrid, April 3–8, 2006. Universidad Autónoma de Madrid Ediciones, Madrid 2008, Vol. II, 743-752.https://www.jstor.org/stable/41147573
* Steven Lundström, From six to seven Royal Tombs. The documentation of the Deutsche Orient-Gesellschaft excavation at Assur (1903-1914) – Possibilities and limits of its reexamination, in: J.M. Córdoba et al. (Ed.), Proceedings of the 5th International Congress on the Archaeology of the Ancient Near East, Madrid, April 3–8, 2006. Universidad Autónoma de Madrid Ediciones, Madrid 2008, Vol. II, 445-463.
* Friedhelm Pedde, The Assur-Project: A new Analysis of the Middle- and Neo-Assyrian Graves and Tombs, in: P. Matthiae – F. Pinnock – L. Nigro – N. Marchetti (Ed.), Proceedings of the 6th International Congress on the Archaeology of the Ancient Near East, May, 5th-10th 2008, “Sapienza” – Università di Roma. Harrassowitz, Wiesbaden 2010, Vol. 1, 913–923.
* Barbara Feller, Seal Images and Social Status: Sealings on Middle Assyrian Tablets from Ashur, in: P. Matthiae – F. Pinnock – L. Nigro – N. Marchetti (Ed.), Proceedings of the 6th International Congress on the Archaeology of the Ancient Near East, May, 5th-10th 2008, “Sapienza” – Università di Roma. Harrassowitz, Wiesbaden 2010, Vol. 1, 721-729.
* Friedhelm Pedde, The Assur Project: The Middle and Neo-Assyrian Graves and Tombs, in: R. Matthews – J. Curtis (Ed.), Proceedings of the 7th International Congress on the Archaeology of the Ancient Near East, London 2010. Harrassowitz, Wiesbaden 2012, Vol. 1, 93-108.
* Friedhelm Pedde, The Assyrian heartland, in: D.T. Potts (Ed.), A Companion to the Archaeology of the Ancient Near East. Wiley-Blackwell, Chichester 2012, Vol. II, 851-866.

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Assur (city)}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | article = ASSYRIA iii. Parthian Assur | last = Schippmann | first = K. | authorlink = | url = http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/assyria-iii | editor-last = | editor-first =  | editor-link = | encyclopedia  = Encyclopaedia Iranica, Vol. II, Fasc. 8 | pages = 816-817 | location = | publisher = | year = 1987 | isbn = |ref=harv}}
* [http://libmma.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15324coll10/id/42692 Assyrian origins: discoveries at Ashur on the Tigris: antiquities in the Vorderasiatisches Museum, Berlin], an exhibition catalog from The Metropolitan Museum of Art Libraries (fully available online as PDF), which contains material on Assur
* Friedhelm Pedde, Recovering Assur. From the German Excavations of 1903–1914 to today’s Assur Project in Berlin [http://asorblog.org/recovering-assur/]

{{World Heritage Sites in Iraq}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:25th-century BC establishments]]
[[Category:Amorite cities]]
[[Category:Ancient Assyrian cities]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites in Iraq]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures destroyed by ISIL]]
[[Category:Populated places established in the 3rd millennium BC]]
[[Category:Saladin Governorate]]
[[Category:World Heritage Sites in Danger]]
[[Category:World Heritage Sites in Iraq]]</text>
      <sha1>5we6dmowkrde5z9t8ylq72xs7b75mmx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
