  <page>
    <title>Balconing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28800940</id>
    <revision>
      <id>933287425</id>
      <parentid>931626169</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-31T01:32:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Retimuko</username>
        <id>31516478</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>ce</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Jumping into a swimming pool from a balcony}}
'''Balconing''' is the act of jumping into a swimming pool from a balcony or falling from height while climbing from one balcony to another, performed by foreign tourists during holidays.&lt;ref name=Segura2017&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Segura-Sampedro|first=Juan José|last2=Pineño-Flores|first2=Cristina|last3=García-Pérez|first3=Jose María|last4=Jiménez-Morillas|first4=Patricia|last5=Morales-Soriano|first5=Rafael|last6=González-Argente|first6=Xavier|date=2017-03-28|title=Balconing: An alcohol-induced craze that injures tourists. Characterization of the phenomenon|journal=Injury|volume=48|issue=7|pages=1371–1375|doi=10.1016/j.injury.2017.03.037|issn=1879-0267|pmid=28377264}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term was formed through a combination of the Spanish word &quot;balcón&quot; (balcony) and the English suffix &quot;ing&quot;, a suffix that most Spanish associate with English culture and English people, in reference the origin of most practitioners.

In 2010 and 2011, a spate of injuries attributed to &quot;balconing&quot; by the Spanish press occurred among tourists in the [[Balearic Islands]] of [[Ibiza]] and [[Majorca]] in [[Spain]]. Videos of people jumping into pools from balconies were posted on video sharing websites such as [[YouTube]], which were alleged to have played a role in the spread of the phenomenon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Giles Tremlett in Madrid |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/aug/11/spanish-authorities-balconies-holidaymakers-warning |title=Spanish authorities warn holidaymakers of 'balconing' dangers &amp;#124; World news |publisher=The Guardian |date= 2010-08-11|accessdate=2010-09-13| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100815121029/http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/aug/11/spanish-authorities-balconies-holidaymakers-warning| archivedate= 15 August 2010 | url-status= live | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A similar phenomenon has been described in college-related events in [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Schaffer|first=Kathryn B.|last2=Schwendig|first2=Gary|last3=Nasrallah|first3=Fady|last4=Wang|first4=Jiayan|last5=Kraus|first5=Jess F.|date=2019-02-11|title=Falls from a balcony while intoxicated: a new injury trend among young adults?|journal=Injury Epidemiology|volume=6|issue=1|pages=4|doi=10.1186/s40621-019-0181-3|pmid=31245253|pmc=6582677|issn=2197-1714}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Injuries and deaths==
In 2010 in Spain, there were six deaths and 11 injuries in falls from balconies which were identified as relating to &quot;balconing&quot; in the Spanish press. Most of the casualties were young British and German tourists with traces of alcohol in their blood, and the incidents occurred between 10 p.m. and 7 a.m.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2010/09/12/baleares/1284291403.html |title=La siniestra lista del balconing suma y sigue &amp;#124; Baleares |publisher=elmundo.es |date=2010-08-22 |accessdate=2010-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same year, hotels were reported to have raised the height of hotel railings from {{convert|1.05|to|1.2|m|ft}} to reduce these incidents.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2010/08/19/baleares/1282227507.html El 'balconing' como fenómeno social de drogas, alcohol y juventud] in elmundo.es&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Mallorca]], three tourists died in 2017 in falls from balconies identified as &quot;balconing&quot; incidents in the Spanish press.&lt;ref&gt;[https://ultimahora.es/sucesos/ultimas/2017/06/04/271612/tres-muertos-por-balconing-menos-mes-mallorca.html Tres muertos por ‘balconing’ en menos de un mes en Mallorca] in ultimahora.es&lt;/ref&gt; Between 2010 and 2015 it has been described up to 46 injured to this practice.&lt;ref name=Segura2017 /&gt;

==Statistics==
According to [[Juan José Segura-Sampedro|Juan José Segura]], [[Doctor of Philosophy|doctor]] at Son Espases´s [[hospital]], 85% of the victims fall accidentally, usually while trying to jump from one balcony to the next or while recklessly moving near the edge, while the rest actively jump off the [[balcony]]. He estimates an average of 10 to 15 cases each year since 2011, with an increase since more of these jumps have been posted on [[YouTube]].&lt;ref&gt;http://cadenaser.com/programa/2018/07/20/la_ventana/1532099949_081845.html/Ser Radio/Entrevista con el Doctor Segura
&lt;/ref&gt;

Doctor Segura and the [[Foreign and Commonwealth Office|British Foreign Office]] established the profile of the &quot;average practitioner&quot; as a 24 year old [[United Kingdom|British]] male. 
97% of people involved in balconing are men and 61% are British. German and other nationalities are less numerous.&lt;ref name=Planchard2018&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.20minutes.fr/monde/2311279-20180721-espagne-baleares-balconing-fait-nouveau-victimes-parmi-touristes |title=Espagne: Aux Baléares le 'balconing' fait de nouveau des victimes parmi les touristes |last=Planchard |first=Claire |date=21 July 2018 |website=[[20 minutes (France)|20 minutes]] |language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The medical costs of the tourists injured in this practice costs an average of €32,000 per case.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url= https://www.diariodeibiza.es/pitiuses-balears/2015/02/17/balconing-30000-euros/750012.html |title=Un 'balconing': 30.000 euros |author=Marta Torres Molina |date=17 February 2015 |work=Diario de Ibiza |access-date=2018-07-23 |language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The balconies have a median height of {{convert|8|m|ft}}, and the people have a median age of 24 years.&lt;ref name=Planchard2018 /&gt;

== Preventive measures ==
In 2018, the [[Foreign and Commonwealth Office|Foreign Office]] teamed up with [[Spaniards|Spanish]] [[surgeon]], [[Juan José Segura-Sampedro]] to run a campaign of video messages to British tourists heading to the [[Balearic Islands]] during the summer.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/spanish-surgeon-warns-holiday-britons-off-fatal-balcony-stunts-5pm9g9z0d|title=Spanish surgeon warns holiday Britons off fatal balcony stunts|last=Madrid|first=Graham Keeley|date=2018-05-12|work=The Times|access-date=2018-05-15|language=en|issn=0140-0460}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[RTÉ]] also made a special program where a doctor from [[Mallorca]] participated.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Watch Prime Time online|url=https://www.rte.ie/player/es/show/prime-time-30003251/10899066/|language=en|access-date=2018-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite these campaigns, &quot;balconing&quot; is still a problem and various hotels in the Balearic Islands have been forced to implement measurements against it, like closing their balconies or building taller walls around them.
[[Magaluf]] has been forced to regulate drinking in an attempt to control reckless behaviour, including but not limited to balconing. It has also introduced heavy fines for the practice of balconing, of between €750 and €1,500.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.abc.es/sociedad/20150521/abci-calvia-alcohol-calle-201505211719.html |title=Ley seca en Magaluf: prohibido beber alcohol en la calle a partir de las 22:00 horas |date=22 May 2015 |work=[[ABC (newspaper)|ABC]] |access-date=2018-07-23 |language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==2018==

In 2018, there were six reported balconing accidents (British, Irish, and one French). Three of them were killed by falling. This is more than during the years 2016 and 2017. Nonetheless, some cases might not be due to the practice of ''balconing'', but might have other causes like accidental fall due to excessive [[alcohol (drug)|alcohol]] consumption.&lt;ref name=Planchard2018 /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Alcohol and health}}

==External links==
*https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/booze-and-balconies-don-t-mix

[[Category:Outdoor recreation]]
[[Category:Causes of death]]</text>
      <sha1>6fzx4i0tr836d8cv4juu7j02wdf76ro</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
