  <page>
    <title>Bangarapet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5707910</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932498166</id>
      <parentid>925853205</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-26T10:15:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Leela52452</username>
        <id>28733330</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Road */fixed typo: ROAD(Bangalore -&gt; ROAD (Bangalore, km.It -&gt; km. It</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2019}}
{{Use Indian English|date=April 2018}}
{{Too many sections|date=January 2018}}
{{Refimprove|date=January 2018}}
{{Infobox settlement
| name                    = Bangarapet
| native_name             = 
| native_name_lang        = Kannada
| other_name              = Bangarapete
| nickname                = 
| settlement_type         = Town
| image_skyline           = 
| image_alt               = 
| image_caption           = 
| pushpin_map             = India Karnataka
| pushpin_label_position  = left
| pushpin_map_alt         = 
| pushpin_map_caption     = Location in Karnataka, India
| coordinates             = {{coord|12.97|N|78.2|E|display=inline,title}}
| subdivision_type        = Country
| subdivision_name        = {{flag|India}}
| subdivision_type1       = [[States and territories of India|State]]
| subdivision_name1       = [[Karnataka]]
| subdivision_type2       = [[List of districts of India|District]]
| subdivision_name2       = [[Kolar district|Kolar]]
| established_title       = &lt;!-- Established --&gt;
| established_date        = 
| founder                 = 
| named_for               = 
| government_type         = 
| governing_body          = 
| unit_pref               = Metric
| area_footnotes          = 
| area_rank               = 
| area_total_km2          = 5.5
| elevation_footnotes     = 
| elevation_m             = 843
| population_total        = 44849
| population_as_of        = 2011
| population_rank         = 
| population_density_km2  = auto
| population_demonym      = 
| population_footnotes    = 
| demographics_type1      = Languages
| demographics1_title1    = Official
| demographics1_info1     = [[Kannada]]
| Other languages = Tamil
Telugu
| timezone1               = [[Indian Standard Time|IST]]
| utc_offset1             = +5:30
| postal_code_type        = [[Postal Index Number|PIN]]
| postal_code             = 563114
| area_code_type          = Telephone code
| area_code               = 08153
| registration_plate      = '''KA-07,KA-08'''
| website                 = {{URL|bangarpettown.gov.in}}
| 
}}
'''Bangarapet'''  is a town in [[Kolar district]] in the [[Indian state]] of [[Karnataka]]. Bangarapet is the headquarters of the taluk of Bangarpet. Bangarpet was originally called Bowringpet, named after an officer working in the [[Kolar Gold Fields]]. This town came into existence as the connecting point of traffic between the gold fields and Bangalore.

This town is known in Karnataka for its rice trading.

==Ancient History==
The earliest know name for Bangarpet was Marmutlu, the british named it Bowringpet during their rule as the town was a connecting point to Kolar Gold Fields, the town was later named to Bangarpet after independence.

==Road==
Bangarpet is connected by State Highway No. 5 up to Kolar and then by National Highway No. 4 up to Bangalore.  The distance through road is approximately 90&amp;nbsp;km. It takes about 15&amp;nbsp;km to get connected to NH4 ROAD (Bangalore to Chennai) &amp; 30&amp;nbsp;km to next nearest town, kuppam of Andhra Pradesh &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kolarcity.gov.in/ |title=Archived copy |accessdate=3 January 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090116022357/http://www.kolarcity.gov.in/ |archivedate=16 January 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Railway==
[[File:Bangarpet.JPG|thumb|Bangarpet]]
[[Bangarapet railway station]] is the last railway junction in Karnataka before the [[Chennai-Bangalore line|Bangalore-Chennai line]] enters [[Andhra Pradesh]] and [[Tamil Nadu]]. Bangarpet is approximately 71&amp;nbsp;km from Bangalore City via rail route.  People travelling to Kolar Gold Fields (KGF) need to change trains here while travelling in trains bound to Bangalore or Chennai. 

[[File:Pani Poori.jpg|thumb|Pani Poori]]

==Administration==
Bangarapet is a town municipality with 23 municipal wards, each ward is represented by a councilor directly elected by the people. Councillors elect the president and vice president among themselves.

==Demographics==
Bangarapet is a Town Municipal Council city in district of Kolar, Karnataka. The Bangarapet city is divided into 23 wards for which elections are held every 5 years. The Bangarapet Town Municipal Council has population of 44,849 of which 22,628 are males while 22,221 are females as per report released by Census India 2011.

Population of Children with age of 0-6 is 5139 which is 11.46% of total population of Bangarapet (TMC). In Bangarapet Town Municipal Council, Female Sex Ratio is of 982 against state average of 973. Moreover, Child Sex Ratio in Bangarapet is around 946 compared to Karnataka state average of 948. Literacy rate of Bangarapet city is 86.69% higher than state average of 75.36%. In Bangarapet, Male literacy is around 90.58% while female literacy rate is 82.74%.

Bangarapet Town Municipal Council has total administration over 10,083 houses to which it supplies basic amenities like water and sewerage. It is also authorized to build roads within Town Municipal Council limits and impose taxes on properties coming under its jurisdiction.

Caste Factor
Schedule Caste (SC) constitutes 23.09% while Schedule Tribe (ST) were 1.00% of total population in Bangarapet (TMC).

'''Work Profile'''
Out of total population, 15,999 were engaged in work or business activity. Of this 12,562 were males while 3,437 were females. In census survey, worker is defined as person who does business, job, service, and cultivator and labour activity. Of total 15999 working population, 88.17% were engaged in Main Work while 11.83% of total workers were engaged in Marginal Work.

The people of Bangarapet depend largely on jobs in [[Bangalore]] for earning money. People generally work in [[Information technology|IT]] and private companies in and around Bangalore.  The town is very well connected with Bangalore city, facilitating in a huge daily floating population travelling to Bangalore to earn their living.  A portion of the people work in the nearby public sector factory of Bharath Earth Movers Limited.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Bangarapet}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110721155429/http://www.bangarpettown.gov.in/home Bangarpet Town Municipal Corporation]
* [http://parisaramahiti.kar.nic.in/NGC/school_list/kolar.html List of NGC Schools in bangarpet Kolar]

[[Category:Cities and towns in Kolar district]]</text>
      <sha1>j9i77s3670d8dwk0to60378lgibvfvb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
