  <page>
    <title>Barbil</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5708129</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934570629</id>
      <parentid>927137777</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-07T07:23:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2409:4062:28A:1DB6:20:F348:3E2B:4331</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2018}}
{{Use Indian English|date=June 2018}}
{{multiple issues|
{{POV|date=November 2017}}
{{original research|date=November 2017}}
{{overly detailed|date=November 2017}}
}}
{{Infobox settlement
| name                            = Barbil
| native_name                     = Bada Barabil
| native_name_lang                = or
| other_name                      = 
| nickname                        = 
| settlement_type                 = City
| image_skyline                   = 
| image_alt                       = 
| image_caption                   = 
| pushpin_map                     = India Odisha#India
| pushpin_label_position          = 
| pushpin_map_alt                 = 
| pushpin_map_caption             = Location in Odisha, India
| coordinates                     = {{coord|22.12|N|85.40|E|display=inline,title}}
| subdivision_type                = Country
| subdivision_name                = {{flag|India}}
| subdivision_type1               = [[States and territories of India|State]]
| subdivision_name1               = [[Odisha]]
| subdivision_type2               = [[List of districts of India|District]]
| subdivision_name2               = [[Keonjhar district|Keonjhar]]
| established_title               = &lt;-- Established --&gt;
| established_date                = 
| founder                         = 
| named_for                       = 
| government_type                 = 
| governing_body                  = 
| unit_pref                       = Metric
| area_footnotes                  = 
| area_rank                       = 
| area_total_km2                  = 80
| elevation_footnotes             = 
| elevation_m                     = 477
| population_total                = 125000
| population_as_of                = 2017
| population_rank                 = 
| population_density_km2          = 1168
| population_demonym              = 
| population_footnotes            = 
| demographics_type1              = Languages
| demographics1_title1            = Official
| demographics1_info1             = [[Odia language|Odia]]
| demographics1_title2           
| timezone1                       = [[Indian Standard Time|IST]]
| utc_offset1                     = +5:30
| postal_code_type                = [[Postal Index Number|PIN]]
| postal_code                     = 758035
| area_code_type                  = Telephone code
| area_code                       = 06767
| registration_plate              = OD 09
| blank1_name_sec1                = [[Human sex ratio|Sex ratio]]
| blank1_info_sec1                = 894 [[male|♂]]/[[female|♀]]
| website                         = {{URL|odisha.gov.in}}
| footnotes                       = 
}}

'''Barbil''' is a City and a [[Municipality]] in the [[Kendujhar district]] (also known as Iron City) of the state of [[Odisha]], [[India]]. It is one of the 5th scheduled areas. The region around Barbil has a largest deposit of Iron ore and manganese ore in the world.  It is a major source of revenue generation for both the Central and the State government. Apart from that, the place is surrounded by breathtaking sceneries unfolded by nature's touch.

==Geography==
Barbil is located at {{coord|22.12|N|85.40|E|}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fallingrain.com/world/IN/21/Barabil.html Falling Rain Genomics, Inc - Barbil]{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; It has an average elevation of {{convert|477|m|ft|abbr=on}}. Barbil is fully surrounded by hills.

==Climate==
It boasts of being a mining area which welcomes all. All Indian cuisine can be found here and very scenic hills and forests, breath taking waters falls, picnic spots can be found here a few kilometers from the town.
{{Weather box
| location = Barbil, Odisha
| metric first = Y
| single line = yes
| Jan high C = 25.6
| Feb high C = 28.1
| Mar high C = 33.2
| Apr high C = 37.3
| May high C = 39.0
| Jun high C = 34.9
| Jul high C = 29.8
| Aug high C = 29.6
| Sep high C = 30.0
| Oct high C = 29.3
| Nov high C = 27.1
| Dec high C = 25.3
| Jan low C = 11.2
| Feb low C = 13.5
| Mar low C = 17.9
| Apr low C = 22.5
| May low C = 25.4
| Jun low C = 25.0
| Jul low C = 23.7
| Aug low C = 23.5
| Sep low C = 23.2
| Oct low C = 20.3
| Nov low C = 14.5
| Dec low C = 10.8
| Jan rain mm = 12
| Feb rain mm = 25
| Mar rain mm = 25
| Apr rain mm = 20
| May rain mm = 56
| Jun rain mm = 201
| Jul rain mm = 354
| Aug rain mm = 370
| Sep rain mm = 237
| Oct rain mm = 65
| Nov rain mm = 11
| Dec rain mm = 2
| rain colour = green
|source= [http://en.climate-data.org/location/968980/ en.climate-data.org]
}}

==Demographics==
According to the 2011 India [[census]], Barbil had a population of 66,540.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.censusindia.net/results/town.php?stad=A&amp;state5=999|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040616075334/http://www.censusindia.net/results/town.php?stad=A&amp;state5=999|archivedate=2004-06-16|title= Census of India 2001: Data from the 2001 Census, including cities, villages and towns  (Provisional)|accessdate=2008-11-01|work= |publisher= Census Commission of India}}&lt;/ref&gt; Males constitute 53% of the population and females 47%. Barbil has an average literacy rate of 72.18%. 16% of the population is under 6 years of age. Barbil has another about 50,000 people floating population from rest of India coming here for business travel and jobs.

==Languages==
As the Barbil area has been dominated by Ho people, local tribal people widely speak in the [[Ho language]] [it is written with the &quot;Varang Kshiti&quot; (also &quot;Warang Chiti&quot; script)] as their mode of communication.Most people can speak, write all three languages [[Odia language|Odia]], [[Hindi]] &amp; [[English language|English]].

==Industry==
Barbil is an industrialised town with a number of steel plants, iron ore pellet plants, ore crushers and mines. The area is very rich in iron ore. The other mineral found is manganese ore. The latest demand is for iron ore [[Iron ore#Beneficiation|fines]]. Nowadays the mines cannot meet up to the demand from the area. The iron ore which is benefited is also exported to China. This town also has Steel manufacturing, Iron ore pellet manufacturer and liquid oxygen production. A large number of industries have come up in the recent past. It remains to be seen how the government's directive increasing the cost of export of raw iron ore affects the economy of Barbil town. Some Government-run Industries have closed after incurring losses.

==Transport==
[[Barbil railway station]] under Chakradharpur division is on a by line in the [[Tatanagar–Bilaspur section]] of the [[Howrah-Nagpur-Mumbai line]] Connecting the main line at Rajkharshavan station which is about 100&amp;nbsp;km from Barbil . Barbil is connected to Howrah,  [[Kolkata]], Bhubaneshwar, Puri and Tatanagar [[Jamshedpur]] by train. Jan Shatabdi Express runs from Howrah to Barbil and one passenger train from Tatanagar to Barbil. Barbil is also connected to Bhubaneshwar &amp; Puri by a daily-running Intercity Express train. Barbil-Chakradharpur Intercity Express (Daily) via Dongoaposi, Jhinkpani Chaibasa at Chakradharpur one can extend the journey to [[Rourkela]] or even [[Sambalpur]] Vizag Chennai Alleppy etc. towards south and Bilaspur Nagpur Mumbai towards West and also via Keonjhar Kendujhar. Jajpur road, Cuttack Bhubaneshwar for connecting trains.
&lt;ref&gt;http://indiarailinfo.com/train/2472/238/7867&lt;/ref&gt; (Puri-Barbil).
Barbil is also connected to Kolkata, [[Kendujhar]] and [[Bhubaneshwar]] by road.
Prior to January 2008, there was air service from Barbil. However, international &amp; local flights can be connected via Netaji Subhas Airport (Dum Dum, Kolkata), and also from Biju Patnaik Airport Bhubaneshwar. The Airstrip at Barbil (Tonto) can be used for private and Chartered flights.

There are many many hotels and lodges located in this town. They are: Padma Inn, Hotel Prateek, Hotel Smita, Lucky India, Aadhar Hotel, Hotel Karrow, Hotel Indrapuri and The World pinaca.

== Social activities ==

'BIKASH MAHAL' is the pavilion where all the social, cultural and national day events are organised.

There are so many social organizations named Barbil Haalchal, 'NATIVE VOICE', PRAYAAS, Niladri, Sambad Sahitya Ghara, SEVA GROUP, MARWADI YUVA MANCH, SAHISTYA SANSADA, AND YBCC who carry out different social events in the town.

A New Town Hall by the name of '''Sita Ram Rungta''' '''Town Hall Barbil''' has come up with all modern amenities and is fully air-conditioned. It has available seating capacity of 300, which can be extended to 500 by temporary arrangement.

== Festivals ==

People of Barbil celebrate together all the festivals during the year - like Durga Puja, Laxmi puja, Raja Sankranti, Ganesh Puja, Makar Sankranti, Sri Ram Naumi, Biswakarma Puja, Chhat Puja, Guru Nanak Day, Ramzan, Idd, Eid ul Zuha (bakrid), Muharram, Eid Miladun Nabi, Kali Puja etc. and National Festivals like Republic Day, Independence Day Gandhi Jayanti, and State Festivals like Odisha Day, Madhusudan Birthday etc..

Viswakarma puja is also celebrated together in Barbil. We can see various pendals all around the town in Viswakarma puja as lord Viswakarma is the lord of machines and of course Barbil is a hub of many industries and heavy machines and vehicles. People worship their machine shop and vehicles on this auspicious occasion. This festival usually falls in the month of September. Durgapuja is celebrated as a grand festival in kalinga nagar which is near to barbil. Lakhs of visitors are eagarly waited for this festival and join during the 4 day festival hails from nearby areas from jharkhand also.

==Health==

The air of Barbil is laden with dust due to mining activities and passage of mineral-laden trucks in the night through the town as no bypass roads for heavy vehicles are being constructed by the government. &quot;People with a dust allergy are advised care before coming here&quot;. In the year 2016 there was a rampant spread of Dengue here which rattled the administration. Hundred were affected and many of them died.

Despite being an important centre it has Community Health Centre and needs urgent up gradation.

Posts of various departments are vacant. Doctors of various specialities are needed here and can contact directly with District Collector @ckeonjhar for direct appointment.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Kendujhar district}}
{{Municipalities of Odisha}}

[[Category:Cities and towns in Kendujhar district]]
[[Category:Iron ore mining in India]]
[[Category:Mining in Odisha]]</text>
      <sha1>ksyuz6xd82rvz2735f3uoa2d9hfj6u4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
