  <page>
    <title>Bhawanipatna</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4773250</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937834907</id>
      <parentid>936488887</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-27T14:19:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FrescoBot</username>
        <id>9021902</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Bot: [[User:FrescoBot/Links|link syntax]] and minor changes</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2019}}
{{Use Indian English|date=January 2019}}
{{more citations needed|date=January 2017}}
{{guidebook}}
{{Infobox settlement
| name                            = Bhawanipatna
| official_name                   = Bhawanipatna
| native_name                     = 
| native_name_lang                = or
| other_name                      = 
| nickname                        = 
| settlement_type                 = [[City]]
| image_skyline                   = Bhawanipatna Shine.JPG
| image_alt                       = 
| image_caption                   = Bhawanipatna Clockwise from top left: Doordarshan Tower, Phurlijharan, Durga Mandap (Big Ben of Bhawanipatna), Manikeshwari Mandir, Bhawanipatna Railway Station, Bhawanipatna Bus Stand
| pushpin_map                     = India Odisha#India
| pushpin_label_position          = right
| pushpin_map_alt                 = 
| pushpin_map_caption             = 
| coordinates                     = {{coord|19.91|N|83.128|E|display=inline,title}}
| subdivision_type                = Country
| subdivision_name                = {{flag|India}}
| subdivision_type1               = [[States and territories of India|State]]
| subdivision_name1               = [[Odisha]]
| established_title               = &lt;!-- Established --&gt;
| established_date                = 
| founder                         = 
| named_for                       = The leading deity Bhawani-Shankar
| government_type                 = [[Nagar Palika|Municipality]]
| governing_body                  = '''Bhawanipatna Municipality'''
| unit_pref                       = Metric
| area_footnotes                  = 
| area_rank                       = 
| area_total_km2                  = 
| elevation_footnotes             = 
| elevation_m                     = 248
| population_total                = 83,756
| population_as_of                = 2011
| population_rank                 = 
| population_density_km2          = auto
| population_demonym              = Kalahandia
| population_footnotes            = 
| demographics_type1              = Languages
| demographics1_title1            = Official
| demographics1_info1             = [[Odia language|Odia]]
| timezone1                       = [[Indian Standard Time|IST]]
| utc_offset1                     = +5:30
| postal_code_type                = [[Postal Index Number|PIN]]
| postal_code                     = 766001, 766002
| area_code_type                  = Telephone code
| area_code                       = 06670
| registration_plate              = OD-08
| blank_name_sec1                 = [[UN/LOCODE]]
| blank_info_sec1                 = IN BWIP
| website                         = {{URL|kalahandi.nic.in}}
| footnotes                       = 
| Place                           = 
}}
[[File:Bhawanipatna City (Drone View).jpg|thumb|Aerial view of Bhawanipatna City]]
'''Bhawanipatna''' is second largest city of South Odisha and district headquarter of the [[Kalahandi district]] in the [[India]]n state of [[Odisha]]. Bhawanipatna is a city of numerous temples dedicated to different deities of Hindu pantheon. It is named after the presiding deity, '''Bhawani-Shankar''' and '''Patnam''' which means place in Odia like &quot;Padaa&quot;. Bhawanipatna municipality is the administrative head of the city, which is divided into twenty wards with different sub-areas called ''pada'' (pronounced &quot;padaa&quot;). Originally, these ''padaas'' were inhabited by people of different communities, but over the last few decades, these Paras have become homogeneous. Bhawanipatna has more than forty-two ''paras''. It is one of the biggest urban areas of southern part of [[Odisha]].[[File:Durga Mandap, Gandhi Chowk, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|Durga Mandap, Gandhi Chowk, Bhawanipatna]]
[[File:Bhawanipatna Palace.jpg|thumb|Kalahandi Palace, Bhawanipatna]]

==Geography and climate==
Bhawanipatna is located at {{coord|19.9|N|83.17|E|}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fallingrain.com/world/IN/21/Bhawanipatna.html Falling Rain Genomics, Inc - Bhawanipatna]&lt;/ref&gt; It has an average elevation of {{convert|248|m|ft|abbr=on}}. Bhawanipatna is located in the centre of large mountains and plateaus. It has eastern ghat mountains in its eastern frontier.

===Climate===
Bhawanipatna has a tropical wet and dry climate, temperatures remain moderate throughout the year, except from March to June, which can be extremely hot. The temperature in April–May sometimes rises above {{Convert|48|C}}. These summer months also have dry and hot winds. In summers, the temperature can also go up to {{Convert|50|C}}. The city receives about {{Convert|1300|mm|}} of rain, mostly in the monsoon season from late June to early October. Winters last from November to January and are mild, although lows can fall to {{Convert|5|C|}}.

==Demographics==
{{As of|2011}} India [[census]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.censusindia.net/results/town.php?stad=A&amp;state5=999|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040616075334/http://www.censusindia.net/results/town.php?stad=A&amp;state5=999|archivedate=2004-06-16|title= Census of India 2011: Data from the 2011 Census, including cities, villages and towns  (Provisional)|accessdate=2008-11-01|work= |publisher= Census Commission of India}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bhawanipatna had a population of 69,045 and total including sub-urban of 83,756. Population of Children with age of 0-6 is 7407 which is 10.73% of total population of Bhawanipatna (M). In Bhawanipatna Municipality, Female Sex Ratio is of 945 against state average of 979. Moreover, Child Sex Ratio in Bhawanipatna is around 911 compared to Orissa state average of 941. Literacy rate of Bhawanipatna city is 85.00% higher than state average of 72.87%. In Bhawanipatna, Male literacy is around 90.95% while female literacy rate is 78.72% according to the 2011 census. Out of total population, 23,705 were engaged in work or business activity. Of this 18,666 were males while 5,039 were females. In census survey, worker is defined as person who does business, job, service, and cultivator and labour activity. Of total 23705 working population, 84.55% were engaged in Main Work while 15.45% of total workers were engaged in Marginal Work.

==Language and literature==
The language spoken by the people of Kalahandi is the [[Kalahandia]] dialect of [[Odia language|Oriya]], locally known as Kalahandia . Local weekly newspapers such as Arjji and Kalahandi Express publish articles in standard Odia and Kalahandia language. Other languages include Kui, Bhatri (another dialect of Odia), Parji, Bhunjia, spoken by approximately 7000 Bhunjia Adivasis.

==Politics==
Current [[Member of the Legislative Assembly (India)|MLA]] from Bhawanipatna (SC) Assembly Constituency is [[Pradip Naik]] of [[Bharatiya Janata party|BJP]], who won the seat in State election of 2019. Previous MLAs from this seat is Dusmanta Kumar Naik of [[Indian National Congress|INC]], who won the seat in State election of 2009. Previous MLAs from this seat include Pradip Kumar Naik of [[Bharatiya Janata Party|BJP]] who won the seat in State elections of 2004 and also in 2000 and 1995, Ajit Das of [[Janata Dal|JD]] who won this seat in 1990, Bhaktacharan Das of [[Janata Party|JNP]] in 1985, and Dayanidhi Naik who won this seat in 1980 as a candidate of [[Indian National Congress|INC(I)]] and as INC candidate in 1977.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://archive.eci.gov.in/March2004/pollupd/ac/states/s18/Partycomp99.htm
|title = State Elections 2004 - Partywise Comparison for 99-Bhawanipatna Constituency of Odisha
|publisher = Election Commission of India
|accessdate = 2008-09-26
}}{{dead link|date=July 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bhawanipatna is part of the [[Kalahandi (Lok Sabha constituency)|Kalahandi constituency]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://archive.eci.gov.in/se2000/background/S18/Orissa_AC_Dist_PC.pdf
 |title=Assembly Constituencies - Corresponding Districts and Parliamentary Constituencies of Odisha
 |publisher=Election Commission of India
 |accessdate=2008-09-26
 |url-status=dead
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090304184320/http://archive.eci.gov.in/se2000/background/S18/Orissa_AC_Dist_PC.pdf
 |archivedate=2009-03-04
}}&lt;/ref&gt; currently held by [[Arka Keshari Deo]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://india.gov.in/govt/loksabhampbiodata.php?mpcode=3264 |title=Detailed Profile - Shri Arka Keshari Deo - Members of Parliament (Lok Sabha) - Who's Who - Government: National Portal of India |work=india.gov.in |year=2005 |quote=1990-1991: Union Minister of State, Railways |accessdate=14 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and before that by his father [[Bikram Keshari Deo]], who was the younger son of Maharaj Pratap Kesari Deo of Kalahandi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.indiaelections.co.in/lok-sabha-constituencies/Odisha/kalahandi/ |title=Kalahandi &amp;#124; Odisha Lok Sabha Constituency Elections Results 2009 Kalahandi &amp;#124; Odisha MP Elections Results Kalahandi 2009 &amp;#124; Candidate of Kalahandi Lok Sabha |work=indiaelections.co.in |year=2012 |quote=Updated Election Results Details of Kalahandi |accessdate=14 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Areas of Bhawanipatna==

{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
# Arkabahali Para
# Amgach pada
# Bag pada
# Baad Para
# Bahadur Bagicha Para
# Balaji Vihar
# Bazarpada
# Braja Vihar
# Banka pada
# Chanchra Pada
# Churi Hari Pada
# Dewansaheb para
# Dhoba Pada
# Godam Para
# Gosal Para
# Haati Saal Pada
# Halia Pada
# Hill Town
# Irrigation Colony
# Jore Pada
# Jenakhal Pada
# Kalimandir Para
# Kumhar Pada
# Mahabir Para
# Mali para
# Mandar Bagicha Para
# Mukti Nagar
# Naktiguda
# Nityananda Nagar
# Nua Para
# Odia Bangti Para
# Pardesi Para
# Purna Para
# Ram Nagar Para
# Ram Sagar Para
# Sambhu Nagar Pada
# Shakti Nagar Pada
# Shanti Nagar Pada
# Shastri Nagar
# Sitabordi Para
# Statue Para
# Tal Pada
# Tarini Mandir Pada
# Telegu Bangti Para
# TV Centre Pada
{{div col end}}

City area of Bhawanipatna includes nearby sub-urban areas like Parmanandapur, Station area, Kesinga road, Bandhapala, Kasakendu, Medinipur, Duarsuni, Raisingpur, Bhangabari and Atangaguda.

==Tourism==

* '''[[Maa Manikeshwari Mandir]] and [[Chatar jatra]]'''
There are two Manikeshwari Mandir located in Kalahandi district of Odisha, one is in Bhawanipatna and other at Thuamal Rampur. The temple is located in the centre of Bhawanipatna. The main deity here is Goddess Manikeshwari. The main devotees are from the fishermen community. During Dussehra festival, animal sacrifice is offered at this temple which is a festival also known as [[Chatar jatra]] where lacs of people gather in the city to get the blessings from their beloved goddess . A film is also documented showing the ritual of animal sacrifice, before Goddess Manikeshwari.

* '''[[Phurlijharan]]'''

[[File:Phurlijharan.JPG|thumb|Phurlijharan Waterfall]]

Phurlijharan is a perennial water fall about {{Convert|30|ft||0|abbr=on|adj=on}} in height and has a special charm of its own. The multi coloured rainbow created by the sunrays falling on the scattered water particles of the fall is an amusing sight to be seen. The evergreen forests around the fall provide ample opportunities to group picnickers.

* '''[[Karlapat Wildlife Sanctuary]]'''

Present on SH-44 Karlapat Wildlife Sanctuary (Odia: କର୍ଲାପାଟ୍;Hindi: कर्लापाट्) is a wildlife sanctuary located in Kalahandi district and a very popular tourist attraction of Odisha in India. The sanctuary covers an area of {{Convert|255|km2||abbr=on}}. It lies within the Eastern Highlands moist deciduous forests ecoregion.[3] Major plant communities include mixed deciduous forests and scrublands.It has also high mineral deposit like bauxite and manganese etc.This sanctuary is home to many wildlife species like tiger, leopard, gaur, sambar, nilgai, barking deer, mouse deer, a wide variety of birds and reptiles.

* '''Jakham'''

It has a wooden guest house.
[[File:Jakam, Kalahandi.jpg|thumb|Jakam, Kalahandi]]

* '''Rabandara'''
[[File:Rabandhara Waterfall, Kalahandi.jpg|thumb|Rabandhara Waterfall, Kalahandi]]
Rabandara is a perennial water fall about {{cvt|13|ft|m|0}} in height and has a special charm of its own.

* '''Sospadar Waterfall'''

[[File:Sospadar Waterfall, Kalahandi.jpg|thumb|Sospadar Waterfall, Kalahandi]]
Sospadar is an exotic location for picnic lovers and adventurers.

* '''Gadagada Twin-Waterfall'''

* '''Zilla Sangrahalaya'''

[[File:District Museum, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|District Museum Bhawanipatna]]
Zilla Sangrahalaya or the District Museum, Bhawanipatna has different artifacts, manuscripts, paintings and many rare items from pre-historic age (Asurgarh coins, Gudahandi paintings etc) depicting ancient history of Kalahandi Redion.

* '''Permunji'''

[[File:Manikeshwari Temple (Panoramic View).jpg|thumb|Manikeshwari Temple (Panoramic View)]]

Permunji is a nursery situated at the foot of great mountain, a place for picnics. Elephants are commonly seen near the nursery crossing roads.

* '''Hello Point'''

Hello Point is a picnic spot and valley view point . It is present on the top of the eastern ghats from where half of the Kalahandi district is visible including Junagarh, Kalampur block etc. One can receive signal from all telecom services for mobile, therefore it is named as Hello Point.

[[File:Indiravati Dam.jpg|thumb|Indiravati Dam]]

&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Phurlijharan Entrance.jpg|Phurlijharan Entrance
Image:Kalahandi Palace, Bhawanipatna.jpg|Kalahandi Palace, Bhawanipatna
Image:Baringdoro Waterfall.jpg|Baringdoro Waterfall
Image:Sabha Mandap, RajMahal Kalahandi.jpg|Sabha Mandap, Raj Mahal Kalahandi
Image:INSIDE kARLAPAT.jpg|Inside Karlapat Wildlife Sanctuary
File:Rabandoro Reservoir.jpg|Bhatang Padar Dam Reservoir
Image:Jakam Road.jpg|SH-44 Jakham Road
Image:Lakshmi Mandir.PNG|Lakshmi Mandir, Bhawanipatna
Image:Statue Square Old Photo.jpg|Statue Square (1950s)
Image:Grand view of Palace.jpg|Grand view of Kalahandi Palace
File:Bhawanipatna town aerial view.jpg|Bhawanipatna Aerial View
&lt;/gallery&gt;

{{panorama|image=File:Hello Point Valley View.jpg|height=320|caption=Panoramic View of Hello Point &quot;Valley View&quot;|alt=caption=Panoramic View of Hello Point &quot;Valley View&quot;}}

==Media and broadcasting==

[[File:Doordarshan Kendra, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|Doordarshan Kendra, Bhawanipatna]][[File:All India Radio, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|All India Radio, Bhawanipatna]]

'''* Doordarshan Kendra (DD-6)'''

It was started as Low Power Transmission on 15 February 1987 and it had been upgraded to High Power Transmission on 20 January 1992. This 10 KW capacity Doordarshan kendra started functioning in 1992 is one of the few HPT centres among Sambalpur, Cuttack in Odisha. Program generating facility (studio) was started on 3 September 2002. Its one of the three Doordarshan Kendras in the state of Odisha other being Sambalpur and Bhubaneshwar. Its studio became operational in 2002. In 2004, it started broadcasting agriculturerelated programmes sponsored by Ministry of Agriculture and simultaneously began broadcasting agriculture programmes in different HPT (high power transmission) centres of KBK region.

Besides this, it also used to produce programmes to promote tribal heritage, culture, drama besides entertainment and awarenessbuilding programmes for the KBK. It was broadcasting agriculture related programmes from 6 pm to 6.30 pm on every Tuesday, Wednesday and Friday and local culture and entertainment based programmes from 5.30 pm to 6 pm each Monday and Thursday. During the period from 2005 to 2009, the centre has bagged 10 national awards and five nominee prizes for different programmes produced by it.

'''* All India Radio (Akashwani Bhawanipatna 103 FM)'''

All India Radio or Akashwani Bhawanipatna started on 30 December 1993 near Naktiguda, outskirt of the city. It has two transmitters 2x100 KW, MW in Belamal near Pastikudi. Frequency of Transmission is 1206&amp;nbsp;kHz, 248 MTs. It has two studios. Sanctioned strength of Radio station in all cadre is 100. No. Of Casual Announcers in the kendra is 56. Composition of originated programmes targets audience programme for Rural, Women Children, Youth &amp; Senior Citizen, Light &amp; Classical Music, Film Music. Broadcasting of programmes are done in Odia, Hindi, and English languages. The broadcasting covers a popuplation of approx. 18,66,000 Lacs from Kalahandi, Nuapada and nearby districts.
All India Radio, #Bhawanipatna was started on 30 Dec 1993 at Naktiguda, Bhawanipatna i.e, Transmission and Studio and Radio Station at Belamal is a Relay Tower.
Recently FM services have been started at AIR station at frequency of 103&amp;nbsp;MHz

Primary service zone, Kalahandi District and Naupada District.
The station has not only popular in its primary zone, rather its audience from the district of Bolangir, Sonepur, Phulbani, Bargarh, Nawrangpur and Rayagara of Orissa and Raigarh district of Chhattisgarh. Moreover this station serves the districts coming under the capital KBK scheme of the Govt. of India.

Transmission Strength~BEL HMB 140- 2 x 100 KW
Frequency of Broadcast~1206 KHz and 248 mtrs.
Mast Height~ 122 Meters

'''* My Channel (Local Media Group)'''

Digital Cable TV and WiMax provider.

'''* Ortel Cable and Broadband Service'''

Digital Cable TV and Broadband provider.

'''* EM Digital'''

==Festivals==
{{Travel guide|section|date=November 2017}}[[File:Maa Manikeswari Chatar Jatra, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|Chatar Jatra, Bhawanipatna]][[File:Kalahandi Utsav, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|Kalahandi Utsav, Bhawanipatna]]
* '''Dasra (Dasahara)''' : [[Durga Puja|Dasara]] or [[Durga Puja]] is celebrated among [[Hindu]] all over India, but it is very popular in Eastern part of India including [[Odisha]], [[West Bengal]], Assam etc. However, goddess [[Durga]] is known as Shaki (Energy) and most of the goddess based on tribal and Shaki is inspired from goddess Durga. The major goddess of Kalahandi including Manikeswari, Lankeswari, Denteswari, Khameswari, Bhandargharen etc. are seen as a reflection of goddess Durga and most of the major festivals like Chhatar Jatra, Kkandabasha, Budharaja Jatra, etc. are celebrated during Dusra. Dusra is significant in all the Skati Pitha in Kalahandi and is one of the popular festival in the region.

* '''Kalahandi Utsav &quot;Ghumura&quot;''' : It is hosted in Lal Bahadur Shastri stadium

* '''Diel or Deepawali''' : Also popularly known as [[Diwali]] is celebrated in Kalahandi. But this is getting popular due to immigrant business community mainly from Marwadi community, however, slowly it has entered the local stream.
* '''Nuakhai''' : This is typically a local festival prevalent in Western Odisha including Kalahandi. It is inspired from harvesting of new crops and historically came from tribal. But now everybody irrespective of caste, creed and religion celebrate it. There are many kinds of Nuakhai according to tribal culture, out of which Dhan (Rice) Nuakhai is most popularly celebrated.
* The Chhatra Yatra of Goddess Manikeswari of Bhawanipatna, a popular ceremony. (October)

==Market==
[[File:Bhawanipatna Market.jpg|thumb|Bhawanipatna Market]]{{Travel guide|section|date=November 2017}}
* ''' Laxmi Bajar'''

There are several market areas in the city, the biggest one is Laxmi Bajar or Main Market which is at the core of the city. Most of the garment showrooms, costume, jwellery, grocery and fancy shops are found here. Fruits and Vegetables are sold in the inner area of the market mainly near Laxmi Mandir.

* ''' Hatpada'''

Hatpada or Weekly Market is situated near Gandhi Pramod Udyaan (park) is a bi-weekly market that takes place on Tuesday and Saturday where traders from different areas come to sell their goods including vegetables, grocery items, masala &amp; spices, metal products(like utensils etc.), animal and their products like milk products, meat, fishes etc.

* '''Mach bazaar'''

It is located near Ghodaghat bridge where different types of fishes and prawns are sold.

* '''Naktiguda Haat'''
It is a small bajar located on NH-26 mainly known for Grocery and Vegetable items.

==Sports==
[[File:LBS Stadium, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|LBS Stadium, Bhawanipatna]]{{Prose|section|date=November 2017}}
# Lal Bahadur Sashtri Stadium is the biggest stadium in [[Odisha]] according to the total field area. It is present near the Bhawani Talkies, Old cinema hall. The stadium has held various matches including the Ranji Trophy and the Kalahandi Cup. It is maintained by Kalahandi District Athletic Association. Various sports and athletic training are conducted including Cricket, football, Karate etc. There are also several tennis courts in the stadium.
# Indoor Stadium (Gymnasium Hall) is present near the LBS Stadium.
# The Reserve Police Stadium is the home ground of the Odisha Police.
# The Govt. Autonomous College Field is one of the largest field present as compared to all others in Bhawanipatana.
# D.I.E.T. Field is one of the biggest groud available in the city used for club cricket, volleyball and football games.

==Entertainment==
{{Prose|section|date=November 2017}}
[[File:New Star Cineplex, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|New Star Cineplex, Bhawanipatna]][[File:Bhagirathi Park, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|Bhagirathi Park, Bhawanipatna]]
'''Talkies/Cinema Halls'''

* Bhawani Talkies- It was the oldest cinema hall in the city present near L.B.S. Stadium with UFO technology. (Now Closed).
* Satyam Cinema- It is the biggest cinema hall in the city with UFO technology and Dolby Digital sound.
* New Star Cineplex- It is the Largest Multiplex of South-Western Odisha (KBK-South Odisha) with 4 screens (#3D technology) and total seating capacity of 385 with #Mall (New Fashion World), Restaurants, Gaming Zone and many more. It is situated near OMFED plant, SH-16 Raipur road, Bhangabari, Bhawanipatna.

'''Parks and Ecological Gardens'''

* Bhagirathi Park- Present near Shirdi Sai Mandir on SH-44 is a tourist attraction.
* Gandhi Pramod Udyaan- Situated near Statue Square.
* Ecological Park- One of the oldest park present on the outskirt of the city on NH-26.

==Education==
[[File:Government College of Engineering, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|Government College of Engineering, Bhawanipatna]][[File:Government Autonomous College, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|Government Autonomous College, Bhawanipatna]]{{Prose|section|date=November 2017}}[[File:College of Agriculture, Bhawanipatna (OUAT).jpg|thumb|College of Agriculture, Bhawanipatna (OUAT)]][[File:Government Polytechnic College.jpg|thumb|Government Polytechnic College]]

===Technical colleges/institutions===
# [[College of Agriculture, Bhawanipatna]]
# [[Government College of Engineering, Kalahandi]] Bhawanipatna
# Government Polytechnic College Bhawanipatna

===General degree colleges===
# Binayak Residential college, Bhawanipatna
# [[Government Autonomous College, Bhawanipatna]]
# Government Womens College Bhawanipatna
# Jayaprakash Sandhya Mahavidyalaya, Bhawanipatna
# Pragati Degree College, Bhawanipatna
# Saraswati Degree College, Bhawanipatna
# Sastriji Science College, Bhawanipatna

===Schools===
# Hi-Tech Public School Bhwanipatna
# Citizens' Model English Medium Academy, Bhawanipatna
# B.M. High School
# Delhi Public Kids &amp; Primary School, Bhawanipatna
# Kendriya Vidyalaya, Bhawanipatna
# Manikeshwari High School
# Saraswati Sishu Vidya Mandir
# Satya Sai Vidya Mandir
# '''Shastriji model school.(English Medium)'''
# '''Shastriji Siksha Niketan. (Odia Medium)'''
# Vimala Convent School

===Computer Institutions===
# CROWN IT &amp; MANAGEMENT, Mahavirpada, Near Maa Medical Store, Bhawanipatna
# NICE - National Institute of Computer Education.

==Health care==
{{Prose|section|date=November 2017}}[[File:District Headquarters Hospital, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|District Headquarters Hospital, Bhawanipatna]]
[[File:Bhawanipatna Roads (State Highway-44).jpg|thumb|Bhawanipatna Roads]]
There is a medical college and several hospitals including nursing homes in the city which provide good health care services in the city.
There are many ambulance services like National Ambulance Service (dial 102,108), Janani Express running for health services.
Recently State Government has announced a government Medical College in Kalahandi. In response 40 acres of land has been handed over to State Health Dept. for the infrastructure development in Bhangabari which is behind Bhawanipatna Ring Road (Proposed). It is adjacent to SH-16 (Proposed NH).
* '''Kalahandi Medical College &amp; Hospital, Bhangabari, Bhawanipatna'''

State Government had signed with Vedanta Group to build a Medical College and 500 bedded Hospital at Bhangabari near Bhawanipatna. Recently MoU has been signed by State Government and Vedanta Group and land acquisition has been done and soon the work is going to be started.

* '''Sardar Rajas Medical College, Hospital &amp; Research Centre (SRMCH)'''

SRMCH is located {{Convert|17|km||abbr=on}} away from Bhawanipatna on NH-26, it was the only medical college in KBK region earlier enhancing health services in the region. It was established in 2009 with support from WODC and Government of Odisha for conducting Under-graduate Medical Courses.It is a self-financing medical institution with 100 seats. Its now abandoned and case is currently going on by the medical students against Sylvian Trust at Odisha High Court.

* '''District Headquarter Hospital'''

District Headquarter Hospital is the main backbone for the health services in the city and whole district. It has many wards for different kind of patients, there's also a Radio Therapy and Regional Diagnostic centre in the hospital. There is also a blood bank in the hospital campus. Currently a new 6-storey hospital building is under construction.

* '''Maa Manikeswari Multispeciality Hospital'''

Earlier known as Life Worth Hospital it was established in 2004 at Bhawanipatna located near Ghodaghat Chowk (SH-16). It was a branch of Life Worth Super Specialty Hospital present at Raipur. Later it was renamed as Maa Manikeswari Multispeciality Hospital at Bhawanipatna is having all the necessary facilities required during emergency.

* '''Police Hospital'''
Situated in Armed Reserve Police Campus near College Chowk, Bhawanipatna.

'''Nursing Homes'''
* Balaji Nursing Home
Near Balaji Mandir
Pardeshi Para
Bhawanipatna

* Surakhya Nursing Home
Near Red Cross Kalyan Mandap
Bhawanipatna

* Jagannath Netralaya Eye Hospital
Near Balaji Mandir
Pardeshi Para
Bhawanipatna

==Transport==
===Air===
[[File:Utkela Airstrip, Kalahandi.jpg|thumb|Utkela Airstrip, Kalahandi]]
[[Utkela Airstrip]] (VEUK) is present near the city ({{Convert|22|km||abbr=on|disp=comma}}) which is scheduled to be operational with daily flights to state capital [[Bhubaneshwar]] and [[Raipur]] in the coming month of September by private air service provider [[Air Odisha]] under [[UDAN]] scheme by Ministry of Civil Aviation, Govt. of India.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.thehindubusinessline.com/economy/logistics/regional-connectivity-gets-wings-five-airlines-get-to-fly-128-routes/article9607388.ece | title=Regional connectivity gets wings; five airlines get to fly 128 routes | newspaper=The Hindu Business Line | first=Ashwini | last=Phadnis | date=15 January 2018 | accessdate=20 January 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Another one, [[Lanjigarh Airstrip]] ({{Convert|58|km||abbr=on|disp=comma}}) is private airstrip conducting VIP and chartered planes. Other nearby Airport are Swami Vivekananda Airport at Raipur, Chhattisgarh is {{Convert|262|km||abbr=on}} away. Biju Patnaik International Airport in the state capital, Bhubaneswar is 427&amp;nbsp;km away by road and 631&amp;nbsp;km by rail.

===Rail===
{{main|Bhawanipatna railway station}}
[[File:Bhawanipatna Railway.png|thumb|Bhawanipatna Railway Station]]
Bhawanipatna railway station was inaugurated on 12 August 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=News |first=Express |url=http://newindianexpress.com/states/odisha/article587845.ece |title=Bhawanipatna railway station opens |publisher=The New Indian Express |date= |accessdate=2013-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eastcoastrail.indianrailways.gov.in/view_detail.jsp?lang=0&amp;dcd=709&amp;id=0,4,268 |title=East Coast Railway |publisher=Eastcoastrail.indianrailways.gov.in |date=2012-08-12 |accessdate=2013-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is situated on Lanjigarh-Junagarh rail line. Currently there are 3 trains (1 express and 2 passengers) running from Bhawanipatna to Bhubanneshwar, Raipur and Sambalpur.kesinga Railway station is connected by many major cities in India,like Delhi,Mumbai, Chennai,Surat etc.

===Road===
[[File:Government Bus Stand, Bhawanipatna (OSRTC).jpg|thumb|Government Bus Stand, Bhawanipatna (OSRTC)]][[File:Old Bus Stand, Bhawanipatna.jpg|thumb|Old Bus Stand, Bhawanipatna]]
Highways connecting Bhawanipatna to various cities :
*NH-26 - [[Bargarh]] - [[Bolangir]] - Bhawanipatna - [[Nabarangpur]] - [[Koraput]] - [[Vizianagram]] - [[Natavalsa]]
*SH-16 -  Bhawanipatna - [[Borda, Odisha|Borda]] - [[Khariar]] - Raipur
*SH-6 -  Bhawanipatna - [[Chatiguda]] - [[Ambodala]] - [[Muniguda]]
*SH-44 - Bhawanipatna - [[Gunupur]] - [[Thuamul Rampur]] - [[Kashipur, Odisha|Kashipur]] - [[Tikri, Odisha|Tikri]]

Bhawanipatna Bus Stand is one of the biggest bus stand in Odisha present on NH-26. Both Private and Govt. buses are available from here. Bhawanipatna is one of the division of Odisha State Road Transport Corporation (O.S.R.T.C.) that runs Govt. Buses from Bhawanipatna to [[Bhubaneshwar]], [[Vishakhapatnam]], [[Sambalpur]], [[Berhampur]], [[Cuttack]], [[Jeypore]]. Private Buses (A/C Sleeper Coaches) provide transportation facility to different cities in [[Odisha]] and [[Raipur]], [[Durg]] etc. in Chhattisgarh. Newly added taxi facility and auto facility including Biju Gaon Gadi throughout Bhawanipatna and villages nearer to it, is adding an advantage to the transport facility.
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:SH-44.jpg|Hill Town Road (SH-44)
Image:Statue Square, Bhawanipatna.jpg|Statue Square, Bhawanipatna
Image:College Square, Bhawanipatna.jpg|College Square, Bhawanipatna
Image:Gandhi Park Road, BPT.jpg|Gandhi Park Road, BPT
Image:Stadium Road, BPT.jpg|Stadium Road, BPT
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Notable personalities==
* [[Rindo Majhi]]: A freedom fighter in [[Odisha]], who started the Kondha revolution against the British in 1853.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;D.K. Joshi, S. Mund, M.P.Mishra, The Kandha Revolution in Kalahandi, Orissa Review, Aug 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Bhubaneswar Behera]]: Engineer, academic, administrator and author.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Sambit Misra |url=http://www.odiya.org/personality/perslink/bbehera.html |title=Professor Bhubaneswar Behera |publisher=Odiya.org |date=2001-04-25 |accessdate=2013-05-22 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924054808/http://www.odiya.org/personality/perslink/bbehera.html |archive-date=24 September 2015 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ram Chandra Patra]], IAS (retd.): (1919-2013) [[Bureaucrat]], social worker, and administrator acknowledged for his simplicity and administration, and for taking initiative in the [[Indravati]] project.&lt;ref&gt;Samabad, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Keun Mahatabanak Pain, Gana nath Das, The Prajatantra, 2 January 1988&lt;/ref&gt; He was the first IAS from Kalahandi.
* Prafulla Ratha: Awarded a natyarashmi for his contribution to Oriya drama.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.airbpn.org/about.htm |title=Akashvani, Bhawanipatna - Home |publisher=Airbpn.org |accessdate=2013-05-22 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://archive.is/20120802091308/http://www.airbpn.org/about.htm |archivedate=2012-08-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dayanidhi Naik: [[Dalit]] leader and former minister from Kalahandi who became popular for his honesty, public service and road infrastructure development in the region&lt;ref&gt;Kalahandi Express, Sept 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Kishen Pattanayak|Kishan Patnaik]]: Socialist leader.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cpiml.org/liberation/year_2004/November/obituary.htm |title=Obituary |publisher=Cpiml.org |date=2004-10-08 |accessdate=2013-05-22 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130525002428/http://www.cpiml.org/liberation/year_2004/November/obituary.htm |archivedate=2013-05-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://archive.deccanherald.com/deccanherald/sep272004/update2.asp |title=Socialist leader Kishan Patnaik dead - Deccan Herald |publisher=Archive.deccanherald.com |date=2004-09-27 |accessdate=2013-05-22 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150925050906/http://archive.deccanherald.com/deccanherald/sep272004/update2.asp |archive-date=25 September 2015 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; He was born in 1930 into a lower-middle-class family in Kalahandi. Mr Patnaik worked in the youth wing of Samajwadi Yuvjan Sabha and soon rose to become its National president. He was elected to Lok Sabha from Sambalpur at the age of 32 and was one of handful members who turned the Lok Sabha into a real forum to discuss matters of national importance. He was perhaps the first person to bring the issue of starvation death in Kalahandi to the Indian parliament. Mr. Patnaik never lost sight of this fundamental plight of rural India, and securing the right to livelihood for the people on the margin therefore always remained central to his politics and to his vision of development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.hindu.com/2004/09/30/stories/2004093001380300.htm | location=Chennai, India | work=The Hindu | title=Kishan Patnaik remembered | date=30 September 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Power and transmission==
There is a 132/33 kV Grid Station near [[OMFED]] diary on SH-16. Power to this grid comes directly from [[Therubali]] Grid.
Power transmission and maintenance is done by [[Grid Corporation of Odisha]].

There is also a sub-station in Naktiguda, Bhawanipatna. It is maintained by [[Western Electricity Supply Company of Odisha]]

[[File:Sunset at Hilltown.jpg|thumb|Sunset at Hilltown]]
[[File:Bpt.png|thumb|NH BYPASS AND RING ROADS, BHAWANIPATNA]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://kalahandi.nic.in/ Official website of Kalahandi]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060904090411/http://www.mapsofindia.com/maps/orissa/districts/kalahandi.htm Map of Kalahandi]

{{Geographic location
|Centre    = Bhawanipatna
|North     = [[Kesinga]], [[Sambalpur]]
|Northeast = [[Madanpur Rampur]], [[Phulbani]]
|East      = [[Narla]]
|Southeast = [[Rayagada]]
|South     = [[Thuamul Rampur]], [[Koraput]]
|Southwest = [[Nabarangpur]], [[Jeypore]]
|West      = [[Junagarh, Kalahandi|Junagarh]], [[Dharamgarh]]
|Northwest = [[Khariar]], [[Raipur]]
}}
{{Kalahandi district}}
{{Municipalities of Odisha}}
{{Western Odisha}}

[[Category:Cities and towns in Kalahandi district]]</text>
      <sha1>5riqvp22qbcglk3yhs2p3lmwxw6bt9r</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
