  <page>
    <title>Bhuban</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5710070</id>
    <revision>
      <id>916541819</id>
      <parentid>916541264</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-19T12:08:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jatara4256</username>
        <id>37390975</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2018}}
{{Use Indian English|date=October 2018}}
{{more citations needed|date=June 2015}}

{{Infobox settlement
| name                    = Bhuban
| other_name              = 
| nickname                = 
| settlement_type         = city
| image_skyline           = 
| image_alt               = 
| image_caption           = 
| pushpin_map             = India Odisha#India
| pushpin_label_position  = right
| pushpin_map_alt         = 
| pushpin_map_caption     = Location in Odisha, India
| coordinates             = {{coord|20.88|N|85.83|E|display=inline,title}}
| subdivision_type        = Country
| subdivision_name        = {{flag|India}}
| subdivision_type1       = [[States and territories of India|State]]
| subdivision_name1       = [[Odisha]]
| subdivision_type2       = [[List of districts of India|District]]
| subdivision_name2       = [[Dhenkanal district|Dhenkanal]]
| established_title       = &lt;!-- Established --&gt;
| established_date        = 
| founder                 = 
| named_for               = 
| government_type         = 
| governing_body          = 
| unit_pref               = Metric
| area_footnotes          = 
| area_rank               = 
| area_total_km2          = 
| elevation_footnotes     = 
| elevation_m             = 64
| population_total        = 
| population_as_of        = 
| population_rank         = 
| population_density_km2  = auto
| population_demonym      = 
| population_footnotes    = 
| demographics_type1      = Languages
| demographics1_title1    = Official
| demographics1_info1     = [[Odia language|Odia]]
| demographics1_title2    = Major local language
| demographics1_info2     = [[Odia,HO Language]]
| timezone1               = [[Indian Standard Time|IST]]
| utc_offset1             = +5:30
| postal_code_type        = [[Postal Index Number|PIN]]
| postal_code             = 759017
| registration_plate      = OD 06
| website                 = {{URL|odisha.gov.in}} 
| footnotes               = 
}}
'''Bhuban''' is a town and a [[Notified area|NAC]], located in the subdivision of [[Kamakhyanagar]], [[Dhenkanal district]] in the state of [[Odisha]], [[India]]. &lt;!-- On which criteria it is largest.  If on population basis than Manjhaul Village in Begusarai (Bihar) population is nearby 87,000. --&gt;  It is well known for its brass and metal crafts (for example, the Kansa pital basan). The village has a blend of cultures, as both Hindus and Muslims reside here. The majority of the population consists of Hindus. Most of the people usually engage in businesses and agricultural cultivation to earn a living. It is a business hub for the area.

==Demographics==
Bhuban is located at {{Coord|20.88|N|85.83|E|}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fallingrain.com/world/IN/21/Bhuban.html Falling Rain Genomics, Inc - Bhuban]&lt;/ref&gt; It has an average elevation of 64&amp;nbsp;metres (209&amp;nbsp;feet). {{As of|2011}} India [[census]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.censusindia.net/results/town.php?stad=A&amp;state5=999|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040616075334/http://www.censusindia.net/results/town.php?stad=A&amp;state5=999|archivedate=2004-06-16|title= Census of India 2011: Data from the 2011 Census, including cities, villages and towns  (Provisional)|accessdate=2011-12-31|work= |publisher= Census Commission of India}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bhuban had a population of 22,200. Males constitute 52% of the population and females 48%. Bhuban has an average literacy rate of 75%, just higher than the national average of 74%; with male literacy of 80.6% and female literacy of 69%. 10.22% of the population is under 6 years of age.

==Cultural life==

===Festivals===
The festival season starts with the celebration of the following festivals; &quot;Dola Purnima/Dola Melana&quot;,&quot;Holi&quot;,&quot;Raja Mahotshava&quot;,''Khudurukuni'', ''Ganesh Puja'',&quot;Vishwakarma Puja&quot;, ''Dussehra'', ''Laxmi Puja'', ''Kali Puja'', &quot;Kartikeshwara Puja&quot;,''Bali jatra'', and ''Hingula jatra'',&quot;Janmastami&quot;,Sitalasasthi/Lord Shiva Vivah&quot;,&quot;Jagara Jatra&quot;. All the festivals are be celebrated in a grand manner by the residents of Bhuban.

The ''Dussehra'' festival is celebrated for two days and attracts attendees who reside outside of Bhuban.

====Bullocks decoration during the Vijayadashami Festival====
During [[Vijayadashami]], bullocks are decorated using beads, furs, and colorful saddles, and they become a part of the procession. This is not done anywhere else in the world. On the second day of the celebration, the immersion of goddess [[Durga]] takes place. The Bullock festival of Bhuban has a special identity. Legend says, in the ancient days, bullocks were used for both transport and conveyance. The Thoriya community and the Baladia bania community (a community of goldsmiths) of Bhuban used bullocks for trade and business purposes. The Baladia community used to travel miles through the neighbouring villages to trade gold and silver jewelry. So to offer homage to the bullocks, during the Dussehra period, when the bullocks were not engaged in any work by farmers, the Thoriya and Baladia community people would take the bullocks to Gramdevi at Banjari and worship them. Then the bullocks would make a few rotations around the Gramdevi. Subsequently, this became a convention and custom for the people of Bhuban.
	
During the present-day, the bullocks are decorated with ornaments, beads, bells on their neck, and colorful velvet saddles in their back. They are treated with the utmost care and are fed well before they are taken for the worship at ''Gramadevi'' (village goddess), as is the tradition. This shows the rich cultural tradition of &quot;Bhubanians&quot; and their empathetic associations with animals. Then the bullocks are taken for a procession with loud music. The bullocks are not frightened by the loud music. The procession covers about 3 to 4&amp;nbsp;km and runs the whole night. The procession starts around 6&amp;nbsp;PM and goes until the next morning. The ''Arisa Pitha'' is a sweet dish prepared at homes during this festival.

====Bali Jatra====
''Bali Jatra'', which means festival of sand, takes place before the day of [[Kartik Poornima]] around the [[Shiva]] temple (also called the Budheswar temple) on the bank of the Brahmani River with much splendor. Many people gather near the temple for Bali Jatra. People bathe very early in the morning in the Brahmani River and worship [[Lingam|Shiva Lingam]], made up of sand, on the bank of the river. The rituals start from the [[Navami]] of the month and last up to the [[Poornima]] (or full Moon day). Sand idols are worshiped among the elderly women of the village, known as ''Balunga Oshaa'' (rituals of the Sand God) and are performed on the same day. Lord [[Kartikeya|Kartikeswar]] and Lord [[Shiva]] are also worshipped on the [[Kartik Poornima]].  
	
In Oriya history, people used to sail across the river for business and trade, after worshipping the Lord. This is popularly known as ''Boita Bandana'' which means &quot;worship of the boat&quot;. So, on the same day, paper boats are lit with candles and are set afloat in the river as a symbol of remembrance of the past traditions of the [[Sadhaba]] Community (BTBS). People make a dish called ''Bada Osha Bhoga'', made up off raw rice grindings, coconut, and sugar to perform the [[Naivedhya]]. 
	
This is also known as ''Bada Oshaa,'' which means large festival.

====Hingula Jatra====
Another important festival celebrated in Bhuban is the ''Hingula Jatra'', in Chatra Purnima. It is likely to fall in April in the Gregorian calendar.

====Sital Sasthi Shiba Bibaha====
The Sital Sasthi, otherwise known as the Shiva Parvati Bibaha Utschava, is also celebrated in Bhuban at Mahadev Temple in Brudheswar Temple, Before some years ago it is also started at Chhata Matha, and mostly dedicated to started this festival at Sri Baba Ashtasambhu Mahadev temple at Ragadi Baba Astasambhu Temple.

===Special Food Dishes===
There are some special food dishes, namely ''khandu'' and ''chunchi patra'', which are uniquely found in Bhuban village.

====Chunchi Patra====
[[File:Chhunchi Patra.jpg|thumb|Chunchi Patra is a special sweet item, made up of coconut, rice and maida flour.]]
	 
''Chunchi Patra'' is a sweet item made on special occasions and consists of coconut grinding, rice and [[maida flour]]. The mixture is made up of ground rice and maida flour and is flattened on a heated [[tava]] using a moderate flame. The coconut is mixed with sugar or [[jaggery]], and used as ''pura'' (sweet masala) inside the cooked cake.

==Geography==
Bhuban is located at {{Coord|20.88|N|85.83|E|}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fallingrain.com/world/IN/21/Bhuban.html Falling Rain Genomics, Inc - Bhuban]&lt;/ref&gt; It has an average elevation of 64&amp;nbsp;metres (209&amp;nbsp;feet). Bhuban is located at 20°53′N 85°50′E / 20.88°N 85.83°E / 20.88; 85.83. It has an average elevation of 64 meters (209&amp;nbsp;feet). Bhuban is around 90&amp;nbsp;km from all the leading power plants, Kaniha NTPC and Talcher NTPC, and the industrial hub of Angul.

==Education==
Bhuban has several schools and high schools for children's education. Among them, Bhuban Bhitaradiga Patana School, established during 1868, is the oldest institution. There are also convent schools like Bhartiya Vidya Niketan Takshasila, Sri Aurobindo Integral Education Centre, Baji Rout Memorial School, Swami Vivekananda Vidya Niketan, and Saraswati Shishu Bidya Mandir. Bhuban Girls' High School and Nua Bhuban High School provide education to the children of this region. In Bhartiya Vidya Niketan Takshasila and Sri Aurobindo Integral Education Centre, hostel facilities are provided to the students who come from outside of the village.
	
Bhuban High School and Bhuban Girls' High School are rated as the top among the high schools category.
	
Baji Rout Memorial College,&lt;ref&gt;[http://brmcollege.org brmcollege.org]&lt;/ref&gt; Bhuban Women's College, and Bhuban Women's Degree College provides education to the students of Bhuban and its surroundings. There are three English medium schools, such as Binayak English Medium School, St. Xavier's International School, and Rohan International School.

==Other information==
Many social organisations such as the Rama Mandir Puja Committee, the Mahila Sangrami Morcha, the Sathya Sai Seva Anusthana, the Budheswar Puja Committee, the Durga Puja Committee, the Rastriya Swayam Sevak Sangh, the Bajrang Dal, the Vishwa Hindu Parishad, the Akhil Bharatiya Vidyarthi Parishad (ABVP) Bhuban Unit, the Maa Hingula Thakurani Puja Committee, the Ganesh Puja Committee in Bhuban, the Krishak Samaj in Bhuban, and the Tailik Vaishya Samaj (BTBS) in Bhuban have been organizing frequent activities every year.

==Notable people==
* [[Baji Rout]] (born in 1925, martyred 10 October 1938), &quot;the youngest martyr&quot; of India.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Dhenkanal district}}
{{Municipalities of Odisha}}

[[Category:Cities and towns in Dhenkanal district]]</text>
      <sha1>2lgo5byvz64gyxkkqvkx01psdv08zam</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
