  <page>
    <title>Bikramganj</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5710253</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931021487</id>
      <parentid>929565893</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-16T12:57:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>43.230.64.7</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Other schools */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2018}}
{{Use Indian English|date=October 2018}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{cleanup|reason=formatting and sourcing|date=August 2018}}
{{unreliable sources|date=August 2018}}
{{More citations needed|date=August 2012}}
}}
&lt;br /&gt;{{Infobox settlement
| name = Bikramganj
| other_name = 
| settlement_type = City
| image_skyline = 
| image_alt = 
| image_caption = 
| nickname = 
| pushpin_map = India Bihar
| pushpin_label_position = right
| pushpin_map_alt = 
| pushpin_map_caption = Location in Bihar, India
| coordinates = {{coord|25.2|N|84.25|E|display=inline,title}}
| subdivision_type = Country
| subdivision_name = {{flag|India}}
| subdivision_type1 = [[States and territories of India|State]]
| subdivision_type2 = [[List of districts of India|District]]
| subdivision_name1 = [[Bihar]]
| subdivision_name2 = [[Rohtas district|Rohtas]]
| established_title = &lt;!-- Established --&gt;
| established_date = 
| founder = 
| named_for = 
| government_type = 
| governing_body = 
| unit_pref = Metric
| area_footnotes = 
| area_total_km2 = 
| area_rank = 
| elevation_footnotes = 
| elevation_m = 77
| population_total = 175873
| population_as_of = 2001
| population_footnotes = 
| population_density_km2 = auto
| population_rank = 
| population_demonym = 
| demographics_type1 = Languages
| demographics1_title1 = Official
| timezone1 = [[Indian Standard Time|IST]]
| utc_offset1 = +5:30
| postal_code_type = [[Postal Index Number|PIN]]
| postal_code = 802212
| area_code = 06185
| area_code_type = Telephone code
| iso_code = [[ISO 3166-2:IN|IN-BR]]
| registration_plate = 
| website = {{URL|rohtas.nic.in/}}
| footnotes = 
| demographics1_info1 = [[Hindi language|Bhojpuri]], [[Hindi]]
}}

'''Bikramganj''' is a City and a [[notified area]] of [[Rohtas district]], [[Bihar]], India.

== The Place -  A Brief Discription ==
Bikramganj is located at {{Coord|25.2|N|84.25|E|}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fallingrain.com/world/IN/34/Bikramganj.html Falling Rain Genomics, Inc - Bikramganj]&lt;/ref&gt; It has an average elevation of 77&amp;nbsp;metres (252&amp;nbsp;feet).
It is an old local center for commercial activities developed at the cross roads connecting Patna to Sasaram and Buxar to Dehri-on-Sone. This crossing is  known as Bikramganj Chowk - quite an obvious landmark there. It is an emerging rurban hub. Located at a &quot;less industrialised&quot; north of Rohtas district, surrounded with well irrigated fertile fields which bestow Rohtas the title of &quot;Rice bowl of Bihar&quot;. 
There is a good railway station on Dehri road which connects the local populace to the nearby cities of Patna, Sasaram and Varanasi. Various Banks have open their units here as commercial activities are generating growth. 
Once a mundane rural town, Bikramganj is trying best to catch up with the developments happening around and India. A natural river called &quot;Kao&quot; flows through the town and tributes to Ganga in Buxar. People with all religions live here, however Hindu are in majority. &quot;Chhath&quot; is a major festival here although Bikramganj is known for &quot;Durga Puja Mela&quot; when all four roads compete for the best pandals..and young folks throng the Chowk area. 
Local delicacy is &quot;LITTI with Chokkha&quot; and famous sweet item is &quot;Chhena ka khurma&quot;.Nearby towns are Suryapura, Karakat, Koath, Maliyabagh and Sanjhauli. Weather is humid sub tropical, good for Rice cultivation.&quot;Katarni&quot; is famous variety of rice grown around Bikramganj.

==Demographics==
{{As of|2001}} India [[census]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.censusindia.net/results/town.php?stad=A&amp;state5=999|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040616075334/http://www.censusindia.net/results/town.php?stad=A&amp;state5=999|archivedate=2004-06-16|title= Census of India 2001: Data from the 2001 Census, including cities, villages and towns  (Provisional)|accessdate=2008-11-01|work= |publisher= Census Commission of India}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bikramganj had a population of 132765. Males constitute 53% of the population and females 47%. &lt;!-- Bikramganj has an average literacy rate of 75%, greater than the national average of 59.5%; with male literacy of 67% and female literacy of 48%. 19% of the population is under 6 years of age.--&gt;

==Educational Institutions==
Bikramganj has some of the good Govt. aided and Private educational institutions as follows:-

===Anjabit Singh College===
Anjabit Singh College, Bikramganj is one of the prestigious and oldest constituent college of  [[Veer Kunwar Singh University]] (V.K.S.U.), [[Arrah]], established in 1957. By Late Shri Nepal Singh, a resident of Dhawan village of Bikramganj sub-division, Rohtas. At the very outset, Justice Anand Singh and Justice Kainhaiya Singh were the members of the Governing body of this college. Shri Vishwanath Singh was the founder principal of this college. The college is imparting education in [[Arts]] and [[Science]] up to Degree levels along with post-graduate teaching in [[History]] and [[Economics]] in the faculty of Arts. It is also running [[Bachelor of Computer Application|B.C.A.]] course under the vocational/professional program. The college has well-equipped science laboratories and adequate library, separate common rooms and toilets for boys and girls.&lt;ref name=&quot;asc&quot;&gt;http://www.ascollegebikramganj.org/index.php?file=about_us.php&amp;&amp;page=College%20:%20At%20a%20glance&lt;/ref&gt;

===Indu Tapeshwar Singh Mahila College===

===Dr. N Jha Mahila College===
Keeping the betterment of the students when it comes to [[academic]], physical and mental progress paramount is Dr. N Jha Mahila College in Rohtas. From the moment it laid its foundation in the ground the establishment became a recognized educational institute in the city. Its eminence lies not just in the academic success of its students but also in their all-around personality and the enhanced sense of maturity at a young age. Widening their horizon when it comes to their studies as well as their code of conduct when interacting with fellow mates, the college takes the initiative of molding them into better citizens. Overlooking the heart of the city, the college is considerably convenient for a number of its students.&lt;ref name=&quot;dnjmc&quot;&gt;https://www.justdial.com/Rohtas/Dr-N-Jha-Mahila-Collage-Near-Mono-Baba-Khuttiya-Bikramganj/9999P6188-6188-180125191911-E8Q7_BZDET?xid=Um9odGFzIENvbGxlZ2VzIEJpa3JhbWdhbmo=&lt;/ref&gt;

===DAV Public School===
Established in the year 2008, DAV Public School is located in Rural area of [[Bihar]] state/ut of [[India]]. School is providing Secondary level education and is being managed by Private Unaided Organisation.
The medium of instruction is English language and school is [[Co-educational]].
School is affiliated with [[Central Board of Secondary Education]] (CBSE) for secondary level.&lt;ref name=&quot;davs&quot;&gt;https://www.studyapt.com/school-dav-public-school-bikramganj-1&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sr. Sec. High School Tenduni===
Established in the year 1975, Sr. Sec. H S Tenduni is located in [[Urban area]] of [[Bihar]] state/ut of [[India]]. In Tenduni area of Bikramganj block of [[Rohtas district|Rohtas]] district.
School is providing Secondary, High Secondary (9-12) level education and is being managed by the Department of Education.
The medium of instruction is Hindi language and school is [[Co-educational]].
School is affiliated with State Board [[Bihar School Examination Board]] for both secondary and high secondary level.&lt;ref name=&quot;sshst&quot;&gt;https://www.studyapt.com/school-h-s-tenduni-bikramganj-rohtas&lt;/ref&gt;

===Utkarmit High School, Ghusia Kalan===
Established in the year 1950, upgraded H S Ghusia Kalan is located in [[Rural]] area of [[Bihar]] state/ut of [[India]]. In Ghusia Kalan area of Bikramganj block of [[Rohtas district|Rohtas]] district.
School is providing Secondary level education and is being managed by the Department of Education.
The medium of instruction is Hindi language and school is [[Co-educational]].
School is affiliated with State Board [[Bihar School Examination Board]] for secondary level.&lt;ref name=&quot;uhsgk&quot;&gt;https://www.studyapt.com/school-upgraded-h-s-ghusiya-kala-rohtas-br&lt;/ref&gt;

===Krishna Sudarshan Public School===
Established in the year 2008, Krishna Sudarshan Public School is located in [[Urban area]] of Bihar state/ut of India. School is providing Upper [[Primary education|primary]] level education and is being managed by Unrecognised Body.
The medium of instruction is English language and school is [[Co-educational]].This school is located near south side of Bikramganj Railway Station. Some alumni from this school are Rajnish Gulandhiya ,Ankit Aditya ,Vishwajeet Mouar, Aman Lal ,Amit singh
&lt;ref name=&quot;ksps&quot;&gt;https://www.studyapt.com/school-krishna-sudarshan-public-schol-bikramganj-rohtas&lt;/ref&gt;

===St. S.n. Global School===
The [[co-educational]] English medium school provides basic infrastructures to its students like classrooms for all classes separately, laboratory, library facilities, having its own playground to encourage its students in various indoor and outdoor sports and games. Admissions in English medium under CBSE syllabus is provided by the school from Class 1 to High School.&lt;ref name=&quot;stsn&quot;&gt;http://www.indiastudychannel.com/schools/61315-St-SN-Global-School-Bikramganj-Sasaram-Rohtas.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The Divine Public School===
The Divine Public School Affiliated to C.B.S.E Delhi is run and managed by &quot;Radhika Sriniwas Educational and Welfare Trust&quot; a registered academic and social institution. The school was started in April 2011. This school is a unique and quality oriented [[co-educational]] school for the sake of children from standard Pre Nursery to class X, located in calm, pleasant and pollution free atmosphere at Bikramganj [[Rohtas district|Rohtas]], [[Bihar]]. It is designed to impact integrated education to children. Highly motivated, dedicated and competent staffs are selected to create a better academic atmosphere. The system of the D.P.S Bikramganj [[Rohtas district|Rohtas]], [[Bihar]] is completely based on the [[Central Board of Secondary Education]] (C.B.S.E) pattern. During this modern computer era, it is very much essential to have a proper and good knowledge of computer. Nowadays, computer is part and parcel of life. The School is well-equipped computer lab to provide enough practical knowledge of computer. Availability of generator fulfills the scarcity of electricity.&lt;ref name=&quot;tdps&quot;&gt;http://thedivinepublicschool.com/academic.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other schools===
* Vinyada Academy 
* Pragya Punj Public School 
* Primary school tenduni boys
* Motherland Convent High School
* Kanya High School Tenduni
* Army Public School Bikramganj
* Montessori Askamini Academy
* The Cambridge Residential School
* Govt Ramadhar Singh High School
* D.K. Dolphin School
* St. Mary Academy
* Stewart Public School
* PATEL college Bikramganj Rohtas
*Swami vivekanand public school
*Divine Gurukul Public School,Natwar

==See also==
*[[Ghusian]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}



[[Category:Cities and towns in Rohtas district]]</text>
      <sha1>8i7f0vrvj8wce0p05qcginygwvxten1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
