  <page>
    <title>Birgunj</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5743421</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937472119</id>
      <parentid>937472079</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-25T06:57:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>49.126.190.93</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
| name                            = Birgunj
| native_name                     = बीरगञ्ज
| native_name_lang                = nep&lt;!-- ISO 639-2 code e.g. &quot;fr&quot; for French. If more than one, use {{lang}} instead --&gt;
| settlement_type                 = [[Metropolitan City]]
| image_skyline                   = Indian-Nepalese border gate at Birgunj.jpg|motto
| image_map                       = 
| map_alt                         = 
| map_caption                     = 
| pushpin_map                     = Nepal Province2#Nepal
| pushpin_label_position          = bothumb|
| pushpin_map_alt                 = 
| pushpin_mapsize                 = 250px
| pushpin_map_caption             = Location of Birgunj in Province No. 2
| coordinates                     = {{coord|27|0|N|84|52|E|region:NP_type:city_source:enwiki-GNS|display=inline,title}}
| coor_pinpoint                   = 
| coordinates_footnotes           = 
| subdivision_type                = Country
| subdivision_name                = {{flag|Nepal}}
| subdivision_type1               = [[Nepalese Federal States|Province]]
| subdivision_type2               = [[Districts of Nepal|District]]
| subdivision_name1               = [[Province No. 2]]
| subdivision_name2               = [[Parsa District|Parsa]]
| established_title               = Founded
| established_date                = 1897
| founder                         = [[Bir Shamsher Jang Bahadur Rana|Bir Shamsher JBR]]
| government_footnotes            = 
| government_type                 = 
| governing_body                  = 
| leader_title                    = [[Mayor]]
| leader_name                     = Mr. Vijay Sarawagi ([[Federal Socialist Forum, Nepal|FSFN]])
| leader_title1                   = [[Deputy Mayor]]
| leader_name1                    = Ms. Shanti Karki ([[Nepali Congress|NC]])
| unit_pref                       = Metric
| area_footnotes                  = 
| area_magnitude                  = &lt;!-- &lt;ref&gt; &lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;
| area_total_km2                  = 75.24
| area_land_km2                   = 
| area_water_km2                  = 
| area_water_percent              = 
| area_urban_km2                  = 
| area_rural_km2                  = 
| area_metro_km2                  = 
| area_rank                       = 
| area_blank1_title               = 
| area_blank1_km2                 = 
| area_blank2_title               = &lt;!-- square kilometers --&gt;
| area_blank2_km2                 = 
| area_note                       = 
| dimensions_footnotes            = 
| length_km                       = 19
| width_km                        = 4
| elevation_footnotes             = 
| elevation_m                     = 92
| population_total                = 204,816
| population_as_of                = 2011
| population_footnotes            = 
| population_density_km2          = auto
| population_demonym              = Birganj
| population_note                 = 
| demographics_type1              = Languages
| demographics1_title1            = Official
| demographics1_info1             = [[Nepali language|Nepali]], [[Bhojpuri language|Bhojpuri]]
| timezone1                       = [[Nepal Standard Time|NST]]
| utc_offset1                     = +5:45
| timezone1_DST                   = 
| utc_offset1_DST                 = 
| postal_code_type                = [[Postal code]]
| postal_code                     = 44300, 44301
| area_code                       = 051
| area_code_type                  = 
| iso_code                        = 
| website                         = [http://birgunjmun.gov.np birgunjmun.gov.np]
| footnotes                       = 
| image_size                      = 
| etymology                       = 
| area_urban_footnotes            = &lt;!-- &lt;ref&gt; &lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;
| area_rural_footnotes            = &lt;!-- &lt;ref&gt; &lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;
| area_metro_footnotes            = &lt;!-- &lt;ref&gt; &lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;
| official_name                   = 
| Official Android App            = [https://apk2mod2018.blogspot.com/2019/09/birgunj-metropolitan-city-app-apk.html Download Now]
}}
[[File:Narayani Rangasala.jpg|thumb|Narayani Rangasala]]
[[File:Birgunj pokhra decoration on chaat.jpg|thumb|Ghadiarwa Pokhari]]
[[File:Mayasthan bb an dashin.jpg|thumb|Maisthan Mandir]]
[[File:Ghantaghar in Birgunj.jpg|thumb|upright|Ghantaghar]]

'''Birgunj''' (''also'' '''Birganj'''; {{lang-ne|बीरगंज}}) is a metropolitan city in [[Parsa District]] in [[Province No. 2]] of southern Nepal. It lies {{Convert|135|km|mi|abbr=on}} south of the capital [[Kathmandu]], attached in the north to [[Raxaul]] in the border of the Indian [[States and territories of India|state]] of [[Bihar]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cgibirgunj.org/page/detail/1|title=ABOUT BIRGUNJ|website=www.cgibirgunj.org|access-date=2017-07-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; As an entry point to Nepal from [[Patna]] and [[Kolkata]], it is known as the &quot;Gateway to Nepal&quot;. The town has significant economic importance for Nepal as most of the trade with India is via Birgunj and the Indian town of [[Raxaul]]. [[Tribhuvan Highway]] links Birgunj to Nepal's capital, [[Kathmandu]]. It was declared a [[Metropolitan City]] on 22 May 2017 along with [[Biratnagar]] and [[Pokhara]]. Birgunj is currently the second largest city in the [[Terai]] region of Nepal after Biratnagar and birgunj is the sixth most populated [[metropolis]] of the nation.

==Etymology==
Birgunj was established as a conglomerate of several villages in and around Gahawa Mai Temple. Gahawa Mai Temple remains the epicenter of the town. The settlement was named after the Rana Prime Minister [[Bir Shamsher Jang Bahadur Rana|Bir Shamsher]], thus acquiring the name Birgunj.

==Demographics==
According to the 2011 [[Census]], Birgunj had a population of 133,238.&lt;ref name=pop&gt;{{cite web|title=Nepal population statistics|url=http://www.geohive.com/cntry/nepal.aspx|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150704051158/http://www.geohive.com/cntry/nepal.aspx|archivedate=2015-07-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the second biggest city in [[Terai]] and the fifth biggest city in Nepal after [[Kathmandu]], [[Pokhara]], [[Lalitpur, Nepal|Lalitpur]], and [[Biratnagar]]. It serves as the headquarters of the [[Parsa District]]. Although Nepali is the official language, the native [[Bhojpuri]] language is the main language spoken. In addition to Bhojpuri, several other languages are spoken, including [[Maithili language|Maithili]], [[Hindi]], [[English language|English]] and [[Newari language|Newari]].

==History==

Birgunj was founded in 1897 by 3rd Rana Prime Minister [[Bir Shamsher Jang Bahadur Rana]]; the ancient name was Gahawa.

On 18 May 2006, the parliament of Nepal declared that the country would become a secular state. This led to unrest by Hindu fundamentalist groups across Nepal; the town of Birgunj was forced to close for nearly two years and was disturbed for more than 10 years .&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0530/p04s01-wosc.html Nepal's Hindu majority is denouncing the recent move to end Nepal's longtime status as the world's only Hindu state]. ''The Christian Science Monitor''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
Birgunj is a major business centre of Nepal, especially for trade with India. Almost all trade with India occurs through this route. The Indian border town of [[Raxaul]] has become one of the busiest towns for heavy transportation due to high trade volume. The {{Convert|29|km|mi|abbr=on}} distance from Birgunj to [[Pathlaiya]] is the busiest highway in Nepal. Most industries are represented, including agriculture, chemicals, textiles, wood, petroleum, etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/asia-pacific/2010/05/2010525101847265629.html|title=Birgunj: Nepal's 'drug capital'|publisher=english.aljazeera.net}}&lt;/ref&gt; Almost 56% of the total products of Birgunj are exported to the [[Indian state]] of [[Bihar]].&lt;ref&gt;CPS, NEPAL 2013, Annual UN Report Bureau.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Transport==
Birgunj was built as the closest Nepalese city connecting the capital Kathmandu with India. Birgunj railway station was connected by the [[Nepal Government Railway (NGR)]] to Raxaul station in Bihar across the border with India. The {{Convert|47|km|mi|abbr=on}} railway extended north to [[Amlekhganj]] in Nepal. It was built in 1927 by the British but discontinued beyond Birgunj in December 1965.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nepal.saarctourism.org/transportation.html|title=Transport in Nepal|publisher=nepal.saarctourism.org|access-date=2008-12-20|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081229011939/http://nepal.saarctourism.org/transportation.html|archive-date=2008-12-29|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rail Transport===
Trains run to major cities of India from Raxaul station (in India, adjacent to Birgunj) and Sugauli station (17 miles from Raxaul) including the [[Satyagrah Express]] to [[Delhi]], [[Mithila Express]] to [[Kolkata]], Lokmanya Tilak express to [[Mumbai]], and HYD-RXL express to [[Hyderabad, India|Hyderabad]]. Thus, Birgunj has direct connectivity to major Indian cities like - Patna, Varanasi, Allahabad, Kolkata, New Delhi, Mumbai, Bhopal, Amritsar, Guwahati, Bhopal, Lucknow, Gorakhpur, Kanpur, Ranchi, Raipur, Nagpur, Hyderabad, etc.

===Air Transport===
Birgunj is served by [[Simara Airport]], which lies 9 miles North of the city. Regular flights operate between Kathmandu &amp; Simara. The Second International Airport of Nepal in under construction at Nijgadh (22 miles from Birganj). There are plans to connect the new airport, Birgunj and Kathmandu via a &quot;Fasttrack&quot; expressway after its completion. This is expected to reduce travel times between the capital and the commercial capital, Birgunj

===Buses===
There are regular bus services to all major cities and towns in Nepal including Kathmandu, Pokhara, Patan, Bhaktapur, Biratnagar, Dharan, Butwal, Nepalgunj, Dhangadhi, Kakarvitta, Janakpur, Bhairahawa(Lumbini), Bharatpur(Chitwan), etc.
Local bus services provide transportation inside the city and into its vicinity. Night buses from Birgunj to Kathmandu are the most luxurious bus services in all over Nepal. Birgunj bus park is the centre to find buses for any route,

===Tanga===
Horse driven carts locally called Tanga have historically been the mode of transport for the Madheshi people. Today it survives as a popular transportation vehicle between Birgunj and its sister city Raxaul.

===Cargo===
The {{Convert|6|km|mi|abbr=on}} railway track from Raxaul to Birgunj was converted to [[broad gauge]] two years after the Indian railways converted the track to Raxaul inside India to broad gauge. Now, broad gauge railway line connects Raxaul to the [[Sirsiya]] (Birgunj) Inland Container Depot (ICD) that became fully operational in 2005. Talks have been held to reopen the railway route from Birgunj to Amlekhganj in Nepal by converting it to broad gauge because of its socio-economic importance.

Goods are transported to and from India via Birgunj dry port, which is the key terminal of surface cargo delivery to Nepal. This cargo point on the south connects the heart of the country, Kathmandu, via another key industrial city, [[Hetauda]]. It is also served by [[Tribhuvan Highway]], extending from the Indian border at Raxaul through Birgunj and Hetauda to Kathmandu with frequent bus service. [[Simara Airport]] — {{Convert|9|mi|km|abbr=on}} north near the highway in [[Pipara Simara]], [[Bara district]] — offers scheduled flights to Kathmandu.

India and Nepal have an open border with no restrictions on the movement of their citizens. There is a [[Geography of Nepal#Border crossing|customs checkpoint]] for the movement of goods and third country nationals.{{Clarify|date=August 2014|reason=How do they prove they are from Nepal or India without a passport?}}

==Places of interest==

[[File:Ghantaghar Birgunj.JPG|thumb|upright|Ghantaghar Birgunj]]
*[[Gadhimai Temple]]
*[[Parsa Wildlife Reserve]]
*[[Narayani Stadium]]
{{Cleanup list|date=November 2017}}
*[[Gahawa Mai Temple]]
*[[Bindwasini Mai Temple]]
*[[Bhiswa Hillock]]
*[[Ghantaghar (Birgunj)|Ghantaghar]]
*[[Shankaracharya Gate]]
*[[Vishwa Hindu Parishad Park]](Shri Narshing Temple Pipra Math)
*[[Ghariarwa Pokhari|Ghadiarwa Pokhari]]
*[[Birta Mai Temple]]

==Sports==
The city has its own stadium, [[Narayani Stadium]] which is Nepal's second largest stadium after Dasarath Rangasala. The stadium has capacity of 15000 seats. In recent times the stadium is in poor condition.
A national level [[Cricket]] Ground is also located beside the Narayani Stadium. The cricket ground has top class outfield and a better [[Cricket Pitch]]. National level and Regional level cricket tournament are regularly held here. Every year day night [[T20 Cricket]] Tournament are held using temporary flood light towers. Day night Cricket match in Nepal was first played here.

The city is known as the cricket hub of Nepal and has Adarsh Nagar Stadium. [[Nepal national cricket team]]'s players [[Haseem Ansari]], [[Aarif Sheikh]] [[Avinash Karn]] and [[Irshad Ahmed]] hail from Birgunj. Cricket is popular and is played more than any other games and sports.

==Education==

Education was started in town with the establishment of Trijuddha School by [[Juddha Shumsher Jang Bahadur Rana]] during his regime.

Thakuram Multiple Campus is the first campus (outside Kathmandu valley) in town as well as in Narayani zone. This city has made a rapid development in the field of education by the establishment of many schools and colleges like Gyan Jyoti Higher Secondary School, [[Gautam School]], GHP secondary school, Shree Adarsha Secondary School, Kadambari Academy, National Infotech college, Birganj College Pvt. Limited, Gurukul Academy, Gyanda Academy, Siddharth College, BPC College, Hari Khetan Campus, Gautam secondary school,Shri Narshingh Madhyamik Vidhalaya, etc. It has many commerce college and a medical college, National Medical College Birganj,The Himal Institute of Health Science, where students from all over Nepal and India come to study.

== Media ==
Birgunj has many [[FM broadcasting|FM]] [[Community radio]] stations including Narayani FM 103.8Mhz, Terai FM, Radio Birgunj, Bhojpuriya FM, Indreni FM, Radio Bindas, Birgunj Musical FM, City FM,Aawaz FM, Public FM etc. It is covered by the local television station, [[Birgunj Television Channel|Birgunj Television]] (BTV). Many local newspapers like Prateek, Loktimes Daily, Kripa, Bhojpuri Time, Jana Aawaz etc. are published. [[TEDxBirgunj]] was successfully held on 17 December,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://facebook.com/tedxbirgunj | title=TEDxBirgunj}}&lt;/ref&gt; that was the first ever [[TED (conference)|TED]] event of Terai region of Nepal.

== Health ==
Narayani Sub-regional Hospital is one of the oldest government hospitals of Nepal. National Medical College&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.nmcbir.edu.np | title=National Medical College Birgunj}}&lt;/ref&gt; under TU and Kedia Dental College&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mbkediadentalcollege.com&lt;/ref&gt; also under TU are two major institutions providing health facilities.  There are many other big and small hospitals, and international standard diagnostic centres throughout the city such as Asharam Hospital, Gandak hospital, Advance Medicare Hospital, Kedia eye hospital, Bhawani Hospital, Mangalam Diagnostic Centre, Vision Diagnostic Private Limited,vayodhya hospital etc. The area extending from Chhapakaiya ward No. 3 up to Gandak is full of private nursing homes and clinics. Mostly the people from village area of Parsa, Bara and Raxaul come here for check ups.

== Culture ==
[[Ganesh Chaturthi]], [[Holi]], [[Teej]], Krishan Janmasthami, [[Maha Shivratri]], [[Durgapuja]], [[Chhath]], [[Dipawali]], [[Eid al-Fitr|Eid]] are major festivals celebrated in Birgunj. Small proportion of the religious diversity of Birgunj is occupied by [[Buddhist]]s. Thus [[Buddha Jayanti]] is also celebrated throughout the city. The culture of this city is not limited to religious diversity but ethnic diversity is found too. People of Madheshi ethnicity occupies greater portion of population which includes [[caste]]s like [[Kurmi]], [[Gupta]], [[Sah (caste)|Sah]], [[Singh]], [[Yadav]], Mahato,Rauniyar etc. [[Marwari people|Marwari]] people who migrated from [[Rajasthan]] are also in great number involved in many economic sectors.There are also large number of muslims in town celebrating their own festivals like Iid,Bakrid etc.

==See also==

* [[Pokhara]]
* [[Butwal]]
* [[Dharan, Nepal|Dharan]]
* [[Janakpur]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://thestatedaily.com The State Daily]
* [http://yatradaily.com Yatra Daily]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20180325003816/http://www.npdailynews.com/ NP Dailynews]
*[https://www.apk2mod.xyz/2019/09/birgunj-metropolitan-city-app-apk.html Birgunj Metropolitan City App]

{{Parsa District}}

[[Category:Populated places in Parsa District]]
[[Category:Transit and customs posts along the India–Nepal border]]
[[Category:Points for exit and entry of nationals from third countries along the India–Nepal border]]
[[Category:Metropolitan cities in Nepal]]
[[Category:Nepal municipalities established in 1953]]</text>
      <sha1>fr4dxipi8e4qkh68io696ifys6o9e3d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
