  <page>
    <title>Bobsleigh</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39693</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932120271</id>
      <parentid>932118398</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-23T15:55:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>81.147.178.44</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Origins */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox sport
|image      = USA I in heat 1 of 2 man bobsleigh at 2010 Winter Olympics 2010-02-20.jpg
|imagesize  = 300px
|caption    = The two-man [[United States]] bobsleigh team at the [[2010 Winter Olympics|2010]] in [[Vancouver]], [[Canada]]  
|union      = [[International Bobsleigh and Skeleton Federation]] ({{lang-fr|Fédération Internationale de Bobsleigh et de Tobogganing}})
|nickname   = Bobsled, Bob, King's Class
|first      = 1870s
|registered =   
|clubs      = 
|contact    = None
|team       = Teams of 2 or 4
|mgender    = Yes, but usually in separate competitions
|category   = Winter sport, time trial
|equipment  = High-tech sleigh, helmet
|venue      = [[List of bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton tracks|Bobsleigh tracks]]
|obsolete   =
|olympic    = since [[Bobsleigh at the 1924 Winter Olympics|1924]]
}}

'''Bobsleigh''' or '''bobsled''' is a team [[winter sport]] that involves making timed runs down narrow, twisting, banked, iced tracks in a gravity-powered [[sled|sleigh]]. International bobsleigh competitions are governed by the [[International Bobsleigh and Skeleton Federation]], also known as FIBT from the French {{lang|fr|Fédération Internationale de Bobsleigh et de Tobogganing}}.  National competitions are often governed by bodies such as the [[United States Bobsled and Skeleton Federation]] and [[Bobsleigh Canada Skeleton]].

The first bobsleds were built in [[St. Moritz]], Switzerland, in the late 19th century by wealthy tourists from [[Victorian Britain]] who were staying at the [[Badrutt's Palace Hotel|Palace Hotel]] owned by [[Caspar Badrutt]]. The early sleds were adapted from boys' delivery sleds and [[toboggan]]s. These eventually evolved into bobsleighs, [[luge]]s and [[skeleton (sport)|skeleton]]s. Initially the tourists would race their hand-built contraptions down the narrow streets of [[St. Moritz]], however, as collisions increased growing opposition from St Moritz residents led to bobsledding being eventually banned from public highways. In the winter of 1884, Badrutt had a purpose-built run constructed near the hamlet of Cresta. The [[Cresta Run]] remains the oldest in the world and is the home of the St. Moritz Tobogganing Club. It has hosted two [[Olympic Winter Games]] and is still in use.

Modern Bobsleigh teams compete to complete a downhill route in the fastest times. An aggregate time from several runs is used to determine the winners. The four-man event has been featured since the first Winter Games in [[1924 Winter Olympics|1924]] in [[Chamonix]], [[France]]. The only exception was the [[1960 Winter Olympics|1960 games]] in [[Squaw Valley, Placer County, California|Squaw Valley]] when the organizing committee decided not to build a track to reduce costs.  The two-man event was introduced at the [[1932 Winter Olympics|1932 games]] and a two-woman event was first contested at the [[2002 Winter Olympics]].

==Etymology==
The name is derived from the action some early competitors adopted of bobbing back and forth inside their sleds to increase speed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/70808/bobsledding |title=bobsledding (sport) - Britannica Online Encyclopedia |encyclopedia=Britannica.com |accessdate=2014-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Origins===
[[Image:Bobfahrer Davos.jpg|thumb|left|The Swiss bobsleigh team from [[Davos]], c. 1910]]
[[Image:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-09740-0004, Oberhof, II. Wintersportmeisterschaften, Bobfahren.jpg|thumb|left|An East German bobsleigh in 1951, [[Oberhof bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|Oberhof track]], [[East Germany]]]]
Although [[sledding]] on snow or ice had long been popular in many northern countries, the origins of bobsleighing as a modern sport are relatively recent. Its foundation began when hotelier [[Caspar Badrutt]] (1848–1904) convinced some wealthy [[Grand Tour|English regulars]] to remain through the entire winter at his hotel in the [[mineral spa]] town of [[St. Moritz]], Switzerland. He had been frustrated that his hotel was only busy during the summer months. By keeping his guests entertained with food, alcohol, and activities, he quickly established the concept of &quot;winter resorting&quot;. Within a few years, wintering at Badrutt's St Moritz hotel became very fashionable in [[Victorian Britain]]. However, with increased numbers this led some guests to search for new diversions. In the early 1870s some adventurous Englishmen began adapting boys' delivery sleds for recreational purposes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Badrutt &quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Grand Hotels: Reality and Illusion|first=Elaine|last=Denby|publisher=Reaktion Books|year=2002|ISBN= 9781861891211|pages=128-131}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

However, when they began colliding with pedestrians in the icy lanes, alleyways and roads of St Moritz, this led to the invention of &quot;steering means&quot; for the sleds. The basic bobsleigh (bobsled) consisted of  two cresta's (skeleton sleds) attached together with a board that had a steering mechanism at the front. The ability to steer meant the sleds could make longer runs through the town. Longer runs also meant higher speeds on curves. Local sentiments varied about these informal competitions but eventually complaints grew so vociferous that Badrutt had to do something. His solution was to build a basic natural ice run for his guests outside the town near the small hamlet named Cresta in the lates 1870s. Badrutt took action because he did not want to make enemies in the town and he had worked hard and investing a lot of time and money in popularizing wintering in St. Moritz so he was not going to let customers stop coming due to boredom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Badrutt &quot;/&gt;

===Competitive discipline===
Formal competitions started down the natural ice [[Cresta Run]] in 1884, which was built in an annual partnership between guests and local people. The run, which is still in operation {{as of | 2014 | lc = on}}, has served as a host track for [[Skeleton (sport)|skeleton]] at two [[Winter Olympics]] ([[Skeleton at the 1928 Winter Olympics|1928]] and [[Skeleton at the 1948 Winter Olympics|1948]]). As one of the few natural weather tracks in the world, it does not use artificial refrigeration. It is not known how much the original track evolved in the early years as the three sports matured and stabilized. The first club formed in 1897, and the first purpose-built track solely for bobsleds opened in 1902 outside St Moritz. Over the years, bobsleigh tracks evolved from straight runs to twisting and turning tracks. The original wooden sleds&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=g_EDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA543&amp;dq=Popular+Mechanics+1931+curtiss&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=3jf_TOt2o96dB_u50OkJ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwBTgK#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true &quot;Rounding The Zigzag Turn Of A Bobsleigh Run&quot;, April 1932, Popular Science] photo of wooden bobsleigh used in early 1930s&lt;/ref&gt; gave way to streamlined fiberglass and metal ones.

The ''[[International Bobsleigh and Skeleton Federation]]'' (FIBT) was founded in 1923.  Men's four-man bobsleigh appeared in the first ever [[Winter Olympic Games]] in 1924, and the men's two-man bobsleigh event was added in 1932.  Though not included in the [[1960 Winter Olympics]], bobsleigh has featured in every [[Winter Olympics]] since. Women's bobsleigh competition began in the US in 1983 with two demonstration races in Lake Placid, New York, one held in February and the second held during the World Cup races in March 1983. Women's two-woman bobsleigh made its Olympic debut at the [[2002 Winter Olympic Games]]. Bobsleigh is also contested at American, European, and World Cup championships.

Germany and Switzerland have proven the most successful bobsleighing nations measured by overall success in European, World, World Cup, and Olympic championships. Since the 1990s Germans have dominated in international competition, having won more medals than any other nation. Italy, Austria, United States and Canada also have strong bobsleigh traditions.

Bobsleighs can attain speeds of {{Convert|150|km/h|mph|abbr=on}}, with the reported world record being {{Convert|201|km/h|mph|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.teamsontour.com/activities/bobsleigh.asp|title=Bobsleigh Activity {{!}} TeamsOnTour.com|website=www.teamsontour.com|access-date=2016-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Bobsleigh competitors are very noble&quot;. The World Fair Play Trophy was awarded to an Italian bobsleigh competitor, [[Eugenio Monti]], 1964, then 30 years later to an Australian bobsleigh competitor, Justin McDonald, 1994.

==Modern era==
===Tracks===
[[Image:Bobbahn-Altenberg-4.JPG|thumb|[[Altenberg bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|Altenberg track]], Germany]]
{{Details|List of bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton tracks}}
Modern tracks  are made of [[concrete]], coated with ice. They are required to have at least one straight section and one labyrinth (three turns in quick succession without a straight section). Ideally, a modern track should be {{convert|1200|to(-)|1300|m|ft}} long and have at least fifteen curves.  Speeds may exceed {{convert|120|km/h|mph}}, and some curves can subject the crews to as much as 5 [[g-force|''g'']].

Some bobsleigh tracks are also used for [[luge]] and skeleton competition.

Some tracks offer tourists rides in bobsleighs, including those at [[Sigulda bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|Sigulda]], Latvia; Innsbruck-Igls, Austria; [[Canada Olympic Park bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|Calgary]], [[Alberta]], Canada; [[Whistler Sliding Centre|Whistler]], [[British Columbia]], Canada; [[Lillehammer Olympic Bobsleigh and Luge Track|Lillehammer]], Norway; [[Cesana Pariol]], Italy; [[Mt. Van Hoevenberg Olympic Bobsled Run|Lake Placid]], US;  [[Utah Olympic Park Track|Salt Lake City]], [[Utah]], US and [[La Plagne bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|La Plagne]], France.

===Sleighs and crews===
[[Image:Army Bobsleigh on a wall.jpg|thumb|Team USA on a wall, [[Shauna Rohbock]] (pilot) and [[Valerie Fleming]] (brakes) during their [[2006 Winter Olympics|2006]] silver run on [[Cesana Pariol]], Italy]]
Modern day sleighs combine light metals, steel runners, and an aerodynamic composite body.  Competition sleighs must be a maximum of {{convert|3.80|m|ft}} long (4-crew) or {{convert|2.70|m|ft}} long (2-crew).  The runners on both are set at {{convert|0.67|m|ft}} [[Rail gauge|gauge]].  Until the weight-limit rule was added in 1952, bobsleigh crews tended to be very heavy to ensure the greatest possible speed.  Nowadays, the maximum [[weight]], including crew, is {{convert|630|kg|lb}} (4-man), {{convert|390|kg|lb}} (2-man), or {{convert|340|kg|lb}} (2-woman), which can be reached via the addition of metal weights.  The bobsleighs themselves are designed to be as light as possible to allow dynamic positioning of mass through the turns of the bobsleigh course.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Niller|first=Eric|title=U.S. Olympic Team Gets BMW Bobsleds|url=http://news.discovery.com/adventure/extreme-sports/bmw-designed-bobsleds-offer-us-team-sleek-speed-140203.htm#mkcpgn=rssnws1|accessdate=3 February 2014|newspaper=[[Discovery News]]|date=4 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although bobsleigh crews once consisted of five or six people, they were reduced to two- and four-person sleighs in the 1930s. The crew has a pilot, a brakeman, and pushers. Athletes are selected based on their speed and strength, which are necessary to push the sleigh to a competitive speed at the start of the race. Pilots must have the skill, timing, and finesse to steer the sleigh along the path, or &quot;line&quot;, that will produce the greatest speed.

In modern bobsleighs, the steering system consists of two metal rings that actuate a pulley system located in the forward cowling that turns the front runners. For example, to turn left, the pilot would pull the left ring. Only subtle steering adjustments are necessary to guide the sled; at speeds up to {{convert|80|mph|km/h}}, anything larger would result in a crash. The pilot does most of the steering, and the brakeman stops the sled after crossing the finish line by pulling the sled's brake lever.

Women compete in women's bobsleigh (which is always two-woman) and men in both two and four-man competitions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fibt.com/ |title= FIBT the international home of Bobsleigh and Skeleton Sports |accessdate=3 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women were confirmed as being able to compete in any four-&quot;man&quot; bobsleigh event, as from 25 September 2014, either as part of a mixed-sex team or an all-female team.

===Racing===
[[Image:USA-1 in heat 3 of 4 man bobsleigh at 2010 Winter Olympics 2010-02-27.jpg|thumb|USA-1 in heat 3 of 4-man bobsleigh at 2010 Winter Olympics, 27 Fevruarb 2010]]

Individual runs down the course, or &quot;heats&quot;, begin from a standing start, with the crew pushing the sled for up to {{convert|50|m|ft}} before boarding; though the pilot does not steer, grooves in the ice make steering unnecessary until the sled leaves the starting area. While poor form during the initial push can lose a team the heat, it is otherwise rarely, if ever, decisive.  Over the rest of the course, a sleigh's speed depends on its weight, aerodynamics, runners, the condition of the ice, and the skill of the pilot.

Race times are recorded in hundredths of seconds, so even seemingly minor errors – especially those at the beginning, which affect the remainder of the heat – can have a measurable impact on the final race standings.

The men's and women's standings for normal races are calculated over the aggregate of two runs or heats. At the Olympic Winter Games and World Championships, all competitions (for both men and women) consist of four heats.

==Olympic medal table==
[[Image:US Navy 020219-N-3995K-304 Gold Medal Women BobSledders 1.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Vonetta Flowers]] (left) and [[Jill Bakken]] power up in the push zone for their {{convert|80|mph|km/h|adj = on}} ride down the [[Winter Olympic]] bobsledding track. Bakken, the driver, and Flowers, the brakeman, won the first gold medal presented in Olympic women's bobsledding (2002).]]
{{Main article|Bobsleigh at the Winter Olympics}}
{{Details|List of Olympic medalists in bobsleigh}}

==Fatal incidents==
{{Expand section|date=December 2010}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 85%;&quot;
|-
! No
! Competitor
! Year
! Track
! Section
! Race
! Event
! Vehicle
|-
|  || {{flagicon|NED}} Jules van Bylandt || 1907 || {{flagicon|SUI}} [[Cresta Run]] ||  ||Practice run || || skeleton
|-
| 
| Oberüberl
| 1911
| 
| 
| Practice run
| 
| 5-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|GER}} Karl Gerloff
| 1933
| {{flagicon|GER}} [[Oberhof bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|Oberhof]]
| 
| Practice run
| 
| 4-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|GER}} Rudolf Gerloff
| 1933
| {{flagicon|GER}} [[Oberhof bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|Oberhof]]
| 
| Practice run
| 
| 4-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|SUI}} [[Reto Capadrutt]]
| 1939
| {{flagicon|ITA}} [[Eugenio Monti track|Cortina d'Ampezzo]]
| 
| Practice run
| [[FIBT World Championships 1939|World Championships 1939]]
| 4-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|BEL}} [[Max Houben]]
| 1949
| {{flagicon|USA}} [[Mt. Van Hoevenberg Olympic Bobsled Run|Lake Placid]]
| Shady corner
| Practice run
| [[FIBT World Championships 1949|World Championships 1949]]
| 2-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|SUI}} [[Felix Endrich]]
| 1953
| {{flagicon|GER}} [[Riessersee|Garmisch-Partenkirchen]]
| Bayernkurve
| Practice run
| [[FIBT World Championships 1953|World Championships 1953]]
| 4-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|ITA}} [[Sergio Zardini]]
| 1966
| {{flagicon|USA}} [[Mt. Van Hoevenberg Olympic Bobsled Run|Lake Placid]]
| Zig-Zag Curves
| Practice run
| 
| 4-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|GER}} [[Toni Pensperger]]
| 1966
| {{flagicon|ITA}} [[Eugenio Monti track|Cortina d'Ampezzo]]
| 
| Practice run
| [[FIBT World Championships 1966|World Championships 1966]]
| 4-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|AUT}} Josef Schnellneger
| 1970
| {{flagicon|GER}} [[Königssee bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|Königssee]]
| 
| Practice run
| Austria-Cup
| 2-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|ESP}} Luis López
| 1971
| {{flagicon|ITA}} [[Breuil-Cervinia|Cervinia]]
| 
| Practice run
| [[FIBT World Championships 1971|World Championships 1971]]
| 2-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|ITA}} Giuseppe Soravia&lt;ref name=Abendblatt&gt;[http://www.abendblatt.de/sport/article672037/46-Todesfaelle.html ''Hamburger Abendblatt'' article], accessed December 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
| 1980
| {{flagicon|AUT}} [[Olympic Sliding Centre Innsbruck|Igls]]
| Finish
| Practice run
| 
| 4-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|USA}} [[James Morgan (bobsleigh)|James Morgan]]&lt;ref name=Abendblatt/&gt;
| 1981
| {{flagicon|ITA}} [[Eugenio Monti track|Cortina d'Ampezzo]]
| Finish
| Practice run
| [[FIBT World Championships 1981|World Championships 1981]]
| 4-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|URS}} Imants Karlsons &lt;ref name=Abendblatt/&gt;
| 1982
| {{flagicon|AUT}} [[Olympic Sliding Centre Innsbruck|Igls]]
| 
| Training session
| Training
| 2-man sled
|-
| 
| {{flagicon|ROM}} Daniel Oaida&lt;ref name=Abendblatt/&gt;
| 1989
| {{flagicon|GER}} [[Altenberg bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|Altenberg]]
| Curve 4
| Training session
| Training
| 4-man sled
|-
| 41
| {{flagicon|GER}} Peter Förster
| 1990
| {{flagicon|GER}} [[Altenberg bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|Altenberg]]
| Finish
| Training session
| Training
| 2-man sled
|-
| 42
| {{flagicon|GER}} [[Yvonne Cernota]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stern.de/sport/sportwelt/bob-tragoedie-bobfahrerin-yvonne-cernota-toedlich-verunglueckt-521475.html |title=Yvonne Cernota crashes during training run}} ''Stern.de'' (German)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/sports/german-bobsledder-killed-in-crash-1.502708 |title=Cernota killed in training accident | work=CBC News | date=2004-03-12}} (German)&lt;/ref&gt;
| 2004
| {{flagicon|GER}} [[Königssee bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|Königssee]]
| Echowand
| Training session
| Training
| 2-man sled
|}

.

==See also==
{{Portal|Sports}}
*[[Luge]]
*''[[Cool Runnings]]''
*[[List of Bobsleigh World Cup champions]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Spoken Wikipedia|Bobsleigh.ogg|2006-02-04}}
*{{Commons category-inline|Bobsleigh}}
{{Bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton}}
{{Winter Olympic sports}}
{{Extreme sports}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Bobsleigh| ]]
[[Category:Human-powered vehicles]]
[[Category:Winter Olympic sports]]
[[Category:Racing]]
[[Category:Racing vehicles]]
[[Category:Sledding]]
[[Category:Sliding vehicles]]
[[Category:Sports originating in Switzerland]]
[[Category:Winter sports]]</text>
      <sha1>onhkcywl0mx9nqvsuq5aay7uuih9co6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
