  <page>
    <title>Braga</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>424790</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937708544</id>
      <parentid>937708460</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-26T19:20:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RogueJMS</username>
        <id>36125867</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Notable citizens */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2014}}
{{Infobox Portuguese subdivision
| type            = municipality
|official_name      = 
|image_flag         = Pt-brg1.png
|image_shield       = BRG.png 
| image_skyline           = {{Photomontage
| photo1a                 = Braga Banco Portugal (cropped).jpg
| photo1b                 = Basílica Nossa Senhora do Sameiro (6) (cropped).jpg
| photo2a                 = Igreja do Convento dos Congregados, Braga (16778987800).jpg
| photo2b                 = Bom Jesus 2017 (9) (cropped).jpg
| photo2c                 = Aerial photograph of Mosteiro de Tibães (6) (cropped).jpg
| photo3a                 = Arco da Porta Nova - panoramio.jpg
| photo3b                 = Paço Episcopal Bracarense Barroco (cropped2).jpg
| spacing                 = 2
| position                = center
| color_border            = white
| color                   = white
| size                    = 280
| foot_montage            = Top: [[Banco de Portugal]]; [[Sameiro Sanctuary]]; middle: [[Congregados Church]]; [[Bom Jesus do Monte]]; [[Monastery of São Martinho de Tibães|Tibães Monastery]]; bottom: [[Arco da Porta Nova]]; [[Episcopal Palace, Braga|Braga Episcopal Palace]].
}}
|image_location     = LocalBraga.svg
|region             = [[Norte Region, Portugal|Norte]]
|CIM                = [[Cávado (intermunicipal community)|Cávado]]
|district           = [[Braga District|Braga]]
|parishes           = [[#Human geography|37, see text]]
|leader_name        = [[Ricardo Rio]] 
|leader_party       = [[Social Democratic Party (Portugal)|PSD]]
|coordinates        = {{coord|41|33|4|N|8|25|42|W|type:adm1st_region:PT_dim:100000|display=inline,title}}
|elevation          = 200
|elevation_min      = 
|elevation_max      = 558
|area_total         = 183.40
|population_as_of   = 2011
|population_total   = 192,494
|patron             = 
|postal_code        = 470x 
|area_code          = 253 
|website            = {{url|http://www.cm-braga.pt}}
}}
'''Braga''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|b|r|ɑː|ɡ|ə}} {{respell|BRAH|gə}}, {{IPA-pt|ˈbɾaɣɐ|lang|Pt-pt Braga FF.ogg}}; {{lang-cel-x-proto|Bracara}}) is a [[cities of Portugal|city]] and a [[concelho|municipality]] in the northwestern [[Portugal|Portuguese]] district of [[Braga (district)|Braga]], in the historical and cultural [[Minho Province]]. The city has a resident population of 192,494 inhabitants (in 2011),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ine.pt/xportal/xmain?xlang=en&amp;xpid=INE&amp;xpgid=ine_indicadores&amp;indOcorrCod=0005889&amp;contexto=pi&amp;selTab=tab0|title=Statistics Portugal|author=|date=|website=www.ine.pt|accessdate=27 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; representing the seventh largest municipality in Portugal (by population). Its area is 183.40&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/portal/page/portal/nuts_nomenclature/documents/PT-LAU.xls Eurostat] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140906094624/http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/portal/page/portal/nuts_nomenclature/documents/PT-LAU.xls |date=6 September 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Its agglomerated urban area extends from the [[Cávado River]] to the Este River. It is the third-largest urban centre in Portugal (after [[Lisbon]] and [[Porto]]).

It is host to the oldest Portuguese archdiocese, the [[Archdiocese of Braga]] of the [[Catholic Church]] and it is the seat of the [[Primacy of the Spains]]. Under the [[Roman Empire]], then known as '''Bracara Augusta''', the settlement was the capital of the province of [[Gallaecia]]. Inside of the city there is also a [[Castle of Braga|castle tower]] that can be visited. Nowadays, Braga is a major hub for inland Northern Portugal and it is an important stop on [[the Portuguese Way]] path of the Road of St James. The city was also the [[European Youth Capital]] in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.bragacej2012.com/?lang=en_GB |title=Braga 2012 Capital Europeia da Juventude |location=Braga, Portugal |year=2012 |accessdate=19 April 2012 |language=Portuguese |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120504074531/http://www.bragacej2012.com/?lang=en_GB |archivedate=4 May 2012 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{see also|Timeline of Braga}}
{{details|topic=the Ecclesiastical history of Braga|Archbishopric of Braga}}
[[File:Braga-mapa mediaval.jpg|235px|left|thumb|A 16th-century map of Braga, when the city was enclosed by its mediaeval wall. The large building in the centre is the [[Braga Cathedral|Cathedral]], while the Episcopal Palace and courtyards can be seen above the cathedral and the ancient [[Braga Castle|Castle of Braga]]]] 
[[File:Ponte_do_Porto_(5).JPG|thumb|235px|left|''Ponte de Prozelo'', Braga]]
[[File:Camara de braga.jpg|thumb|235px|left|The 18th century municipal hall that houses the local government authority]]
[[File:Vista da cidade de Braga c1849-1873.jpg|thumb|235px|left|The skyline of Braga during the mid-19th century.]]

=== Pre-Romans ===

Human occupation of the region of Braga dates back thousands of years, documented by vestiges of monumental structures starting in the [[Megalithic]] era. During the [[Iron Age]], the [[Castro culture]] extended into the northwest, characterized by [[Bracari]] peoples who occupied the high ground in strategically located fortified settlements ([[Castro (village)|castrum]]).

The region became the domain of the ''Callaici Bracarii'', or ''Bracarenses'', a [[Celts|Celtic]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=YFR2AgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA45&amp;dq=origem+celta+braga+bracara&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjV_5aanOHXAhUHLlAKHSg2BH8Q6AEIOTAC#v=onepage&amp;q=origem+celta+braga+bracara&amp;f=false|title=Introdução à História da Língua e Cultura Portuguesas|first=José Barbosa|last=Machado|date=1 January 2014|publisher=Edições Vercial|accessdate=27 March 2018|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; tribe who occupied what is now northern Portugal, Galicia and Asturias in the northwest of [[Iberian Peninsula|Iberia]].

=== Roman rule ===
The [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] began their conquest of the region around 136 BC, and finished it, by pacifying the northern regions, during the reign of [[Emperor Augustus]]. The civitas of '''Bracara Augusta''' was founded in 20 BC; in the context of the administrative reorganization of these Roman acquisitions, Bracara was rededicated to the Emperor taking on the name ''Bracara Augusta''. The city of Bracara Augusta developed greatly during the 1st century and reached its maximum extension around the 2nd century.

Towards the end of the 3rd century, the [[Diocletianus|Emperor Diocletian]] promoted the city to the status of capital of the administrative area [[Conventus bracarensis]], the southwestern area of the newly founded Roman province of [[Gallaecia]].

===Braga in Late Antiquity and Middle Ages===
[[File:Iberia 500.svg|left|355x355px|frameless]]
During the [[Migration Period|Germanic Invasions of the Iberian Peninsula]], the area was conquered by the [[Suebi]], a [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] people from Central Europe. In 410, the Suebi established a [[Kingdom of the Suebi|Kingdom]] in northwest Iberia covering what is present-day's Northern half of Portugal,&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson154&quot;&gt;Thompson, 153&amp;ndash;154.&lt;/ref&gt; Galicia and Asturias, which they maintained as ''Gallaecia'', and had Bracara as their capital. This kingdom was founded by [[Hermeric]] and lasted for over 150 years.By about 584, the [[Visigoths]] took over control of Gallaecia from the Suebi, and Braga was made a provincial capital. 

[[File:Braga-sec-xvii.png|235px|thumb|A 17th-century engraving of Braga, showing the walls of the city, which were progressively demolished to make way for new constructions]]
[[File:Rua Júlio Lima.JPG|235px|thumb|A view of ''Rua Júlio Lima'' at the beginning of the 20th century]]

Braga had an important role in the ''Christianization'' of the Iberian Peninsula. The first known bishop of Braga, ''Paternus'', lived at the end of the 4th century, although [[Saint Ovidius]] (d. 135 AD) is sometimes considered one of the first bishops of this city. In the early 5th century, [[Paulus Orosius]] (a friend of [[Augustine of Hippo]]) wrote several theological works that expounded the Christian faith. Thanks to the work of [[Martin of Braga|Saint Martin of Braga]] the Suebi in [[Iberian Peninsula|Iberia]] renounced the [[Arianism|Arian]] and [[Priscillianist]] heresies during two synods held here in the 6th century. At the time, Martin also founded an important [[Monastery of Dumio|monastery]] in [[Dumio]] (''Dume''), and it was in Braga that the [[Archbishopric of Braga]] held their councils. As a consequence, the archbishops of Braga later claimed the title of Primate of [[County of Portugal|Portugal]], then a county, and for a long period, claimed supremacy over the entire Hispanic church. Yet, their authority was never accepted throughout [[Hispania]]. 

The transition from [[Visigoths|Visigothic]] reigns to the [[Muslim conquest of Iberia]] was very obscure, representing a period of decline for the city. The Moors briefly captured Braga early in the 8th century, but were repelled by Christian forces under [[Alfonso III of Asturias]] in 868 with intermittent attacks until 1040 when they were definitely ousted by [[Ferdinand I of León and Castile]]. As a consequence, the bishopric was restored in 1070: the first new bishop, ''Pedro'' (Peter), started rebuilding the [[Braga Cathedral|Cathedral]] (which was modified many times during the following centuries).

Between 1093 and 1147, Braga became the residential seat of the Portuguese court. In the early 12th century, [[Henry, Count of Portugal|Count Henry of Portugal]] and bishop [[Gerald of Braga|Geraldo de Moissac]] reclaimed the archbishopric seat for Braga, with power over a large area in Iberia. The medieval city developed around the cathedral, with the maximum authority in the city retained by the archbishop.

===Braga in the Kingdom of Portugal===
Braga as the main center of Christianity in Iberia, during the Reconquista (until the emergence of [[Santiago de Compostela]] and, later, the conquest of [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]] from the Muslims, in 1085), held a prominent stage in medieval politics, being a major contributor to the Independence of Portugal with the intervenience of the [[Paio Mendes|Archbishop D. Paio Mendes]] in the Vatican, with [[Pope Alexander III]], which lead to the promulgation of the [[Manifestis Probatum|Bula Manifestis Probatum]], in 1179, recognizing Portugal as an independent Kingdom under [[Afonso I of Portugal|D. Afonso I Henriques]].

The following centuries marked a slow decline in its prestige and influence marked by the infamous theft of Holy Relics (including those of [[Martin of Braga|Saint Martin of Dume]]) by the then [[Diego Gelmírez|Archbishop of Santiago of Compostela Gelmirez]]. The relics only returned to Braga in the 1960s.

In the 16th century, due to its distance from the coast and provincial status, Braga did not profit from the adventures associated with the [[Age of Discovery|Age of Portuguese Discoveries]] (which favoured cities like [[Lisbon]], [[Évora]] and [[Coimbra]], new seats for the Portuguese court). Yet, Archbishop Diogo de Sousa, who sponsored several urban improvements in the city, including the enlargement of streets, the creation of public squares and the foundation of hospitals and new churches managed to modernize the community. He expanded and remodelled the cathedral by adding a new chapel in the [[Manueline]] style, and generally turning the mediaeval town into a Renaissance city.

A similar period of rejuvenation occurred during the 18th century, when the archbishops of the [[House of Braganza]] contracted architects like [[André Soares (architect)|André Soares]] and Carlos Amarante, to modernize and rejuvenate the city; they began a series of architectural transformations to churches and civic institutions in the Baroque style, including the municipal hall, public library, the [[Bom Jesus do Monte|Sanctuary of Bom Jesus do Monte]] and many urban palaces.

With the invasion of French troops, during the [[Peninsular Wars]] the city was relegated, once again, to a provincial status. But, by the second half of that century, with influence from Portuguese immigrants living in Brazil, new money and tastes resulted in improvements to architecture and infrastructures.

===Republic===
In the 20th century Braga faced similar periods of growth and decline; demographic and urban pressures, from urban-to-rural migration meant that the city's infrastructures had to be improved in order to satisfy greater demands.

==Geography==

===Physical geography===
[[File:Bom Jesus (Braga).jpg|thumb|right|200px|Snow in Braga. Picture: [[Bom Jesus do Monte|Sanctuary of Bom Jesus do Monte]]]]
Situated in the heart of [[Minho (province)|Minho]], Braga is located in a transitional region between the east and west: between mountains, forests, grand valleys, plains and fields, constructing natural spaces, moulded by human intervention. Geographically, with an area of {{convert|184|km2|mi2}} it is bordered in the north by the municipalities of [[Vila Verde Municipality|Vila Verde]] and [[Amares Municipality|Amares]], northeast and east by [[Póvoa de Lanhoso Municipality|Póvoa de Lanhoso]], south and southeast with [[Guimarães Municipality|Guimarães]] and [[Vila Nova de Famalicão Municipality|Vila Nova de Famalicão]] and west by the municipality of [[Barcelos Municipality, Portugal|Barcelos]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Diagnostic&quot;&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.saudepublica.web.pt/TrabPedro/ACES-Brg_DS-2009-2.pdf |contribution=Caracterização do Concelho de Braga |title=Diagnóstico do Concelho de Braga |first=P. Gomes |last=Pereira |publisher=Unidade de Saúde Pública de Braga |location=Braga, Portugal |language=Portuguese |year=2009 |accessdate=21 March 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924094453/http://www.saudepublica.web.pt/TrabPedro/ACES-Brg_DS-2009-2.pdf |archive-date=24 September 2015 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The topography in the municipality is characterized by irregular valleys, interspersed by mountainous spaces, fed by rivers running in parallel with the principal rivers. In the north it is limited by the [[Cávado River]], in the south by terrain of the Serra dos Picos to a height of {{convert|566|m|ft}} and towards the east by the Serra dos Carvalhos to a height of {{convert|479|m|ft}}, opening to the municipalities of Vila Nova de Famalicão and Barcelos. The territory extends from the northeast to southwest, accompanying the valleys of the two rivers, fed by many of its tributaries, forming small platforms between {{convert|20|m|ft}} and {{convert|570|m|ft}}.

The municipality lies between {{convert|20|m|ft}} and {{convert|572|m|ft}}, with the urbanized centre located at approximately {{convert|215|m|ft}}. In the north, where the municipality is marked by the Cavado, the terrain is semi-planar, the east is mountainous owing to the Serra do Carvalho {{convert|479|m|ft}}, Serra dos Picos {{convert|566|m|ft}}, Monte do Sameiro {{convert|572|m|ft}} and Monte de Santa Marta {{convert|562|m|ft}}. Between the Serra do Carvalho and Serra dos Picos is the River Este, forming the valley of Vale d’Este. Similarly, between the Serra dos Picos and Monte do Sameiro exists the plateau of Sobreposta-Pedralva. To the south and west, the terrain is a mix of mountains, plateaus and medium-size valleys, permitting the passage of the River Este, and giving birth to other confluences including the River Veiga, River Labriosca and various ravines.

===Climate===
Braga has a [[Mediterranean climate]] similar to other cities in the northwest Iberian Peninsula' except for having significantly hotter summer temperatures due to being some distance from the ocean: the absolute maximum is as much as {{convert|5|C-change|0}} higher than neighbouring [[A Coruña]] or [[Santiago de Compostela]]. The lowest recorded is {{convert|-6.3|°C|1}}. The climate of Braga is hot in summer with temperatures that can approach 45&amp;nbsp;°C (113&amp;nbsp;°F).
The climate is affected by the Atlantic Ocean which influences westerly winds that are channeled through the region's valleys, transporting large humid air masses. Consequently, the climate tends to be pleasant with clearly defined seasons. The air masses have the effect of maintaining the relative humidity around 80%: annual mean temperatures hover between {{convert|12.5|C|F}} and {{convert|17.5|C|F}}. Owing to nocturnal cooling, frost usually forms frequently between three and four months of the year (about 30 days of frost annually), and annually the region receives {{convert|1659|mm|in}} of precipitation, with the major intensity occurring between fall/winter and spring.

===Human geography===
{{wide image|Braga do Monte Picoto.jpg|800px|align-cap=center|Panorama of Braga, as seen from the Picoto hill}}
{{wide image|Braga-vale do Rio Este.jpg|800px|align-cap=center|A similar panorama taken from the Este River valley}}
[[File:Braga freguesias.png|thumb|235px|left |Distribution of civil parishes in the municipality of Braga]]
{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;20&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;float:right;&quot;
|
{{stack|
{{Historical populations
|title = Population of the&lt;br/&gt;municipality of Braga&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;(1849 - 2004)&lt;/small&gt;
| 1849 | 40004
| 1900 | 58339
| 1911 | 60836
| 1920 | 57019
| 1930 | 60761
| 1940 | 75846
| 1950 | 84142
| 1960 | 92938
| 1970 | 96220
| 1981 | 125472
| 1991 | 141256
| 2001 | 164192
| 2011 | 181474
}}
}}
|}
The municipality is densely populated, with approximately 962 inhabitants per square kilometre, equivalente to 181,474 residents (2011); it is one of the more populous territories in Portugal, as well as one of the &quot;younger&quot; markets.&lt;ref name=&quot;INE&quot;&gt;{{Citation |url=http://www.ine.pt/|title=Census de 1991, 2001 e Território em números de 2004 |language=Portuguese |publisher=INE - Instituto Nacional de Estatistica |location=Lisbon, Portugal |accessdate=24 March 2012 |year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of the population concentrates in the urban area of Braga, itself, where densities are more than 10000 per square kilometre.

The Bracarense population consists of approximately 78954 male and 85238 female individuals, with 35% of the population less than 25 years of age, while seniors conform to 11% of the population; the working population of the municipality occupies 54% of this structure.&lt;ref name=INE/&gt; Although largely native Portuguese, other segments of the population include  [[Brazilians]], [[Africans]] (principally from the former Portuguese colonies), [[Chinese language|Chinese]] and eastern European peoples, namely [[Ukrainians]].&lt;ref name=INE/&gt;

The urban structure includes approximately 70,268 residences (2001), even as the typical classic representation of family only includes 51,173 members in the municipality.&lt;ref name=INE/&gt; The &quot;extra&quot; homes are primarily temporary residences, normally for students, migrant workers and professionals working in the city. There is, also, a great number of homes owned by Portuguese residents living overseas (who use the homes periodically while in Portugal) even as constant and development has attracted new growth in the population.&lt;ref name=INE/&gt; Further, the difference in resident to transitory population means that, on average, the population of Braga hovers between 174,000 and 230,000 individuals annually.&lt;ref name=INE/&gt;

Growth in the population, roughly 16.2% between 1991 and 2001, occurred mainly in the older suburban civil parishes, such as [[Nogueira (Braga)|Nogueira]] (124.6%), [[Frossos (Braga)|Frossos]] (68.4%), [[Real (Braga)|Real]] (59.8%) and [[Lamaçães]] (50.9%).&lt;ref name=INE/&gt;
[[File:Adaúfe (P1000332).JPG|thumb|center|200px|Beach in Cávado River, Braga]]
Administratively, the municipality is divided into 37 civil parishes (''[[freguesia (Portugal)|freguesias]]''):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Law nr. 11-A/2013, pages 552 26-28|url=http://dre.pt/pdf1sdip/2013/01/01901/0000200147.pdf |accessdate=18 July 2014|author=''[[Diário da República]]''|language=Portuguese|format=pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Adaúfe]]
* [[Arentim e Cunha]]
* [[Braga (Maximinos, Sé e Cividade)]]
* [[Braga (São José de São Lázaro e São João do Souto)]]
* [[Cabreiros e Passos (São Julião)]]
* [[Celeirós, Aveleda e Vimieiro]]
* [[Crespos e Pousada]]
* [[Escudeiros e Penso (Santo Estêvão e São Vicente)]]
* [[Espinho (Braga)|Espinho]]
* [[Esporões]]
* [[Este (São Pedro e São Mamede)]]
* [[Ferreiros e Gondizalves]]
* [[Figueiredo (Braga)|Figueiredo]]
* [[Gualtar]]
* [[Guisande e Oliveira (São Pedro)]]
* [[Lamas (Braga)|Lamas]]
* [[Lomar e Arcos]]
* [[Merelim (São Paio), Panoias e Parada de Tibães]]
* [[Merelim (São Pedro) e Frossos]]
* [[Mire de Tibães]]
* [[Morreira e Trandeiras]]
* [[Nogueira, Fraião e Lamaçães]]
* [[Nogueiró e Tenões]]
* [[Padim da Graça]]
* [[Palmeira (Braga)|Palmeira]]
* [[Pedralva (Braga)|Pedralva]]
* [[Priscos]]
* [[Real, Dume e Semelhe]]
* [[Ruilhe]]
* [[Santa Lucrécia de Algeriz e Navarra]]
* [[São Vicente (Braga)|São Vicente]]
* [[São Victor]]
* [[Sequeira]]
* [[Sobreposta]]
* [[Tadim]]
* [[Tebosa]]
* [[Vilaça e Fradelos]]
{{div col end}}

The city of Braga proper includes only the following urban [[freguesia|civil parishes]]:{{citation needed|date=August 2014}}
{{Div col|colwidth=18em}}
*[[Arcos (Braga)|Arcos]]
*[[Cividade]]
*[[Dume]]
*[[Espinho (Braga)|Espinho]]
*[[Ferreiros (Braga)|Ferreiros]]
*[[Fraião]]
*[[Frossos (Braga)|Frossos]]
*[[Gondizalves]]
*[[Gualtar]]
*[[Lamaçães]]
*[[Lamas (Braga)|Lamas]]
*[[Lomar (Braga)|Lomar]]
*[[Maximinos]]
*[[Nogueira (Braga)|Nogueira]]
*[[Nogueiró]]
*[[Real (Braga)|Real]]
*[[São João do Souto]]
*[[São José de São Lázaro]]
*[[São Pedro de Este]]
*[[São Vicente (Braga)|São Vicente]]
*[[São Vítor]]
*[[Sé (Braga)|Sé]]
*[[Tenões]]
{{div col end}}
There is no formal city government, only municipal government authority, with local administration handled by the individual ''juntas de freguesia'' or civil parish councils.

==Politics and government==
:''See also: [[:pt:Braga#Política|Braga politics]] (in Portuguese)''

==Economy==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Avenida_Central_em_Braga.jpg|Central Avenue in Braga
File:Campo das Hortas 2017 (7).jpg|Campo das Hortas, Braga
&lt;/gallery&gt;

The major industries in the municipality are construction, metallurgy and mechanics, software development and web design. The computer industry is growing rapidly.

==Transport==
Although the region hosts its own airfield ([[Aerodromo de Braga]]) in [[Palmeira (Braga)|Palmeira]], the principal airport of note is [[Sá Carneiro International Airport]] located {{convert|50|km|mi}} away, in [[Porto]]. Access is made by public transit to the city centre (roughly 40 minutes) or Aerobus (50 minutes). Braga is serviced by both regional and high-speed rail connection to major centres in the region.

==Architecture==
[[File:Torre de Menagem de Braga (2).JPG|thumb|170px|right|The remains of the historic [[keep]] of the [[Braga Castle|Castle of Braga]], a defensive structure that circled the old town]]
[[File:Capela dos Coimbras II.jpg|thumb|170px|right|The [[Coimbras Chapel|Chapel of the Coimbras]], one of the first [[Manueline]] era chapels in Braga]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Arco da Porta Nova 01.jpg|thumb|right|170px|The Arch of ''Rua Souto'', commonly referred as the ''Arco da Porta Nova'', an 18th-century ceremonial arch]]The region of Braga is scattered with Neolithic, Roman, Medieval and Modernist monuments, buildings and structures attracting tourists. Although there are many examples of these structures, only the following have been classified by the [[IGESPAR|Instituto de Gestão do Património Arquitectónico e Arqueológico]] as [[National monuments of Portugal|National Monuments]]:

===Archaeological===
[[File:Geira Milha XXIX caminho.jpg|thumb|right|250px|[[Ancient Rome|Roman]] milestone XXIX on Via Romana XVIII – the road linking the [[Iberia]]n cities of Bracara Augusta and [[Astorga, Spain|Asturica Augusta]]]]
* Castro of São Mamede ({{lang|pt|Castro de Monte Redondo/Castro Monte Cossourado/Castro de São Mamede}})
* Roman [[Milestone#Roman Empire|milestones]], several Roman-era granite markers currently on display at the Museum D. Diogo de Sousa, dating from AD 41 to 238, that is, the reigns of Emperor [[Claudius]] to [[Maximinus II]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SIPA1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=364 |title=21 Marcos Miliários (série Capela) Braga incerta via (v.PT01130700002) |publisher=SIPA–Sistema de Informação para o Património Arquitectónico |editor=SIPA |location=Lisbon, Portugal |language=Portuguese |first=Isabel |last=Sereno |first2=Paulo |last2=Dordio |year=1994 |accessdate=26 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Roman Thermae of Maximinus]] ({{lang-pt|Termas romanas de Maximinos/Alto da Cividade/Colina dos Maximinos}}), discovered in the 20th century, the [[thermae]] occupy {{convert|800|m2|ft2}}, in the civil parish of [[Cividade]], and were constructed in the 1st to late 3rd century;&lt;ref name=&quot;SIPA2&quot;&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=307 |title=Termas romanas de Maximinos/Alto da Cividade/Colina dos Maximinos (v.PT010303070040) |publisher=SIPA – Sistema de Informação para o Património Arquitectónico |editor=SIPA|location=Lisbon, Portugal |language=Portuguese|first=Isabel |last=Sereno |first2=Paulo |last2=Dordio |year=1994 |accessdate=26 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Civic===
* [[Arco da Porta Nova|Arch of Porta Nova/''Rua de Souto'']] ({{lang|pt|Arco da Porta Nova/Arco da Rua do Souto}}), a [[Baroque architecture|Baroque]] and [[Neoclassical architecture|Neoclassical]] arch, designed by [[André Soares (architect)|André Soares]] in the late 18th century, and decorates the western gate of a medieval wall. It was opened in 1512 and since has been traditionally used to present to promote to visiting dignitaries and celebrities.&lt;ref name=&quot;SIPA3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=762 |title=Arco da Porta Nova/Arco da Rua do Souto (v.PT01130700002) |publisher=SIPA–Sistema de Informação para o Património Arquitectónico |editor=SIPA |location=Lisbon |language=Portuguese |first=Isabel |last=Sereno |first2=Miguel |last2=Leão |first3=Sónia |last3=Basto |year=2010 |accessdate=26 February 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120317130402/http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=762 |archivedate=17 March 2012 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Palace of the Falcões ({{lang-pt|Palácio dos Falcões/Governo Civil de Braga}}), a Baroque-era palace originally commissioned by Francisco de Meira Carrilho on 23 July 1703, and later, upon successive renovations, used by the Civil Governor's residence;
* [[Fountain of the Idol]] ({{lang-pt|Fonte do Ídolo}}), the 1st century [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] fountain dedicated to an indigenous god, located in the central civil parish of [[São José de São Lázaro]];
* [[Aguas Ferreas Fountain|Fountain of the Iron Waters]] ({{lang-pt|Fonte das Águas Férreas}}), following the discovery in July 1173 of iron-rich springs in the parish of Fraião, Archbishop Gaspar de Bragança ordered the municipal council to begin the canalization of these waters for public use, giving rise to a series of fountains, such as the Baroque decorated main fountain;
* Hospital of São Marcos ({{lang-pt|Hospital de São Marcos}}), with a façade comparable to any religious monument in the city, the Hospital of São Marcos, is an example of the complex Baroque style of [[Carlos Amarante]], featuring ornate double belfry and accents;
* [[Pillory of Braga]] ({{lang-pt|Pelourinho de Braga}}), the 15th century pillory, that marks municipal authority for the town, was constructed, demolished and moved various times, before being relocated on the grounds of the Sé Cathedral;&lt;ref name=&quot;SIPA&quot;&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=207 |title=Pelourinho de Braga (IPA.00000207/PT010303520013) |publisher=SIPA – Sistema de Informação para o Património Arquitectónico |editor=SIPA |location=Lisbon, Portugal |language=Portuguese |first=Isabel |last=Sereno |first2=João |last2=Santos |year=1994 |accessdate=15 August 2016 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160821211406/http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=207 |archivedate=21 August 2016 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Raio Palace|Palace of Raio]] ({{lang-pt|Palácio de Raio}}), an 18th-century Baroque-Rococo urban residence, with richly decorated blue azulejo façade of Andre Soares;
* [[Residence of the Crivos]] ({{lang-pt|Casas das Gelosias/Casa dos Crivos}}), a [[Renaissance]]-era shop-residence constructed outside the old walls characteristic of late Renaissance architecture and one of the few examples of a building covered in wood-lattice façade from this period.
* [[Sete Fontes (Braga)|Seven Sources Aqueduct]] ({{lang-pt|Sete Fontes}}), a complex network of aqueducts that provided [[potable water]] to citizenry of Braga;
* [[Theatro Circo]] ({{lang-pt|Teatro Circo de Braga}}), 20th century revivalist theatre, known for its architecture, as much for the films, theatre plays and performances;
* [[Ponte do Prado|Bridge of Prado]] ({{lang|pt|Ponte do Prado}})
* Bridge of Prozelo ({{lang|pt|Ponte de Prozelo/Ponte do Porto}})

===Military===
* Tower of Santiago ({{lang-pt|Torre de Santiago e troço das antigas muralhas de Braga}}), part of the ancient walls of Braga, the Tower of Santiago was designed by Portuguese Baroque master André Soares, based on a mixture of Gothic, Baroque and Rococo elements;
* Tower of [[Braga Castle|Castle of Braga]] ({{lang|pt|Castelo de Braga}}), actually the remnants of the castle's [[keep]], constructed during the reign of King [[Denis of Portugal]], which was part of the defensive system of the city of Braga, and included a semi-circular walled enclosure centred on the Sé Cathedral.&lt;ref name=&quot;SIPA6&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=1114 |editor=SIPA |publisher=SIPA–Sistema de Informação para o Património Arquitectónico |title=Castelo de Braga, designadamente a Torre de Menagem (restos) |location=Lisbon |language=Portuguese |year=2007 |accessdate=26 February 2012 |first=Isabel |last=Sereno |first2=Paulo |last2=Dordio |first3=Joaquim |last3=Gonçalves |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131112034135/http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=1114 |archivedate=12 November 2013 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religious===
[[File:Se Catedral de Braga.jpg|299x299px|thumb|The sculpted black rock of the [[Braga Cathedral|Sé Cathedral of Braga]]: seat of the Archbishop of Braga and [[Primate (bishop)|Primate of Portugal and of the Hispanias]].]]
[[File:Igrega de S Paulo Braga.jpg|thumb|170px|The simple Romanesque façade of the [[St Paul's Church, Braga|Church of São Paulo]]]]
[[File:PópuloBraga.jpg|thumb|170px|The [[Pópulo Church]], that includes convent, dependencies and cloister]]
[[File:Igreja de Santa Cruz em Braga.jpg|thumb|170px|The [[Holy Cross Church, Braga|Church of Santa Cruz]] courtesy the ''Irmandade de Santa Cruz]]
* [[Archbishop's Palace of Braga|Archiepiscopal Palace of Braga]] ({{lang-pt|Antigo Paço Arquiepiscopal de Braga}}), between the 14th–18th centuries, a religious residence, but after the 20th century, the home of the municipal offices, public library and archive;
* Chapel of the Espírito Santo ({{lang-pt|Capela do Espírito Santo}}), an example of mixed styles, the chapel includes elements of Baroque, Neoclassical and Mannerist eras;
* Chapel of Nossa Senhora da Consolaçã ({{lang-pt|Capela de Nossa Senhora da Consolação}}), a simple single-nave chapel constructed in the Baroque-style
* Chapel of São Bento ({{lang-pt|Capela de São Bento}}), constructed in the middle of the 18th century, the chapel was blessed by Archbishop José of Bragança in 1755;
* Chapel of Senhor do Bom Sucesso ({{lang-pt|Capela do Senhor do Bom Sucesso}}), a Baroque and Neoclassical chapel, is highlighted by a main façade, typical of [[André Soares (architect)|André Soares]], but constructed by [[Carlos Amarante]], at the beginning of his career, who timidly applied Neoclassical decorative elements;
* [[Coimbras Chapel|Chapel of the Coimbras]] ({{lang|pt|Capela de Nossa Senhora da Conceição/Capela dos Coimbras/Capela do Senhor Morto}}), a [[Manueline]] chapel, probably designed by Castillian architect Filipe Odarte, with sculptures attributed to Hodart, an altar by João de Ruão and posterior tomb sculptures by the same artist.&lt;ref name=&quot;SIPA4&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=770 |title=Capela de Nossa Senhora da Conceição/Capela dos Coimbras/Capela do Senhor Morto |publisher=SIPA –Sistema de Informação para o Património Arquitectónico |editor=SIPA |location=Lisbon, Portugal |language=Portuguese |first=Isabel |last=Sereno |first2=João |last2=Santos |year=1994 |accessdate=26 February 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120401044642/http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=770 |archivedate=1 April 2012 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Holy Cross Church, Braga|Church of Santa Cruz]] ({{lang-pt|Igreja de Santa Cruz}}), and the ''Hospital of the Brotherhood of the Holy Cross of Jerusalem'' ({{lang-pt|Irmandade de Santa Cruz de Jerusalem}}), constructed in 1581, and later supported by the nuns of the Order Hospitaler;
* [[Saint Eulalia Church|Church of Santa Eulália]] ({{lang-pt|Igreja de Santa Eulália}}), is a 13th-14th century [[Romanesque art|Romanesque]] church, located near [[Bom Jesus do Monte]];
* Church of Santa Maria ({{lang-pt|Igreja Paroquial de Ferreiros/Igreja de Santa Maria}}), constructed in 1560, under the orders of Archbishop Bartolomeu dos Mártires, as a church of the [[Society of Jesus]];
* Church of Santo André ({{lang-pt|Igreja Paroquial de Gondizalves/Igreja de Santo André}}), an example of the reformulations of the Modernist aesthetic of the mid-20th century: the 18th-century church was adapted and expanded after the parish's de-annexation in 1975;
* [[Chapel of São Frutuoso (Braga)|Chapel of São Frutuoso]], also known as the Chapel of São Frutuoso of Montélios or the Chapel of São Salvador of Montélios, is a pre-[[Romanesque architecture|Romanesque]] chapel, forming part of group of religious buildings that include the Royal Church originally built by the Visigoths in the 7th century, in the form of a Greek cross.&lt;ref name=&quot;SIPA5&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=1903 |editor=SIPA |publisher=SIPA – Sistema de Informação para o Património Arquitectónico |title=Capela de São Frutuoso de Montélios/Capela de São Salvador de Montélios |location=Lisbon, Portugal |language=Portuguese |year=2004 |first1=Isabel |last1=Sereno |first2=Paulo |last2=Dordio |first3=Joaquim |last3=Gonçalves |url-status=dead |accessdate=15 November 2013 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131203072716/http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=1903 |archivedate=3 December 2013 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Chapel of São Sebastião das Caravelheiras ({{lang-pt|Capela de São Sebastião das Caravelheiras}})
* Church of São Martinho ({{lang-pt|Igreja Matriz de Espinho/Igreja de São Martinho}}), the Baroque and Classical parochial church of Espinho, known for its ornate façade and belfrey, as well as its Rococo interior;
* Church of São Miguel de Frossos ({{lang-pt|Igreja Paroquial de Frossos/Igreja de São Miguel}}), a 16th-century parochial church in the civil parish of Frossos;
* Church of São Miguel de Gualtar ({{lang-pt|Igreja Paroquial de Gualtar/Igreja de São Miguel}}), part of the intense building period of the 16th-17th century, the parochial church of Gultar was constructed in the 17th century, but later remodelled during the 18th century;
* Church of São Paio ({{lang-pt|Igreja Paroquial de Arcos/Igreja de São Paio}}), located in [[Arcos (Braga)|Arcos]], the church is an early 18th-century church (built in 1706);
* [[St Paul's Church, Braga|Church of São Paulo]] ({{lang-pt|Igreja de São Paulo e Seminário de Santiago}}), the historical seminary and church of Saint Paul with its contrast between stoic façade and decorated Baroque interior, built in the era of archbishop [[Bartholomew of Braga|Bartholomew]];
* Church of São Pedro de Lomar ({{lang-pt|Igreja de São Pedro de Lomar}}), remnant of ancient Benedictine monastery of São Pedro in [[Lomar (Braga)|Lomar]], the Church of Saint Peter exemplifies a mix of Baroque, Mannerist and Neoclassical architecture;
* Church of São Pedro de Maximinos ({{lang-pt|Igreja de São Pedro de Maximinos}}), known for the missing organ of organist Manuel de Sá Couto;
* Church of São Tiago ({{lang-pt|Igreja Paroquial da Cividade/Igreja de São Tiago}})
* [[St Vincent's Church, Braga|Church of São Vicente]] ({{lang-pt|Igreja de São Vicente}})
* [[Carmo Church (Braga)|Convent of Nossa Senhora do Carmo]] ({{lang-pt|Convento de Nossa Senhora do Carmo}}), principally recognizable for its central spire/belfrey, which was designed by João de Moura Coutinho de Almeida e Eça, and constructed in the 17th-18th century;
* [[Misericordia Church|Church of the Misericórdia]] ({{lang-pt|Igreja da Misericórdia}})
* Church of the Third Order of St. Francis ({{lang-pt|Igreja dos Terceiros}}), the ''Terceiros'' began the process of constructing their church in 1685, which they dedicated to ''Our Lady of Conception'' ({{lang-pt|Nossa Senhora da Conceição}});
* Church, Convent and College of the Congregation of São Filipe de Néri ({{lang-pt|Igreja dos Congregados}}), attributed to the architect  André Soares, for the complex/risky façade of the church and corner convent windows, Monk's chapel (or Chapel of Our Lady of the Appearance), and retable of ''Our Lady of Pain'' ({{lang-pt|Nossa Senhora das Dores}})
* Convent of Nossa Senhora da Conceição ({{lang-pt|Convento da Nossa Senhora da Conceição}}), which includes the Chapel of São Domingos, an 18th-century convent, home to the Instituto Monsenhor Ariosa;
* Convent of Pópulo ({{lang-pt|Convento do Pópulo}}), the Mannerist, Baroque, Rococo and Neoclassical austere elements of the convent belying the extravagant interior, that was originally the home to Augustine monks, highlighted by the Baroque façade of the [[Populo Church|Church of Pópulo]] ({{lang-pt|Igreja de Pópulo}});
* Convent of Salvador ({{lang-pt|Convento do Salvador/Lar Conde de Agrolongo}}), began with the need to transfer the nuns from the Monastery of Vitorino das Donas in 1528
* Convent of São Francisco de Montélios ({{lang-pt|Convento de São Francisco/Igreja de São Jerónimo de Real}}), the Baroque, Rococo and Neoclassical convent, highlighted by the imposing three-storey façade of the Church of São Jerónimo;
* Cross of Nossa Senhora dos Aflitos ({{lang-pt|Cruzeiro da Nossa Senhora dos Aflitos}}), a Baroque cross on an ionic column, with an image of Christ in wood, surmounted by a rectangular Tuscan colonnade and roof;
* Cross of the Espírito Santo ({{lang-pt|Cruzeiro do Espírito Santo}})
* [[Monastery of Dumio]] ({{lang-pt|Ruínas Arqueológicas de São Martinho de Dume}}), the ancient religious seat founded by [[Martin of Braga]] in the provincial centre of [[Dume]];
* [[Monastery of Tibães]] ({{lang-pt|Mosteiro de Tibães}}), the 17th–18th century [[Benedictine]] monastery renowned for the ornate/artistic gilt work in its chancel and altars;
* [[Bom Jesus do Monte|Sanctuary of Bom Jesus do Monte]] (inscribed on the World Heritage List in July, 2019&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://whc.unesco.org/en/statesparties/pt/|title=Portugal|last=Centre|first=UNESCO World Heritage|website=UNESCO World Heritage Centre|language=en|access-date=2019-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;), constructed on Monte Santo, overlooking the urban sprawl of Braga, the 18th to early-19th century, [[Neoclassical architecture|Neoclassic]] sanctuary and church (itself preceded by Baroque stairway), is reachable by trail or [[Bom Jesus funicular]] (one of the oldest in [[Iberian Peninsula]]);
* [[Sameiro Sanctuary|Sanctuary of Nossa Senhora do Sameiro]] ({{lang-pt|Santuário de Nossa Senhora do Sameiro}}), isolated on the hilltop of ''Monte do Sameiro'', the church and retreat began in 1861, from the mind of Father Martinho António Pereira da Silva, who wished to construct a monument dedicated to ''Our Lady of the Conception'';
* [[Falperra Church|Sanctuary of Santa Maria Madalena]] ({{lang-pt|Santuário de Santa Maria Madalena/Santuário da Falperra}}), located on Monte Falperra, the Baroque-era sanctuary church, was designed by local architect André Soares, incorporating decorative elements into a two-bell tower homage to the Mary Magdalene;
* [[Braga Cathedral|Sé Cathedral of Braga]] ({{lang-pt|Sé Catedral de Braga}})
* Wayside shrine of São Brás ({{lang-pt|Alminhas de São Brás}}), although conjecturally a contemporary monument, the wayside shrine in Ferreiros has the characteristics of many Baroque monuments in Braga;
* Cross of Campo das Hortas ({{lang|pt|Cruzeiro do Campo das Hortas}})
* Cross of Santana ({{lang|pt|Cruzeiro de Santa Ana/Cruzeiro de Santana}})
* Cross of Tibães ({{lang|pt|Cruzeiro de Tibães}})

{{multiple image|align=center|image1=Abertura Braga Romana.JPG|image4=Braga Romana Opening.JPG|image2=Romanos.JPG|image3=Braga Romana 2012 01.JPG|width1=230|width2=156|width3=230|width4=230|footer=The city's annual Bracara Augusta Roman [[historical reenactment]] festival, which transforms the city's historical center and its citizens to their ancient selves.}}
{{clear}}

==Museums==
[[File:Aerial_photograph_of_Braga_2018_(31).jpg|thumb|250px|center|Braga, Portugal]]
In addition, many of the district's treasures and historical artifacts are housed in several museums that are scattered throughout the city, such as:
* [[Biscainhos Museum|Museum of the Biscainhos]] ({{lang-pt|Museu dos Biscainhos}}), housed in the historical ''Palace of the Biscainhos'', the museum exhibits a permanent collection of [[decorative art]], that includes [[furniture]], [[ceramics]], European and Oriental [[porcelain]], European [[Glass]], European and Portuguese [[watches]] and [[clocks]];
* [[Braga Cathedral Treasure|Treasure Museum of the Sé Cathedral]] ({{lang-pt|Tesouro Museu da Sé Catedral}}), the collection varies, but collects together artefacts from the 16th to 18th century during the period of religious/cultural exploration, associated with the Cathedral, including images and [[azulejo]] tiles;
* [[Image Museum (Portugal)|Museum of Image]] ({{lang-pt|Museu da Imagem}}), dedicated to photography, located near the ''Arco da Porta Nova'' and ''Braga Castle'';
* [[Museum Medina]] ({{lang-pt|Museu Medina}}), located in the same building as the Museum of Pius XII, the collection is the home to the 83 oil paintings and 21 drawings of the painter [[Henrique Medina]];
* [[Nogueira da Silva Museum|Museum of Nogueira da Silva]] ({{lang-pt|Museu Nogeuira da Silva}}), bequeathed to the [[University of Minho]], the collection includes artefacts, paintings, furniture and sculptures collected over a lifetime, such as Renaissance artwork, 17th furniture, ceramics and objects in [[ivory]], [[silver]] and [[religious art]];
* [[Pius XII Museum|Museum of Pius XII]] ({{lang-pt|Museu Pio XII}}), housing a collection of [[Palaeolithic]], [[Neolithic]] and [[Bronze Age]] [[Tool|implements]], [[Pre-historic]] and Luso-Roman [[pottery]];
* [[Dom Diogo de Sousa Museum]] ({{lang-pt|Museu D. Diogo de Sousa}}), its collection includes many items discovered during archaeological excavations within the municipality, extending as far back as the [[Palaeolithic]] to the [[Middle Ages]].
* [[Stringed Instruments Museum|Museum of String Instruments]] ({{lang-pt|Museu dos Cordofones}}), the collection features Portuguese instruments as far back as the Middle Ages including Cavaquinhos, Portuguese guitars, Mandolins and banjos among others.

==Education==
[[File:Avenida da Liberdade (Teatro Circo), Braga.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Circo Theatre, Avenida da Liberdade, Portugal]]
The city is the headquarters and main campus for the [[Universidade do Minho]] (Minho University), a [[public university]] founded in 1973. A campus of Portugal's oldest [[private university]] of Portugal, the [[Universidade Católica Portuguesa]], was also established in 1967, as well as the [[Escola Secundária Sá de Miranda]] (the oldest Secondary school in Braga).

In the late 2000s, the [[International Iberian Nanotechnology Laboratory]] also opened their international research centre in the city.

The [[Braga Pedagogical Farm]] is a [[farm]] dealing with [[animal]]s and [[agriculture]], welcoming extra-curricular activities from [[school]]s and visitors.

==Sports==
Braga's [[Association football|football]] team, [[S.C. Braga|Sporting Clube de Braga]], was founded in 1921 and play in the top division of Portuguese football, the [[Primeira Liga|Liga NOS]], from [[Estádio Municipal de Braga|Braga Municipal Stadium]], carved out of the Monte Castro hill that overlooks the city. Braga has had considerable success in recent years, winning the [[Taca de Portugal]] for the second time in 2016 and reaching the [[Europa League]] final in 2011 which they lost to fellow Portuguese side [[FC Porto]].

The Rampa da Falperra, a round of the [[European Hillclimb Championship]], is held every year in the outskirts of the city.

The [[Circuito Vasco Sameiro]] and adjacent the Kartódromo Internacional de Braga are located around the local airfield. The racing track held [[European Touring Car Cup]] events in 2009 and 2010, and the KIB has held rounds of the [[Karting World Championship]].

==Notable citizens==
*'''Saint [[Engratia]]''' is venerated as a virgin martyr and saint, tradition is that she was martyred with eighteen companions in 303 AD
* '''[[Paulus Orosius]]''' (c. 385{{snd}}c. 420), Important historian and [[theology|theologue]] from the Braga diocese, friend of [[Augustine of Hippo|St. Augustine]].
*'''[[Saint Ovidius]]''' (martyred 135 AD): third Bishop of Braga, buried in the cathedral.
*'''[[Martin of Braga]]''' (c. 520–580), Bishop of Braga that converted the Suebi to Catholicism.
*'''[[Henry, Count of Portugal]]''' (1066–1112): Henry was [[County of Portugal|Count of Portugal]] from 1093 up to his death. He turned Braga into his capital and promoted the building of the cathedral. He is buried in a 16th-century tomb in the Chapel of the Kings in [[Braga Cathedral]].
*[[Teresa of León, Countess of Portugal|'''Theresa, Countess and Queen of Portugal''']] (1080–1130): Theresa of León was married to Count Henry in 1094. Her 16th-century tomb is also located in the Chapel of the Kings.
*[[Paio Mendes|'''D. Paio Mendes''']] (?-1137): he was the [[Archbishop of Braga]] from 1118 until his death. He was an important adherent of the cause of [[Afonso Henriques]], [[Count of Portugal]] and diplomatically fought for Portuguese independence in [[Pope Alexander III|Alexander III]]`s papal court.
*'''[[Pope John XXI]]''' (c. 1215–1277): Born in Lisbon as Pedro Julião, was [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Braga|Archbishop of Braga]] in the 13th century. Elected [[Pope]] in 1276.
*'''[[Antipope Gregory VIII]]''' (died 1137): Maurice Bourdin (Maurício Burdino) was the second Archbishop of Braga. Of French origin, helped organise the diocese. He was involved in a dispute between  [[Henry V, Holy Roman Emperor|Holy Roman Emperor Henry V]] and the [[Pope Gelasius II]], and was elected [[Antipope]] as Gregory VIII by the Emperor's followers, he was later imprisoned by [[Pope Callixtus II|Pope Calixtus II]] and died in an Italian convent.
*'''D. Lourenço Vicente''' (died 1398): was an [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Braga|Archbishop of Braga]] and defender of [[John I of Portugal|John I]], participated in the [[Battle of Aljubarrota]], where he was given a scar in his face, and in the retaking of [[Guimarães]]. He is buried in the Chapel of the Kings where his [[Incorruptibility|naturally mummified body]] is displayed.
*'''D. Diogo de Sousa''' (c. 1461–1532), Archbishop of Braga after 1505, sponsor of the arts, he remodelled the Cathedral and promoted the urbanisation of the city following Renaissance models. He also founded several churches and the São Paulo School.
*'''[[Francisco Sanches]]''' (c. 1550{{snd}}c. 1623), born [[Sephardi Jew]] and [[New Christian]], physician and philosopher, responsible for ''Quod Nihil Scitur'' (''That Nothing Is Known''), written in 1576 and published in 1581 a sceptical treatise on science.
* '''[[Miguel de Carvalho]]''' (1579–1624), a Roman Catholic missionary who was [[History of the Catholic Church in Japan|burned at the stake in Japan]] and was beatified in 1867.
* [[André Soares (architect)|'''André Soares''']] (1720–1769), 18th-century architect, designed several important Rococo buildings in Braga and northern Portugal, including the [[Raio Palace|Palace of Raio]], [[Monastery of Tibães]], [[Falperra Church|Church of Falperra]], and [[Arco da Porta Nova|Porta Nova Arch]]
* '''[[Carlos Amarante]]''' (1748–1815) an important Portuguese engineer and architect, moved from late Baroque-Rococo architecture of northern Portugal to modern [[Neoclassical architecture]].
* '''[[Manuel António Martins]]''' (1772–1845) a Portuguese administrator and colonial governor of Cape Verde and Portuguese Guinea from 1833 to 1835. After moving to Cape Verde in 1792, Martins was said to be the richest man in the country
* '''[[João Crisóstomo de Amorim Pessoa]]''' (1810–1888) Bishop of Santiago de Cabo Verde and archbishop of Goa and [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Braga|Braga]]
* '''[[Domingos Leite Pereira]]''' (1882–1956), [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] politician of the [[Portuguese First Republic]]
* '''[[Luís de Almeida Braga]]''' (1890–1970) a Portuguese writer and politician, leading figure in the [[Integralismo Lusitano]] movement.
*'''Irmã Maria Estrela Divina''' (1904–1961), religious and stigmatic woman, buried in Braga Cathedral.
*'''Francisco [[Salgado Zenha]]''' (1923–1993) a Portuguese left-wing politician and lawyer.
*'''[[General officer|General]] [[Manuel de Oliveira Gomes da Costa|Gomes da Costa]]''' (1863-1929), although born in Lisbon he was a Portuguese [[army]] [[Officer (armed forces)|officer]] and [[politician]], the [[List of Presidents of Portugal|tenth President of the Portuguese Republic]] and the second of the [[Ditadura Nacional]] and led the famous [[28 May 1926 coup d'état|28 May 1926 ''coup d'état'']] that started in Braga; he has a statue celebrate him in the city square also named after him, where the [https://web.archive.org/web/20190323000325/https://www.cm-braga.pt/en City Town Council] is located. 
*'''Maria Ondina Braga''' (1932–2003), an author who of ''A China Fica ao Lado'' (1968), ''Angústia em Pequim'' (1984) and ''Nocturno em Macau'' (1984), as well as a translator for the works of [[Graham Greene]], [[John le Carré]] and [[Anaïs Nin]].
* '''[[António Variações]]''' (1944–1984), innovative pop composer and singer; he created music which for many is symbolic of the liberalization that occurred in Portuguese society after the [[Carnation Revolution]] of 1974.
* '''[[Torcato Sepulveda]]''' (1951–2008), an important and influential Portuguese newspaper journalist.
*'''[[Marie Myriam]]''' (born 1957), French singer of Portuguese origin, winner of 1977 [[Eurovision Song Contest]] with ''L'oiseau et l'enfant'' (The Bird and the Child), written by [[Jean-Paul Cara|Jean Paul Cara]] and Joe Grace.

==International relations==
{{See also|List of twin towns and sister cities in Portugal}}

Braga is [[Twin towns and sister cities|twinned]] with:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Geminações|url=https://www.cm-braga.pt/pt/0104/municipio/cooperacao-institucional/geminacoes|website=cm-braga.pt|publisher=Braga|language=pt|accessdate=2019-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
*{{flagicon|GNB}} [[Bissorã]], Guinea Bissau
*{{flagicon|FRA}} [[Clermont-Ferrand]], France
*{{flagicon|ROU}} [[Cluj-Napoca]], Romania
*{{flagicon|ECU}} [[Cuenca, Ecuador|Cuenca]], Ecuador
*{{flagicon|UKR}} [[Ivano-Frankivsk]], Ukraine
*{{flagicon|FRA}} [[Puteaux]], France
*{{flagicon|CPV}} [[Ribeira Brava, Cape Verde (municipality)|Ribeira Brava]], Cape Verde
*{{flagicon|ARG}} [[Santa Fe, Argentina|Santa Fe]], Argentina
*{{flagicon|CPV}} [[Tarrafal de São Nicolau (municipality)|Tarrafal de São Nicolau]], Cape Verde
{{div col end}}

== See also ==

*[[Organ Festival of Braga]]

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{See also|Timeline of Braga#Bibliography|l1=Bibliography of the history of Braga}}

== External links ==
{{commons category|Braga}}
* {{wikivoyage-inline|Braga}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20061213204332/http://www.braga.com.pt/ Braga Portal]
* [http://www.bragavirtual.com/index.php?lang=en Virtual Braga]

{{Braga}}
{{European Youth Capital}}

[[Category:Braga| ]]
[[Category:Roman towns and cities in Portugal]]
[[Category:Municipalities of Braga District]]</text>
      <sha1>hzbhxgzz6p1mrommx6i40wfxnc7eu7k</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
