  <page>
    <title>Brandjacking</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26594253</id>
    <revision>
      <id>919281242</id>
      <parentid>896189774</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-02T21:00:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Monkbot</username>
        <id>20483999</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Brandjacking examples */[[User:Monkbot/task 16: remove replace deprecated dead-url params|Task 16]]: replaced (1×) / removed (0×) deprecated |dead-url= and |deadurl= with |url-status=;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Brandjacking''' is an activity whereby someone acquires or otherwise assumes the online identity of another entity for the purposes of acquiring that person's or business's [[brand equity]]. The term combines the notions of 'branding' and '[[wikt:hijacking|hijacking]]', and has been used since at least 2007 when it appeared in ''[[Business Week]]'' referencing the term used in a publication by the firm [[MarkMonitor]] (MarkMonitor and its PR firm, the Zeno Group, coined the phrase; MarkMonitor registered &quot;BrandJacking Index&quot; as a trademark, but not the term &quot;brandjacking&quot; on its own).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title = 'Brandjacking' on the Web
  | publisher = Arik Hesseldahl
  | date = 2007-05-01
  | url = http://www.businessweek.com/technology/content/may2007/tc20070501_555089.htm
  | accessdate = 2010-07-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The tactic is often associated with use of individual and corporate identities on [[social media]] or [[Web 2.0]] sites, as described in Quentin Langley's 2014 book ''Brandjack'',&lt;ref name=Brandjack&gt;{{cite book|last1=Langley|first1=Quentin|title=Brandjack|date=2014|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|location=Basingstoke|isbn=9781137375353}}&lt;!--|accessdate=16 February 2015--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; and may be used alongside more conventional (offline) campaign activities.

While similar to [[cybersquatting]], [[identity theft]] or [[phishing]] in nature and in possible tactics, brandjacking is usually particular to a politician, celebrity or business and more indirect in its nature. A brandjacker may attempt to use the reputation of its target for selfish reasons or seek to damage the reputation of its target for hostile,&lt;ref name=Waddington&gt;{{cite book|last=Waddington|first=Steven|title=Brand Anarchy: Managing corporate reputation|year=2012|publisher=Bloomsbury|isbn=9781408157220|page=94}} Waddington, quoting Quentin Langley's ''[http://www.brandjacknews.com Brandjack News]'', describes brandjacking as &quot;the ability for an individual to criticise and publicly shame a company ... [placing] the brand in a hostile relationship with the consumer.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; malicious or for political or campaigning reasons. These reasons may not be directly financial, but the effects on the original brand-holder may often include financial loss - for example, negative publicity may result in the termination of a celebrity's sponsorship deal, or, for a corporation, potentially lead to lost sales or a reduced share price.

==Brandjacking examples==
* [[Coca-Cola]] - in 2013, a commercial, &quot;The Bitter Taste of Sugar&quot;, for [[Oxfam]] ([[Oxfam Novib]] Netherlands) parodied a Coca-Cola Zero commercial, drawing attention to its unsustainable business practices.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oxfamnovib.nl/De-bittere-nasmaak-van-suiker.html De bittere nasmaak van suiker] Accessed: 7 April 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;  
* [[Starbucks]] - in 2006, a [[YouTube]]-hosted video presented a spoof advert for a Starbucks Frappuccino underlining the contrast between consumption and poverty.
* [[Nestle]] - in March 2010, [[Greenpeace]] campaigners used a YouTube video that parodied Nestlé's [[KitKat]] 'Take a Break' advertising, to draw attention to the multinational's use of palm oil from unsustainable operations in [[Indonesia]] and the consequent impact on [[Orangutan]] habitats.&lt;ref&gt;Dunlevy, Gabrielle (18 March 2010), Gory Greenpeace KitKat video goes viral, ''Daily Telegraph'' - http://www.dailytelegraph.com.au/news/gory-greenpeace-kitkat-video-goes-viral/story-e6freuy9-1225842479332&lt;/ref&gt; Protesters outside Nestlé's UK head office in [[Croydon]] carried signs with the words 'Give me a break' and 'Killer' printed in the distinctive red and white [[Gill Sans]].&lt;ref name=metro&gt;Nestlé faces KitKat boycott over links to 'palm oil killing orangutans' claim (18 March 2010), ''Metro'' - http://www.metro.co.uk/news/818000-nestle-faces-kitkat-boycott-over-links-to-palm-oil-killing-orangutans-claim&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Exxon Mobil]] - in 2008, a [[Twitter]] account (@ExxonMobilCorp) was set up purporting to be the views of an official spokesperson for the oil company, only for it later to be exposed as fake.&lt;ref&gt;Fowler, Tom (2008), Exxon Mobil says it's not behind 'its' Twitter account, ''Houston Chronicle'' - http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/chronicle/5920513.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* Also on Twitter, @BPglobalPR is not an official voice for [[BP]], but a satirical account that has grown in popularity during the 2010 [[Deepwater Horizon oil spill]], attracting more followers than the official BP Twitter account.&lt;ref&gt;BP’s Global PR vs. BPGlobalPR (2010) ''Newsweek'' - http://www.newsweek.com/2010/06/04/bp-s-global-pr-vs-bpglobalpr.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* Politicians - fake [[Facebook]] pages were created for US President [[Barack Obama]]&lt;ref&gt;Tapper, Jake (2008), Barack Obama's Fake Facebook Page (Courtesy of the RNC), ABC News - http://blogs.abcnews.com/politicalpunch/2008/07/barack-obamas-f.html&lt;/ref&gt; and US Republican governor [[Sarah Palin]]&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Palin's Facebook Alter-Ego Gets Found Out (29 August 2009) ''Wall Street Journal'' - https://blogs.wsj.com/speakeasy/2009/08/13/sarah-palins-facebook-alter-ego-gets-found-out/&lt;/ref&gt; (among other politicians). Major corporations have also been the subject of brandjack-based protests on Facebook.
* [[Fake blog]]s - may be considered a form of brandjacking if created by a critic or opponent of the person or brand supposed to be behind the blog.
* Affiliate Brand Bidding - This is a tactic used by some affiliate marketers. Some consider such tactics unethical or [[Black hat hacking|Black Hat]]. The method is to bid on keywords related to your site / product, but to do so seemingly as a competitor.&lt;ref&gt;Weiman, Lori (June 23, 2010), Watch Out For These Unsavory Affiliate Tactics, Search Engine Land - http://searchengineland.com/watch-out-for-these-unsavory-affiliate-tactics-44692&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation| last1 = Rosso| first1 = Mark| last2 = Jansen| first2 = Bernard (Jim)| title = Brand Names as Keywords in Sponsored Search Advertising| url = http://aisel.aisnet.org/cais/vol27/iss1/6| journal = Communications of the Association for Information Systems| volume = 27| issue = 1| pages= 81–98| date = August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Colleges and Universities - In 2008, college guidebook company [[College Prowler]] created hundreds of Facebook groups purporting to consist of actual incoming first-year students of various universities in order to surreptitiously gather their personal data and promote the business.&lt;ref&gt;[http://chronicle.com/article/Company-Created/42157/ Company Created Official-Looking 'Class of 2013' Facebook Groups for Hundreds of Colleges] - [http://chronicle.com Chronicle of Higher Education]&lt;/ref&gt;
*In June 2011, Greenpeace activists launched a campaign against [[Mattel]]'s use of a packaging supplier, APP, said to be desecrating Indonesian rainforests, using images of Mattel dolls [[Barbie]] and Ken.&lt;ref name=Barbie&gt;{{cite news|last1=Whitcomb|first1=Dan|title=&quot;Ken&quot; doll protesters arrested at Mattel headquarters|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2011/06/07/us-mattel-protest-idUSTRE75667S20110607|accessdate=23 February 2015|work=Reuters|agency=Reuters|date=7 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Brandchannel&gt;{{cite news|last1=Waltzer|first1=Michael|title=Greenpeace Breaks Up Barbie and Ken to Save the Rainforest|url=http://www.brandchannel.com/home/post/Greenpeace-Mattel-Activism.aspx|accessdate=23 February 2015|work=Brandchannel|date=10 June 2011|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150224180744/http://www.brandchannel.com/home/post/Greenpeace-Mattel-Activism.aspx|archivedate=24 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Greenpeace video showed Ken dumping Barbie (&quot;I don't date girls who are into deforestation&quot;), the group created a mock Twitter feud and a stunt involving Barbie in a pink bulldozer, and unfurled a banner on the wall of Mattel’s Los Angeles headquarters;&lt;ref&gt;Langley (2014), pp.183-185&lt;/ref&gt; some  500,000 people sent protest emails to Mattel. In October 2011, Mattel announced a global policy to keep rainforest destruction out of its supply chains.&lt;ref name=Ethical&gt;{{cite news|title=Success. Mattel and Barbie stop toying with the rainforest|url=http://www.ethicalconsumer.org/latestnews/tabid/62/entryid/810/success-mattel-and-barbie-stop-toying-with-the-rainforest.aspx|accessdate=23 February 2015|work=Ethical Consumer|date=17 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Brandjack'' author Quentin Langley praised Greenpeace for its integration of online (YouTube, Twitter) and offline (stunts, etc.).&lt;ref&gt;Langley (2014), p.185&lt;/ref&gt;

== Brandjacking avoidance ==
Brandjacking avoidance may include:
* Pre-emptive registration of brand names and sub-brands as screen names on social media sites.
* Staying vigilant &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Frederick
  | first = Felman
  | title = The Cure for Social Media Brandjacking
  | publisher = E-Commerce News
  | date = 2009-05-04
  | url = http://www.ecommercetimes.com/story/66969.html?wlc=1268859644
  | accessdate = 2010-03-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Use of social media and general media monitoring tools to seek evidence of infringement
* Legal action against those seen as responsible for the infringement.
However, action against the brandjackers and their supporters can actually draw attention to the problem (the [[Streisand effect]]). For example, following Greenpeace's KitKat campaign, Nestlé had the video removed from YouTube, but Greenpeace quickly re-posted it to video-sharing site [[Vimeo.com]] and highlighted the attempted censorship using Twitter and other social media.&lt;ref name=metro /&gt; Attempts by Nestlé to constrain user activity on its Facebook fan page further fanned the controversy.

== See also ==
* [[Culture jamming]]
* [[Cybersquatting]]
* [[Fake blog]]
* [[Identity theft]]
* [[Phishing]]
* [[Subvertising]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://blogs.zdnet.com/security/?p=1240 Online brand-jacking increasing]

[[Category:Identity theft]]
[[Category:Cybercrime]]</text>
      <sha1>s3p706ipqb19f44fqbqje9gj3mbh9ud</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
