  <page>
    <title>Butwal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5743823</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932455909</id>
      <parentid>932091675</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-26T02:12:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Places of interest */HTTP → HTTPS for [[UNESCO]] [[World Heritage Site]], replaced: http://whc.unesco.org/ → https://whc.unesco.org/</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2018}}
{{guidebook|date= May 2017}}
{{Infobox settlement
&lt;!--See the Table at Infobox settlement for all fields and descriptions of usage--&gt;
&lt;!-- Basic info  --&gt;| name                            = Butwal
| native_name                     = '''बुटवल'''
| image_skyline                   = Butwal city.jpg
| imagesize                       = 
| image_caption                   = Butwal at a Glance
| image_flag                      = 
| image_seal                      = 
| nickname                        = Batauli Bazaar
| motto                           = &lt;!-- images and maps  --&gt;
| image_map                       = 
| mapsize                         = 
| map_caption                     = Map of Rupandehi District, Butwal is shaded in light blue at the top.
| pushpin_map                     = Nepal &lt;!-- the name of a location map as per http://en..org/wiki/Template:Location_map --&gt;
| pushpin_label_position          = top
| pushpin_mapsize                 = 280
| pushpin_map_caption             = Location of Butwal in Nepal
&lt;!-- Location --&gt;
| coordinates                     = {{coord|27.70|N|83.466|E|region:NP_type:city_source:enwiki-GNS|display=inline,title}}
| subdivision_type                = [[List of sovereign states|Country]]
| subdivision_name                = {{NPL}}
| subdivision_type1               = 
| subdivision_name1               = 
| subdivision_type2               = [[Provinces of Nepal|Province]]
| subdivision_name2               = [[Province No. 5]]
| subdivision_type3               = [[Districts of Nepal|District]]
| subdivision_name3               = [[Rupandehi District]]
| subdivision_type4               = [[List of cities in Nepal#Alphabetical list|Metropolitan]]
| subdivision_name4               = Butwal
| established_title               = 
| established_date                = &lt;!-- Area    --&gt;
| government_footnotes            = 
| government_type                 = 
| leader_title                    = [[Mayor]]
| leader_name                     = Shiva Prasad Subedi ([[Nepal Communist Party|NCP]])
| leader_title1                   = [[Deputy Mayor]]
| leader_name1                    = Goma Acharya ([[Nepal Communist Party|NCP]])
| unit_pref                       = &lt;!--Enter: nepal--&gt;
| area_footnotes                  = 
| area_total_km2                  = 101.61
| elevation_footnotes             = &lt;!--for references: use &lt;ref&gt; &lt;/ref&gt; tags--&gt;
| elevation_m                     = &lt;!-- Area/postal codes &amp; others --&gt;
| population_total                = 118,462
| population_as_of                = 2011
| population_footnotes            = 
| population_density_km2          = 80
| population_blank1_title         = Ethnicities
&lt;!-- General information  --&gt;| population_note                 = Nepal Census 2011&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.digitalhimalaya.com/collections/nepalcensus/form.php?selection=1 
 |title=Nepal Census 2011 
 |work=Nepal's Village Development Committees 
 |publisher=[[Digital Himalaya]] 
 |accessdate=6 December 2008 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081012163506/http://www.digitalhimalaya.com/collections/nepalcensus/form.php?selection=1 
 |archivedate=12 October 2008 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| postal_code_type                = [[Post code]]
| postal_code                     = 32907
| area_code                       = 071
| website                         = [https://web.archive.org/web/20110724190135/http://www.butwalmun.org.np/ www.butwalmun.org.np]
| footnotes                       = 
| unemployment_rate               = |&lt;!-- Politics --&gt;
| timezone                        = [[Nepal Standard Time|NST]]
| utc_offset                      = +5:45
| timezone_DST                    = 
| utc_offset_DST                  = 
| blank_name                      = 
| blank_info                      = 
}}

'''Butwal''' ({{lang-ne|बुटवल}}) officially '''Butwal Sub-Metropolitan''' is one of the twin cities of rapidly growing Butwal-[[Bhairahawa]] [[urban agglomeration]] in [[Nepal]]. It lies in [[Province No. 5]], [[Rupandehi District]] and also the interim capital of province 5 of Nepal. It is also home to the administrative headquarters of [[Lumbini Zone]]. This city stands beside the bank of Tilottama River ([[Tinau |Tinau River]], and at the northern edge of the [[Terai]] plain below the [[Siwalik Hills]]. Its name, Butwal was derived from ''Batauli Bazaar'', the town's oldest residential area which is located on the western bank of Tinau river. Butwal is a lively city comprising the Panoramic views of the combination of hills and plains.

Geographically, Butwal is at the [[Intersection (road)|intersection]] of Nepal's two different National Highways, [[Mahendra Highway]] and [[Siddhartha Highway]]. It connects western Nepal with the capital [[Kathmandu]] through highway and air links (via airport at Siddharthanagar). It is one of the fastest-growing cities in Nepal for education, infrastructure, highway, marketing, health and safety, communication, trade and banking sectors. It has highway connections to the Indian border at [[Sunauli]] and to the hilly towns in [[Tansen]] and [[Pokhara]] valley, and holds the title of being &quot;The Best City in Nepal&quot; five times in a row.

Notable areas within Butwal includes:

*[[Charange]] - Residential area on the eastern suburb of city.
*[[Traffic Chowk]] - City Center of Butwal.
*[[Maitri Path]] - Also known as IT Market Local people called Computer Market (कम्प्युटर बजार) computer, Laptops, Mobile, Printers, CCTV etc.
*[[Amar path]] - Usually known as a shopping line for clothing, food, furnishings, etc.
*[[Golpark]] - Residential area below the shades of hills.
*[[Milan chowk]] - Commercial site.
*[[Raj Margh Chaurah]] - Central junction of Mahendra Highway and Siddhartha Highway.
*Kalikanagar - Chief residential area of Butwal.
*[[Devinagar]] - Residential area accompanying an ANFA Football Stadium.
*[[Butwal Bus Terminal]] - City's main transportation hub also called Bus Park in Local terms and site for small business hotels.
*[[Haat Bazaar]] - Weekly organized market or Greengrocer (Saturdays and Wednesdays).
*[[Deepnagar]] - Residential area at the foothills of Siwalik range.
*[[Paari Butwal]] - Also known as Batauli or Khasayuli. The oldest residential area of Butwal.
*[[Maina Bagar]] - Automobiles zone for repairs, sales and service. Also called Auto Village.
*[[Tamnagar]] - Former VDC, now a part of Butwal Sub-Metropolitan that lies on the western suburb of the city. Located 10&amp;nbsp;km from the city centre.
*[[Chidiyakhola]]- Ward no. 03, nearby Tinau river, is known for the Sarswoti Dhara, Ramapithecus Park and Lower Sidhhababa Temple. It is surrounded by hills, and has a supply of water from Sarswoti Dhara.{{citation needed|date=December 2018}}

Butwal was officially declared as sub-metropolitan city on 2 December 2014 by combining two neighbouring VDCs [[Motipur, Nepal|Motipur]] and [[Semlar]].

==History==

===Prehistory===
[[Fossil]]s of ancient hominoids [[Sivapithecus|Ramapithecus]] were found near the [[Tinau]] (Tilottama) River as early as 1932, including a 10.1-million-year-old tooth.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Citation
  | last = Barry | first = J.C.
  | editor-last = Else	| editor-first = James G.
  | editor2-last = Lee	| editor2-first = Phyllis C.
  | title = Primate Evolution.
  | chapter = A Review of the Siwalik hominoids
  | pages= 93–106
  | volume = Vol. 1
  | place = Nairobi, Kenya
  | publisher = Selected Proceedings of the Tenth Congress of the International Primatological Society
  |date=July 1984
  | accessdate = April 13, 2011
  | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=zWs5AAAAIAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_v2_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern history===
[[File:Tinau river in butwal.jpg|thumb|As recently as 1950, Butwal was a minor village on the western bank of Tilottama River (also known as Tinau)]]
The area was a loose settlement which acted as a trading post between the hilly districts of [[Lumbini Zone|Lumbini zone]] and the Indian plains. Thus, historically Butwal connected Nepali people with their Indian neighbors. As the British [[East India Company]] annexed [[Awadh]] from its [[Nawab of Awadh|hereditary rulers]] while the [[Shah Dynasty]] attempted to annex the [[Terai]], Butwal became one of bones of contention leading to the [[Gurkha War]] 1814-16.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite book
  | last = Handa | first = O.C.
  | title = History of Uttaranchal
  | place = New Delhi
  | publisher = Indus Publishing Co.
  | year = 2002
  | pages = 170ff.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | editor-last = Saugat
 | editor-first = Om
  | title = Encyclopedic History of Indian Freedom Movement
  | chapter = Chapter 10: Relations with Nepal and Burma
  | place = New Delhi
  | publisher =saugat
  | year = 2003
  | accessdate = April 13, 2011
  | pages = 280–282
  | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=0pypah0WAzEC&amp;lpg=PA281&amp;dq=butwal%20raja&amp;pg=PA280#v=onepage&amp;q=butwal%20raja&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When King [[Tribhuvan]] fled to India in 1950 during the revolt against the [[Rana dynasty]] he travelled through Butwal. Then it was little more than a village on the western bank of Tilottama River (also known as Tinau).

Butwal is a relatively newly urbanized area, emerging and growing rapidly only since 1960. With the completion of [[Siddhartha Highway]] in 1968, starting from the border at Sunauli through Butwal to Pokhara and then in the 1990s [[Mahendra Highway]] across the full east–west expanse of Nepal's Terai; i.e. [[Mechi]] Zone in the east to [[Mahakali Zone]] in the West, Butwal have made a tremendous progress in the country.

==Demographics==

The population of Butwal is 91,733 (census 2015), according to present stage the population is rapidly increasing with around 150,000 above and consists of people of mixed groups and castes; these includes [[Pahari people|Pahari]] immigrants from nearby hill districts especially [[Palpa District|Palpa]], [[Arghakhanchi]], [[Parbat]], [[Gulmi]], [[Syangja]] and  also local people from Terai origin.l&lt;ref&gt;http://worldpopulationreview.com/countries/nepal-population/cities/&lt;/ref&gt;

The population distribution in different wards in 2011 was as follows:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Butwal |first1=Municipality |title=Butwal Nagarpalika |url=http://www.butwalmun.org.np/page-Statistical_reports |website=www.butwalmun.org.np |accessdate=20 October 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150608221618/http://www.butwalmun.org.np/page-Statistical_reports |archivedate=8 June 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Ward No.|| Households || Population || Male || Female
|-
| 1||205||980||489||491
|-
| 2||189||1053||520||522
|-
| 3||240||1337||664||673
|-
| 4||1491||6487||3353||3134
|-
| 5||3039||10842||5476||5366
|-
| 6||2,368||9,603||4,995||4,608
|-
| 7||669||3202||1725||1477
|-
| 8||1,598||6,787||3,470||3,317
|-
| 9||2631||10597||5019||5578
|-
| 10||3175||11942||5856||6086
|-
| 11||2445||9170||4723||4447
|-
| 12||1114||24361||2092||22269
|-
| 13||7258||28193||13834||14359
|-
| 14||1566||6542||3101||3441
|-
| 15||1674||7366||3491||3875
|-
| 16||778||3566||1640||1926
|-
| 17||****||****||****||****
|-
| 18||****||****||****||****
|-
| 19||****||****||****||****
|-
| 20||****||****||****||****
|-
| 21||****||****||****||****
|-
| 22||****||****||****||****
|-
| Total||29662||118462||58808||59654

|}

The majority of the population is [[Hindu]]. They celebrate [[Holi]], [[Teej]], [[Maha Shivratri]], [[Dashain]], [[Tihar (festival)|Tihar]] and [[Bhai Tika]]. There are also [[Buddhist]]s and [[Muslim]]s.

Nepali, bhojpuri and maithli are the common languages spoken in butwal.

==Economy==
Butwal is mostly a commercial and trading city, an upcoming link city for the nearby tourist spots. The [[GDP]] of Butwal was about US$1 billion in 2018 making one of the major city in Nepal.{{citation needed|date=March 2019}} The economy of Butwal centers around trade, services and industries. The old trading spots are Traffic Chowk, B P Chowk, Amarpath, Raj Margh Chaurah and Nepalgunj Road. Besides modern shopping, a traditional form of market called ''Haat Bazar'' similar to greengrocer, runs twice a week on Wednesdays and Saturdays. It has the second largest vegetable market in the country called ''Butwal Sabji Mandi'' in local terms. All kinds of traders, farmers and entrepreneurs sell goods and vegetables directly to the retail &amp; wholesale customers in busy market setup.

Service aspects of the economy are mainly centered on banking, education, transportation and health sectors. Thus, increasing numbers of people are involved in these sectors for their jobs.

Butwal is also a connecting city between nearby tourist towns of [[Tansen]], [[Taulihawa, Nepal|Kapilvastu]], and [[Lumbini]]. It is the gateway to nearby cities of [[Sunwal]], [[Pokhara]] and [[Bharatpur, Nepal|Bharatpur]]. It is also a busy land-route to enter Nepal from India for tourists and others. Thus, Butwal is witnessing huge investments in the hospitality sector as well. To boost up tourism and MICE opportunities, the government plans to set up an international conference centre at Ramnagar in Butwal. All these developments hint towards a large economic potential for development of the region.
[[File:Mahendra Rajmarg0471 Butwal.JPG|thumb|The Mahendra Rajmarg (East-West-Highway) is an important thoroughfare in Butwal]]
The private commerce and trade in Butwal is united under the umbrella of Butwal Chamber of Commerce &amp; Industry (BuCCI). Audhyogig Byapar Mela-Butwal is an industrial exhibition held in Butwal. This exhibition is organized annually in the month of [[Poush]] (generally December–January), and is one of the largest of its kind in Nepal.

==Transport==
This city dominates any other city in terms of number of bus services in Nepal. Until 2003, most of the fleet was older large buses; since then operators have added newer [[minibus]]es popularly called ''micro''. Older [[jeep]]s are used to take people to nearby hilly regions. [[Rickshaws]] are used for short-distance urban transport. [[Motorcycle]]s are a common means of personal transportation around town. The number registered has increased from 1,200 in 1999 to 80,000 in 2008.{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}

Nearly 100 buses depart everyday to [[Kathmandu]] from Butwal Bus Terminal. Besides the capital Kathmandu, the bus services are also frequently available to other major cities of [[Pokhara]], [[Dharan, Nepal|Dharan]], [[Kakarbhitta]], [[Janakpur]], [[Birgunj]], [[Hetauda]], [[Bharatpur, Nepal|Bharatpur]], [[Tansen]], [[Siddharthanagar]], [[Dang Deukhuri District|Dang]], [[Nepalgunj]], [[Dhangadhi|Dhangadi]], and [[Mahendranagar, Mahakali|Mahendranagar]].

==Education==
Butwal is set to be an educational hub in Rupandehi district. Literacy rate in the city is considered to be high. It has held the record for Nepal Top students in SLC as well as HSEB examination numerous times.

* Achievers Higher Secondary School, Aadarshanagar
* Annapurna Model College (AMC),Chaandbari
* Apex School, Shankarnagar
* Axis Higher Secondary School, Sukkhanagar
* [[Butwal Bahumukhi Campus]], Golpark
* Butwal Elite English School
* Butwal EX-Army Higher Secondary School, Belbas, Butwal-15
* [[Butwal Glory English Boarding School]], Belbas, Butwal-15
* Butwal Public School, Yogikuti
* Canon College
* [[CCT College]], Milanchowk
* [[Deep Boarding High School]]
* [[Eden English Boarding School]], Naharpur, Butwal-16
* Ever Shining Higher Secondary School, Nayagaun
* Everest Boarding School, Sukhanagar
* Galaxy English Boarding High School, Murgiya, Sainamaina-4
* Gargi Academy, Devinagar
* [[Glorious College]], Devinagar
* Kalika College, Kalikanagar
* Kanti Public School, Haatbazar Line
* KNIT (Korean-Nepal Institution of Technology), Tamnagar
* Lumbini Banijya Campus, Devinagar (लुम्बिनि वाणिज्य क्याम्पस)
* Malmala Devi Higher Secondary School, Gadawa
* [[Manimukunda College]], Yogikuti
* [[Mayadevi Technical College]], Dhawaha
* Nabin Audhyogic Kadar Bahadur Rita Higher Secondary School, Devinagar
* Nava Prabhat English School, Rupandehi
* Nepathya College, Tilottama-2
* [[New Horizon College|New Horizon English Boarding Higher Secondary School, Kalikanagar]]
[https://www.newhorizon.edu.np]
* New Environment Higher Secondary School, Manigram, Rupandehi
* New Standard Higher Secondary School, Nayagaun
* Our Peaceland Academy
* [[Oxford College, Butwal, Rupandehi|Oxford College]], Sukhanagar
* Prabhat Higher Secondary School, Murgiya, सैनमैना-३
* Rammani Campus
* Sagarmatha Higher Secondary Boarding School, Devdaha
* Shining Star English Boarding Higher Secondary School, Deepnagar
* Shree Nayagaun Higher Secondary School, Nayagaun
* Shree Siddhartha Memorial Academy, Ramapur
* Shree Siddhi Vinayak Secondary School, Butwal-15 Mainapur
* Shree Navaratna Boarding School, Tamnagar
* Siddhartha College
* Siddhartha English Boarding School [http://sebs.edu.np/]
* Siddhartha Gautam English School
* Sky International College
* Swarnim Sagarmatha College, Devdaha
* [[Tilottama College]], Tilottama-2
* Tinau English Boarding School, Devinagar
* Lumbini Technical Institute
* oxford secondary school  sukhanagar
* lumbini shikshyalaya

==Places of interest==
*'''[[Devdaha]]''' - a site 13&amp;nbsp;km east of Butwal and is known as the maternal home of lord Gautam Buddha.{{citation needed|date=May 2017}} Shitalnagar Kheirani, Bhawanipur, Bairimai, Kan yamai, Khayardanda are some sites for visitors.
* '''[[Gajedi Taal]]''' - A lake located about 21&amp;nbsp;km west of Butwal. [[Lausha]] village of [[Gajedi]] VDC. Few hillocks and landscapes makes it more artistic and adventurous. It is well known as a spot for picnic, gatherings, and boating in the lake.
*'''Aap Khola''' (Mango River) - people go for swimming and to bring water during droughts. The Manakamana Temple is nearby.
*'''[[Butwal Hill Park]]''' (''Deepnagar'') - is one of the few notable areas in Butwal. People go there for hiking, morning walks, enjoying and having fun with friends &amp; families. Wide view of Butwal City can be viewed from the top of this park.
*'''[[Jitgadhi]]''' - A fortress during Angol Nepal war, Narayan temple built by (1864 B.S.) Hanuman temple and Shivalaya of Hanumagngadhi, Jalabinayak M9ehadev temple, Narayan Temple, Siddababa temple, Nuwakot etc. are centerss of attraction in Butwal.{{citation needed|date=May 2017}}
* '''[[Murgiya Jharbaira]]''' (Bolbom Dham) - is about 13&amp;nbsp;km west from Butwal city centre. The Temple of Lord Shiva (Parroha Parmeshower Bolbam Dham) is situated here and is a holy site for Hindu Followers.
* '''[[Manimukunda Sen Park]]''' (Phulbari) - The winter palace of [[Tansen, Nepal|Palpali]] Sen clan. There are ruins and antiquities of the palace of Manimukunda Sen, an ancient Palpali king, containing 6 large rooms as well as royal residence, administrative and grandeur of Butwal. Siddharthanagar and other neighboring villages of Rupandehi district can be seen from here at night. His Majesty's Government, archaeological department has attempted to maintain it since 1991. Now, Butwal municipality has formed council for the conservation of Manimukunda Sen Park to conduct Phulbari Development Programme and attempt to make it a tourist resort.
*'''[[Sainamaina]]''' - Located about 12&amp;nbsp;km. west from Butwal and to North from Banakatti, Sainamaina is as an open museum. Among the different Gramas villages of Shakya King, it was in the samgrama site. An Indian queen ([[Begum Hazrat Mahal]] of [[Awadh]]) came to this area with her soldiers and porters (‘Sena’ and Mena’) because of the British disturbance in her kingdomand finally this area came to be known as Saina Maina. It is a treasure trove of ancient ruins and antiquities: statues of dancing saints, ruins of palace, well etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.thehindu.com/news/international/south-asia/a-link-to-indian-freedom-movement-in-nepal/article5884467.ece|title=A link to Indian freedom movement in Nepal|date=2014-04-08|work=The Hindu|access-date=2017-11-23|others=Special Correspondent|language=en-IN|issn=0971-751X}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Siddha Baba Temple]]''' - Lies on the outskirts of Butwal Sub-Metro, in [[Palpa District]]. The area near this temple is prone to landslides. The temple is overcrowed by devotees during the festival of Shiva Ratri, Nepali New Year (Bikram Sambat-B.S) and weekends. (See photo) [[File:Siddhartha Rajmarg0469.JPG|thumb|Siddha Baba Temple]] 
*The '''Statue of [[Buddha]]''' (''Jogidanda'') - It was very significant ruins of having the values of classical art are scattered here and there.{{clarify|date=May 2017}} This archaeological site is occupied by homeless and landless people. Some of the antiquities of this site are seen around the Lumbini museum.
* '''Muktidham, Nayagaon''' - is a sacred temple site for devotees located in Nayagaon, approximately 10&amp;nbsp;km from the city center.
* '''Global Peace Park''' - This is a newly built site in Butwal near [[Tamnagar]]. A place for outings during the summer and peaceful surroundings.
* '''[[Banbatika Forest Resort]]''' - This is a kind of forest park opened for locals which lies in the [[Tilottama Municipality]] adjacent to Butwal Sub-Metropolitan. Usually known for picnic spots and small zoo for visitors and Research Centre. [https://web.archive.org/web/20170919070216/http://shankarnagarbanbihar.org.np/]
* '''[[Lumbini]]''' - The Birthplace of Gautama Buddha. The Mecca for Buddhist followers in Nepal &amp; all over the world. [[Lumbini]] is situated 40&amp;nbsp;km south-west of Butwal and is known as the birthplace of lord Gautam Buddha. [https://whc.unesco.org/en/list/666/]

==See also==
* [[Kathmandu]]
* [[Pokhara]]
* [[Sunwal]]
* [[Biratnagar]]
* [[Dharan, Nepal|Dharan]]
* [[Birgunj]]
* [[Bhairahawa]]
* [[Bharatpur, Nepal]]

==References==
{{commons category|Butwal}}
&lt;references /&gt;

{{Rupandehi District}}

[[Category:Populated places in Rupandehi District]]
[[Category:Butwal| ]]
[[Category:Nepal municipalities established in 1959]]</text>
      <sha1>0f5jqgt8u46xaqd3yjsgjut36x83wht</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
