  <page>
    <title>Byasanagar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5711453</id>
    <revision>
      <id>935867527</id>
      <parentid>929580674</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-15T07:05:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>103.74.223.23</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2018}}
{{Use Indian English|date=August 2018}}
{{refimprove|date=July 2013}}
{{Infobox settlement
| name                   = Byasanagar
| native_name            = 
| native_name_lang       = 
| other_name             = 
| nickname               = 
| settlement_type        = Town
| image_skyline          = 
| image_alt              = 
| image_caption          = 
| pushpin_map            = India Orissa#India
| pushpin_map_alt        = 
| pushpin_map_caption    = Location in Odisha, India
| coordinates            = {{coord|20.9460|N|86.1301|E|display=inline,title}}
| subdivision_type       = Country
| subdivision_name       = {{flag|India}}
| subdivision_type1      = [[States and territories of India|State]]
| subdivision_name1      = [[Odisha]]
| subdivision_type2      = [[List of districts of India|District]]
| subdivision_name2      = [[Jajapur district|Jajapur]]
| established_title      = &lt;!-- Established --&gt;
| established_date       = 
| founder                = 
| named_for              = 
| government_type        = 
| governing_body         = 
| unit_pref              = Metric
| area_footnotes         = 
| area_rank              = 
| area_total_km2         = 
| elevation_footnotes    = 
| elevation_m            = 
| population_total       = 
| population_as_of       = 2011
| population_rank        = 
| population_density_km2 = auto
| population_demonym     = 
| population_footnotes   = 
| demographics_type1     = Languages
| demographics1_title1   = Official
| demographics1_info1     = [[Odia language|Odia]]
| demographics1_title2            = Other local languages
| demographics1_info2             = [[Ho language]]
| timezone1              = [[Indian Standard Time|IST]]
| utc_offset1            = +5:30
| postal_code_type       = &lt;!-- [[Postal Index Number|PIN]] --&gt;
| postal_code            = 
| registration_plate     = 
| website                = {{URL|odisha.gov.in}}
| footnotes              = 
}}

'''Byasanagar''' or '''Vyasanagar''' is a town and a [[municipality]] in [[Jajapur district]] in the state of [[Odisha]], India. Colloquially it is also called Jajpur Road.&lt;ref name=&quot;S. C. Bhatt 2005 p. 184&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=S. C. Bhatt | first=G.K.B. | title=Land and people of Indian states and union territories : (in 36 volumes). 21. Orissa | publisher=Kalpaz publ. | series=Land and people of Indian states and union territories / eds. S.C. Bhatt; 3011 | year=2005 | isbn=978-81-7835-377-7 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=iDsORXsjZ5QC&amp;pg=PA184 | access-date=2019-05-24 | page=184}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name=&quot;Pioneer 2019&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last=Pioneer | first=The | title=Vyasa Sarovar Mela, civic body jubilee end | website=The Pioneer | date=2019-05-24 | url=https://www.dailypioneer.com/2013/state-editions/vyasa-sarovar-mela-civic-body-jubilee-end.html | access-date=2019-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is home to an industrial belt and hosts several steel companies including Neelachal Ispat Nigam Limited, MESCO, Tata Steel, Jindal Steel etc. According to district officials there are around 14 major companies and several small companies in the vicinity. The city is also home to some eminent people in Odisha, including P. C. Ghadei (Ex-Finance Minister), Late Ashok Das (earlier MLA), Ram Chandra Khuntia (Congress) Priti Ranjan Ghadei (MLA), actor [[Akash Dasnayak]], and his actress aunt the veteran Ms. Anita Dash, actress Naina Das, political leader Giridhari Barik (BJD). its come under the Korei vidhan shabha 

==History==
The town developed around the railway station on Howrah Puri Line. At that time it was the nearest rail head for the two towns Jajpur and Keonjhar. That is how the station came to be known as JajPur Keonjhar Road. The municipality was established in 1963. It celebrated its golden jubilee in 2013.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pioneer 2019&quot;/&gt; &lt;ref name=&quot;Orissa (India) Senapati Sahu p. &quot;&gt;{{cite book | author=Orissa (India) | last2=Senapati | first2=N. | last3=Sahu | first3=N.K. | title=Orissa District Gazetteers: Cuttack | publisher=Superintendent, Orissa Government Press | series=Gazetteer of India | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sAVDAAAAYAAJ | language=en | access-date=2019-06-21 | page=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Demographics==
{{As of|2011}} India [[census]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.censusindia.net/results/town.php?stad=A&amp;state5=999|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040616075334/http://www.censusindia.net/results/town.php?stad=A&amp;state5=999|archivedate=2004-06-16|title= Census of India 2001: Data from the 2001 Census, including cities, villages and towns (Provisional)|accessdate=2008-11-01|publisher= Census Commission of India}}&lt;/ref&gt; Byasanagar had a population of 37,609. Males constitute 53% of the population and females 47%. Byasanagar has an average literacy rate of 80%, higher than the national average of 59.5%; with male literacy of 79% and female literacy of 66%; 11% of the population is under 6 years of age. It is one of the fastest growing city in terms of industries.

==Transportation==
The railway station is the [[Jajpur Keonjhar Road Railway Station]] which falls on the [[Howrah-Chennai main line]] and is the only major stop between [[Bhadrak]] and [[Cuttack]].

The town is also only about {{convert|15|km|0|abbr=on}} from the National Highway 5. Various bus services connect Byasanagar to [[Bhubaneswar]] via Cuttack, [[Rourkela]] via [[Keonjhar]], and [[Balasore]] via [[Bhadrak]].

The nearest airport is [[Biju Patnaik International Airport]] at Bhubaneswar, the state capital.

==Culture==
The mythological Vyasa Sarovara is located here. It hosts an 11-day fair in celebration of Lord [[Vyasadeva]] in the month of March.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pioneer 2019&quot; /&gt;

==Industry==

Ferrochrome Plant was initially commissioned in November 1969 as a division of IDCOL with an installed manufacturing capacity of 12,000 MT p.a. of High Carbon Ferro Chrome (HCFC) with reduction furnace. Subsequently,  additional capacity of  10,000 MT p.a. of Low Carbon Ferro Chrome (LCFC) with slag furnace was created in October 1970. However, due to entry of relatively cheaper South African ferrochrome and general slow down in the demand of LCFC, IDCOL decided to stop the production of LCFC and with minor modifications, converted its slag furnace into reduction furnace in July 1998, so as to produce an additional 6,000 MT p.a. of HCFC.  With  this, the total installed capacity of the HCFC stood at 18,000 MT p.a. The current installed capacity is 19,000 MT p.a. The rated capacity of the furnaces are 9 MVA and 6.5 MVA. The plant was taken over by IFCAL in April, 2002. The operations at the Ferrochrome plant include mining of chrome ore from open cast mines, beneficiation of ore and smelting. The production process involves reduction of [[chromium oxide]] to [[chromium]] by [[electric arc furnace]] to produce HCFC by further reduction of the metallic oxide with the help of carbon.

The plant is located at Jajpur Road in the district of Jajpur, Odisha, and is about 12&amp;nbsp;km from NH-5 connecting Bhubaneswar and Kolkata.  The nearest railway station is Jajpur Keonjhar Road Railway Station which is about 2&amp;nbsp;km away from the plant and the nearest airport is Bhubaneswar (also the State Capital) about 120&amp;nbsp;km from the plant.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Jajpur district}}
{{Municipalities of Odisha}}

[[Category:Cities and towns in Jajapur district]]


{{Jajapur-geo-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>seql35euen2qgs796zqnpfya83wjqx5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
