  <page>
    <title>Caivano</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6770707</id>
    <revision>
      <id>925523799</id>
      <parentid>925523644</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-10T17:48:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>188.153.230.5</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Italian comune
| name                = Caivano
|  official_name       = 
| native_name         = 
| image_skyline       = Caivano.jpg
| imagesize           = 
| image_alt           = 
| image_caption       = 
| image_shield        = Caivano-Stemma.svg
| shield_alt          =
| image_map           =  
| map_alt             = 
| map_caption         = 
| pushpin_label_position = 
| pushpin_map_alt     = 
| coordinates         = {{coord|40|57|N|14|18|E|type:city(36,980)_region:IT|display=inline}}
| coordinates_footnotes = 
| region              = [[Campania]]
| metropolitan_city   = [[Metropolitan City of Naples|Naples]] (NA)
| frazioni            = Casolla Valenzano, Pascarola
| mayor_party         = 
| mayor               = Simone Monopoli
| area_footnotes      = 
| area_total_km2      = 27.1
| population_footnotes = &lt;ref name=&quot;istat&quot;&gt;All demographics and other statistics: Italian statistical institute [[National Institute of Statistics (Italy)|Istat]].&lt;/ref&gt;
| population_total    = 37874
| population_as_of    = 30 September 2015
| pop_density_footnotes = 
| population_demonym  = Caivanesi, Pascarolesi
| elevation_footnotes = 
| elevation_m         = 27
| twin1               = 
| twin1_country       = 
| saint               = Holy Mary of  Campiglione
| day                 = 2nd Sunday in May
| postal_code         = 80023
| area_code           = 081
| website             = {{official website|http://www.comunecaivano.it/}}
| footnotes           = 
}}
'''Caivano''' is an Italian town of 37603 inhabitants, situated in the North of Naples.
Its name comes from the Latin word Calvius to which the suffix 'anus' was added. Then the letter 'I' replaced the 'L'.
In the IV century Samnites settled there first, but only in VI century B.C. the place was made habitable by the Etruscan people that reclaimed the marshy lands. Then the Romans divided the area into estates. With the Lombard invasion the region was part of the Principality of Benevento. After the coming of Normans, instead, it become property of the Duke of Naples. In 1441 Alfonso D'Aragona occupied the castle of Caivano to conquer the Kingdom of Naples.

'''Sites of interest'''&lt;br&gt;
The Castle is the main monument of the city and from the 1981 it is the centre of the municipal library. Before the current architecture in XVI century style, it was a fortress formed by four towers divided by thick walls.

The Sanctuary of the Madonna of Campiglione dates back to the XV century. According to reports a miracle happened there. In the 1483 a boy was unjustly accused of murder and condemned to death, so his mother went to visit the church every night and light a candle near the image of the Holy Mary asking her to save him. One particular night, while the woman was praying, the Virgin's head emerged from the painting as if she was nodding in sign of assent. The boy was saved. Today people can still see the head that came out of the painting.
The Madonna of Campiglione is the patroness of the town and people celebrate her day on the second Sunday of May.

'''Prominent Personalities'''&lt;br&gt;
Stelio Maria Martini (Ancona, 13 January 1934 – Caivano, 1 May 2016) was an artist, a poet and a literary critic. He was one of the leading exponents of the visual poetry in Italy. Martini cooperated with many avant-garde magazines in the years between ‘50s and ‘70s and wrote “Schemi” in 1962, the first Italian book about visual poetry. Moreover his activity as a literary critic is very remarkable, since he gave a huge contribute to the critic revaluation of Futurism. Well-known in the national cultural scene, he lived in Caivano and there he spent his last years in solitude and away from the spotlight.

'''Economy'''&lt;br&gt;
The locality of Pascarola, which is a part of Caivano, is one of the major industrial areas of the South of Italy. Among the many factories present here are Algida, Magneti Marelli, the printing house of Il Mattino and other manufacturing industrial groups.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.comunedicaivano.it/ Official website]

{{clear}}
{{Province of Naples}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Cities and towns in Campania]]


{{Campania-geo-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>pnncwbjp0beqrqpiq10otcb3j5xxnr4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
