  <page>
    <title>Camping</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>228012</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938342373</id>
      <parentid>938336853</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-30T16:32:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MrOllie</username>
        <id>6908984</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 2 edits by [[Special:Contributions/208.46.87.85|208.46.87.85]] ([[User talk:208.46.87.85|talk]]) to last revision by Praxidicae ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{Original research|date=January 2017}}

[[File:Night Campaign.jpg|thumb|Camping in the [[Bandarban district]] of [[Chittagong]], [[Bangladesh]].]]

'''Camping''' is an [[outdoor activity]] involving overnight stays away from home in a shelter, such as a [[tent]] or a [[recreational vehicle]]. Typically participants leave developed areas to spend time outdoors in more natural ones in pursuit of activities providing them enjoyment. To be regarded as &quot;camping&quot; a minimum of one night is spent outdoors, distinguishing it from day-tripping, picnicking, and other similarly short-term recreational activities. Camping can be enjoyed through all four seasons.

Luxury may be an element, as in early 20th century African [[safari]]s, but including accommodations in fully equipped fixed structures such as high-end [[sporting camp]]s under the banner of &quot;camping&quot; blurs the line.

Camping as a [[recreation]]al activity became popular among elites in the early 20th century. With time, it grew more democratic, and varied. Modern campers frequent [[protected area|publicly owned natural resources]] such as [[national park|national]] and [[state park]]s, [[wilderness area]]s, and commercial campgrounds. Camping is a key part of many youth organizations around the world, such as [[Scouting]], which use it to teach both self-reliance and teamwork.

==Definition==
[[File:Unidentified group of men camping.jpg|thumb|Camping in [[Ontario]], circa 1907]]

Camping describes a range of activities and approaches to outdoor accommodation. [[Survivalist]] campers set off with as little as possible to get by, whereas [[recreational vehicle]] travelers arrive equipped with their own electricity, heat, and patio furniture. Camping may be combined with [[hiking]], as in [[backpacking (wilderness)|backpacking]], and is often enjoyed in conjunction with other outdoor activities such as [[canoeing]], [[climbing]], [[fishing]], and [[hunting]]. [[Fastpacking]] involves both [[running]] and camping.

There is no universally held definition of what is and what is not camping. Just as with [[motel]]s which serve both recreational and business guests, the same campground may serve recreational campers, migrant workers, and homeless at the same time. Fundamentally, it reflects a combination of ''intent'' and the nature of activities involved.  A children's [[summer camp]] with dining hall meals and bunkhouse accommodations may have &quot;camp&quot; in its name but fails to reflect the spirit and form of &quot;camping&quot; as it is broadly understood. Similarly, a [[homelessness|homeless]] person's lifestyle may involve many common camping activities, such as sleeping out and preparing meals over a fire, but fails to reflect the elective nature and pursuit of spirit rejuvenation that are integral aspect of camping.  Likewise, cultures with itinerant lifestyles or lack of permanent dwellings cannot be said to be &quot;camping&quot;, it is just their way of life.

==History==
{{Globalize|article|United Kingdom|2name=the United Kingdom|date=October 2013}}
[[File:Thomas Hiram Holding.jpg|thumb|[[Thomas Hiram Holding]] outside his camping tent.]]
The history of recreational camping is often traced back to [[Thomas Hiram Holding]], a British travelling tailor, but it was actually first popularised in the UK on the [[river Thames]]. By the 1880s large numbers of visitors took part in the pastime, which was connected to the late Victorian craze for pleasure boating. The early camping equipment was very heavy, so it was convenient to transport it by boat or to use craft that converted into tents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Wenham|first=S. M.|title=The River Thames and the Popularisation of Camping, 1860–1980|url=http://www.oxoniensia.org|work=[[Oxoniensia]] LXXX|date=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although [[Thomas Hiram Holding]] is often seen as the father of modern camping in the UK, he was responsible for popularising a different type of camping in the early twentieth century. He experienced the activity in the wild from his youth, when he had spent much time with his parents traveling across the American prairies. Later he embarked on a cycling and camping tour with some friends across [[Ireland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Wills|first=Dixe|title=Camping? It should be about the simple life|url=https://www.theguardian.com/travel/2011/apr/16/campsites-outdoors-dixe-wills|accessdate=24 July 2011|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=16 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; His book on his Ireland experience, ''Cycle and Camp in Connemara'' led to the formation of the first camping group in 1901, the Association of Cycle Campers, later to become the [[Camping and Caravanning Club]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Thomas Hiram Holding|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/269179/Thomas-Hiram-Holding|work=[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]|accessdate=24 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He wrote ''The Campers Handbook'' in 1908, so that he could share his enthusiasm for the great outdoors with the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Thomas Hiram Holding|url=http://www.npg.org.uk/collections/search/person/mp103685/thomas-hiram-holding|publisher=[[National Portrait Gallery, London]]|accessdate=24 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Possibly the first commercial camping ground in the world was [[Cunningham's Camp Escalator|Cunningham’s camp]], near [[Douglas, Isle of Man]], which opened in 1894. In 1906 the Association of Cycle Campers opened its first own camping site, in [[Weybridge]]. By that time the organization had several hundred members. In 1910 the Association was merged into the National Camping Club. Although WW1 was responsible for a certain hiatus in camping activity, the association received a new lease of life after the war when [[Sir Robert Baden-Powell]] (founder of the [[Scouting|Boy Scouts movement]]) became its president.

In the US, camping may be traced to [[William Henry Harrison Murray]] 1869 publication of ''Camp-Life in the Adirondacks'' resulting in a flood of visitors to the Adirondacks that summer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Young|first1=Terence|title=The Minister Who Invented Camping in America Read more|url=https://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/religious-roots-of-americas-love-for-camping-180965280/|accessdate=23 October 2017|work=[[Smithsonian (magazine)|Smithsonian]]|date=17 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The International Federation of Camping Clubs (Federation Internationale de Camping et de Caravanning) was founded in 1932 with national clubs from all over the world affiliating with it. By the 1960s camping had become an established family holiday standard and today camp sites are ubiquitous across [[Europe]] and [[North America]].

==Forms==
[[File:Mt. Forbes bivy site; by North Glacier.jpg|thumb|Camping as part of mountaineering]]
Different types camping may be named after their form of transportation, such as with [[Canoe camping]], car camping, 
[[Recreational vehicle|RVing]], and [[Backpacking (wilderness)|backpacking]], which can involve [[Ultralight backpacking|ultralight]] gear. 

Camping is also labeled by lifestyle: [[Glamping]] (glamorous camping) combines camping with the luxury and amenities of a home or hotel,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://travel.usatoday.com/destinations/story/2011/08/Go-glamping-in-the-Ohio-Wilds/49819754/1| title='Glamping' brings creature comforts to outdoors|date=2011-08-04|accessdate= 2015-11-27 |work=USA Today |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131206162540/http://travel.usatoday.com/destinations/story/2011/08/Go-glamping-in-the-Ohio-Wilds/49819754/1 |archive-date=December 6, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has its roots are in the early 1900s European and American [[safari]]s in Africa. [[Workamping]] allows campers to trade their labor variously for discounts on campsite fees, campground utilities, and even some degree of pay. [[Migrant_worker|Migrant]] camps are formed not for recreation, but as a temporary housing arrangement. Campgrounds for [[custom harvesting|custom harvesters]] in the United States may include room to park combines and other large farm equipment.

Another way of describing camping is by the manner of arrangement: reservation camping vs. drop camping. Campgrounds may require campers to check in with an employee or campground host prior to setting up camp, or they may allow &quot;drop camping,&quot; where this is not required. Drop-in campsites may be free or a drop-box may be provided to accept payments on the [[Honor_system#Tourism|honor system]]. Although drop camping is often specifically allowed by law, it may also exist in a legal [[Loophole|grey area]], such as at California's [[Slab City]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=EOERtAEACAAJ Slab City: Dispatches from the Last Free Place] by Charlie Hailey, MIT Press, 2018&lt;/ref&gt; Social media-oriented towards drop camping provides information on recent police enforcement, campsite quality, cost, and length-of-stay requirements.

==Campgrounds and commercial campsites==
[[File:Trailer Camping Marmora KOA May 2006.jpg|thumb|[[Tent trailer]] camping provides comfort in a towable package]]

Campers span a broad range of age, ability, and ruggedness, and [[campsite]]s are designed in many ways as well. Many campgrounds have sites with facilities such as fire rings, barbecue grills, utilities, shared bathrooms and laundry, as well as access to nearby recreational facilities, but not all campsites have similar levels of development. Campsites can range from a patch of dirt, to a level, paved pad with sewer and electricity. (For more information on facilities, see the campsite and [[RV park]] articles.)

Other vehicles used for camping include motorcycles, touring bicycles, boats, canoes, [[pack animal]]s, and even [[bush planes]]; although [[Backpacking (wilderness)|backpacking]] on foot is a popular alternative.
[[File:Camping-car de type bus.JPG|thumb|A large [[recreational vehicle]] provides many amenities when camping.]]
Tent camping sites often cost less than campsites with full amenities, and most allow direct access by car. Some &quot;walk-in&quot; sites lie a short walk away from the nearest road, but do not require full backpacking equipment. Those who seek a rugged experience in the outdoors prefer to camp with only tents, or with no shelter at all (&quot;under the stars&quot;).

==By country==

===United States===
From 2012 to 2013, over 40 million Americans - 14% of the United States population - went camping with a net loss of only 423,955 participants. According to an infographic produced by Red Rover Camping and based on data from the 2014 American Camper Report published by the Coleman Company, Inc. and the Outdoor Foundation, camping in the United States is gaining popularity after losing a net of 4.2 million participants from 2011 to 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2014 American Camper Report|url=http://www.outdoorfoundation.org/pdf/research.camping.2014.pdf|publisher=The Coleman Company, Inc. and the Outdoor Foundation|accessdate=17 June 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150405060353/http://www.outdoorfoundation.org/pdf/research.camping.2014.pdf|archive-date=5 April 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
According to data provided by the Great British Tourism Survey conducted by Visit England, almost 4.5 million camping and caravanning holidays were taken by British residents during the first half of 2015, for an average of 3.7 nights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.visitengland.com/sites/default/files/gbts_june_2015_detailed_report_final_1.pdf | title=Great Britain Tourism Survey | publisher=VisitEngland | date=June 2015 | accessdate=21 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; As with the United States, camping is gaining popularity, with an 8% increase in trips versus the same period of 2014.


===France===
Data collected by the Federation Nationale De L’Hotelleire De Plein Air (FNHPA) shows that around 113 million nights were taken of French campsites in 2015 which was up by 3.9% on the same period in 2014. This figure consisted of around 77 million French holidaymakers and the rest was made up of other nationalities, the majority of which were Dutch, German and UK tourists. The French Government are hoping to have 100 million tourists each year by 2030. The most popular region for camping is Languedoc and Roussillon with around 19,331,663 nights spent at campsites during 2015, whilst the department with the most campsites is the Vendee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.fnhpa-pro.fr/dossierdepresse2016.pdf | title=FNHPA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
[[File:Camping by Barriere Lake, British Columbia - 20040801.jpg|thumb|Camping by [[Barrière River (North Thompson River)|Barrière Lake]], [[Barriere, British Columbia|Barriere]], [[British Columbia]]]]
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
*[[Backpacking with animals]]
* [[Camping coach]]
* [[Camping food]]
* [[Campsite]]
* [[Caravan parks]]
* [[Fire]]
** [[Bow drill]]
** [[Firelighting]]
** [[Firesteel]]
** [[Lighter]]
* [[Hammock]]
* [[Hammock camping]]
* [[Backpacking (wilderness)#food|Hiking-wilderness food]]
* [[List of human habitation forms]]
* [[Outdoor cooking]]
* [[Bell tent]]
* [[Tarp tent]]
* [[Wilderness acquired diarrhea]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
[[File:Backcountry camping in the Tropics.jpg|thumb|Backcountry camping in [[Costa Rica]]]]
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links |wikt=camp |commons=Category:Camping |b=Backpack camping and woodland survival |n=no |q= no|s=no |v=no |voy=Camping |species=no |d=no |display=Camping }}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100528004529/http://cdi.uvm.edu/collections/getCollection.xql?title=Long%20Trail%20Photographs Images of historic camping and hiking on the Long Trail, Center for Digital Initiatives, University of Vermont Library]
* [http://watch.opb.org/video/2365530785/ Reflections of Summer: Car Camping!]  Video produced by [[Oregon Field Guide]]

{{Adventure travel}}

[[Category:Camping| ]]
[[Category:Procedural knowledge]]
[[Category:Scoutcraft]]
[[Category:Survival skills]]
[[Category:Types of tourism]]

[[eu:Kanpin]]</text>
      <sha1>dzyyqxshrz1ciimza3i4gh64mgkgwww</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
