  <page>
    <title>Catfishing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43964358</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937381383</id>
      <parentid>937367864</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-24T17:36:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Paul Magnussen</username>
        <id>363188</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Grammar.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Deceptive online social network presence}}
{{distinguish|Catfisting}}
'''Catfishing''' is a  [[deception|deceptive]] activity where a person creates a [[Sockpuppet (Internet)|sockpuppet]] [[social networking]] presence, or [[Privacy concerns with social networking services|fake identity]] on a social network account, usually targeting a specific victim for abuse, deception, or fraud.  Catfishing is often employed for [[romance scam]]s on dating websites. The practice may be used for financial gain, to compromise a victim in some way, or simply as forms of [[trolling]] or wish fulfillment.  Catfishing media have been produced, often centering around victims who wish to identify their catfisher.  Celebrities have been targeted, which has brought media attention to catfishing practices.

==History==
Although some sources state that the modern term originated from the 2010 [[United States|American]] documentary ''[[Catfish (film)|Catfish]]'', the word has actually been used figuratively in the English language for decades.&lt;ref name=&quot;slate&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slate.com/blogs/browbeat/2013/01/18/catfish_meaning_and_definition_term_for_online_hoaxes_has_a_surprisingly.html |first=Aisha |last=Harris |title=Catfish meaning and definition: term for online hoaxes has a surprisingly long history |date=January 18, 2013 |work=[[Slate (magazine)|Slate]] |accessdate=2015-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Catfishing has become more widely known throughout the subsequent decade. It started from the documentary, and it eventually became a popular television series. This series follows the main star of the movie, Yaniv (Nev) Schulman. He helps other people investigate their possible catfish situation. This gives a lot of insight into the real lives that have been affected by catfishing. It also explores the motives behind the people who use fake identities to build relationships with online users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Martin|first1=Denise|title=Here's How MTV's Catfish Actually Works|url=http://www.vulture.com/2014/05/catfish-mtv-casting-production-process.html|publisher=Vulture|accessdate=6 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Vince Pierce, the husband of Angela Pierce—the subject of the ''Catfish'' documentary—the term catfish comes from fishermen &quot;putting [[sea catfish]] in with the [[cod]] to nip at their tails and keep them active&quot; during overseas transport in order to produce more lively and fresh meat.&lt;ref name=&quot;starcasm&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://starcasm.net/archives/184454|title=Why is MTV's 'Catfish' TV show called Catfish? |date=November 26, 2012 |work=starcasm.net |accessdate=2015-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; This etymology has been described as having &quot;all the hallmarks of [[apocryphal]] folklore&quot; by [[Ben Zimmer]] writing for ''[[The Boston Globe]]'', pointing out that catfish were used &quot;as a kind of [[Christianity|Christian]] [[parable]] (referring to the Atlantic rather than [as in Pierce's explanation] the Pacific fishing trade) in [[Henry W. Nevinson]]'s 1913 ''Essays in Rebellion'' and again in Charles Marriott's novel ''The Catfish'' published later the same year.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;boston-globe&quot; /&gt;

The term rose in popularity during an incident involving [[Notre Dame Fighting Irish football|University of Notre Dame football]] star [[Manti Te'o]] in 2013.&lt;ref name=&quot;slate&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;boston-globe&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bostonglobe.com/ideas/2013/01/27/catfish-how-manti-imaginary-romance-got-its-name/inqu9zV8RQ7j19BRGQkH7H/story.html |first=Ben |last=Zimmer |title=Catfish: How Manti Te'o's imaginary romance got its name |date=January 27, 2013 |newspaper=[[The Boston Globe]] |accessdate=2015-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a ''[[The Washington Post|Washington Post]]'' article&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/education/u-va-students-challenge-rolling-stone-account-of-attack/2014/12/10/ef345e42-7fcb-11e4-81fd-8c4814dfa9d7_story.html?hpid=z1 |title=U-Va. students challenge Rolling Stone account of alleged sexual assault |first=T. Rees |last=Shapiro |date=December 10, 2014|newspaper=[[The Washington Post]] |accessdate=2015-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ''[[Rolling Stone]]'' [[A Rape on Campus|University of Virginia rape hoax story]] may have been an example of catfishing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2014/dec/15/friends-uva-rape-accuser-begin-doubt-story/#ixzz3M2CfV7vo |title=U.Va. rape accuser's friends begin to doubt story |first=Jeffrey Scott |last=Shapiro |date=December 15, 2014 |newspaper=[[The Washington Times]] |accessdate=2015-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Sociology ==
Some online users  have used catfishing to explore their gender and/or sexual identities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lexington Books&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Slade|first1=Alison F.|last2=Narro|first2=Amber J.|last3=Buchanan|first3=Burton P. |title=Reality Television: Oddities of Culture |publisher=Lexington Books |isbn=978-0-7391-8564-3 |pages=237–244 |date=2014 |lastauthoramp=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, on the MTV show ''[[Catfish: The TV Show|Catfish]]'', based on the [[Catfish (film)|documentary]], a girl named Sonny connects with a male model named Jamison who is, in reality, Chelsea, a woman using her alternative identity to interact with other women in an online space.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lexington Books&quot;/&gt;

Financial gain can be another motive of catfishing. In 2015, three girls created a fake social media profile and managed to steal $3,300 from the [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|Islamic State]], a terrorist group. They had been approached by a recruitment officer and asked for money to go to Syria. After being given the money, they immediately deleted their account and pocketed the cash for their own personal travel.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.rt.com/news/311030-chechen-girls-con-isis/|title=Chechen girls swindle ISIS fighters for travel money|last=|first=|date=29 July 2015|website=RT News|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Catfishing can also be a tactic to stop criminals. In 2004, ''[[Dateline NBC]]'' produced the segment, ''[[To Catch a Predator]]'', which documented undercover cops posing as minors online to catch pedophiles.

Catfishing is used for multiple reasons. The person with the fake identity can catfish another user on the Internet to believe they are the person they portray themselves as. This often is used for relationships, such as the scenario in the movie ''Catfish.'' The person catfishing usually uses another real person's photos and life facts to make them appear as a real person. Often, the real person who is being used for the fake identity does not even know that they are having their pictures and name used. They are not aware that their identity was used to create these fake relationships online. The person uses catfishing in order to appear as a better version of themselves by using a fake identity. Their primary reason to appear as a fake person is to befriend the other person for a relationship or other sexual reasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Lohmann|first1=Raychelle|title=The Two-Sided Face of Teen Catfishing|url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/teen-angst/201304/the-two-sided-face-teen-catfishing|publisher=Psychology Today|accessdate=6 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; It can also be used as a way to cyberbully someone online. By using a fake identity, it is easy for the person to get away with bullying on the internet. Since they are using another person's identity or a made up identity, the person will not get in trouble and will not have any consequences. The [[cyberbullying]] cannot be traced back to them, which is a big reason why they use a fake identity in the first place. This type of cyberbullying has increased the number of [[suicides]] in teens over the past few years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Patchin|first1=Justin W.|title=Catfishing as a Form of Cyberbullying|url=https://cyberbullying.org/catfishing-as-a-form-of-cyberbullying|publisher=Cyberbullying Research Center|accessdate=29 March 2018|date=2013-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Dangers ==
There are many dangers of catfishing. It can be used to attract a person from the Internet and allow them to meet them in person. The person catfishing can lure people to a place to kidnap, or hurt in any other way. It is a new way for sexual predators to interact with their victims and possibly harm. These sexual predators use their fake identity to talk to teens, allowing them to get close to them so that the victim will trust them. It is then easy for the predator to get information from the victim so that they can use that information to harm them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Lohmann|first1=Raychelle|title=The Two-Sided Face of Teen Catfishing|url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/teen-angst/201304/the-two-sided-face-teen-catfishing|publisher=Psychology Today|accessdate=29 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Signs ==
There are several ways people can spot a catfisher, all of which are imperfect. If a random person starts following or messaging a user, and the person's profile picture looks fake or too good to be true, then the person may be catfishing. If the person messaging does not want to video chat, or keeps finding excuses to not meet up, they might be a catfisher as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=McHugh|first1=Molly|title=It's catfishing season! How to tell lovers from liars online, and more|url=https://www.digitaltrends.com/web/its-catfishing-season-how-to-tell-lovers-from-liars-online-and-more/|publisher=Digital Trends|accessdate=6 April 2018|date=2013-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; [https://tineye.com Tineye Image Search] and [https://images.google.com/ Google Image Search] can be used to help verify images.

Additionally, some catfishers have poor English and you can tell it isn't their first language. Therefore, they use copy/paste functions to send a long, generic message talking about love, trust, sincerity, and/or faith. If such a message is relayed with very little typing time, there's good chance that they are a catfisher using copy/paste. Particularly if the rest of their English isn't that good.

===Example===
The identity of an [[Australia]]n actor, [[Lincoln Lewis]], was used by an impersonator over four years. The actions resulted in the suicide of one victim, who had at one point reached out to the real Lincoln Lewis as they had attended [[primary school]] together, so she was familiar with some aspects of his life that were discovered and exploited by the perpetrator. The female perpetrator operated from at least mid-2011 until arrested in mid-2016, and in early 2019 was found guilty of stalking six people.&lt;ref name=&quot;2019-04-09_ABC&quot;&gt;[https://www.abc.net.au/news/2019-04-09/lincoln-lewis-warns-of-social-media-catfish-dangers/10985118 Lincoln Lewis warns of social media dangers after online impersonator convicted of stalking], [[ABC News Online]], 2019-04-09&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;2019-04-09_ABC_JO&quot;&gt;[https://www.abc.net.au/news/2019-04-09/lincoln-lewis-fake-catfish-internet-stalker-court-trial/10919538 Catching a catfish: A terrifying story of virtual deceit and inexplicable malice, perpetrated by the last person anyone expected.], James Oaten, ABC News Online]], 2019-04-09&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{wiktionary}}
* [[Gaslighting]]
* [[Trojan Horse]]
* [[Münchausen syndrome]]
* [[Phishing]]
* [[Honey trapping]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{scams and confidence tricks}}

[[Category:Deception]]
[[Category:Internet fraud]]
[[Category:Social networks]]</text>
      <sha1>467uprttf958kbdj9iebwb5zys0jp56</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
