  <page>
    <title>Commerce</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39208</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937772441</id>
      <parentid>937772420</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-27T03:53:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>El C</username>
        <id>92203</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>{{pp-protected|small=yes}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{About|the business concept}}
{{Refimprove|date=March 2007}}
{{mergeto|Trade|discuss=Talk:Trade#Merge from commerce|date=November 2019}}

[[File:Hans Holbein The Younger Portrait of the merchant Georg Gisze 1532.jpg|thumb|upright=1.15|Portrait of 16th century merchant Georg Gisze]]

'''Commerce''' is the exchange of [[goods and services]], especially on a large scale.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/commerce
|work=English: Oxford Living Dictionaries
|title=commerce 
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|quote =  '''1''' The activity of buying and selling, especially on a large scale.
|date=n.d. |access-date=December 11, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; It includes legal, economic, political, social, cultural and technological [[system]]s that operate in a country or in [[international trade]].

In economic sense it refers to the conduct of trade among economic agents.[https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/commerce.asp]  Commerce generally affects the well being and welfare of the citizens as it is known to directly impact the money which people have and their job opportunities as well. Commerce may also refer to buying and selling of commodities globally or across borders between governments and even business firms.  

Many scholars and ancient philosophers have known to mix up the terms trade and commerce. But in essence these two are distinct terms carrying different meanings. Trade on one hand may mean the selling and buying of commodities for money or anything of value but Commerce is a much broader term and includes Trade along with the services which facilitate such buying and selling of goods. These services may include insurance, warehousing, transporting and advertising.[https://keydifferences.com/difference-between-trade-and-commerce.html] 

==Etymology==
The English-language word ''commerce'' has been derived from the [[Latin]] word ''commercium'', from ''cum'' (&quot;together&quot;) and ''merx'' (&quot;merchandise&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite EB1911
|wstitle= Commerce |volume= 6 |page= 766
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The word then got converted to French language to finally give us &quot;Commerce&quot; which essentially means facilitating trading or allowing for exchange of goods and services.

==History==
[[File:Caduceus.svg|thumb|left|upright=0.45|The [[caduceus]] - used today as the symbol of commerce,&lt;ref&gt;Hans Biedermann, James Hulbert (trans.), ''Dictionary of Symbolism - Cultural Icons and the Meanings behind Them'', p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt; and traditionally associated with the Roman god [[Mercury (mythology)|Mercury]], patron of commerce, trickery and thieves.]]

Apart from traditional [[self-sufficiency]], [[trade|trading]] became a principal{{cn|date=January 2020}} [[Faculty (disambiguation)|facility]] of [[prehistoric people]], who [[barter]]ed what they had for goods and services from each other (the barter system was popular in ancient times where one could get goods and services by offering the other person some other good and service according to their need instead of paying with [[monetary systems]], which developed later). Historian [[Peter Watson (business writer) | Peter Watson]] and Ramesh Manickam date the [[History of international trade| history of long-distance commerce]] from [[circa]] 150,000 years ago.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Watson, Peter | title = Ideas : A History of Thought and Invention from Fire to Freud | publisher = HarperCollins | year = 2005| isbn = 0-06-621064-X}} Introduction......./&lt;/ref&gt; [[Roman commerce]] included routes across the Mediterranean and to and from India.

In historic times, the introduction of [[currency]] as a standardized [[money]] facilitated the wider exchange of goods and services. [[Numismatist]]s have collections of tokens, which include [[coin]]s from some Ancient-World large-scale societies, although initial usage involved unmarked lumps of [[precious metal]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Gold]] served especially commonly as a form of early [[money]], as described in [http://www.ex.ac.uk/~RDavies/arian/origins.html &quot;Origins of Money and of Banking&quot;] - {{cite book | author= Davies, Glyn | title = Ideas: A history of money from ancient times to the present day | publisher = University of Wales Press | year = 2002| isbn = 0-7083-1717-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; This means that even if there were no notes or coins people used precious metal like Gold, Silver etc. attached a value to it and then use them for exchange in return for commodities.

The circulation of a standardized currency provides a method of overcoming the major disadvantage to commerce through use of a [[barter (economics) |barter]] system, the &quot;[[double coincidence of wants]]&quot; (which means if someone wants something from a person, that person should also be in need of a thing or a service which they can provide), necessary for barter trades to occur. For example, if a person who makes pots for a living needs a new house, they may wish to hire someone to build it for them. But they cannot make an equivalent number of pots to equal this service done for them, because even if the builder could build the house, the builder might not want many or need any pots.  

The barter system also has a major drawback in that whatever goods a person gets as payment may not necessarily store for long amounts of time. For example: if a person receives dozens of fruits as  payment, the fruit may not store for long or may rot - which means that person will have to bear a loss. 

Currency alleviated these problems by allowing a [[society]] as a whole to assign [[Value (economics) | values]]{{citation needed|date = November 2013}} and thus to collect goods and services effectively and to store them for later use, or to split them among minions.

During the [[Middle Ages]], European commerce developed through the trading of [[luxury goods]] at trade [[fair]]s. Some{{quantify|date=January 2020}} [[wealth]] became converted into movable wealth or [[Capital (economics) |capital]].{{cn|date= August 2018}} [[Banking system]]s developed where money on account was transferred{{by whom?|date= August 2018}} across national boundaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howell2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author= Martha C. Howell |title= Commerce Before Capitalism in Europe, 1300-1600 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=ZKhZTqkqfkEC |date= 12 April 2010 |publisher= Cambridge University Press |isbn= 978-0-521-76046-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hand-to-hand [[marketplace | market]]s became a feature of town life, and were regulated by town authorities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Braudel1982&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|author= Fernand Braudel
|title= Civilization and Capitalism, 15th-18th Century: The wheels of commerce
|url= https://books.google.com/books?id=WPDbSXQsvGIC
|year= 1982|publisher= University of California Press
|isbn= 978-0-520-08115-4|page= 30
|quote = Taken over by towns, the markets grew apace with them.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

{{As of |2007 |alt= Today}} commerce includes as a subset of itself a complex system of [[corporation |companies]] which try to maximize their profits by offering [[product (business) | product]]s and [[Service (economics) | services]] to the [[Market (economics) | market]] (which consists both of individuals and groups and other companies or institutions) at the lowest [[production cost]]. A system of [[international trade]] has helped to develop the [[world economy]]; but, in combination with bilateral or multilateral agreements to lower [[tariff]]s or to achieve [[free trade]], has sometimes harmed [[Third World | third-world markets]] for local products (see [[Globalization]]).

== Components ==
A majorly important component of Commerce is '''Trade.''' It is essentially a smaller version of commerce in a way that it refers to the actual buying and selling of goods only. Commerce includes all the activities related to Trade such as-:

* Insurance : Protection of Goods against theft, fire etc. any human or natural calamity as stipulated before hand
* Banking : Related to financing of the transactions
* Warehousing : Puts focus over storage related issues such keeping goods in a safe place such as a &quot;warehouse&quot; till they are sold to the customers, etc.
* Transportation : This involves carrying goods from the place of their production to their actual place of sale

==See also==
{{cols|colwidth=13em}}
* [[Advertising]]
* [[Bachelor of Commerce]]
* [[Business]]
* [[Capitalism]]
* [[Commeircial law]]
* [[Distribution (business)]]
** [[Wholesale]]
** [[Retailing]]
* [[Cargo]]
* [[Eco commerce]]
* [[Economics|Economy]]
* [[Electronic commerce]]
* [[Export]]
* [[Fair]]
* [[Finance]]
* [[Fishery]]
* [[Harvest]]
* [[Industry]]
* [[BBA]]
* [[Import]]
* [[Laissez-faire]]
* [[Manufacturing]]
* [[Marketing]]
* [[Marketplace]]
* [[Mass production]]
* [[Master of Commerce]]
* [[Merchandising]]
* [[Trade]]
{{colend}}

==References==
{{wiktionary}}
{{reflist}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Trade]]</text>
      <sha1>ero58ay7ku6g8gmknjogrnlh8o1dlr7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
