  <page>
    <title>Cricket</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25675557</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938093811</id>
      <parentid>938092496</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-29T02:17:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DocWatson42</username>
        <id>38455</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Cleaned up [[MOS:LAYOUT]] and other matters.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Team sport played with bats and balls}}
{{About|the sport|the insect|Cricket (insect)|other uses}}
{{Redirect|Cricketer}}
{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{Use British English|date=May 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2019}}
{{Infobox sport
| name              = Cricket
| image             = Eden Gardens under floodlights during a match.jpg
| imagesize         = 300 px
| caption           = {{Longitem|[[Eden Gardens]], India under floodlights during [[2016 ICC World Twenty20 Final]]}}
| union             = [[International Cricket Council]]
| first             = 16th century; South-East England
| registered        =
| clubs             =
| contact           = No
| team              = 11 players per side ([[Substitute (cricket)|substitutes]] permitted in some circumstances)
| mgender           = Yes, separate competitions
| type              = [[Team sport]], [[bat-and-ball games|Bat-and-Ball]]
| ball              = [[cricket ball|Cricket Ball]], [[Cricket Bat]], [[Wicket]] ([[Stump (cricket)|Stumps]], [[Bail (cricket)|Bails]]), [[Cricket clothing and equipment|Various protective equipment]]
| venue             = [[Cricket field]]
| glossary          = [[Glossary of cricket terms]]
| region            = Commonwealth
| olympic           = ([[1900 Summer Olympics]] only)
}}
{{Cricket sidebar |expanded=all}}

'''Cricket''' is a [[Bat-and-ball games|bat-and-ball game]] played between two teams of eleven players on a [[cricket field|field]] at the centre of which is a {{convert|20|m|yds|adj=on|abbr=off}} [[cricket pitch|pitch]] with a [[wicket]] at each end, each comprising two [[Bail (cricket)|bails]] balanced on three [[stump (cricket)|stumps]]. The [[batting (cricket)|batting]] side scores [[run (cricket)|runs]] by striking the [[cricket ball|ball]] bowled at the wicket with the bat, while the [[Bowling (cricket)|bowling]] and [[fielding (cricket)|fielding]] side tries to prevent this and [[dismissal (cricket)|dismiss]] each player (so they are &quot;out&quot;). Means of dismissal include being [[bowled]], when the ball hits the stumps and dislodges the bails, and by the fielding side catching the ball after it is hit by the bat, but before it hits the ground. When ten players have been dismissed, the [[innings]] ends and the teams swap roles. The game is adjudicated by two [[umpire (cricket)|umpires]], aided by a [[third umpire]] and [[match referee]] in international matches. They communicate with two off-field [[Scoring (cricket)|scorers]] who record the match's [[Cricket statistics|statistical information]].

There are various [[forms of cricket|formats]] ranging from [[Twenty20]], played over a few hours with each team batting for a single innings of 20 [[Over (cricket)|overs]], to [[Test cricket|Test matches]], played over five days with unlimited overs and the teams each batting for two innings of unlimited length. Traditionally cricketers play in all-white [[Cricket clothing and equipment|kit]], but in [[limited overs cricket]] they wear club or team colours. In addition to the basic kit, some players wear [[cricket clothing and equipment|protective gear]] to prevent injury caused by the ball, which is a hard, solid spheroid made of compressed [[leather]] with a slightly raised sewn seam enclosing a [[cork (material)|cork]] core which is layered with tightly wound string.

[[History of cricket|Historically]], cricket's origins are uncertain and the earliest definite reference is in [[South East England|south-east England]] in the middle of the 16th century. It spread globally with the expansion of the [[British Empire]], leading to the first international matches in the second half of the 19th century. The game's governing body is the [[International Cricket Council]] (ICC), which has over 100 members, twelve of which are [[List of International Cricket Council members|full members]] who play Test matches. The game's rules are held in a code called the ''[[Laws of Cricket]]'' which is owned and maintained by [[Marylebone Cricket Club]] (MCC) in [[London]]. The sport is followed primarily in the [[Indian subcontinent]], Australasia, the United Kingdom, [[southern Africa]] and the [[West Indies]], its globalisation occurring during the expansion of the British Empire and remaining popular into the 21st century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.espncricinfo.com/story/_/id/23920270/icc-survey-reveals-billion-fans-90-subcontinent|title=ICC survey reveals over a billion fans – 90% in subcontinent}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Women's cricket]], which is organised and played separately, has also achieved international standard. The most successful side playing [[international cricket]] is [[Australia national cricket team|Australia]], which has won seven [[One Day International]] trophies, including five [[Cricket World Cup|World Cups]], more than any other country and has been the [[ICC Test Championship|top-rated Test side]] more than any other country.

==History==
{{main|History of cricket}}

===Origins===
{{main|History of cricket to 1725}}
Cricket is one of many games in the &quot;club ball&quot; sphere that basically involve hitting a ball with a hand-held implement; others include [[baseball]], [[golf]], [[hockey]], [[tennis]], [[squash (sport)|squash]], [[badminton]] and [[table tennis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;JM17&quot;&gt;Major (2007), p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; In cricket's case, a key difference is the existence of a solid target structure, the wicket (originally, it is thought, a &quot;wicket gate&quot; through which sheep were herded), that the batsman must defend.&lt;ref name=&quot;BWC1&quot;&gt;Barclays (1986), p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; The cricket historian [[Harry Altham]] identified three &quot;groups&quot; of &quot;club ball&quot; games: the &quot;hockey group&quot;, in which the ball is driven to and fro between two targets (the goals); the &quot;golf group&quot;, in which the ball is driven towards an undefended target (the hole); and the &quot;cricket group&quot;, in which &quot;the ball is aimed at a mark (the wicket) and driven away from it&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;HSA19&quot;&gt;Altham (1962), pp. 19–20.&lt;/ref&gt;

It is generally believed that cricket originated as a [[children's game]] in the south-eastern counties of England, sometime during the [[England in the Middle Ages|medieval period]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BWC1&quot;/&gt; Although there are claims for prior dates, the earliest definite reference to cricket being played comes from evidence given at a court case in [[Guildford]] on Monday, 17 January 1597 ([[Julian calendar]]; equating to 30 January 1598 in the [[Gregorian calendar]]). The case concerned ownership of a certain plot of land and the court heard the testimony of a 59-year-old [[coroner]], [[John Derrick]], who gave witness that:&lt;ref name=&quot;HSA21&quot;&gt;Altham (1962), p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DU3&quot;&gt;Underdown (2000), p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JM19&quot;&gt;Major (2007), p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Being a scholler in the [[Royal Grammar School, Guildford|ffree schoole of Guldeford]] hee and diverse of his fellows did runne and play there at creckett and other plaies.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Given Derrick's age, it was about half a century earlier when he was at school and so it is certain that cricket was being played c. 1550 by boys in [[Surrey]].&lt;ref name=&quot;JM19&quot;/&gt; The view that it was originally a children's game is reinforced by [[Randle Cotgrave]]'s 1611 English-French dictionary in which he defined the noun &quot;''crosse''{{-&quot;}} as &quot;the crooked staff wherewith boys play at cricket&quot; and the verb form &quot;''crosser''{{-&quot;}} as &quot;to play at cricket&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;HSA22&quot;&gt;Altham (1962), p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JM31&quot;&gt;Major (2007), p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;

One possible source for the sport's name is the [[Old English language|Old English]] word &quot;''cryce''{{-&quot;}} (or &quot;''cricc''{{-&quot;}}) meaning a crutch or staff. In [[Samuel Johnson]]'s ''Dictionary'', he derived cricket from &quot;''cryce'', Saxon, a stick&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;HSA21&quot;/&gt; In [[Old French]], the word &quot;''criquet''{{-&quot;}} seems to have meant a kind of club or stick.&lt;ref name=&quot;DB3&quot;&gt;Birley (1999), p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Given the strong medieval trade connections between south-east England and the [[County of Flanders]] when the latter belonged to the [[Duchy of Burgundy]], the name may have been derived from the [[Middle Dutch]] (in use in [[County of Flanders|Flanders]] at the time) &quot;''krick''{{-&quot;}}(''-e''), meaning a stick (crook).&lt;ref name=&quot;DB3&quot;/&gt; Another possible source is the Middle Dutch word &quot;''krickstoel''{{-&quot;}}, meaning a long low stool used for kneeling in church and which resembled the long low [[wicket]] with two [[stump (cricket)|stumps]] used in early cricket.&lt;ref&gt;Bowen (1970), p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Heiner Gillmeister, a European language expert of [[Bonn University]], &quot;cricket&quot; derives from the Middle Dutch phrase for [[hockey]], ''met de (krik ket)sen'' (i.e., &quot;with the stick chase&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;17CGC&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.la84foundation.org/SportsLibrary/SportsHistorian/2000/sh201e.pdf |last=Terry |first=David |title=The Seventeenth Century Game of Cricket: A Reconstruction of the Game |work=The Sports Historian, No. 20 |publisher=The British Society of Sports History |location=London |year=2000 |pages=33–43 |accessdate=2 May 2016 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/5laxwhCZO?url=http://www.la84foundation.org/SportsLibrary/SportsHistorian/2000/sh201e.pdf |archivedate=27 November 2009 |df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gillmeister has suggested that not only the name but also the sport itself may be of Flemish origin.&lt;ref name=&quot;17CGC&quot;/&gt;

===Growth of amateur and professional cricket in England===
[[File:Historical cricket bat art.jpg|thumb|right|Evolution of the cricket bat. The original &quot;hockey stick&quot; (left) evolved into the straight bat from c. 1760 when [[pitched delivery bowling]] began.]]
Although the main object of the game has always been to score the most [[run (cricket)|runs]], the early form of cricket differed from the modern game in certain key technical aspects. The [[cricket ball|ball]] was [[underarm bowling|bowled underarm]] by the [[bowling (cricket)|bowler]] and all along the ground towards a [[batting (cricket)|batsman]] armed with a [[cricket bat|bat]] that, in shape, resembled a [[hockey stick]]; the batsman defended a low, two-stump [[wicket]]; and runs were called &quot;notches&quot; because the [[scoring (cricket)|scorers]] recorded them by notching tally sticks.&lt;ref name=&quot;DB9&quot;&gt;Birley (1999), p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BWC2&quot;&gt;Barclays (1986), pp. 1–2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JM21&quot;&gt;Major (2007), pp. 21–22.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1611, the year Cotgrave's dictionary was published, [[ecclesiastical court]] records at [[Sidlesham]] in [[Sussex]] state that two parishioners, Bartholomew Wyatt and Richard Latter, failed to attend church on Easter Sunday because they were playing cricket. They were fined 12[[Penny (British pre-decimal coin)|d]] each and ordered to do [[penance]].&lt;ref&gt;McCann (2004), p. xxxi.&lt;/ref&gt; This is the earliest mention of adult participation in cricket and it was around the same time that the earliest known organised inter-parish or [[village cricket|village]] match was played – at [[Chevening, Kent]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HSA21&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DU4&quot;&gt;Underdown (2000), p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1624, a player called [[Jasper Vinall]] died after he was accidentally struck on the head during a match between two parish teams in Sussex.&lt;ref&gt;McCann (2004), pp. xxxiii–xxxiv.&lt;/ref&gt;

Cricket remained a low-key local pursuit for much of the century.&lt;ref name=&quot;JM31&quot; /&gt; It is known, through numerous references found in the records of ecclesiastical court cases, to have been proscribed at times by the [[Puritans]] before and during the [[Commonwealth of England|Commonwealth]].&lt;ref&gt;McCann (2004), pp. xxxi–xli.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DU11&quot;&gt;Underdown (2000), pp. 11–15.&lt;/ref&gt; The problem was nearly always the issue of Sunday play as the Puritans considered cricket to be &quot;profane&quot; if played on the [[Sabbath]], especially if large crowds and/or [[gambling]] were involved.&lt;ref name=&quot;DB7&quot;&gt;Birley (1999), pp. 7–8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JM23&quot;&gt;Major (2007), p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the social historian [[Derek Birley]], there was a &quot;great upsurge of sport after the [[English Restoration|Restoration]]&quot; in 1660.&lt;ref name=&quot;DB11&quot;&gt;Birley (1999), p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; Gambling on sport became a problem significant enough for Parliament to pass the 1664 Gambling Act, limiting stakes to £100 which was, in any case, a colossal sum exceeding the annual income of 99% of the population.&lt;ref name=&quot;DB11&quot;/&gt; Along with [[prizefighting]], [[horse racing]] and blood sports, cricket was perceived to be a gambling sport.&lt;ref&gt;Birley (1999), pp. 11–13.&lt;/ref&gt; Rich patrons made matches for high stakes, forming teams in which they engaged the first professional players.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW10&quot;&gt;Webber (1960), p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the century, cricket had developed into a major sport which was spreading throughout England and was already being taken abroad by English mariners and colonisers – the earliest reference to cricket overseas is dated 1676.&lt;ref&gt;Haygarth (1862), p. vi.&lt;/ref&gt; A 1697 newspaper report survives of &quot;a great cricket match&quot; played in Sussex &quot;for fifty guineas apiece&quot; – this is the earliest known match that is generally considered [[first-class cricket|top-class]].&lt;ref&gt;McCann (2004), p. xli.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Major (2007), page 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

The patrons, and other players from the social class known as the &quot;[[gentry]]&quot;, began to classify themselves as &quot;[[Amateur status in first-class cricket|amateurs]]&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;amateur&quot; group=&quot;fn&quot;&gt;The term &quot;amateur&quot; in this context does not mean someone who played cricket in his spare time. Many amateurs in [[first-class cricket]] were full-time players during the cricket season. Some of the game's greatest players, including [[W. G. Grace]], held amateur status.&lt;/ref&gt; to establish a clear distinction ''vis-à-vis'' the professionals, who were invariably members of the [[working class]], even to the point of having separate changing and dining facilities.&lt;ref&gt;Major (2007), pp. 268–269.&lt;/ref&gt; The gentry, including such high-ranking nobles as the [[Duke of Richmond|Dukes of Richmond]], exerted their honour code of ''[[noblesse oblige]]'' to claim rights of leadership in any sporting contests they took part in, especially as it was necessary for them to play alongside their &quot;social inferiors&quot; if they were to win their bets.&lt;ref name=&quot;DB19&quot;&gt;Birley (1999), p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; In time, a perception took hold that the typical amateur who played in [[first-class cricket]], until 1962 when amateurism was abolished, was someone with a [[Public school (United Kingdom)|public school]] education who had then gone to one of [[University of Cambridge|Cambridge]] or [[University of Oxford|Oxford University]] – society insisted that such people were &quot;officers and gentlemen&quot; whose destiny was to provide leadership.&lt;ref name=&quot;CW23&quot;&gt;Williams (2012), p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; In a purely financial sense, the cricketing amateur would ''theoretically'' claim expenses for playing while his professional counterpart played under contract and was paid a wage or match fee; in practice, many amateurs claimed somewhat more than actual expenditure and the derisive term &quot;shamateur&quot; was coined to describe the syndrome.&lt;ref&gt;Williams (2012), pp. 94–95.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DB146&quot;&gt;Birley (1999), p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt;

===English cricket in the 18th and 19th centuries===
[[File:Francis Cotes - The young cricketer (1768).jpg|thumb|upright|[[Francis Cotes]], ''The Young Cricketer'', 1768]]
The game underwent major development in the 18th century to become England's national sport.{{citation needed|date=September 2017}} Its success was underwritten by the twin necessities of patronage and betting.&lt;ref&gt;Birley (1999), pp. 14–16.&lt;/ref&gt; Cricket was prominent in London as early as 1707 and, in the middle years of the century, large crowds flocked to matches on the [[Artillery Ground]] in Finsbury.{{citation needed|date=September 2017}} The [[single wicket cricket|single wicket]] form of the sport attracted huge crowds and wagers to match, its popularity peaking in the [[1748 English cricket season|1748 season]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ASW&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://stats.acscricket.com/Cricket/1900/index.html#10 |last=Ashley-Cooper |first=F. S. |authorlink=F. S. Ashley-Cooper |title=At the Sign of the Wicket: Cricket 1742–1751 |work=[[Cricket: A Weekly Record of the Game]] |publisher=[[Association of Cricket Statisticians and Historians|ACS]] |location=Cardiff |year=1900 |pages=4–85 |accessdate=8 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowling underwent an evolution around 1760 when bowlers began to [[Pitched delivery bowling|pitch the ball]] instead of rolling or skimming it towards the batsman. This caused a revolution in bat design because, to deal with the [[bouncing ball]], it was necessary to introduce the modern straight bat in place of the old &quot;hockey stick&quot; shape.&lt;ref&gt;Nyren (1833), pp. 153–154.&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=September 2017}}

The [[Hambledon Club]] was founded in the 1760s and, for the next twenty years until the formation of [[Marylebone Cricket Club]] (MCC) and the opening of [[Lord's Old Ground]] in 1787, Hambledon was both the game's greatest club and its focal point.{{citation needed|date=September 2017}} MCC quickly became the sport's premier club and the custodian of the ''[[Laws of Cricket]]''. New Laws introduced in the latter part of the 18th century included the three stump wicket and [[leg before wicket]] (lbw).&lt;ref name=&quot;WCA63&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Wisden |article=Evolution of the Laws of Cricket |title=Wisden Cricketers' Almanack, 100th edition |edition=1963 |publisher=Sporting Handbooks Ltd |location=London |pages=184–187}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 19th century saw [[underarm bowling]] superseded by first [[roundarm bowling|roundarm]] and then [[overarm bowling]]. Both developments were controversial.&lt;ref&gt;Birley (1999), pp. 64–67, 97–101.&lt;/ref&gt; Organisation of the game at county level led to the creation of the county clubs, starting with [[Sussex County Cricket Club|Sussex]] in 1839.&lt;ref&gt;Barclays (1986), p. 456.&lt;/ref&gt; In December 1889, the eight leading county clubs formed the official [[County Championship]], which began in 1890.&lt;ref name=&quot;AMCS&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://stats.acscricket.com/Cricket/1889/index.html#523/z |title=Annual Meeting of County Secretaries – the programme for 1890 |work=[[Cricket: A Weekly Record of the Game]] |publisher=[[Association of Cricket Statisticians and Historians|ACS]] |location=Cardiff |year=1889 |pages=478–479 |accessdate=3 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The most famous player of the 19th century was [[W. G. Grace]], who started his long and influential career in 1865. It was especially during the career of Grace that the distinction between amateurs and professionals became blurred by the existence of players like him who were nominally amateur but, in terms of their financial gain, ''de facto'' professional. Grace himself was said to have been paid more money for playing cricket than any professional.{{citation needed|date=September 2017}}

The last two decades before the [[World War I|First World War]] have been called the &quot;[[Golden Age of cricket]]&quot;. It is a nostalgic name prompted by the collective sense of loss resulting from the war, but the period did produce some great players and memorable matches, especially as organised competition at county and Test level developed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Frith |first=David |authorlink=David Frith |title=The Golden Age of Cricket: 1890–1914 |year=1978 |publisher=Lutterworth Press |location=Guildford |isbn=0-7188-7022-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cricket becomes an international sport===
[[File:England in North America 1859.jpg|thumb|right|The first English team to tour overseas, on board ship to North America, 1859]]
Meanwhile, the British Empire had been instrumental in spreading the game overseas and by the middle of the 19th century it had become well established in Australia, the Caribbean, India, New Zealand, North America and South Africa.&lt;ref&gt;Barclays (1986), pp. 62, 78, 87, 99, 113, 127 &amp; 131.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1844, the [[United States v Canada (1844)|first-ever international match]] took place between the [[United States national cricket team|United States]] and [[Canada national cricket team|Canada]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://content-uk.cricinfo.com/usa/content/story/141158.html |title=Cricinfo – Cricket in the USA |last=Das |first=Deb |accessdate=9 March 2007 |date=n.d. |publisher=ESPNcricinfo}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1859, a team of English players went to North America on [[English cricket team in North America in 1859|the first overseas tour]].&lt;ref&gt;Birley (1999), pp. 96–97.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1862, an English team made the first tour of Australia.&lt;ref&gt;Birley (1999), p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt; The first Australian team to travel overseas consisted of [[Indigenous Australians|Aboriginal]] [[Stockman (Australia)|stockmen]] who [[Australian Aboriginal cricket team in England in 1868|toured England in 1868]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nma.gov.au/collections/collection_interactives/cricketing_journeys/cricket_html/the_australian_eleven/the_australian_eleven_the_first_australian_team |title=The Australian Eleven: The first Australian team |publisher=National Museum of Australia |accessdate=30 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1876–77, an [[England cricket team|England team]] took part in what was retrospectively recognised as the first-ever [[Test cricket|Test match]] at the [[Melbourne Cricket Ground]] against [[Australia national cricket team|Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;Reg Hayter, &quot;The Centenary Test Match&quot;, ''[[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack|Wisden]]'' 1978, pp. 130–32.&lt;/ref&gt; The rivalry between England and Australia gave birth to [[The Ashes]] in 1882, and this has remained Test cricket's most famous contest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Wendy |last=Lewis |author-link=Wendy Lewis |author2=Simon Balderstone |author3=John Bowan |last-author-amp=yes |title=Events That Shaped Australia |page=75 |publisher=New Holland |year=2006 |isbn=978-1-74110-492-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Test cricket began to expand in 1888–89 when [[South Africa national cricket team|South Africa]] played England.{{citation needed|date=September 2017}}

===World cricket in the 20th century===
[[File:Bradman&amp;Bat.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Don Bradman]] of [[Australia national cricket team|Australia]] had a record Test batting average of 99.94.]]
The inter-war years were dominated by [[Australia national cricket team|Australia]]'s [[Don Bradman]], statistically the greatest Test batsman of all time. Test cricket continued to expand during the 20th century with the addition of the [[West Indies cricket team|West Indies]] (1928), [[New Zealand national cricket team|New Zealand]] (1930) and [[India national cricket team|India]] (1932) before the Second World War and then [[Pakistan national cricket team|Pakistan]] (1952), [[Sri Lanka national cricket team|Sri Lanka]] (1982), [[Zimbabwe national cricket team|Zimbabwe]] (1992), [[Bangladesh national cricket team|Bangladesh]] (2000), [[Ireland national cricket team|Ireland]] and [[Afghanistan national cricket team|Afghanistan]] (both 2018) in the post-war period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Wisden |article=Dates in Cricket History |title=Wisden Cricketers' Almanack, 100th edition |edition=1963 |publisher=Sporting Handbooks Ltd |location=London |page=183}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.espncricinfo.com/wisdenalmanack/content/story/152210.html |title=Notes by the Editor |work=Wisden Cricketers' Almanack online |date=1982 |publisher=ESPNcricinfo |accessdate=2 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[South Africa cricket team|South Africa]] was banned from international cricket from 1970 to 1992 as part of the [[Sporting boycott of South Africa during the apartheid era|apartheid boycott]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Booth |first=Douglas |title=The Race Game: Sport and Politics in South Africa |publisher=Routledge |year=1998 |page=88 |isbn=0-7146-4799-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The rise of limited overs cricket===
Cricket entered a new era in 1963 when English counties introduced the [[limited overs cricket|limited overs]] variant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Wisden |article=One-Day Knockout Competition, 1963 |title=Wisden Cricketers' Almanack, 100th edition |edition=1963 |publisher=Sporting Handbooks Ltd |location=London |pages=1074–1076}}&lt;/ref&gt; As it was sure to produce a result, limited overs cricket was lucrative and the number of matches increased.&lt;ref&gt;Barclays (1986), pp. 495–496.&lt;/ref&gt; The first [[Limited Overs International]] was played in 1971 and the governing [[International Cricket Council]] (ICC), seeing its potential, staged the first limited overs [[Cricket World Cup]] in 1975.&lt;ref&gt;Barclays (1986), pp. 496–497.&lt;/ref&gt; In the 21st century, a new limited overs form, [[Twenty20]], made an immediate impact.{{citation needed|date=September 2017}} On 22 June 2017, [[Afghanistan national cricket team|Afghanistan]] and [[Ireland cricket team|Ireland]] became the 11th and 12th ICC full members, enabling them to play [[Test cricket]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.espncricinfo.com/ci-icc/content/story/1105347.html |title=Afghanistan, Ireland get Test status |work=ESPNcricinfo |access-date=2 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.com/sport/cricket/40364481 |title=Ireland &amp; Afghanistan awarded Test status by International Cricket Council |date=2017 |work=BBC Sport |access-date=2 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Laws and gameplay==
{{main|Laws of Cricket}}
[[File:cricket field parts.svg|right|thumb|upright=0.9|A typical [[cricket field]].]]
In cricket, the rules of the game are specified in a code called ''[[The Laws of Cricket]]'' (hereinafter called &quot;the Laws&quot;) which has a global remit. There are 42 Laws (always written with a capital &quot;L&quot;). The earliest known version of the code was drafted in 1744 and, since 1788, it has been owned and maintained by its custodian, the [[Marylebone Cricket Club]] (MCC) in London.&lt;ref name=Laws&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/ |title=Laws |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=4 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Playing area===
{{main|Cricket field|Cricket pitch|Crease (cricket)|Wicket}}
Cricket is a [[bat-and-ball games|bat-and-ball game]] played on a [[cricket field]] (see image, right) between two teams of eleven players each.&lt;ref name=Law1&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-1-the-players/ |title=Law 1 – Players |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=1 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The field is usually circular or oval in shape and the edge of the playing area is marked by a [[boundary (cricket)|boundary]], which may be a fence, part of the stands, a rope, a painted line or a combination of these; the boundary must if possible be marked along its entire length.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-19-boundaries/ |title=Law 19 – Boundaries |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=3 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the approximate centre of the field is a rectangular [[cricket pitch|pitch]] (see image, below) on which a wooden target called a [[wicket]] is sited at each end; the wickets are placed {{convert|22|yd}} apart.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-7-the-pitch/ |title=Law 7 – The pitch |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=3 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The pitch is a flat surface {{convert|3|m|ft}} wide, with very short grass that tends to be worn away as the game progresses (cricket can also be played on artificial surfaces, notably matting). Each wicket is made of three wooden [[stump (cricket)|stumps]] topped by two [[bail (cricket)|bails]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-8-the-wickets/ |title=Law 8 – The wickets |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=3 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Cricket pitch.svg|thumb|upright=3.4|centre|Cricket pitch and creases]]
As illustrated above, the pitch is marked at each end with four white painted lines: a [[crease (cricket)|bowling crease]], a [[crease (cricket)|popping crease]] and two [[crease (cricket)|return creases]]. The three stumps are aligned centrally on the bowling crease, which is eight feet eight inches long. The popping crease is drawn four feet in front of the bowling crease and parallel to it; although it is drawn as a twelve-foot line (six feet either side of the wicket), it is, in fact, unlimited in length. The return creases are drawn at right angles to the popping crease so that they intersect the ends of the bowling crease; each return crease is drawn as an eight-foot line, so that it extends four feet behind the bowling crease, but is also, in fact, unlimited in length.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-9-bowling-popping-and-return-creases/ |title=Law 9 – The bowling, popping and return creases |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=3 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Match structure and closure===
{{main|Innings|Result (cricket)}}
[[File:A modern Cricket bat (back view).jpg|thumb|upright|A modern [[Sanspareils Greenlands|SG]] cricket bat (back view).]]
Before a match begins, the team [[captain (cricket)|captains]] (who are also players) [[toss (cricket)|toss a coin]] to decide which team will bat first and so take the first [[innings]].&lt;ref name=inns/&gt; [[Innings]] is the term used for each phase of play in the match.&lt;ref name=inns&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-12-innings/ |title=Law 12 – Innings |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=2 July 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170702074358/https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-12-innings/ |archive-date=2 July 2017 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; In each innings, one team [[batting (cricket)|bats]], attempting to [[scoring (cricket)|score]] [[run (cricket)|runs]], while the other team [[bowling (cricket)|bowls]] and [[fielding (cricket)|fields]] the [[cricket ball|ball]], attempting to restrict the scoring and [[dismissal (cricket)|dismiss]] the batsmen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-18-scoring-runs/ |title=Law 18 – Scoring runs |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=2 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-27-appeals/ |title=Law 27 – Appeals |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=2 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the first innings ends, the teams change roles; there can be two to four innings depending upon the type of match. A match with four scheduled innings is played over three to five days; a match with two scheduled innings is usually completed in a single day.&lt;ref name=inns/&gt; During an innings, all eleven members of the fielding team take the field, but usually only two members of the batting team are on the field at any given time. The exception to this is if a batsman has any type of illness or injury restricting his or her ability to run, in this case the batsman is allowed &quot;A Runner&quot; who can run between the wickets when the batsman hits a scoring run or runs,&lt;ref name=Law25&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws/batsman-s-innings;-runners|title=LAW 25 BATSMAN'S INNINGS; RUNNERS {{!}} MCC|website=www.lords.org|accessdate=2020-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; though this does not apply in international cricket.&lt;ref name=ICCTestPlayCond&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://icc-static-files.s3.amazonaws.com/ICC/document/2019/09/02/9182955c-04a4-4fa0-a2b6-f5908f02a51d/ICC-Test-Match-Playing-Conditions-Final-1-September-2019.pdf|title=ICC Test Match Playing Conditions|last=|first=|date=1 September 2019|website=ICC|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The order of batsmen is usually announced just before the match, but it can be varied.&lt;ref name=Law1/&gt;

The main objective of each team is to score more runs than their opponents but, in some forms of cricket, it is also necessary to dismiss all of the opposition batsmen in their final innings in order to win the match, which would otherwise be [[result (cricket)#Draw|drawn]].&lt;ref name=result&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-21-the-result/ |title=Law 21 – The result |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=2 July 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170115221857/https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-21-the-result/ |archive-date=15 January 2017 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; If the team batting last is all out having scored fewer runs than their opponents, they are said to have &quot;lost by ''n'' runs&quot; (where ''n'' is the difference between the aggregate number of runs scored by the teams). If the team that bats last scores enough runs to win, it is said to have &quot;won by ''n'' wickets&quot;, where ''n'' is the number of wickets left to fall. For example, a team that passes its opponents' total having lost six wickets (i.e., six of their batsmen have been [[dismissal (cricket)|dismissed]]) have won the match &quot;by four wickets&quot;.&lt;ref name=result/&gt;

In a two-innings-a-side match, one team's combined first and second innings total may be less than the other side's first innings total. The team with the greater score is then said to have &quot;won by an innings and ''n'' runs&quot;, and does not need to bat again: ''n'' is the difference between the two teams' aggregate scores. If the team batting last is all out, and both sides have scored the same number of runs, then the match is a [[Result (cricket)#Tie|tie]]; this result is quite rare in matches of two innings a side with only 62 happening in [[first-class cricket|first-class matches]] from the earliest known instance in 1741 until January 2017. In the traditional form of the game, if the time allotted for the match expires before either side can win, then the game is declared a [[result (cricket)#Draw|draw]].&lt;ref name=result/&gt;

If the match has only a single innings per side, then a maximum number of [[over (cricket)|overs]] applies to each innings. Such a match is called a &quot;limited overs&quot; or &quot;one-day&quot; match, and the side scoring more runs wins regardless of the number of wickets lost, so that a draw cannot occur. If this kind of match is temporarily interrupted by bad weather, then a complex mathematical formula, known as the [[Duckworth-Lewis method]] after its developers, is often used to recalculate a new target score. A one-day match can also be declared a &quot;no-result&quot; if fewer than a previously agreed number of overs have been bowled by either team, in circumstances that make normal resumption of play impossible; for example, wet weather.&lt;ref name=result/&gt;

In all forms of cricket, the umpires can abandon the match if bad light or rain makes it impossible to continue.&lt;ref name=Law3&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-3-the-umpires/ |title=Law 3 – The umpires |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=4 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; There have been instances of entire matches, even [[Test cricket|Test matches]] scheduled to be played over five days, being lost to bad weather without a ball being bowled: for example, the third Test of the 1970/71 series in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cricketarchive.co.uk/Archive/Scorecards/31/31362.html |title=Australia v England, 3rd Test, 1970/71 |publisher=CricketArchive |accessdate=4 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bat and ball===
{{main|Cricket bat|Cricket ball}}
{{multiple image
| footer = Two types of [[cricket ball]], both of the same size:
i) A used white ball. White balls are mainly used in [[limited overs cricket]], especially in matches played at night, under [[floodlights]] (left).&lt;br /&gt;
ii) A used red ball. Red balls are used in [[Test cricket]], [[first-class cricket]] and some other forms of cricket (right).
| image1 = White ball 2 (cropped).JPG
| alt1 = Used white ball
| width1 = 150
| width2 = 150
| image2 = Used cricket ball (cropped).jpg
| alt2 = Used red ball
}}
The essence of the sport is that a [[bowling (cricket)|bowler]] [[delivery (cricket)|delivers]] (i.e., bowls) the [[cricket ball|ball]] from his or her end of the [[cricket pitch|pitch]] towards the [[batting (cricket)|batsman]] who, armed with a [[cricket bat|bat]], is &quot;on strike&quot; at the other end (see next sub-section: ''Basic gameplay'').

The [[cricket bat|bat]] is made of wood, usually ''[[salix alba]]'' (white willow), and has the shape of a blade topped by a cylindrical handle. The blade must not be more than four and one quarter inches (108&amp;nbsp;mm) wide and the total length of the bat not more than 38 inches (965&amp;nbsp;mm). There is no standard for the weight, which is usually between 2&amp;nbsp;lb 7 oz and 3&amp;nbsp;lb (1.1 and 1.4&amp;nbsp;kg).&lt;ref name=Law6&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-6-the-bat/ |title=Law 6 – The bat |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=4 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/appendix-e-the-bat/ |title=Appendix E – The bat |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=4 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[cricket ball|ball]] is a hard leather-seamed [[spheroid]], with a circumference of {{convert|22.9|cm|in}}. The ball has a &quot;seam&quot;: six rows of stitches attaching the leather shell of the ball to the string and cork interior. The seam on a new ball is prominent and helps the bowler propel it in a less predictable manner. During matches, the quality of the ball deteriorates to a point where it is no longer usable;  during the course of this deterioration, its behaviour in flight will change and can influence the outcome of the match. Players will, therefore, attempt to modify the ball's behaviour by modifying its physical properties. Polishing the ball and wetting it with sweat or saliva is legal, even when the polishing is deliberately done on one side only to increase the ball's [[swing bowling|swing through the air]], but the acts of rubbing other substances into the ball, scratching the surface or picking at the seam are illegal [[ball tampering]].&lt;ref name=Law5&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-5-the-ball/ |title=Law 5 – The ball |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=4 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Basic gameplay: bowler to batsman===
During normal play, thirteen players and two [[umpire (cricket)|umpires]] are on the field. Two of the players are batsmen and the rest are all eleven members of the fielding team. The other nine players in the batting team are off the field in the [[cricket pavilion|pavilion]]. The image with overlay below shows what is happening when a ball is being bowled and which of the personnel are on or close to the pitch.&lt;ref&gt;The photo was taken during an international match between [[Australia national cricket team|Australia]] and [[Sri Lanka national cricket team|Sri Lanka]]; [[Muttiah Muralitharan]] of Sri Lanka is bowling to Australian batsman [[Adam Gilchrist]].&lt;/ref&gt;
{{overlay
|image=Muralitharan bowling to Adam Gilchrist.jpg
|width=500
|height=340
|grid=no
|overlay1=Umpire|overlay1left=75|overlay1top=2|overlay1tip=Bowler's end umpire|overlay1link=Umpire (cricket)
|overlay2=Wicket|overlay2left=105|overlay2top=68|overlay2tip=Wicket, bowler's end or non striking batsman's end|overlay2link=Wicket
|overlay3=Non-striking batsman|overlay3left=50|overlay3top=50|overlay3tip=Non-striking batsman|overlay3link=Batting (cricket)
|overlay4=Bowler|overlay4left=155|overlay4top=55|overlay4tip=Bowler, Muttiah Muralitharan|overlay4link=Bowling (cricket)
|overlay5=Ball|overlay5left=230|overlay5top=75|overlay5tip=White cricket ball in flight|overlay5link=Cricket ball
|overlay6=Pitch|overlay6left=235|overlay6top=165|overlay6tip=Cricket pitch, the whole area paler in colour|overlay6link=Cricket pitch
|overlay7=Popping crease|overlay7left=295|overlay7top=105|overlay7tip=Batting or popping crease|overlay7link=Crease (cricket)
|overlay7left2=265|overlay7top2=265|overlay7tip2=Batting or popping crease
|overlay8=Striking batsman|overlay8left=390|overlay8top=160|overlay8tip=Striking batsman, Adam Gilchrist|overlay8link=Batting (cricket)
|overlay9=Wicket|overlay9left=425|overlay9top=225|overlay9tip=Wicket, striking end|overlay9link=Wicket
|overlay10=Wicket-keeper|overlay10left=420|overlay10top=270|overlay10tip=Fielder in position, wicket keeper|overlay10link=Wicket-keeper
|overlay11=First slip|overlay11left=325|overlay11top=300|overlay11tip=Fielder in position, first slip for left hand batsman|overlay11link=Fielding (cricket)#Catching positions
|overlay12=Return crease|overlay12left=15|overlay12top=105|overlay12tip=Return crease, one each side of each wicket|overlay12link=Crease (cricket)
|overlay12left2=455|overlay12top2=235|overlay12tip2=Return crease, one either side of each wicket
}}

In the photo, the two [[batting (cricket)|batsmen]] (3 &amp; 8; wearing yellow) have taken position at each end of the [[cricket pitch|pitch]] (6). Three members of the [[fielding (cricket)|fielding]] team (4, 10 &amp; 11; wearing dark blue) are in shot. One of the two umpires (1; wearing white hat) is stationed behind the [[wicket]] (2) at the [[bowling (cricket)|bowler's]] (4) end of the pitch. The bowler (4) is [[delivery (cricket)|bowling]] the [[cricket ball|ball]] (5) from his end of the pitch to the batsman (8) at the other end who is called the &quot;striker&quot;. The other batsman (3) at the bowling end is called the &quot;non-striker&quot;. The [[wicket-keeper]] (10), who is a specialist, is positioned behind the striker's wicket (9) and behind him stands one of the fielders in a position called &quot;[[Fielding (cricket)#Catching positions|first slip]]&quot; (11). While the bowler and the first slip are wearing conventional kit only, the two batsmen and the wicket-keeper are wearing protective gear including safety helmets, padded gloves and leg guards (pads).

While the umpire (1) in shot stands at the bowler's end of the pitch, his colleague stands in the outfield, usually in or near the fielding position called &quot;[[square leg]]&quot;, so that he is in line with the [[popping crease]] (7) at the striker's end of the pitch. The bowling crease (not numbered) is the one on which the wicket is located between the return creases (12). The bowler (4) intends to hit the wicket (9) with the ball (5) or, at least, to prevent the striker (8) from scoring [[run (cricket)|runs]]. The striker (8) intends, by using his bat, to defend his wicket and, if possible, to hit the ball away from the pitch in order to score runs.

Some players are skilled in both batting and bowling, or as either or these as well as wicket-keeping, so are termed [[all-rounder]]s.  Bowlers are classified according to their style, generally as [[fast bowling|fast bowlers]], [[seam bowling|seam bowlers]] or [[spin bowling|spinners]]. Batsmen are classified according to whether they are right-handed or left-handed.

===Fielding===
{{main|Fielding (cricket)}}
[[File:Cricket fielding positions2.svg|thumb|upright=1.1|[[Fielding positions in cricket]] for a right-handed batsman]]
Of the eleven fielders, three are in shot in the image above. The other eight are elsewhere on the field, their positions determined on a tactical basis by the captain or the bowler. Fielders often change position between deliveries, again as directed by the captain or bowler.&lt;ref name=Law41&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-41-the-fielder/ |title=Law 41 – The fielder |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

If a fielder is injured or becomes ill during a match, a [[substitute (cricket)|substitute]] is allowed to field instead of him, but the substitute cannot bowl or act as a captain, except in the case of concussion substitutes in international cricket.&lt;ref name=ICCTestPlayCond/&gt; The substitute leaves the field when the injured player is fit to return.&lt;ref name=Law2&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-2-substitutes-and-runners-batsman-or-fielder-leaving-the-field-batsman-retiring-or-batsman-commencing-innings/ |title=Law 2 – Substitutes, etc. |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Laws of Cricket were updated in 2017 to allow substitutes to act as wicket-keepers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Marylebone Cricket Club|title=Summary of changes to the Laws of Cricket 2017 Code|url=https://www.lords.org/assets/2017-Law-Changes-Summary-Paper.pdf|website=Lords the Home of Cricket|accessdate=4 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Specialist roles===
{{main|captain (cricket)|wicket-keeper}}
The captain is often the most experienced player in the team, certainly the most tactically astute, and can possess any of the main skillsets as a [[batsman]], a [[Bowling (cricket)|bowler]] or a [[wicket-keeper]]. Within the Laws, the captain has certain responsibilities in terms of nominating his players to the umpires before the match and ensuring that his players conduct themselves &quot;within the spirit and traditions of the game as well as within the Laws&quot;.&lt;ref name=Law1/&gt;

The wicket-keeper (sometimes called simply the &quot;keeper&quot;) is a specialist fielder subject to various rules within the Laws about his equipment and demeanour. He is the only member of the fielding side who can effect a [[stumped|stumping]] and is the only one permitted to wear gloves and external leg guards.&lt;ref name=Law40&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-40-the-wicket-keeper/ |title=Law 40 – The wicket-keeper |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=4 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Depending on their primary skills, the other ten players in the team tend to be classified as specialist batsmen or specialist bowlers. Generally, a team will include five or six specialist batsmen and four or five specialist bowlers, plus the wicket-keeper.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.talkcricket.co.uk/guides/bowling_strategy.html |title=Bowling Strategy |work=TalkCricket |publisher= |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.talkcricket.co.uk/guides/cricket_batting_strategy.html |title=Batting Strategy |work=TalkCricket |publisher= |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Clothing and equipment===
{{main|Cricket clothing and equipment}}
[[File:WGGrace.jpg|thumb|upright|right|English cricketer [[W. G. Grace]] &quot;taking guard&quot; in 1883. His pads and bat are very similar to those used today. The gloves have evolved somewhat. Many modern players use more defensive equipment than was available to Grace, notably helmets and arm guards.]]
The wicket-keeper and the batsmen wear protective gear because of the hardness of the ball, which can be delivered at speeds of more than {{convert|145|km/h|mph}} and presents a major health and safety concern. Protective clothing includes [[batting pads|pads]] (designed to protect the knees and shins), [[batting gloves]] or [[wicket-keeper's gloves]] for the hands, a [[helmet (cricket)|safety helmet]] for the head and a [[box (cricket)|box]] for male players inside the trousers (to protect the [[crotch]] area).&lt;ref name=AppD&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/appendix-d/ |title=Appendix D |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some batsmen wear additional padding inside their shirts and trousers such as thigh pads, arm pads, rib protectors and shoulder pads. The only fielders allowed to wear protective gear are those in positions very close to the batsman (i.e., if they are alongside or in front of him), but they cannot wear gloves or external leg guards.&lt;ref name=Law41/&gt;

Subject to certain variations, on-field clothing generally includes a collared shirt with short or long sleeves; long trousers; woolen pullover (if needed); [[cricket cap]] (for fielding) or a safety helmet; and spiked shoes or boots to increase traction. The kit is traditionally all white and this remains the case in Test and first-class cricket but, in limited overs cricket, team colours are worn instead.&lt;ref&gt;Birley (1999), p. 343.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Innings===
{{main|Innings}}
The innings (ending with 's' in both singular and plural form) is the term used for each phase of play during a match. Depending on the type of match being played, each team has either one or two innings. Sometimes all eleven members of the batting side take a turn to bat but, for various reasons, an innings can end before they have all done so. The innings terminates if the batting team is &quot;all out&quot;, a term defined by the Laws: &quot;at the [[dismissal (cricket)|fall of a wicket]] or the retirement of a batsman, further balls remain to be bowled but no further batsman is available to come in&quot;.&lt;ref name=inns/&gt; In this situation, one of the batsmen has not been dismissed and is termed [[not out]]; this is because he has no partners left and there must always be two active batsmen while the innings is in progress.

An innings may end early while there are still two not out batsmen:&lt;ref name=inns/&gt;
* the batting team's [[captain (cricket)|captain]] [[Declaration and forfeiture|may declare the innings closed]] even though some of his players have not had a turn to bat: this is a tactical decision by the captain, usually because he believes his team have scored sufficient runs and need time to dismiss the opposition in their innings
* the set number of [[over (cricket)|overs]] (i.e., in a limited overs match) have been bowled
* the match has ended prematurely due to bad weather or running out of time
* in the final innings of the match, the batting side has reached its target and won the game.

===Overs===
{{main|Over (cricket)}}
The Laws state that, throughout an innings, &quot;the ball shall be bowled from each end alternately in overs of 6 balls&quot;.&lt;ref name=Law22&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-22-the-over/ |title=Law 22 – The over |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=4 July 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170702061242/https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-22-the-over/ |archive-date=2 July 2017 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The name &quot;over&quot; came about because the umpire calls &quot;Over!&quot; when six balls have been bowled. At this point, another bowler is deployed at the other end, and the fielding side changes ends while the batsmen do not. A bowler cannot bowl two successive overs, although a bowler can (and usually does) bowl alternate overs, from the same end, for several overs which are termed a &quot;spell&quot;. The batsmen do not change ends at the end of the over, and so the one who was non-striker is now the striker and vice-versa. The umpires also change positions so that the one who was at &quot;square leg&quot; now stands behind the wicket at the non-striker's end and vice-versa.&lt;ref name=Law22/&gt;

===Umpires and scorers===
{{main|Umpire (cricket)|Scoring (cricket)|Cricket statistics}}
[[File:Cricket Umpire.jpg|thumb|right|An umpire signals a decision to the scorers]]
The game on the field is regulated by the two [[umpire (cricket)|umpires]], one of whom stands behind the wicket at the bowler's end, the other in a position called &quot;square leg&quot; which is about 15–20 metres away from the batsman on strike and in line with the popping crease on which he is taking guard. The umpires have several responsibilities including adjudication on whether a ball has been correctly bowled (i.e., not a [[no-ball]] or a [[wide (cricket)|wide]]); when a run is scored; whether a batsman is out (the fielding side must first [[appeal (cricket)|appeal]] to the umpire, usually with the phrase &quot;How's that?&quot; or &quot;Owzat?&quot;); when intervals start and end; and the suitability of the pitch, field and weather for playing the game. The umpires are authorised to interrupt or even abandon a match due to circumstances likely to endanger the players, such as a damp pitch or deterioration of the light.&lt;ref name=Law3/&gt;

Off the field in televised matches, there is usually a [[third umpire]] who can make decisions on certain incidents with the aid of video evidence. The third umpire is mandatory under the playing conditions for [[Test cricket|Test]] and [[Limited Overs International]] matches played between two ICC full member countries. These matches also have a [[match referee]] whose job is to ensure that play is within the Laws and the spirit of the game.&lt;ref name=Law3/&gt;

The match details, including runs and dismissals, are recorded by two official [[scoring (cricket)|scorers]], one representing each team. The scorers are directed by the hand signals of an umpire (see image, right). For example, the umpire raises a forefinger to signal that the batsman is out (has been dismissed); he raises both arms above his head if the batsman has hit the ball for six runs. The scorers are required by the Laws to record all runs scored, wickets taken and overs bowled; in practice, they also note significant amounts of additional data relating to the game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-4-the-scorers/ |title=Law 4 – The scorers |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=4 July 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170702065817/https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-4-the-scorers/ |archive-date=2 July 2017 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A match's [[Cricket statistics|statistics]] are summarised on a scorecard. Prior to the popularisation of scorecards, most scoring was done by men sitting on vantage points cuttings notches on [[tally stick]]s and runs were originally called notches.&lt;ref&gt;Bowen (1970), p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Rowland Bowen]], the earliest known scorecard templates were introduced in 1776 by T. Pratt of [[Sevenoaks]] and soon came into general use.&lt;ref&gt;Bowen (1970), p. 266.&lt;/ref&gt; It is believed that scorecards were printed and sold at [[Lord's]] for the first time in 1846.&lt;ref&gt;Bowen (1970), p. 274.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spirit of the Game===
{{main|Laws of Cricket}}
Besides observing the Laws, cricketers must respect the &quot;Spirit of Cricket,&quot; which is the &quot;Preamble to the Laws,&quot; first published in the 2000 code, and updated in 2017, and now opens with this statement:&lt;ref name=preamble&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/preamble-to-the-laws/ |title=Preamble to the Laws |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=10 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Cricket owes much of its appeal and enjoyment to the fact that it should be played not only according to the Laws, but also within the Spirit of Cricket&quot;.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The Preamble is a short statement that emphasises the &quot;Positive behaviours that make cricket an exciting game that encourages leadership, friendship, and teamwork.&quot;&lt;ref name=2017_changes&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/assets/2017-Law-Changes-Summary-Paper.pdf |title=Summary of changes to the Laws of Cricket 2017 Code|work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=10 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The major responsibility for ensuring fair play is placed firmly on the captains, but extends to all players, umpires, teachers, coaches, and parents involved.

The umpires are the sole judges of fair and unfair play. They are required under the Laws to intervene in case of dangerous or unfair play or in cases of unacceptable conduct by a player.

Previous versions of the Spirit identified actions that were deemed contrary (for example, appealing knowing that the batsman is not out) but all specifics are now covered in the Laws of Cricket, the relevant governing playing regulations and disciplinary codes, or left to the judgement of the umpires, captains, their clubs and governing bodies. The terse expression of the Spirit of Cricket now avoids the diversity of cultural conventions that exist in the detail of sportsmanship – or its absence.

===Bowling and dismissal===
{{main|Bowling (cricket)|Dismissal (cricket)}}
[[File:Glenn McGrath 01 crop 2.jpg|right|upright=0.7|thumb|[[Glenn McGrath]] of [[Australian Cricket Team|Australia]] holds the world record for most wickets in the [[Cricket World Cup]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/most-wickets-taken-in-an-icc-world-cup-career-(male) |title=Most wickets taken in an ICC World Cup career (male)|work=[[Guinness World Records]] |accessdate=23 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Most bowlers are considered specialists in that they are selected for the team because of their skill as a bowler, although some are all-rounders and even specialist batsmen bowl occasionally. The specialists bowl several times during an innings but may not bowl two overs consecutively. If the captain wants a bowler to &quot;change ends&quot;, another bowler must temporarily fill in so that the change is not immediate.&lt;ref name=Law22/&gt;

A bowler reaches his delivery stride by means of a &quot;run-up&quot; and an over is deemed to have begun when the bowler starts his run-up for the first delivery of that over, the ball then being &quot;in play&quot;.&lt;ref name=Law22/&gt; Fast bowlers, needing momentum, take a lengthy run up while bowlers with a slow delivery take no more than a couple of steps before bowling. The fastest bowlers can deliver the ball at a speed of over {{convert|145|km/h|mph}} and they sometimes rely on sheer speed to try to defeat the batsman, who is forced to react very quickly.&lt;ref name=pace&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.talkcricket.co.uk/guides/types_of_fast_bowling.html |title=Types of fast bowling |work=TalkCricket |publisher= |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other fast bowlers rely on a mixture of speed and guile by making the ball [[seam bowling|seam]] or [[swing bowling|swing]] (i.e. curve) in flight. This type of delivery can deceive a batsman into miscuing his shot, for example, so that the ball just touches the edge of the bat and can then be &quot;caught behind&quot; by the wicket-keeper or a slip fielder.&lt;ref name=pace/&gt; At the other end of the bowling scale is the [[Spin bowling|spin bowler]] who bowls at a relatively slow pace and relies entirely on guile to deceive the batsman. A spinner will often &quot;buy his wicket&quot; by &quot;tossing one up&quot; (in a slower, steeper [[Parabolic trajectory|parabolic]] path) to lure the batsman into making a poor shot. The batsman has to be very wary of such deliveries as they are often &quot;flighted&quot; or spun so that the ball will not behave quite as he expects and he could be &quot;trapped&quot; into getting himself out.&lt;ref name=spin&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.talkcricket.co.uk/guides/cricket_skills_spin_bowling.html |title=Spin bowling |work=TalkCricket |publisher= |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In between the pacemen and the spinners are the medium paced seamers who rely on persistent accuracy to try to contain the rate of scoring and wear down the batsman's concentration.&lt;ref name=pace/&gt;

There are ten ways in which a batsman can be dismissed: five relatively common and five extremely rare. The common forms of dismissal are [[bowled]],&lt;ref name=Law30&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-30-bowled/ |title=Law 30 – Bowled |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[caught]],&lt;ref name=Law32&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-32-caught-1/ |title=Law 32 – Caught |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[leg before wicket]] (lbw),&lt;ref name=Law36&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-36-leg-before-wicket/ |title=Law 36 – Leg before wicket |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[run out]]&lt;ref name=Law38&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-38-run-out/ |title=Law 38 – Run out |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[stumped]].&lt;ref name=Law39&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-39-stumped/ |title=Law 39 – Stumped |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rare methods are [[hit wicket]],&lt;ref name=Law35&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-35-hit-wicket/ |title=Law 35 – Hit wicket |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[hit the ball twice]],&lt;ref name=Law34&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-34-hit-the-ball-twice/ |title=Law 34 – Hit the ball twice |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[obstructing the field]],&lt;ref name=Law37&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-37-obstructing-the-field/ |title=Law 37 – Obstructing the field |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[handled the ball]]&lt;ref name=Law33&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-33-handled-the-ball/ |title=Law 33 – Handled the ball |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[timed out]].&lt;ref name=Law31&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-31-timed-out-1/ |title=Law 31 – Timed out |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Laws state that the fielding team, usually the bowler in practice, must appeal for a dismissal before the umpire can give his decision. If the batsman is out, the umpire raises a forefinger and says &quot;Out!&quot;; otherwise, he will shake his head and say &quot;Not out&quot;.&lt;ref name=Law27&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-27-appeals/ |title=Law 27 – Appeals |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is, effectively, an eleventh method of dismissal, [[retired out]], which is not an on-field dismissal as such but rather a retrospective one for which no fielder is credited.&lt;ref name=Law2RO&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-2-substitutes-and-runners-batsman-or-fielder-leaving-the-field-batsman-retiring-or-batsman-commencing-innings/ |title=Law 2 – Section 9: Batsman retiring |publisher=MCC |accessdate=18 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Batting, runs and extras===
{{main|Batting (cricket)|Run (cricket)|Extra (cricket)}}
[[File:cricket shots.svg|thumb|left|upright|The directions in which a right-handed batsman, facing down the page, intends to send the ball when playing various cricketing shots. The diagram for a [[left-handed]] batsman is a [[mirror image]] of this one.]]
Batsmen take turns to bat via a [[batting order (cricket)|batting order]] which is decided beforehand by the team captain and presented to the umpires, though the order remains flexible when the captain officially nominates the team.&lt;ref name=Law1/&gt; Substitute batsmen are generally not allowed,&lt;ref name=Law2/&gt; except in the case of concussion substitutes in international cricket.&lt;ref name=ICCTestPlayCond/&gt;

In order to begin batting the batsman first adopts a batting stance. Standardly, this involves adopting a slight crouch with the feet pointing across the front of the wicket, looking in the direction of the bowler, and holding the bat so it passes over the feet and so its tip can rest on the ground near to the toes of the back foot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cricketweb.net/grip-stance-back-lift/ |title=Grip, Stance, Back-Lift |access-date=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A skilled batsman can use a wide array of &quot;shots&quot; or &quot;strokes&quot; in both defensive and attacking mode. The idea is to hit the ball to the best effect with the flat surface of the bat's blade. If the ball touches the side of the bat it is called an &quot;[[Edge (cricket)|edge]]&quot;. The batsman does not have to play a shot and can allow the ball to go through to the [[wicketkeeper]]. Equally, he does not have to attempt a run when he hits the ball with his bat. Batsmen do not always seek to hit the ball as hard as possible, and a good player can score runs just by making a deft stroke with a turn of the wrists or by simply &quot;blocking&quot; the ball but directing it away from fielders so that he has time to take a run. A wide variety of shots are played, the batsman's repertoire including strokes named according to the style of swing and the direction aimed: e.g., &quot;[[List of cricket terms#Cut|cut]]&quot;, &quot;drive&quot;, &quot;hook&quot;, &quot;pull&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.talkcricket.co.uk/guides/cricket_batting.html |title=Batting |work=TalkCricket |publisher= |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The batsman on strike (i.e. the &quot;striker&quot;) must prevent the ball hitting the wicket, and try to score [[Run (cricket)|runs]] by hitting the ball with his bat so that he and his partner have time to run from one end of the pitch to the other before the fielding side can return the ball. To register a run, both runners must touch the ground behind the popping crease with either their bats or their bodies (the batsmen carry their bats as they run). Each completed run increments the score of both the team and the striker.&lt;ref name=Law18&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-18-scoring-runs/ |title=Law 18 – Scoring runs |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Master Blaster at work.jpg|right|thumb|[[Sachin Tendulkar]] is the only player to have scored one hundred international [[Century (cricket)|centuries]]]]

The decision to attempt a run is ideally made by the batsman who has the better view of the ball's progress, and this is communicated by calling: usually &quot;yes&quot;, &quot;no&quot; or &quot;wait&quot;. More than one run can be scored from a single hit: hits worth one to three runs are common, but the size of the field is such that it is usually difficult to run four or more.&lt;ref name=Law18/&gt; To compensate for this, hits that reach the boundary of the field are automatically awarded four runs if the ball touches the ground ''en route'' to the boundary or six runs if the ball clears the boundary without touching the ground within the boundary. In these cases the batsmen do not need to run.&lt;ref name=Law19&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-19-boundaries/ |title=Law 19 – Boundaries |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hits for five are unusual and generally rely on the help of &quot;overthrows&quot; by a fielder returning the ball. If an odd number of runs is scored by the striker, the two batsmen have changed ends, and the one who was non-striker is now the striker. Only the striker can score individual runs, but all runs are added to the team's total.&lt;ref name=Law18/&gt;

Additional runs can be gained by the batting team as [[extra (cricket)|extras]] (called &quot;sundries&quot; in Australia) due to errors made by the fielding side. This is achieved in four ways: [[no-ball]], a penalty of one extra conceded by the bowler if he breaks the rules;&lt;ref name=Law24&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-24-no-ball/ |title=Law 24 – No ball |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[wide (cricket)|wide]], a penalty of one extra conceded by the bowler if he bowls so that the ball is out of the batsman's reach;&lt;ref name=Law25a&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-25-wide-ball/ |title=Law 25 – Wide ball |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[bye (cricket)|bye]], an extra awarded if the batsman misses the ball and it goes past the wicket-keeper and gives the batsmen time to run in the conventional way;&lt;ref name=Law26&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lords.org/mcc/laws-of-cricket/laws/law-26-bye-and-leg-bye/ |title=Law 26 – Bye and Leg bye |work=Laws of Cricket |publisher=MCC |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[leg bye]], as for a bye except that the ball has hit the batsman's body, though not his bat.&lt;ref name=Law26/&gt; If the bowler has conceded a no-ball or a wide, his team incurs an additional penalty because that ball (i.e., delivery) has to be bowled again and hence the batting side has the opportunity to score more runs from this extra ball.&lt;ref name=Law24/&gt;&lt;ref name=Law25a/&gt;

==Women's cricket==
{{main|Women's cricket}}
[[File:Mithali Raj Truro 2012.jpg|right|thumb|[[Mithali Raj]] of India, is the only player to surpass the 6,000 run mark in [[Women's One Day International cricket]].]]
[[Women's cricket]] was first recorded in [[Surrey]] in 1745.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.icc-cricket.com/about/cricket/history-of-cricket/early-cricket |title=ICC History of Cricket (pre-1799) |publisher=ICC |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; International development began at the start of the 20th century and the first Test Match was played between [[Australia Women cricket team|Australia]] and [[England women's cricket team|England]] in December 1934.&lt;ref name=ICC20C&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.icc-cricket.com/about/cricket/history-of-cricket/20th-century |title=ICC History of Cricket (20th century) |publisher=ICC |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, [[New Zealand Womens cricket team|New Zealand]] women joined them, and in 2007 [[Netherlands women cricket team|Netherlands women]] became the tenth women's Test nation when they made their debut against [[South Africa women cricket team|South Africa women]]. In 1958, the International Women's Cricket Council was founded (it merged with the ICC in 2005).&lt;ref name=ICC20C/&gt; In 1973, the first Cricket World Cup of any kind took place when a Women's World Cup was held in England.&lt;ref name=ICC20C/&gt;  In 2005, the [[International Women's Cricket Council]] was merged with the International Cricket Council (ICC) to form one unified body to help manage and develop cricket. The ICC Women's Rankings were launched on 1 October 2015 covering all three formats of women's cricket. In October 2018 following the ICC's decision to award T20 International status to all members, the Women's rankings were split into separate [[One Day International|ODI]] (for Full Members) and T20I lists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.icc-cricket.com/media-releases/877811|title=ICC Launches Global Women's T20I Team Rankings|access-date=12 October 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Governance==
{{main|International Cricket Council}}
[[File:International_Cricket_Council_members_(by_status)_2017.svg|thumb|upright=1.5|[[International Cricket Council|ICC]] member nations. The (highest level) Test playing nations are shown in red; the associate member nations are shown in orange, with those with [[One Day International|ODI status]] in a darker shade; suspended or former members are shown in dark grey.]]

The [[International Cricket Council]] (ICC), which has its headquarters in [[Dubai]], is the global governing body of cricket. It was founded as the Imperial Cricket Conference in 1909 by representatives from England, Australia and South Africa, renamed the International Cricket Conference in 1965 and took up its current name in 1989.&lt;ref name=ICC20C/&gt; The ICC in 2017 has 105 member nations, twelve of which hold full membership and can play [[Test cricket]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.icc-cricket.com/about |title=About the ICC |publisher=ICC |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ICC is responsible for the organisation and governance of cricket's major international tournaments, notably the men's and women's versions of the [[Cricket World Cup]]. It also appoints the umpires and referees that officiate at all sanctioned Test matches, Limited Overs Internationals and Twenty20 Internationals.

Each member nation has a national cricket board which regulates cricket matches played in its country, selects the national squad, and organises home and away tours for the national team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.ecb.co.uk/about-us/about-the-ecb |title=About the England and Wales Cricket Board |website=ECB |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the West Indies, which for cricket purposes is a federation of nations, these matters are addressed by [[Cricket West Indies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cricketwestindies.org/ |title=Cricket West Indies |publisher=Cricket West Indies |accessdate=7 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The table below lists the ICC full members and their national cricket boards:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.icc-cricket.com/team-rankings |title=ICC Rankings |website=International Cricket Council |publisher=ICC Development (International) Limited |accessdate=9 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
!Nation
!Governing body
!Member since&lt;ref name=&quot;A Brief History...&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://content-usa.cricinfo.com/ci-icc/content/current/story/209608.html |title=A brief history ... |accessdate=2 May 2008 |publisher=Cricinfo}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{cr|AFG}}
| [[Afghanistan Cricket Board]]
| {{Dts|format=dmy|2017|6|22}}
|-
| {{cr|AUS}}
| [[Cricket Australia]]
| {{Dts|format=dmy|1909|7|15}}
|-
| {{cr|Bangladesh}}
| [[Bangladesh Cricket Board]]
| {{Dts|format=dmy|2000|6|26}}
|-
| {{cr|ENG}}
| [[England and Wales Cricket Board]]
| {{Dts|format=dmy|1909|7|15}}
|-
| {{cr|IND}}
| [[Board of Control for Cricket in India]]
| {{Dts|format=dmy|1926|5|31}}
|-
| {{cr|Ireland}}
| [[Cricket Ireland]]
| {{Dts|format=dmy|2017|6|22}}
|-
| {{cr|NZL}}
| [[New Zealand Cricket]]
| {{Dts|format=dmy|1926|5|31}}
|-
| {{cr|PAK}}
| [[Pakistan Cricket Board]]
| {{Dts|format=dmy|1953|7|28}}
|-
| {{cr|ZAF}}
| [[Cricket South Africa]]
| {{Dts|format=dmy|1909|7|15}}
|-
| {{cr|LKA}}
| [[Sri Lanka Cricket]]
| {{Dts|format=dmy|1981|7|21}}
|-
| {{cr|West Indies}}
| [[Cricket West Indies]]
| {{Dts|format=dmy|1926|5|31}}
|-
| {{cr|Zimbabwe}}
| [[Zimbabwe Cricket]]
| {{Dts|format=dmy|1992|7|06}}
|}

==Types of match==
{{main|Forms of cricket}}
[[File:England vs South Africa.jpg|thumb|A [[Test cricket|Test match]] between South Africa and England in January 2005. The men wearing black trousers are the [[umpire (cricket)|umpires]]. Teams in Test cricket, [[first-class cricket]] and [[club cricket]] wear traditional white uniforms and use red [[cricket ball]]s.]]
Cricket is a multi-faceted sport with multiple formats that can effectively be divided into [[first-class cricket]], [[limited overs cricket]] and, historically, [[single wicket cricket]]. The highest standard is [[Test cricket]] (always written with a capital &quot;T&quot;) which is in effect the international version of first-class cricket and is restricted to teams representing the twelve countries that are full members of the ICC (see above). Although the term &quot;Test match&quot; was not coined until much later, Test cricket is deemed to have begun with two matches between [[Australia national cricket team|Australia]] and [[England national cricket team|England]] in the [[1876-77 Australian cricket season|1876–77 Australian season]]; since 1882, most Test series between England and Australia have been played for a trophy known as [[The Ashes]]. The term &quot;first-class&quot;, in general usage, is applied to top-level domestic cricket. Test matches are played over five days and first-class over three to four days; in all of these matches, the teams are allotted two innings each and the draw is a valid result.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Dictionary of Cricket |last=Rundell |first=Michael |year=2006 |publisher=A&amp;C Black Publishers Ltd |location=London |isbn=978-0-7136-7915-1 |page=336 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6Vu9cih3u1kC&amp;lpg=PT336&amp;dq=%22dictionary%20of%20cricket%22%20test&amp;pg=PT336#v=onepage&amp;q=%22dictionary%20of%20cricket%22%20test |accessdate=17 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Limited overs cricket is always scheduled for completion in a single day. There are two types: [[List A cricket|List A]] which normally allows fifty overs per team; and [[Twenty20]] in which the teams have twenty overs each. Both of the limited overs forms are played internationally as [[Limited Overs International]]s (LOI) and [[Twenty20 International]]s (T20I). List A was introduced in England in the 1963 season as a knockout cup contested by the first-class county clubs. In 1969, a national league competition was established. The concept was gradually introduced to the other leading cricket countries and the first limited overs international was played in 1971. In 1975, the first [[Cricket World Cup]] took place in England. Twenty20 is a new variant of limited overs itself with the purpose being to complete the match within about three hours, usually in an evening session. The first [[Twenty20 World Championship]] was held in 2007. Limited overs matches cannot be drawn, although a tie is possible and an unfinished match is a &quot;no result&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.espncricinfo.com/ci/content/story/255055.html |title=ICC clarification of limited overs |publisher=ESPNcricinfo |accessdate=8 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.espncricinfo.com/blogs/content/story/980687.html |title=The first official T20 |publisher=ESPNcricinfo |accessdate=8 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Single wicket was popular in the 18th and 19th centuries and its matches were generally considered top-class. In this form, although each team may have from one to six players, there is only one batsman in at a time and he must face every delivery bowled while his innings lasts. Single wicket has rarely been played since limited overs cricket began. Matches tended to have two innings per team like a full first-class one and they could end in a draw.&lt;ref&gt;Major (2007), pp. 155–167 &amp; 404–410.&lt;/ref&gt;

==International competitions==
{{main|International cricket}}

Most international matches are played as parts of 'tours', when one nation travels to another for a number of weeks or months, and plays a number of matches of various sorts against the host nation. Sometimes a [[Test cricket#Perpetual trophies|perpetual trophy]] is awarded to the winner of the Test series, the most famous of which is [[The Ashes]].

The ICC also organises competitions that are for several countries at once, including the [[Cricket World Cup]], [[ICC T20 World Cup]] and [[ICC Champions Trophy]]. A league competition for Test matches played as part of normal tours, the [[ICC World Test Championship]], had been proposed several times, and its [[2019–21 ICC World Test Championship|first instance]] began in 2019. A league competition for ODIs, the [[2020–22 ICC Cricket World Cup Super League]], is planned to begin in 2020. The ICC maintains [[ICC Test Championship|Test rankings]], [[ICC ODI Championship|ODI rankings]] and [[ICC T20I Championship|T20 rankings]] systems for the countries which play these forms of cricket.

Competitions for member nations of the ICC with [[List of International Cricket Council members#Associate members|Associate status]] include the [[ICC Intercontinental Cup]], for first-class cricket matches, and the [[World Cricket League]] for one-day matches, the final matches of which now also serve as the [[ICC World Cup Qualifier]].

==National competitions==
{{see also|Category:Domestic cricket competitions}}
[[File:Yorkshire-CCC-1895.jpg|right|thumb|[[Yorkshire County Cricket Club]] in 1895. The team first won the County Championship in 1893.]]

===First-class===
{{main|List of current first-class cricket teams}}
First-class cricket in England is played for the most part by the 18 county clubs which contest the [[County Championship]]. The concept of a [[Champion County|champion county]] has existed since the 18th century but the official competition was not established until 1890.&lt;ref name=&quot;AMCS&quot;/&gt; The most successful club has been [[Yorkshire County Cricket Club|Yorkshire]], who had won 32 official titles (plus one shared) as of 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Playfair |title=Playfair Cricket Annual (70th edition) |edition=2017 |editor-last=Marshall |editor-first=Ian |editor-link= |publisher=Headline |page=216 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Australia established its national first-class championship in 1892–93 when the [[Sheffield Shield]] was introduced. In Australia, the first-class teams represent the various states.&lt;ref name=&quot;CH175&quot;&gt;Harte, p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt; [[New South Wales cricket team|New South Wales]] has the highest number of titles.

The other ICC full members have national championship trophies called the [[Ahmad Shah Abdali 4-day Tournament]] (Afghanistan); the [[National Cricket League]] (Bangladesh); the [[Ranji Trophy]] (India); the [[Inter-Provincial Championship]] (Ireland); the [[Plunket Shield]] (New Zealand); the [[Quaid-e-Azam Trophy]] (Pakistan); the [[Sunfoil Series|Currie Cup]] (South Africa); the [[Premier Trophy]] (Sri Lanka); the [[Regional Four Day Competition|Shell Shield]] (West Indies); and the [[Logan Cup]] (Zimbabwe).

===Limited overs===
{{main|List of domestic Twenty20 cricket competitions}}

===Other===
{{see also|Minor Counties Cricket Championship|Second XI Championship}}

==Club and school cricket==
{{main|Village cricket|Club cricket|Schools cricket}}
The world's earliest known cricket match was a [[village cricket]] meeting in [[Kent]] which has been deduced from a 1640 court case recording a &quot;cricketing&quot; of &quot;the Weald and the Upland&quot; versus &quot;the Chalk Hill&quot; at [[Chevening]] &quot;about thirty years since&quot; (i.e., {{circa|1611}}). Inter-parish contests became popular in the first half of the 17th century and continued to develop through the 18th with the first local leagues being founded in the second half of the 19th.&lt;ref name=&quot;DU4&quot;/&gt;

At the grassroots level, local [[club cricket]] is essentially an amateur pastime for those involved but still usually involves teams playing in competitions at weekends or in the evening. [[Schools cricket]], first known in southern England in the 17th century, has a similar scenario and both are widely played in the countries where cricket is popular.&lt;ref&gt;Birley (1999), pp. 9–10.&lt;/ref&gt; Although there can be variations in game format, compared with professional cricket, the Laws are always observed and club/school matches are therefore formal and competitive events.&lt;ref&gt;Birley (1999), pp. 151–152.&lt;/ref&gt; The sport has numerous informal variants such as [[French cricket]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.topendsports.com/sport/cricket/french.htm |title=Rules of French Cricket |publisher=topend sports |accessdate=8 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Culture==
{{main|:Category:Cricket culture}}

===Influence on everyday life===
Cricket has had a broad impact on popular culture, both in the [[Commonwealth of Nations]] and elsewhere. It has, for example, influenced the lexicon of these nations, especially the English language, with various phrases such as &quot;that's not cricket&quot; (that's unfair), &quot;had a good [[Innings#Usage outside of cricket|innings]]&quot; (lived a long life) and &quot;[[sticky wicket]]&quot;. &quot;On a sticky wicket&quot; (''aka'' &quot;sticky dog&quot; or &quot;glue pot&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Green |first=Jonathon |title=Dictionary of Jargon |publisher=Routledge |year=1987 |isbn=9780710099198 |page=[https://archive.org/details/dictionaryofjarg00jona/page/528 528] |url=https://archive.org/details/dictionaryofjarg00jona/page/528 }}&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[metaphor]]&lt;ref name=&quot;CalliesKeller2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author1=Marcus Callies |author2=Wolfram R. Keller |author3=Astrid Lohöfer |title=Bi-directionality in the Cognitive Sciences: Avenues, Challenges, and Limitations |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SC3cBXfj4UcC&amp;pg=PA73 |year=2011 |publisher=John Benjamins Publishing |isbn=90-272-2384-X |pages=73–}}&lt;/ref&gt; used to describe a difficult circumstance. It originated as a term for difficult batting conditions in cricket, caused by a damp and soft pitch.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hendrickson2001&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Robert Hendrickson |title=World English: From Aloha to Zed |url=https://archive.org/details/worldenglishfrom00hend |url-access=registration |year= 2001 |publisher=Wiley |isbn=978-0-471-34518-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In the arts and popular culture===
{{see also|Cricket in fiction|Cricket in film and television|Cricket poetry}}
Cricket is the subject of works by noted English poets, including [[William Blake]] and [[Lord Byron]].&lt;ref name=art&gt;Smart, Alastair (20 July 2013). [https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/art/art-features/10191131/The-art-of-cricket-Enough-to-leave-you-stumped.html &quot;The art of cricket: Enough to leave you stumped&quot;], ''The Telegraph''. Retrieved 12 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Beyond a Boundary]]'' (1963), written by Trinidadian [[C. L. R. James]], is often named the best book on any sport ever written.&lt;ref&gt;Rosengarten, Frank (2007). ''Urbane Revolutionary: C. L. R. James and the Struggle for a New Society''. University Press of Mississippi, {{ISBN|87-7289-096-7}} p. 134&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:William Handcock Tom Wills.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Tom Wills]], cricketer and co-founder of [[Australian football]]]]
In the visual arts, notable cricket paintings include [[Albert Chevallier Tayler]]'s ''[[Kent vs Lancashire at Canterbury]]'' (1907) and [[Russell Drysdale]]'s ''[[The Cricketers]]'' (1948), which has been called &quot;possibly the most famous Australian painting of the 20th century.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meacham&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.smh.com.au/news/entertainment/arts/montmartre-with-eucalypts/2009/06/05/1243708612484.html |title=Montmartre, with eucalypts |last=Meacham |first=Steve |date=6 June 2009 |work=Sydney Morning Herald |publisher=Fairfax |accessdate=31 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; French [[impressionism|impressionist]] [[Camille Pissarro]] painted cricket on a visit to England in the 1890s.&lt;ref name=art/&gt; [[Francis Bacon (artist)|Francis Bacon]], an avid cricket fan, captured a batsman in motion.&lt;ref name=art/&gt; [[Caribbean]] artist [[Wendy Nanan]]'s cricket images&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/shared/spl/hi/picture_gallery/07/in_pictures_caribbean_cricket_art/html/1.stm |publisher=BBC News |title=Caribbean cricket art, in the middle |accessdate=11 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; are featured in a limited edition first day cover for [[Royal Mail]]'s &quot;World of Invention&quot; stamp issue, which celebrated the London Cricket Conference 1–3 March 2007, first international workshop of its kind and part of the celebrations leading up to the 2007 [[Cricket World Cup]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bletchleycovers.com |title=Cricket: Dawn of a New World |date=March 2007 |publisher=Bletchley Park Post Office |accessdate=11 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Influence on other sports===
Cricket has close historical ties with [[Australian rules football]] and many players have [[List of Australian rules footballers and cricketers|competed at top levels in both sports]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Blainey |first=Geoffrey |title=A Game of Our Own: The Origins of Australian Football |publisher=Black Inc. |year=2010 |page=186 |isbn=1-86395-347-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1858, prominent Australian cricketer [[Tom Wills]] called for the formation of a &quot;foot-ball club&quot; with &quot;a code of laws&quot; to keep cricketers fit during the off-season. The [[Melbourne Football Club]] was founded the following year, and Wills and three other members codified the first laws of the game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=de Moore |first=Greg |title=Tom Wills: His Spectacular Rise and Tragic Fall |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |year=2008 |pages=77, 93–94 |isbn=978-1-74175-499-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is typically played on [[Australian rules football playing field|modified cricket fields]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Hess |first=Rob |title=A National Game: The History of Australian Rules Football |publisher=Viking |year=2008 |page=44 |isbn=978-0-670-07089-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In England, a number of [[association football]] clubs owe their origins to cricketers who sought to play football as a means of keeping fit during the winter months. [[Derby County F. C.|Derby County]] was founded as a branch of the [[Derbyshire County Cricket Club]] in 1884;&lt;ref&gt;Goldstein, p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aston Villa F. C.|Aston Villa]] (1874) and [[Everton F. C.|Everton]] (1876) were both founded by members of church cricket teams.&lt;ref&gt;Goldstein, pp. 15 &amp; 184.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sheffield United F. C.|Sheffield United]]'s [[Bramall Lane]] ground was, from 1854, the home of the [[Sheffield Cricket Club]], and then of [[Yorkshire County Cricket Club|Yorkshire]]; it was not used for football until 1862 and was shared by Yorkshire and Sheffield United from 1889 to 1973.&lt;ref&gt;Goldstein, p. 458.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 19th century, a former cricketer, English-born [[Henry Chadwick (writer)|Henry Chadwick]] of [[Brooklyn]], New York, was credited with devising the baseball [[box score (baseball)|box score]]&lt;ref&gt;His Hall of Fame plaque states, in part: &quot;Inventor of the box score. Author of the first rule-book&amp;nbsp;...  Chairman of rules committee in first nationwide baseball organization.&quot;  Lederer, Rich. ''By the Numbers: Computer technology has deepened fans' passion with the game's statistics. Memories and Dreams'' (Vol. 33, No. 6; Winter 2011[–2012], pp. 32–34). [[National Baseball Hall of Fame]] official magazine.&lt;/ref&gt; (which he adapted from the cricket scorecard) for reporting game events. The first box score appeared in an 1859 issue of the ''Clipper''.&lt;ref name=NPR&gt;{{cite web |last=Pesca |first=Mike |title=The Man Who Made Baseball's Box Score a Hit |url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=106891539 |publisher=[[National Public Radio]] |access-date=8 March 2014 |date=30 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The statistical record is so central to the game's &quot;historical essence&quot; that Chadwick is sometimes referred to as &quot;the Father of Baseball&quot; because he facilitated the popularity of the sport in its early days.&lt;ref name=Myth&gt;{{cite news |last1=Arango |first1=Tim |title=Myth of baseball's creation endures, with a prominent fan |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/13/sports/baseball/13doubleday.html |accessdate=8 November 2014 |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=12 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Cricket}}
* [[Glossary of cricket terms]]

'''Related sports'''
* [[Baseball]]
* [[Stoolball]]

==Footnotes==
&lt;references group=&quot;fn&quot; /&gt;

== Citations ==
{{Reflist}}

== General sources ==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book |last=Altham |first=H. S. |authorlink=Harry Altham |title=A History of Cricket, Volume 1 (to 1914) |year=1962 |publisher=George Allen &amp; Unwin |location=London}}
* {{cite book |last=Ashley-Cooper |first=F. S. |authorlink=F. S. Ashley-Cooper |title=At the Sign of the Wicket: Cricket 1742–1751 |year=1900 |work=Cricket: A Weekly Record of the Game |publisher=Cricket Magazine |location=London |OCLC=28863559}}
* {{cite book |last=Barclays |title=Barclays World of Cricket |editor-last=Swanton |editor-first=E. W. |editor-link=E. W. Swanton |publisher=Willow Books |location=London |year=1986 |isbn=0-00-218193-2}}
* {{cite book |last=Birley |first=Derek |authorlink=Derek Birley |title=A Social History of English Cricket |year=1999 |publisher=Aurum Press Ltd |location=London |isbn=1-85410-710-0}}
* {{cite book |last=Bowen |first=Rowland |authorlink=Rowland Bowen |title=Cricket: A History of its Growth and Development |year=1970 |publisher=Eyre &amp; Spottiswoode |location=London |isbn=0-413-27860-3}}
* {{cite book |title=The Rough Guide to English Football (2000–2001) |last=Goldstein |first=Dan |publisher=Rough Guides |location=London |date=2000 |isbn=1-85828-557-7 |url=https://archive.org/details/roughguidetoengl00dang }}
* {{cite book |last=Harte |first=Chris |title=A History of Australian Cricket |year=1993 |publisher=Andre Deutsch |location=London |page=175 |isbn=0-233-98825-4}}
* {{cite book |last=Haygarth |first=Arthur |authorlink=Arthur Haygarth |title=Frederick Lillywhite's Cricket Scores &amp; Biographies, Volume 1 (1744–1826) |year=1862 |publisher=Frederick Lillywhite |location=London}}
* {{cite book |last=Major |first=John |authorlink=John Major |title=More Than A Game |year=2007 |publisher=HarperCollins |location=London |isbn=978-0-00-718364-7}}
* {{cite book |last=McCann |first=Tim |authorlink=Timothy J. McCann |title=Sussex Cricket in the Eighteenth Century |year=2004 |publisher=Sussex Record Society |location=Lewes |isbn=0-85445-055-6}}
* {{cite book |last=Nyren |first=John |authorlink=John Nyren |title=The Cricketers of my Time |origyear=First published 1833 |editor=Ashley Mote |year=1998 |publisher=Robson Books |location=London |isbn=1-86105-168-9}}
* {{cite book |last=Underdown |first=David |authorlink=David Underdown |title=Start of Play |year=2000 |publisher=Allen Lane |location=London |isbn=0-713-99330-8}}
* {{cite book |last=Webber |first=Roy |authorlink=Roy Webber |title=The Phoenix History of Cricket |year=1960 |publisher=Phoenix House Ltd |location=London}}
* {{cite book |last=Williams |first=Charles |authorlink=Charles Williams, Baron Williams of Elvel |title=Gentlemen &amp; Players – The Death of Amateurism in Cricket |year=2012 |publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson |location=London |isbn=978-0-7538-2927-1}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |last=Guha |first=Ramachandra |authorlink=Ramachandra Guha |year=2002 |title=A Corner of a Foreign Field: The Indian History of a British Sport |location=London |publisher=Picador |isbn=0-330-49117-2 |oclc=255899689}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links|c=Category:Cricket|voy=Cricket|d=Q5375|wikt=cricket|m=no|mw=no|species=no|n=Category:Cricket}}

'''Organisations and competitions'''
* [http://www.icc-cricket.com/ International Cricket Council (ICC)]

'''Statistics and records'''
* [http://stats.espncricinfo.com/ci/engine/records/index.html ESPNcricinfo]

'''News and other resources'''
* [https://www.britannica.com/sports/cricket-sport &quot;Cricket&quot;]. ''[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]'' Online

{{Navboxes
|title=Articles relating to Cricket
|list1=
{{Cricket positions}}
{{Cricket equipment}}
{{International cricket}}
{{Full Members of the International Cricket Council}}
{{Cricket by country}}
{{Forms of cricket}}
{{Cricket at multi-sport events}}
{{Cricket statistics}}
{{Team sports}}
}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Cricket| ]]
[[Category:Ball and bat games]]
[[Category:Former Summer Olympic sports]]
[[Category:Sports originating in England]]
[[Category:Team sports]]</text>
      <sha1>51jweluifcsyaoelek308joy7fv0dj9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
