  <page>
    <title>Dakyu</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>35592602</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934285418</id>
      <parentid>913575657</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-05T18:48:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Trappist the monk</username>
        <id>10289486</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>lang fix;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:The mikado's empire (1894) (14804178323).jpg|thumb|350px|The game of dakyu in the 19th century in Japan]]
{{Nihongo|'''Dakyu'''|打毬''','''| da kyū{{noitalic|''';''' also, {{zh|p=''dǎ qiú''}}}}}} is an [[equestrianism|equestrian]] sport in East Asia with some similarities to [[polo]].

It also goes by the name of '''Kyuk Koo''' in Korea ({{korean|격구|擊毬|gyeok gu|kyŏk ku}}) since the [[Chinese characters|Hanzi character]] 擊 ({{zh|p=jī}}) is transliterated as: ''gyeok'' {{korean|hangul=격|rr=gyeok}} or {{transl|ja|hepburn|geki}} and carries the same meaning as the {{zh|t=打|rr=ta|revhep=da}}, which translates as: ''to beat, to strike,'' or ''to hit.''  As one might expect, '''{{nihongo2|毬}}''' translates to ''ball.''

==History==
[[File:Xin 223090511133790616148.jpeg|thumb|350px|A dakyu game in progress in ancient China]]
Originally from China,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Nihon Yunesuko Kokunai Iinkai
|title=Japan; its land, people and culture
|publisher=University of Tokyo Press|page=592|year=1973}}&lt;/ref&gt; dakyu was played in Japan as early as the [[Nara period]], making its way there via the [[Korean Peninsula]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Dakyu (Ancient Japanese polo) |url=http://www.kunaicho.go.jp/e-culture/bajutsu.html |website=Traditional Horsemanship in Japan |publisher=The Imperial Household Agency |accessdate=20 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; It remained popular amongst the aristocracy until the [[Kamakura period]], when it gradually died out (the last recorded game being in 986).&lt;ref name=&quot;Mangan &amp; Hong&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Mangan|first1=J. A.|last2=Hong|first2=Fan|title=Sport in Asian Society: Past and Present|publisher=Routledge|ISBN=9780714653426|year=2003|page=396}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the eighteenth century the game reappeared, largely due to support from [[Tokugawa Yoshimune]]. By this time it had evolved from a polo-like game (using mallets) to something more akin to mounted [[lacrosse]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mangan &amp; Hong&quot;/&gt; During this period, dakyu was considered a corollary to military training (working the skills needed to wield a spear from horseback).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Turnbull|first=Stephen|title=The Samurai Swordsman: Master of War|page=54|year=2008|ISBN=9784805309568|publisher=Tuttle publishing}}&lt;/ref&gt; This aspect was downplayed in the [[Meiji era]], when the game again lost favour; today, it survives only as a cultural asset.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guttmann &amp; Thompson&quot;/&gt;

==Gameplay==
[[File:Dakyu (ball game), 16th century, Tokyo National Museum.JPG|thumb|350px|Dakyu on foot in the 16th century in Japan]]
Dakyu was played both on foot and on horseback, but the equestrian version was more popular among the aristocracy and was thus better documented. Rules vary, but two main forms survive to the present day. Both involve two teams of riders (designated by the colours red and white) attempting to project a number of balls into a goal. This goal, originally a hoop placed on the ground, is now more commonly a circular hole on a wall.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guttmann &amp; Thompson&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first1=Allen|last1=Guttmann|first2=Lee Austin|last2=Thompson|title=Japanese Sports: A History|ISBN=9780824824648|publisher=University of Hawaii Press|year=2001|pages=36–38}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Kagemiryu'' style===
In Kagemiryu or Hachinohe style play, which dates from the eighteenth century, the teams are made up of four riders each. The players race to propel the 30&amp;nbsp;cm diameter balls of their colour into the four raised goals (two for each side), shooting from a preset distance of between 18 and 27 metres from the goal. A successful goal is signalled by percussion; drums for the white team, gongs for the red. The winning team is the first to get all of their balls into the goals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guttmann &amp; Thompson&quot;/&gt;

===''Yamagata'' style===
In the Yamagata or Imperial style of play, shorter sticks (at only 1m, less than half the length of those used in the Hachinohe style) are used, and both teams shoot for a single goal. The ball is also smaller, being only a few centimetres in diameter. Five balls are used in Yamagata style games, and eleven in Imperial games. When one side has successfully got all of its balls into the goal, a final ball called the ''agemari'' is put into play - whichever team then scores with the agemari then wins the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guttmann &amp; Thompson&quot;/&gt; This aspect of play has drawn comparisons with the game of [[billiards]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Sport As Symbol: Images of the Athlete in Art, Literature and Song|last=Womack|first=Mari|ISBN=9780786415793|page=131|year=2003|publisher=McFarland}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commonscat}}
* [http://www.kunaicho.go.jp/e-culture/bajutsu.html Dakyu (Ancient Japanese polo)] - from the [[Imperial Household Agency|Imperial Household Agency of Japan]]

[[Category:Sport in Japan]]
[[Category:Equestrian sports]]
[[Category:Team sports]]</text>
      <sha1>r04ojeosaw1biiysa2nox79olirkhqt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
