  <page>
    <title>Dilbat</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13920113</id>
    <revision>
      <id>916224510</id>
      <parentid>916224276</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-17T18:46:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gomaza</username>
        <id>36838845</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{coord|32|09|N|44|30|E|type:city|display=title}}
{{Infobox settlement
|pushpin_map            = Iraq
|pushpin_label_position =bottom
|pushpin_mapsize        =250
|pushpin_map_caption    =Location in Iraq
|coordinates            = {{coord|32|09|00|N|44|30|00|E|display=inline}}
|official_name          = Dilbat
|subdivision_type = Country
|subdivision_name = {{flag|Iraq}}
}}
'''Dilbat''' (modern '''Tell ed-Duleim''' or '''Tell al-Deylam''', [[Iraq]]) was an ancient [[Sumer]]ian minor ''[[Tell (archaeology)|tell]]'' (hill city)  located southeast from [[Babylon]] on the eastern bank of the Western [[Euphrates]] in modern-day [[Al-Qādisiyyah Governorate|Al-Qādisiyyah]], [[Iraq]]. The [[ziggurat]] [[E (temple)|E]]-ibe-Anu, dedicated to the goddess [[Urash]], was located in the center of the city and was mentioned in the [[Epic of Gilgamesh]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/18897] Stephen  Langdon, The Epic of Gilgamish. A Fragment of the Gilgamish Legend in Old-Babylonian Cuneiform, 1919&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
Dilbat was founded during the Sumerian [[History of Sumer|Early Dynastic II]] period, around 2700 BC. It is known to have been occupied, at least, during the [[Akkadian Empire|Akkadian]], Old Babylonian, [[Kassite]], [[Sasanian]] and Early Islamic periods. It was an early agricultural center cultivating [[einkorn wheat]] and producing reed products.&lt;ref&gt;A. Goddeeris, Economy and Society in Northern Babylonia, Peeters , 2002, {{ISBN|90-429-1123-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; It lay on the Arahtum canal.

== Archaeology ==
The site of Tell al-Deylam consists of two mounds, a small western mound with 1st millennium BC and Early Islamic  remains and a larger east mound, roughly 500 meters in circumference, with remains from the 1st to 3rd millennium BC. Dilbat was excavated briefly by [[Hormuzd Rassam]], who recovered some cuneiform tablets at the site, mainly from
the Neo-Babylonian period.&lt;ref&gt;Hormuzd Rassam and Robert William Rogers, Asshur and the land of Nimrod, Curts &amp; Jennings, 1897&lt;/ref&gt; The site was worked in 1989 by J. A. Armstrong of the [[Oriental Institute of Chicago]].&lt;ref&gt;J. A. Armstrong, Dilbat revisited: the Tell al-Deylam project, Mar Sipri, vol. 3, no. 1, pp, 1-4, 1990&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;James A. Armstrong, West of Edin: Tell al-Deylam and the Babylonian City of Dilbat, The Biblical Archaeologist, vol. 55, no. 4, pp. 219-226, 1992&lt;/ref&gt; Though Dilbat itself has only been lightly excavated by archaeologists, numerous tablets from there have made their way to the antiquites market over the years as the result of unauthorized digging.

== See also ==
*[[Cities of the Ancient Near East]]
* [[Tell (archaeology)]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* [http://www.metmuseum.org/publications/journals/1/pdf/1512957.pdf.bannered.pdf] Christine Lilyquist, The Dilbat Hoard, Metropolitan Museum Journal, vol. 29, pp.&amp;nbsp;5–36, 1994
* S. G. Koshurnikov and N. Yoffee, Old Babylonian Tablets from Dilbat in the Ashmolean Museum, Iraq, vol. 48, pp.&amp;nbsp;117–130, 1986
* Matthew W. Stolper, Late Achaemenid Texts from Dilbat, Iraq, vol. 54, pp.&amp;nbsp;119–139, 1992
*Joseph Etienne Gautier, Archives d'une famille de Dilbat au temps de la premiere dynastie de Babylone, Le Caire, 1908
*SG Koshurnikov,A Family Archive from Old Babylonian Dilbat, Vestnik Drevnii Istorii, vol. 168, pp.&amp;nbsp;123ff, 1984

== External links ==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20071011194205/http://users.ox.ac.uk/~wolf0126/lm.html#dilbat Sumer Map with Dilbat labeled as T. ed Duleim]

[[Category:Al-Qādisiyyah Governorate]]
[[Category:Sumerian cities]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites in Iraq]]
[[Category:Former populated places in Iraq]]


{{Iraq-geo-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>b4nxj3hlc8gqualj54kta2tptf19bpx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
