  <page>
    <title>Diplomatics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>639170</id>
    <revision>
      <id>926960789</id>
      <parentid>916349874</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-19T14:31:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date = February 2019}}
{{Short description|Academic study of the protocols of documents}}
{{Use American English|date = February 2019}}
{{about|the discipline concerned with the analysis and authentication of historical and other documents|the practice of conducting negotiations between groups or states|Diplomacy}}

'''Diplomatics''' (in American English, and in most anglophone countries), or '''diplomatic''' (in British English),&lt;ref&gt;{{OED|diplomatic, adj. and n.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;brooke&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;beal&quot;/&gt; is a scholarly discipline centred on the critical analysis of [[document]]s: especially, [[historical document]]s. It focuses on the conventions, protocols and formulae that have been used by document creators, and uses these to increase understanding of the processes of document creation, of information transmission, and of the relationships between the facts which the documents purport to record and reality.

The discipline originally evolved as a tool for studying and determining the authenticity of the official [[charter]]s and [[diploma]]s issued by royal and papal [[chancery (medieval office)|chanceries]]. It was subsequently appreciated that many of the same underlying principles could be applied to other types of official document and [[legal instrument]], to non-official documents such as private [[Letter (message)|letters]], and, most recently, to the [[metadata]] of electronic records.

Diplomatics is one of the [[auxiliary sciences of history]]. It should not be confused with its sister-discipline of [[palaeography]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Duranti12&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Duranti |first=Luciana |authorlink=Luciana Duranti |title=Diplomatics: New uses for an Old Science |journal=Archivaria |volume=28 |year=1989 |url=http://archivaria.ca/index.php/archivaria/article/viewFile/11567/12513 |pages=7–27 (12) }}&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, its techniques have more in common with those of the literary disciplines of [[textual criticism]] and [[historical criticism]].

==Etymology==
[[File:De re diplomatica 17765.jpg|thumb|right|Title page of [[Jean Mabillon]]'s ''De re diplomatica'' (1681)]]

Despite the verbal similarity, the discipline has nothing to do with [[diplomacy]]. Both terms are derived, by separate linguistic development, from the word ''diploma'', which originally referred to a folded piece of writing material—and thus both to the materials which are the focus of study in diplomatics, and to accreditation papers carried by diplomats.

The word ''diplomatics'' was effectively coined by the [[Benedictine]] monk [[Jean Mabillon]], who in 1681 published his treatise, ''De re diplomatica'' ([[Latin]]: roughly, &quot;The Study of Documents&quot;). From there, the word entered the French language as ''diplomatique'', and then English as ''diplomatic'' or ''diplomatics''.

==Definitions==
''[[Webster's Dictionary]]'' (1828) defines diplomatics as the &quot;science of diplomas, or of ancient writings, literary and public documents, letters, decrees, charters, codicils, etc., which has for its object to decipher old writings, to ascertain their authenticity, their date, signatures, etc.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Webster's Dictionary'' (1828); quoted in [[Oxford English Dictionary]] (2d ed.)&lt;/ref&gt;

Giorgio Cencetti (1908–1970) defined the discipline as &quot;the study of the ''Wesen'' [being] and ''Werden'' [becoming] of documentation, the analysis of genesis, inner constitution and transmission of documents, and of their relationship with the facts represented in them and with their creators&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Giorgio |last=Cencetti |chapter=La Preparazione dell'Archivista |title=Antologia di Scritti Archivistici |editor-first=Romualdo |editor-last=Giuffrida |place=Rome |publisher=Archivi di Stato |year=1985 |page=285}} Translation from Duranti 1989, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Commission International de Diplomatique]] has defined diplomatics as &quot;the science which studies the tradition, the form and the issuing of written documents&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://www.cei.lmu.de/VID/VID.php?1 |title=Vocabulaire Internationale de Diplomatique |editor-first=Maria Milagros |editor-last=Cárcel Ortí |edition=2nd |place=Valencia |year=1997 |publisher=Collecció Oberta |page=21 |quote=La Diplomatique est la science qui étudie la tradition, la forme et l'élaboration des actes écrits. |access-date=November 27, 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161206012859/http://www.cei.lmu.de/VID/VID.php?1 |archive-date=December 6, 2016 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

More pragmatically, Peter Beal defines diplomatics as &quot;the science or study of documents and records, including their forms, language, script and meaning. It involves knowledge of such matters as the established wording and procedures of particular kinds of document, the deciphering of writing, and document analysis and authentication&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;beal&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Peter|last=Beal |title=A Dictionary of English Manuscript Terminology, 1450–2000 |url=https://archive.org/details/dictionaryofengl0000beal|url-access=registration|year=2008 |place=Oxford| publisher=Oxford University Press| page=[https://archive.org/details/dictionaryofengl0000beal/page/121 121] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Theo Kölzer defines diplomatics as &quot;the teaching and the study of charters&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kölzer |first=Theo |chapter=Diplomatics |title=Handbook of Medieval Studies: Terms – methods – trends |editor-first=Albrecht |editor-last=Classen |place=Berlin |publisher=De Gruyter |year=2010 |isbn=9783110184099 |volume=1 |pages=405–424 (405) }}&lt;/ref&gt; He treats the terms &quot;charter&quot;, &quot;diploma&quot;, and &quot;document&quot; as broadly synonymous, and refers to the German scholar [[Harry Bresslau]]'s definition of &quot;documents&quot; as &quot;written declarations recorded in compliance with certain forms alternating according to the difference in person, place, time, and matter, which are meant to serve as a testimony of proceedings of a legal nature&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bresslau |first=Harry |authorlink=Harry Bresslau |title=Handbuch der Urkundenlehre für Deutschland und Italien |volume=1 |edition=4th |year=1969 |place=Berlin |publisher=De Gruyter |page=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Properly speaking, and as usually understood by present-day scholars, diplomatics is concerned essentially with the analysis and interpretation of the linguistic and textual elements of a document. It is, however, closely associated with several parallel disciplines, including [[palaeography]], [[sigillography]], [[codicology]], and [[provenance]] studies, all of which are concerned with a document's physical characteristics and history, and which will often be carried out in conjunction with a diplomatic analysis. The term diplomatics is therefore sometimes used in a slightly wider sense, to encompass some of these other areas (as it was in Mabillon's original work, and as is implied in the definitions of both Webster and Beal quoted above). The recent development of the science in non-English Europe is expanding its scope to a cultural history of documentation including aspects of [[pragmatic literacy]] or [[symbolic communication]].

[[Christopher N. L. Brooke|Christopher Brooke]], a distinguished teacher of diplomatics, referred to the discipline's reputation in 1970 as that of &quot;a formidable and dismal science ... a kind of game played by a few scholars, most of them medievalists, harmless so long as it does not dominate or obscure historical enquiry; or, perhaps, most commonly of all, an aid to understanding of considerable use to scholars and research students if only they had time to spare from more serious pursuits&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;brooke&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Brooke |first=Christopher N. L. |authorlink=Christopher N. L. Brooke |title=The teaching of Diplomatic |journal=Journal of the Society of Archivists |volume=4 |year=1970 |pages=1–9 |doi=10.1080/00379817009513930}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[image:Traité de diplomatique tome 4 17008.jpg|thumb|Title page of Volume 4 of [[René-Prosper Tassin|Tassin]] and [[Charles-François Toustain|Toustain]]'s ''Nouveau traité de diplomatique'' (1759)]]
In the [[Ancient history|ancient]] and [[Middle Ages|medieval]] periods, the authenticity of a document was considered to derive from the document's place of preservation and storage, in, for example, temples, public offices, and archives. As a result, those with nefarious motives were able to give [[Forgery|forged documents]] a spurious authenticity by depositing them in places of authority. Diplomatics grew from a need to establish new standards of authenticity through the critical analysis of the textual and physical forms of documents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duranti12&quot;/&gt;

The first notable application of diplomatics was by [[Nicolas of Cusa]], in 1433, and [[Lorenzo Valla]], in 1440, who determined, independently, that the [[Donation of Constantine]], which had been used for centuries to legitimize papal temporal authority, was a forgery. Diplomatic techniques were further developed as part of a wider battery of [[antiquarian]] skills during the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]] and [[Counter-Reformation]] eras.&lt;ref&gt;Duranti 1989, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; The emergence of diplomatics as a recognisably distinct sub-discipline, however, is generally dated to the publication of [[Jean Mabillon|Mabillon's]] ''De re diplomatica'' in 1681. Mabillon had begun studying old documents with a view towards establishing their authenticity as a result of the doubts raised by the [[Jesuit]] [[Daniel van Papenbroek]] over supposed [[Merovingian]] documents from the [[Abbey of Saint-Denis]]. During the [[Middle Ages]], the production of spurious [[charter]]s and other documents had been common, either to provide written documentation of existing rights or to bolster the plausibility of claimed rights. Mabillon's work engendered a far livelier awareness of the potential presence of forged or spurious documents, in the fields of both [[history]] and [[law]].

Although Mabillon is still widely seen as the &quot;father&quot; of diplomatics, a more important milestone in the formation of the battery of practical techniques which make up the modern discipline was the publication of [[René-Prosper Tassin]] and [[Charles-François Toustain]]'s ''Nouveau traité de diplomatique'', which appeared in six volumes in 1750–65.

The most significant work in English was [[Thomas Madox]]'s ''Formulare Anglicanum'', published in 1702. In general, however, the discipline was always studied more intensively by continental scholars than by those in Britain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Harrison |first=Charlotte |title=Thomas Madox and the Origins of English Diplomatic Scholarship |journal=Journal of the Society of Archivists |volume=29 |issue=2 |year=2009 |pages=147–169 |doi=10.1080/00379810902916282}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Diplomatics is often associated with the study of documents of the medieval period. However, scholars such as [[Luciana Duranti]] have argued that many of its theories and principles can be adapted and applied to contemporary [[archival science]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Williams |first=Caroline |title=Diplomatic Attitudes: from Mabillon to Metadata |journal=Journal of the Society of Archivists |volume=26 |year=2005 |pages=1–24 |doi=10.1080/00039810500047417}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Duranti 1989.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Uses==
The study of diplomatics is a valuable tool for [[historian]]s, enabling them to determine whether alleged [[historical document]]s and [[archive]]s are in fact genuine or [[forgery|forgeries]]. Its techniques may also be used to help date undated documents.

Diplomatics has many similar applications in the field of [[law]].

Some famous cases in which the principles of diplomatics have been employed have included:
* [[Lorenzo Valla]]'s proof of the forgery of the [[Donation of Constantine]]. Valla's work preceded Mabillon by roughly two centuries, and was the first application of the principles of modern, scientific diplomatics.
* The [[Hitler diaries]] [[hoax]] (1983).
* The [[The National Archives (United Kingdom)#Forgeries discovered in 2005|National Archives forgeries]] (the Martin Allen forgeries, or [[Himmler]] forged documents) (2005).

==Diplomatic editions and transcription==
A '''diplomatic edition''' is an edition (in print or online) of an historic manuscript text that seeks to reproduce as accurately as possible in typography all significant features of the manuscript original, including spelling and punctuation, abbreviations, deletions, insertions, and other alterations. Similarly, '''diplomatic transcription''' attempts to represent by means of a system of editorial signs all features of a manuscript original.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Gregory A. |last=Pass |title=Descriptive Cataloging of Ancient, Medieval, Renaissance, and Early Modern Manuscripts |place=Chicago |publisher=Association of College and Research Libraries |year=2003 |page=144 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The term ''semi-diplomatic'' is used for an edition or transcription that seeks to reproduce only some of these features of the original. A diplomatic edition is thus distinguished from a ''normalized edition'', in which the editor, while not altering the original wording of the text, renders it using normal (modern) [[orthography]].

A diplomatic edition is also to be distinguished both from a ''[[facsimile]] edition'', which, in the modern era, normally employs photographic or digital images; and from a ''type facsimile'' (such as [[Abraham Farley]]'s [[Publication of Domesday Book#Abraham Farley's edition (1773–1783)|edition of ''Domesday Book'']]), which seeks to reproduce the appearance of the original through the use of a [[Record type|special typeface]] or [[Medieval Unicode Font Initiative|digital font]].

==See also==
* [[False document]]
* [[Forensic science]]
* [[Palaeography]]
* [[Papal diplomatics]]
* [[Questioned document examination]] (for document forensics related to criminal activity)
* [[Sigillography]]
* [[Textual scholarship]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{wikisource|Portal:Diplomatics|Diplomatics}}
* [http://www.vl-ghw.lmu.de/diplomatik_en.html Virtual Library Historical Auxiliary Sciences - Diplomatics]
* [http://www.monasterium.net/ monasterium.net] largest online database of charters
* [http://lba.hist.uni-marburg.de/lba/pages/ Online-Database LBA online] provided by the [[:de:Lichtbildarchiv älterer Originalurkunden|Lichtbildarchiv älterer Originalurkunden]] at [[Marburg University]] (Germany, state of Hesse)
* [http://www.cei.lmu.de/VID/ Vocabulaire international de la diplomatique, ed. Maria Milagros Cárcel Ortí, 2. ed., Valéncia 1997 (Collecció Oberta), online version]
* [http://cidipl.org/ Commission internationale de Diplomatique]
* [http://www.interpares.org/ The International Research on Permanent Authentic Records in Electronic Systems (InterPARES)]

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Historiography]]
[[Category:Archival science]]
[[Category:Writing]]
[[Category:Diplomatics]]
[[Category:Document forgery]]
[[Category:Forensic disciplines]]
[[Category:Textual criticism]]
[[Category:Textual scholarship]]</text>
      <sha1>lzw0uuifoka6yu1p5nsm2v0u0pc0ct3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
