  <page>
    <title>Drummer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>38490</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938247870</id>
      <parentid>927284880</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-30T00:41:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BazingaFountain42</username>
        <id>38013597</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>I added two important drummers.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{multiple issues|
{{more citations needed|date=August 2011}}
{{update|date=August 2011}}
}}

[[File:Two hand drummers, both wearing sunglasses, about 1966.jpg|upright|thumb|Hand drummers in [[Berkeley, California]], about 1966]]
[[File:ASC Leiden - Coutinho Collection - 1 20 - Life in Canjambari, Guinea-Bissau - Party - 1973.tiff|thumb|Drummer at a party in Canjambari, [[Guinea-Bissau]], 1974]]
[[File:EHSBANDBATTERY.jpg|thumb|A marching drum line warming up, 2011]]
[[File:Independence Day Parade - Flickr - Kerri-Jo (119).jpg|thumbnail|Turkmenistan Independence Day, 2011]]

A '''drummer''' is a [[percussionist]] who creates music using [[drum]]s.

Most contemporary western [[music ensemble|bands]] that play [[Rock music|rock]], [[Pop music|pop]], [[jazz]], or [[R&amp;B]] music include a drummer for purposes including timekeeping and embellishing the musical [[timbre]]. The drummer's equipment includes a [[drum kit]] (or &quot;drum set&quot; or &quot;trap set&quot;) which includes various drums, [[cymbal]]s and an assortment of accessory hardware such as pedals, standing support mechanisms, and [[drum stick]]s.

In other genres, particularly in the traditional music of many countries, drummers use individual drums of various sizes and designs rather than drum kits. Some use only their hands to strike the drums.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marshall2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=John Marshall|title=Hand Drums for Beginners: An Easy Beginning Method|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KkZbdLuMQ0wC&amp;pg=PA2|year=2000|publisher=Alfred Music Publishing|isbn=978-0-7390-0324-4|pages=2–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In larger ensembles, the drummer may be part of a rhythm section with other percussionists playing, for example, vibraphone, marimba or xylophone. These musicians provide the timing and rhythmic foundation which allow the players of melodic instruments, including voices, to coordinate their musical performance.

Some famous drummers include: [[Ringo Starr]], [[John Bonham]], [[Ginger Baker]], [[Keith Moon]] (The Who), [[Neil Peart]], [[Buddy Rich]], Gene Krupa, Tim &quot;Herb&quot; Alexander (Primus), [[Phil Rudd]] (AC/DC), Rashied Ali, Carl Allen, Steve White, Craig Blundell, Travis Barker, Tony Royster Jr., Rick Allen (Def Leppard), [[Tré Cool]] ([[Green Day]]), [[Dave Grohl]] ([[Nirvana (band)|Nirvana]]).

As well as the primary rhythmic function,&lt;ref name=&quot;Spagnardi1992&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Ron Spagnardi|title=The Great Jazz Drummers|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yU5EoN3Mms8C&amp;pg=PA39|year=1992|publisher=Hal Leonard Corporation|isbn=978-0-7935-1526-4|pages=39–}}&lt;/ref&gt; in some musical styles, such as world, jazz, classical, and electronica, the drummer is called upon to provide solo and lead performances, at times when the main feature of the music is the rhythmic development.

There are many tools that a drummer can use for either timekeeping or soloing.
These include cymbals (china, crash, ride, splash, hi-hats, etc.), snare, toms, 
auxiliary percussion (bells, Latin drums, cowbells, temple blocks) and many others.
Also there are single, double, and triple bass pedals for the bass drum.

==Military==
{{see also|Drummer (military)}}

[[File:Fanfare 27BCA 03.JPG|thumb|300px|Drummer of the French [[Chasseurs alpins]], 2007]]

Before motorized transport became widespread, drummers played a key role in [[military]] conflicts. Military drummers provided [[wiktionary:drum cadence|drum cadence]]s that set a steady marching pace and elevated troop [[morale]] on the battlefield. In some armies drums also assisted in combat by keeping cadence for firing and loading drills with muzzle loading guns. Military drummers were also employed on the parade field, when troops passed in review, and in various ceremonies including ominous [[drum roll]]s accompanying disciplinary punishments. Children also served as [[Drummer boy (military)|drummer boys]] well into the nineteenth century, though less commonly than is popularly assumed; due to the nature of the job, experienced older men were preferred.

In modern times, drummers are not employed in battle, but their ceremonial duties continue. Typically [[bugle]]rs and drummers mass under a sergeant-drummer and during marches alternately perform with the regiment or battalion ensembles.

Military-based musical percussion traditions were not limited exclusively to the western world. When Emir [[Osman I]] was appointed commander of the Turkish army on the Byzantine border in the late 13th century, he was symbolically installed via a handover of musical instruments by the Seldjuk sultan. In the [[Ottoman Empire]], the size of a military band reflected the rank of its commander in chief: the largest band was reserved for the Sultan (viz. his Grand Vizier when taking the field). It included various percussion instruments, often adopted in European military music (as 'Janissary music'). The [[Bass drum|pitched bass drum]] is still known in some languages as the Turkish Drum.

Military drumming is the origin of [[Traditional grip]] as opposed to [[Matched grip]] of drumsticks.

==Parades==
The [[drumline]] is a type of marching ensemble descended from military drummers, and can be arranged as a performance of a drum, a group of drummers, or as a part of a larger [[marching band]]. Their uniforms will often have a military [[Music genre|style]] and a fancy hat. In recent times, it is more common to see drummers in parades wearing costumes with an [[African culture|African]], [[Culture of Asia|Asian]], [[Latin]], [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native American]], or [[tribal]] look and sound.

==Cultural drumming==
Various indigenous cultures use the drum to create a sense of unity with others especially during recreational events. The drum also helps in prayers and meditations.&lt;ref&gt;Dene Kede, p. 15, {{cite web |url=http://www.ece.gov.nt.ca/grades-k-12-curriculum/dene-kede-dene-perspective/dene-kede-kindergarten-grade-6-curriculum-document |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2015-05-01 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160826011217/https://www.ece.gov.nt.ca/grades-k-12-curriculum/dene-kede-dene-perspective/dene-kede-kindergarten-grade-6-curriculum-document |archivedate=2016-08-26 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
Drummer in a parade.JPG|A drummer in a parade, 2008
Young Dene Drummers.jpg|The Young Dene Drummers performed when Prince William and Kate visited Yellowknife, NWT on July 5, 2011.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{wiktionary}}
* [[List of drummers]]
* [[Drum beat]]
* [[Drum machine]]
* [[Drum tracks]]
* [[Pipe band]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}
*{{Cite EB1911 |wstitle=Drum |volume=8 |page=598 |first=Kathleen |last=Schlesinger}}

[[Category:Occupations in music]]
[[Category:Drummers]]
[[Category:Drumming]]
[[Category:Military ranks of the British Army]]</text>
      <sha1>fd2h0cpnqnvog95w0wxfbreczs37fjb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
