  <page>
    <title>Eight-ender</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33577240</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936752753</id>
      <parentid>931387395</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-20T20:06:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Grimes2</username>
        <id>28331428</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>markup fix</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox sport
| name = Curling
| image = 8-ender.tiff
| imagesize = 264
| caption = Final stone placement when Kelly Scott scored an eight-ender against Cathy King at the 2006 Player's Championship
}}
An '''eight-ender''', also called a '''snowman''', is a perfect score within a single end of [[curling]]. In an end, both sides throw eight rocks, and in an eight-ender, all eight rocks from one team score points.

Eight-enders are extremely rare in competitive curling and are analogous to a [[Perfect game (baseball)|perfect game in baseball]] or a [[Perfect game (bowling)|perfect game in bowling]] (300). Eight-enders are so rare that the [[Canadian Curling Association]] has an award to recognize any eight-ender scored in [[Canada]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.curling.ca/about-the-organization/awards-and-certificates/eight-ender-awards/|title=About the CCA – Awards and Certificates – Eight Ender Awards|publisher=[[Canadian Curling Association]]|accessdate=9 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007 Asham Curling Supplies awarded an $8000 prize randomly to one of the 145 teams that registered an eight-ender in the [[2005–06 curling season]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://curlnews.blogspot.com/2007/01/8000-for-curling-8-ender.html|title=$8,000 for a curling 8-ender|date=19 January 2007|publisher=The Curling News Blog Archive|accessdate=9 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The eight-ender in team curling is analogous to the six-ender in [[mixed doubles curling]], as there is a total of six rocks in play per team instead of eight.

There has never been an eight-ender in [[Olympics|Olympic]] competition, the closest being a 'seven-ender' scored by Scotland's [[Eve Muirhead]] at the [[2014 Winter Olympics]], in a 10–3 [[round-robin tournament|round-robin]] stage victory over the [[USA Curling|United States]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://ca.sports.yahoo.com/blogs/eh-game/curling-rarity-eve-muirhead-great-britain-hang-seven-181426735.html|title=A curling rarity: Eve Muirhead and Great Britain hang a 'seven-ender' on the United States in Olympic curling|publisher=[[Yahoo|Yahoo Sports]]|accessdate=20 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In mixed doubles curling, the maximum score of six has been achieved at the Olympics, with Switzerland's [[Jenny Perret]] and [[Martin Rios]] doing so against the United States in the last end of their 9–4 round-robin win at the [[Curling_at_the_2018_Winter_Olympics_–_Mixed_doubles_tournament|2018 Winter Olympics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Curling - Results|url=https://www.pyeongchang2018.com/en/game-time/results/OWG2018/en/curling/results-mixed-doubles-prel-000302-.htm|website=PyeongChang 2018 Winter Olympic Games|publisher=PyeongChang 2018 Winter Olympic Games|accessdate=24 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Occurrences==
===Saskatchewan vs Quebec===
At the 1952 Canadian Schoolboys Championship (now called the [[Canadian Junior Curling Championships]]), Saskatchewan's [[Gary Thode]] rink scored an eight ender against Quebec. The team would go on to win the match 17-5. To date, it has been the only eight-ender in Canadian juniors history. &lt;ref&gt;2019 Canadian Juniors Media Guide: History of the Canadian Juniors&lt;/ref&gt;

===Consecutive eight-enders===
In 1993, the team of [[Kim Gellard]], [[Corie Beveridge]], [[Lisa Savage]], and Sandy Graham recorded two consecutive eight-enders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Weeks|first=Bob|title=Curling, Etcetera: A Whole Bunch of Stuff About the Roaring Game|year=2008|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons Canada, Ltd.|location=Mississauga|isbn=9780470156131|pages=13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scott vs King===
{{Unreferenced|section|date=August 2018}}
Perhaps the most famous eight-ender occurred at the [[2006 Players' Championships]] in [[Calgary]], [[Alberta]] on April 15, 2006. The tournament was the final Grand Slam event in the 2005-06 [[Capital One Grand Slam of Curling|Grand Slam of Curling]] and had a [[Canadian dollar|CAD]]$100,000 purse – one of the largest in women's curling.

The match between [[Kelly Scott]], who at the time was the reigning [[Scotties Tournament of Hearts|Canadian women's champion]] and went on to become a [[World Curling Championships|world champion]], and [[Cathy King]] a former world bronze medalist. In the 6th end of their match, King and her rink played rather poorly, while Scott and her rink capitalized on King's mistakes. King ricocheted her final stone out the side of a crowded house, leaving Scott a draw for 8. Although her shot was heavy, Scott's rock came to a stop eighteen inches from the back of the house, enough to score her eighth point.

===Leskiw vs Hamblin===
Another notable eight-ender occurred on January 22, 2011 at the [[MCA Bonspiel]], the world's largest [[bonspiel]]. In this match Leskiw ''stole'' his eight points. In curling, when the team that does not have last rock in the end scores, the points scored are termed as stolen points. In this game, Leskiw managed an eight-ender even though Hamblin had the last rock, which gave him the opportunity to score or prevent Leskiw from scoring eight. In fact, Hamblin knocked Leskiw's eighth rock into the house with his final shot, turning a seven-point end into an eight-ender.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.winnipegsun.com/sports/curling/2011/01/23/16997816.html|title=Historic eight-ender a showstopper at the Granite|date=12 January 2011|publisher=[[Winnipeg Sun]]|accessdate=9 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jacobs vs. Phillips===
2014 Olympic champion [[Brad Jacobs (curler)|Brad Jacobs]] scored an eight-ender in the sixth end of the semi final of [[The Dominion 2012 Northern Ontario Men's Curling Championship]] against [[Tim Phillips (curler)|Tim Phillips]] in [[Sault Ste. Marie, Ontario]]. Jacobs had been leading 6-3 at the time, and had the hammer. After allowing the eight points, the Phillips rink conceded the game. On his last rock, Phillips ricocheted off two Jacobs stones, and out the rings, exposing one of his rocks that had been buried. Jacobs still had to make a delicate hit to ensure the Philips stone was removed, and he had to stick it to score his eight, which he did.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dev.curlingzone.com/event.php?eventid=2665&amp;view=Scores&amp;showdrawid=14|title=2012 The Dominion Provincial Championship: Brad Jacobs vs Tim Phillips|publisher=CurlingZone|accessdate=9 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Einarson vs. McLean===
Winnipeg's [[Kerri Einarson]] scored an eight-ender in the seventh end of her first round robin game at the [[2015 Manitoba Scotties Tournament of Hearts]] against [[Tiffany McLean]] of [[Brandon, Manitoba|Brandon]] in [[Winkler, Manitoba|Winkler]] on January 21, 2015. Einarson's rink stole the eight points, after having scored five points the previous end. Einarson won the game by a total score of 16-3. The feat was the first time an eight-ender had been scored at the Manitoba Scotties in recorded history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.winnipegfreepress.com/sports/curling/Einarson-scores-first-eight-ender-in-Scotties-history-289346401.html|title=Einarson scores first eight ender in Scotties history|date=21 January 2015|newspaper=[[Winnipeg Free Press]]|accessdate=21 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australia vs. Hong Kong===
The Australian men's team (skipped by [[Ian Palangio]]) scored an eight-ender in the first end of their match against Hong Kong ([[John Li]]) at the [[2015 Pacific-Asia Curling Championships]]. The Aussies went on to win the match 16-3, after Hong Kong conceded after seven ends. It was the first international event for Hong Kong.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.worldcurling.org/pacc2015/session6&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prince Edward Island vs. Nunavut===
The Prince Edward Island women's team (skipped by [[Lisa Jackson (curler)|Lisa Jackson]]) scored an eight-ender in the first end of their match against Nunavut (Angela Dale) at the [[2015 Travelers Curling Club Championship]], Canada's national curling club championship. P.E.I. went on to win the match 21-0, with Nunavut conceding after 6 ends (games at the Travelers are 8 ends in length).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.curling.ca/scoreboard/#!/competitions/1680/draws/3770&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first eight-ender ever scored at a national championship in Canada.&lt;ref&gt;http://cornwallcurling.com/2015/11/26/curling-canada-confirms-that-team-peis-eight-ender-is-first-ever-for-a-canadian-chship/&lt;/ref&gt;

===South Korea vs. Qatar===
The South Korean's women's national team skipped by [[Kim Eun-jung (curler)|Kim Eun-jung]] scored an eight-ender in the first end of their match against Qatar (skipped by Mubarkah Al-Abdulla) at the [[2016 Pacific-Asia Curling Championships]]. The Koreans went on to win the match 30-0 with Qatar conceding after six ends. It was the first international event for Qatar.&lt;ref&gt;http://live.ktgsports.com/data/CUR_PACC2016P/Women's_Teams/06~Session_6/C73~~Game_Results_KOR-QAT.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

===USA vs. Brazil===
The United States women's national team skipped by [[Nina Roth]] scored an eight-ender in the sixth end of their first match against Brazil (skipped by [[Aline Gonçalves]]) at the [[2017 Americas Challenge]]. The Americans went on to win the game 16-2 with the Brazilians immediately conceding after the 6th end. It was the first international event for the Brazilian women's team.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.teamusa.org/USA-Curling/Features/2017/January/27/USA-women-score-eight-ender-as-Americas-Challenge-begins-in-Duluth&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tardi vs. Schneider===
[[Tyler Tardi]] and his team from [[Langley, British Columbia (city)|Langley]] scored an eight-ender in the second end of their game against Team Stephen Schneider of [[Vancouver]] in their final round robin game at the 2018 [[King Cash Spiel]], an event on the [[World Curling Tour]]. Even though it was just the second end, Team Schneider conceded, losing the game 10-0. Tardi went on to win the event.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.worldcurl.com/events.php?eventid=5357&amp;view=Scores&amp;showdrawid=9&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Curling terminology]]
[[Category:Perfect scores in sports]]</text>
      <sha1>lwopo0kf2tgf7y4a5p7woeffj95ka58</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
