  <page>
    <title>Floorball</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11247</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938322588</id>
      <parentid>937793508</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-30T13:55:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.155.184.194</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Updated the description of the floorball blade photo to be more objective.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox sport
| image      = Finland is the World Champion in Floorball.jpg
| alt        = 
| imagesize  = &lt;!-- 200px --&gt;
| caption    = Finland celebrating after the gold in 2018 championship
| union      = [[International Floorball Federation]]
| nickname   = indoor [[bandy]], innebandy, salibandy, unihockey, Plastic hockey
| first      = late 1960s in [[Gothenburg]], Sweden
| region     = Czechia, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, Germany, Latvia, Norway, Slovakia, Sweden, Switzerland
| registered = 
| clubs      = 4396
| contact    = Yes
| team       = 6, including goalkeeper
| mgender    = Yes, separate competitions
| type       = Indoor
| equipment  = Shoes, Floorball stick, Glasses for safety
| venue      = 
| olympic    = No
| paralympic = No
| IWGA       = [[2017 World Games|2017]]
}}
'''Floorball''' is a type of [[floor hockey]] with five players and a goalkeeper in each team. Men and women play indoors with {{convert|96|–|115.5|cm|in|abbr=on|adj=mid|-long}} sticks and a {{convert|70-72|mm|in|abbr=on| adj=mid|-circumference}} plastic ball with holes. Matches are played in three twenty-minute periods. Floorball was included in the [[World Games]] for the first time in [[2017 World Games|2017]] in [[Wroclaw]], Poland. Sweden were the first World Games gold [[List of 2017 World Games medal winners#Floorball|medal winners]].

The game was invented in Sweden in the late 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theworldgames.org/sports/Floorball-56|title=Floorball {{!}} IWGA|website=www.theworldgames.org|access-date=2018-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The basic rules were established in 1979 when the first floorball club in the world, Sala IBK, from [[Sala, Sweden|Sala]], was founded in Sweden.&lt;ref name=if&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.innebandy.se/StatistikHistorik/Innebandyns-fodelse/ |title=Innebandyns födelse - Innebandy.se |website=Innebandy.se |accessdate=7 September 2016|language=sv|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180908194118/http://www.innebandy.se/StatistikHistorik/Innebandyns-fodelse/|archive-date=8 September 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Official rules for matches were first written down in 1981.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |last         = Houmann
 |first        = Steen
 |publisher    = Et samarbejde af Dansk Skoleidræt og Dansk Floorball Union
 |title        = Skolernes Floorball
 |url          = http://www.danskfloorball.dk/UserFiles/File/Breddeudvalget/SF2006.pdf
 |format       = PDF
 |accessdate   = 7 September 2016
 |date         = 2006
 |language     = Danish
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20150402110611/http://www.danskfloorball.dk/UserFiles/File/Breddeudvalget/SF2006.pdf
 |archive-date = 2 April 2015
 |url-status     = dead
 |df           = dmy-all
}} p. 2&lt;/ref&gt;

The sport is organized internationally by the [[International Floorball Federation]] (IFF). As of 2014, there are over 300,133 registered floorball players worldwide.&lt;ref name=ifftoday /&gt; Events include an annual Euro Floorball Cup for club teams and the biennial [[World Floorball Championships]] with separate divisions for men and women. Norway, Czechia, Finland, Sweden, and Switzerland have consistently placed 1st, 2nd, or 3rd at the World Floorball Championships. Professional club leagues include [[Finland]]'s [[Salibandyliiga]] and [[Sweden]]'s [[Swedish Super League (men's floorball)|Svenska Superligan]].

While the IFF contains 58 members, floorball is most popular where it has been developed the longest, such as the [[Czechia]], [[Denmark]], [[Estonia]], [[Finland]], [[Latvia]], [[Norway]], [[Sweden]], and [[Switzerland]].  It is gaining popularity in [[Australia]], [[New Zealand]], [[India]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.floorballaustralia.org.au/ |title=Floorball Australia &gt; Home |website=Floorballaustralia.org |accessdate=7 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Canada]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://globalnews.ca/video/1762155/what-is-floorball |title=What is floorball? |newspaper=Globalnews.ca |accessdate=7 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Germany]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.floorball.de/ |title=Floorball Deutschland |website=Floorball.de |accessdate=6 September 2016|language=de}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ireland]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.killarneyvikings.yolasite.com/about-floorball.php |title=Killarney Vikings |website=Killarneyvikings.yolasite.com |accessdate= 7 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Japan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.floorball.jp/ |script-title=ja:トップページ |website=Floorball.jp |accessdate=7 September 2016|language=ja}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Singapore]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://innebandyplaneten.se/?p=6305 |title=Interview with GK from Singapore! |accessdate=18 April 2015 |website=innebandyplaneten.se |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150418182756/http://innebandyplaneten.se/?p=6305 |archivedate=18 April 2015 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Malaysia]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://floorballmalaysia.com/ |title=MALAYSIA FLOORBALL ASSOCIATION |website=Floorballmalaysia.com |accessdate=September 6, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.aftonbladet.se/sportbladet/a/wEVeEo/wayne-gretzky-alskar-innebandy|title=&quot;Wayne Gretzky älskar innebandy&quot; |website=Aftonbladet.se |accessdate=September 6, 2016|language=sv}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[United Kingdom]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://ukfloorball.com/|title=UKFF - Home|access-date=2020-01-26|language=en-gb}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
In various forms the game has been played since the early 20th Century in [[Canada]] as a recreational sport, especially in high school gymnasiums, as a playful variant of [[hockey]], where the sticks got their form from the hockey game [[bandy]]. Most Canadian males born in the 1950s and before could attest to this.{{Citation needed|date = December 2015}} Similarly, during the 1950s and 1960s{{citation needed|reason=Need source because there is some crossover between the history of floor hockey and floorball||date=September 2015}} many public school systems within Michigan incorporated floorball into their primary and secondary school gym classes. Later, Americans claimed to have invented it, and held interstate tournaments in the 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://floorballcoach.org/development-of-floorball/ |title=DEVELOPMENT OF FLOORBALL : Floorball Coach – everything about floorball training |website=Floorballcoach.org |accessdate=7 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The game was formally organized as an international and more organised sport in the late 1970s in [[Gothenburg]], [[Sweden]].&lt;ref name=&quot;floorballnation1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=The History of Floorball|url=http://floorballnation.com.au/history-floorball.html|website=floorballnation.com.au|accessdate=7 September 2016|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130424172015/http://floorballnation.com.au/history-floorball.html|archivedate=24 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Malm|first1=William|last2=Olsson|first2=Rebecca|title=Floorball - The Future Sport|url=http://www.freeway.org/issue4/sports/floorball.htm|website=www.freeway.org|accessdate=7 September 2016|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130316062621/http://www.freeway.org/issue4/sports/floorball.htm|archivedate=16 March 2013|date=1998|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.floorballcentral.org/2010/01/true-history-of-floorball.html |title=The True History of Floorball |website=www.floorballcentral.org |date=16 January 2010 |accessdate=7 September 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160910115136/http://www.floorballcentral.org/2010/01/true-history-of-floorball.html |archive-date=10 September 2016 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The sport began as something that was played for fun as a pastime in schools.&lt;ref name=&quot;floorballnation1&quot;/&gt; After a decade or so, floorball began showing up in [[Nordic countries]] where the former schoolyard pastime was becoming a developed sport. Formal rules soon were developed, and clubs began to form. After some time, several countries developed national associations, and the IFF was founded in 1986.

The game of floorball is also known by many other names, such as '''salibandy''' (in Finland), '''innebandy''' (in Sweden and Norway), and '''unihockey''' (in Switzerland and Ireland). The names &quot;salibandy&quot; and &quot;innebandy&quot; are derived from [[bandy]]; they translate to &quot;hall bandy&quot; and &quot;indoor bandy&quot; respectively. Unihockey is derived from &quot;universal hockey&quot; since it is meant to be a special and simplified [[hockey]] form.

=== Expansion ===
{{Main|List of IFF member nations}}

When the IFF was founded in 1986, the sport was played in mostly Nordic countries, [[Japan]], and several parts of [[Europe]]. By 1990, floorball was recognized in 7 countries, and by the time of the first European Floorball Championships in 1994, that number had risen to 14. That number included the [[United States Floorball Association|United States]], who was the first country outside Europe and [[Asia]] to recognize floorball.&lt;ref name=ifftoday&gt;{{cite web |url=https://floorball.sport/this-is-floorball/history-in-short/ |title=History in short - IFF |website=floorball.sport |accessdate=26 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the time of the [[1996 Men's World Floorball Championships|first men's world championships]] in 1996, 20 nations played floorball, with 12 of them participating at the tournament.

As of 2009, the sport of floorball has been played in almost 80 countries. Of those, 58 have national floorball associations that are recognized by the IFF. With the addition of [[Sierra Leone]], [[Africa]]'s first floorball nation, the IFF has at least one national association on each [[continent]] of the [[world]], with the exception of [[Antarctica]].

=== Development ===
10 years after the IFF was founded, the first world championships were played, with a sold out final of 15,106 people at the [[Ericsson Globe|Globen]] in [[Stockholm]], Sweden. In addition to that, the world's two largest floorball leagues, Finland's Salibandyliiga and Sweden's Svenska Superligan were formed, in 1986 and 1995 respectively.

==== Recognition ====
In December 2008, the IFF and the sport of floorball received recognition from the [[International Olympic Committee]] (IOC). In July 2011, the IOC officially welcomed the IFF into its family of Recognised International Sports Federations (ARISF). This will pave the way for floorball to enter the official sport programme.  The IFF hopes that this recognition will help allow floorball to become a part of the [[2020 Summer Olympics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.floorball.org/news.asp?tyyppi=vanhat&amp;offset=20&amp;kieli=826&amp;id_tiedote=832&amp;alue=171&amp;yhteinen= |title=Floorball moves towards becoming an Olympic Sport |website=Floorball.org |date=12 December 2008 |accessdate=7 September 2016|url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160305183240/http://www.floorball.org/news.asp?tyyppi=vanhat&amp;offset=20&amp;kieli=826&amp;id_tiedote=832&amp;alue=171&amp;yhteinen= |archivedate=5 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2009, the IFF and the sport of floorball received recognition from the [[Special Olympics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.floorball.org/news.asp?kieli=826&amp;id_tiedote=882&amp;alue=171 |title=Floorball receives recognition by the Special Olympics |website=Floorball.org |date=23 Jan 2009 |accessdate=7 September 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304235259/http://www.floorball.org/news.asp?kieli=826&amp;id_tiedote=882&amp;alue=171|archive-date=4 March 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to recognition by the International Olympic Committee and Special Olympics, the IFF is also a member of the Sport Accord &amp;ndash; formerly known as [[General Association of International Sports Federations]] (GAISF), and co-operates with the [[International University Sports Federation]] (FISU).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://floorball.sport/theiff/ |title=The IFF |website=floorball.sport |accessdate=26 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Floorball is now also member of IWGA which runs the [[World Games]] and floorball will be for the first time on programme in [[World Games 2017|Wrocław 2017]].

== World championships ==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Sweden2006.jpg|thumb|320px|[[Sweden men's national floorball team|Sweden]] celebrates their [[2006 Men's World Floorball Championships|2006 World Floorball Championship]] after defeating [[Finland men's national floorball team|Finland]] 7–6 in [[Overtime (sports)|Sudden Victory Overtime]].]] --&gt;
{{Main|Floorball World Championships|List of World Floorball Champions}}
The world floorball championships are an annual event where teams from across the world gather to play in a tournament in order to win the world championship. As of 2011, eight Men's, eight Women's, six Men's Under-19, and four Women's Under-19 World Floorball Championships have taken place. Czechia, Finland, Norway, Sweden, and Switzerland remain the only five countries to have ever captured a medal at a World Championship event.
* The Men's World Floorball Championships take place every December (since 2008) in every even year.
* The Women's World Floorball Championships take place every December (since 2009) in every odd year.
* The Men's under-19 World Floorball Championships take place every May (since 2009) in every odd year.
* The Women's under-19 World Floorball Championships take place every May (since 2008) in every even year.

From 1996 to 2009, the IFF used a World Floorball Championship format where the last team in the A-Division was relegated to the B-Division, while the top team in the B-Division was promoted to the A-Division. This format caused much hardship for countries such as [[Men's national floorball team of Australia|Australia]], [[Men's national floorball team of Canada|Canada]], [[Men's national floorball team of Slovakia|Slovakia]], and [[Men's national floorball team of Spain|Spain]], who have all been trying to get to the B-Division from the C-Division since 2004. In 2010, the IFF adopted a [[FIFA]]-like continental qualification system, where teams must qualify to play at the world championships. Depending on the number of countries registered per [[continent]] or region, the IFF gives spots for the world championships. For example, [[Men's national floorball team of Argentina|Argentina]], [[Men's national floorball team of Brazil|Brazil]], [[Men's national floorball team of Canada|Canada]] and the [[Men's national floorball team of the United States|United States]] would need to play for one spot at the world championships in a continental qualification tournament for the Americas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.floorball.org/Liitetiedostot/CB2007_3_Appex%2014a%20WFC%20new%20system.pdf |title=WFC new style system |website=floorball.org |accessdate=27 January 2020 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Gameplay ==
[[File:Floorball rink1.svg|thumb|230px|The dimensions of a floorball rink]]

=== Measurements ===
Floorball is played indoors on a rink whose size can officially vary from {{convert|18|–|20|m|ft|abbr=on}} wide to {{convert|36|–|40|m|ft|abbr=on}} long,&lt;ref name=&quot;IFF&quot;/&gt; and which is surrounded by {{cvt|50|cm}} high enclosed boards with rounded corners. The goals are {{cvt|160|cm}} wide and {{cvt|115|cm}} high. Their depth is {{cvt|65|cm}} and they are {{cvt|2.85|m}} from the end of the nearest boards. Face-off dots are marked on the center line. Dots are also marked {{cvt|1.5|m}}  from both sides of the rink on the goal lines imaginary extensions.  The dots don't exceed {{cvt|30|cm}} in diameter.  They do not have to be dots, they can also be crosses.&lt;ref name=&quot;IFF&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://floorball.sport/rules-and-regulations/rules-of-the-game/|title=Rules of the Game |website=floorball.sport |date=1 July 2018 |accessdate=26 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Equipment ===
[[File:Floorball stick blade.jpg|right|thumb|Floorball stick blade that is worn on the left side]]
Typical equipment for a floorball player consists of a stick, a pair of shorts, a shirt, socks, and indoor sport shoes.  Players may wear [[shin guard]]s, eye protectors and protective padding for vital areas although most do not. Protective eyewear is, in some countries, compulsory for junior players.

A floorball stick is short compared with one for ice hockey; the maximum size for a stick is 114&amp;nbsp;cm. As a stick cannot weigh any more than 350&amp;nbsp;grams, floorball sticks are often made of carbon and composite materials. The blade of the stick can either be &quot;right&quot; or &quot;left&quot; which indicates which way stick is supposed to be held from the players point of view. A player who is right-handed will often use a &quot;left&quot; blade since this he/she will be holding the stick to left and the other way around for left-handed people.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.myactivesg.com/sports/floorball/how-to-play/floorball-for-beginners/stick-holding-and-posture-in-floorball]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Goalkeepers ===
Goalkeepers wear limited protection provided by padded pants, a padded chest protector, knee pads and a helmet. Some goalkeepers like to wear gloves and/or wristbands The goalkeeper may also wear other protective equipment such as elbow pads and jock straps but bulky padding is not permitted. Goalkeepers do not use sticks and may use their hands to play the ball when they are within the goalkeeper's box. There, they are allowed to throw the ball out to their teammates provided that the ball touches the ground before the half court mark. When they are completely outside the box, goalkeepers are considered field players and are not allowed to touch the ball with their hands.

=== Ball ===
[[File:Innebandy boll.jpg|right|thumb|A floorball ball. This is a plastic precision type ball, characterized by 1,516 tiny dimples that reduce air resistance, as well as friction on the floor.]]
A floor ball weighs {{cvt|23|g}} and its diameter is {{cvt|72|mm}}. It has 26 holes in it, each of which are {{cvt|10|mm}} in diameter. Many of these balls now are made with aerodynamic technology, where the ball has over a thousand small dimples in it that reduce air resistance. There have been several times where a ball has been recorded to have traveled at a speed of approximately {{convert|200|km/h|mph|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.floorballcentral.org/2010/11/new-world-record.html |title=New World Record |website=Floorballcentral.org |date=5 November 2010 |author= |accessdate=7 September 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170506132124/http://www.floorballcentral.org/2010/11/new-world-record.html|archive-date=6 May 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Rules ===
Each team can field six players at a time on the court, one player being a [[goalkeeper]]. But the [[Coach (sport)|coach]] can take the goalkeeper off for a short amount of time, and switch him with a field player. This can make advantages for the attacking side of the team, and disadvantages when it comes to their own defense. The team is also allowed to change players any time in the game; usually, they change the whole team. Individual substitution happens sometimes, but it usually happens when a player is exhausted or is hurt.

A floorball game is officially played over three periods lasting 20 minutes each (15 minutes for juniors). The time is stopped in the case of penalties, goals, time-outs and any situation where the ball is not considered to be in play. The signal of a timeout should be a triple sound.&lt;ref name=&quot;IFF&quot; /&gt; An intermission of 10 minutes (or maximum 15 minutes in some competitions)&lt;ref name=&quot;IFF&quot; /&gt; takes place between each period, where teams change ends and substitution areas. Each team is allowed one timeout of 30 seconds (which is often used late in matches). There are two [[referee]]s to oversee the game, each with equal authority. If a game ends in a tie, teams play ten minutes extra, and the team that scores first wins.&lt;ref name=&quot;IFF&quot; /&gt;. If the game is still drawn after extra-time, a penalty shootout similar to ice-hockey decides over the winner.

[[Checking (ice hockey)|Checking]] is prohibited in floorball. Controlled shoulder-to-shoulder contact is allowed, but [[ice hockey]]-like checking is forbidden. Pushing players without the ball or competing for a loose ball is also disallowed, and many of these infractions lead to two-minute [[penalty (ice hockey)|penalties]]. The best comparison in terms of legal physical contact is [[Association football]] (soccer), where checking is used to improve one's positioning in relation to the ball rather than to remove an opposing player from the play. In addition to checking, players cannot lift an opponent’s stick or perform any stick infractions in order to get to the ball. As well, players may not raise their stick or play the ball above their knee level, and a stick may not be placed between a player's legs. Passing the ball by foot is allowed, but only once, after that it the ball has to be touched by the stick. After stopping the ball by foot the ball has to be touched with the stick before it can be passed to a fellow player by foot (Rule change 2014). Passing by hand or head deliberately may result in a two minutes penalty for the offending player. A field player may not enter the marked goal area and playing without stick is prohibited.

When a player commits a foul, or when the ball is deemed unplayable, the play is resumed from a free-hit or a [[face-off]]. A free hit involves a player from one team to start play from the place where the ball was last deemed unplayable. A comparison of this is a free kick in soccer. For many fouls, such as stick infractions, a free hit is the only discipline provided. However, at the referee's discretion, a penalty may be worth either two or five minutes. At that point, the player who committed the foul sits in the penalty area, and his team is shorthanded for the time of the penalty. If an 'extreme' foul is committed, such as physical contact or unsportsmanlike behavior, a player may receive a 10-minute penalty or even a match misconduct.

==== Penalties ====
Two-minute penalties can arise from a number of infractions and result in the offending player being sat on a penalty seat next to the scorers/timekeepers and away from the team benches. Each penalty has a specific code that is recorded on the [http://www.floorball.org/Liitetiedostot/IFF%20Match%20Record%202010.pdf official match record] along with the time of the foul. The team of the offending player will play short-handed for the full length of the penalty. The codes are as follows;

Two Minute Penalties
* 201: Hit
* 202: Blocking Stick
* 203: Lifting Stick
* 204: Incorrect Kick
* 205: High Kick
* 206: High Stick
* 207: Incorrect Push
* 208: Tackle/Trip
* 209: Holding
* 210: Obstruction
* 211: Incorrect Distance
* 212: Lying Play
* 213: Hands
* 214: Header
* 215: Incorrect Substitution
* 216: Too Many Players
* 217: Repeated Offences
* 218: Delaying
* 219: Protest
* 220: Incorrect Entering of the Rink
* 221: Incorrect Equipment
* 222: Measuring Stick
* 223: Incorrect Numbering
* 224: Play without Stick
* 225: Non-removal of Broken Stick
* 226: Penalty at Penalty Shot

5 Minute Penalties
* 501: Violent Hit
* 502: Dangerous Play
* 503: Hooking
* 504: Roughing
* 505: Repeated Offences

Personal Fouls/Penalties
* 101: Unsportsperson-like Behaviour

== Forms ==

=== Freebandy ===
Freebandy is a sport that developed in the 2000s from floorball fanatics who specialize in a technique called &quot;zorro&quot;, which involves lifting the ball onto a stick and allowing air resistance and fast movements to keep the ball &quot;stuck&quot; to the stick. This technique is also referred to as &quot;airhooking&quot; or &quot;skyhooking&quot;. In freebandy, the rules are very much the same of those of floorball, with the exception of high nets and no infractions for high sticking. As well, the sticks are slightly tweaked from those of a floorball variety to include a &quot;pocket&quot; where the ball can be placed.

=== Special Olympics ===
Floorball at the Special Olympics is slightly modified from the &quot;regular&quot; form of floorball. Matches are played 3-on-3 with a goaltender, on a smaller court that measures {{convert|20|m|ft}} long by {{convert|12|m|ft}} wide. This form of floorball was developed for the intellectually disabled, and has yet to be played at the Special Olympics. Floorball was played as a demonstration sport at the [[2013 Special Olympics World Winter Games]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.specialolympics.org/our-work/sports/floorball |title=Special Olympics: Floorball |website=Specialolympics.org |accessdate=7 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was played as an official sport at the [[2017 Special Olympics World Winter Games|games in 2017]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.specialolympics.org/Stories/General/Floorball_is_now_an_official_Special_Olympics_World_Games_Sport.aspx |title=Special Olympics: Floorball is now an official Special Olympics World Games Sport |website=Specialolympics.org |date=14 May 2014 |author=Mariusz Damentko |accessdate=7 September 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180729013030/http://www.specialolympics.org/Stories/General/Floorball_is_now_an_official_Special_Olympics_World_Games_Sport.aspx|archive-date=29 July 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Streetbandy ===
A simplified less formal version of Floorball, played with smaller team numbers and shorter periods, and typically outdoors on various surfaces, including AstroTurf. In its most basic form, it is an informal pick up game amongst friends. However, a more formal version is played in Sweden, with the following structure:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://streetgames.se/om-street-games/streetbandy/ |title=Streetbandy |website=Streetgames.se |accessdate=7 September 2016|language=sv|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160917175326/http://streetgames.se/om-street-games/streetbandy/|archive-date=17 September 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 3 field players on each team, with smaller overall team sizes (including subs.)
* small goals, with no goalie
* smaller playing area, usually closer to a half rink.
* 10 minute length.
* tendency towards &quot;first team to score 5 goals in the time limit&quot; rather than traditional scoring. Sudden death on a draw.
* penalties are taken from the centre line.
* most situations arising from the ball leaving play are resumed from a fixed point (e.g. corner, centre line)
* no physical contact, high sticks or dangerous activity allowed.

=== Swiss floorball ===
Swiss floorball called unihockey is a revised version of a floorball match. The match is played on a slightly smaller court and often involves only three field players playing on each side, in 3-on-3 floorball. This form of floorball is also slightly shorter, with only two periods of 15 to 20 minutes each played. In Switzerland this form of playing is called &quot;smallcourt&quot; (Kleinfeld), opposed to the usual style of playing on a bigger court, which is called &quot;bigcourt&quot; (Grossfeld).

=== Wheelchair floorball ===
Originally developed for players with disabilities, wheelchair floorball is played with exactly the same rules as &quot;regular&quot; floorball. Players use the same stick and ball, and goaltenders are also allowed to play.

The first ever IFF-sanctioned wheelchair floorball matches were played between the men's teams of the [[Men's national wheelchair floorball team of Czechia |Czechia]] and [[Men's national wheelchair floorball team of Sweden|Sweden]], during the [[2008 Men's World Floorball Championships]] in [[Prague]], Czechia.

In addition to this, there is also an electric wheelchair variation. {{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

== Competitions ==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Efc0708celebration.jpg|thumb|300px|[[AIK Innebandy]] celebrate their [[2007–08 Men's EuroFloorball Cup Finals|2007–08 EuroFloorball Cup]] after narrowly defeating [[Warberg IC]] 2–1 in [[Overtime (sports)|Overtime]] in the final match.]] --&gt;
In addition to the [[Floorball World Championships]], there are other IFF Events for club teams such as the Champions Cup which is for the national competition winners from the Top-4 ranked nations, and the EuroFloorball Cup for the national competition winners from the 5th and lower ranked nations. There are also many international floorball club competitions.

=== Asia Pacific Floorball Championship ===
{{Main|List of Asia Pacific Floorball champions}}
The Asia Pacific Floorball Championships are played every single year in New Zealand, Australia, Singapore, or Japan. The event was created by the [[Singapore Floorball Association]] together with the cooperation of the [[Asia Oceania Floorball Confederation]] (AOFC). Members of the AOFC get together during this tournament to play for the Asia Pacific Floorball Championship every year. The most recent champions are [[Men's national floorball team of Australia]].

As of 2010, the Asia Pacific Floorball Championship is also the qualifying tournament for the [[World Floorball Championships]].

=== Canada Cup ===
{{Main|List of Canada Cup winners}}
The [[Canada Cup (floorball)|Canada Cup]] is an international club tournament that is held every year in [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]], Canada. It is the largest floorball club tournament outside of Europe, and attracts 55+ clubs from worldwide, every year. The winners of the 2015 Canada Cup floorball tournament were the Ottawa Blizzard floorball club.

=== USA Cup ===
{{Main|List of USA Cup winners}}
The [[USA Cup (Floorball)|USA Cup]] is an international club tournament that is held annually in [[Dallas–Fort Worth metroplex]], United States. It is a part of [[North American Championship (Floorball)|NAFC series]] with [[Canada Cup (floorball)|Canada Cup]] and [[Falls floorball classic]].

=== NAFC - North American Floorball Championship ===
{{Main|List of NAFC Winners}}
The [[North American Floorball Championship|NAFC - North American Floorball Championship]] is an international club tournament series currently including three tournaments: [[Canada Cup (floorball)|Canada Cup]], [[Falls floorball classic]] and [[USA Cup (Floorball)|USA Cup]]. Teams must attend at least one tournament in Canada and one in the United States with a roster that is made up of at least 50% of the same players and using the same club name to be eligible.

=== Czech Open ===
{{Main|List of Czech Open (floorball) winners}}
The world's largest club team tournament, the [[Czech Open (floorball)|Czech Open]] is a traditional summer tournament held in Prague, Czechia. It is famous not only for its on-court activities, but also for those off-court. The tournament attracts 200+ clubs every year from 20 different countries. The most recent champions of the prestigious Czech Open are Sweden's [[IBF Falun]].

=== Champions Cup ===
The Champions Cup was played for the first time in 2011. It is now the premier IFF event for Men's and Women's Club teams. The national championship winners from the Top-4 ranked nations receive automatic qualification, while the remaining two spots are made up by a team nominated by the Local Event organiser and the winner of the previous year's EuroFloorball Cup.

In 2011, the winners were Men: SSV Helsinki (Finland) and Women: IF Djurgårdens IBF (Sweden).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.floorball.org/pages/EN/Champions-Cup-2011 |title=Champions Cup 2011 |website=Floorball.org |accessdate=26 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== EuroFloorball Cup ===
{{Main|EuroFloorball Cup}}
The EuroFloorball Cup (formerly European Cup) is an IFF-organised club event for both men's and women's teams. It has taken place every single year since 1993, and in 2000 it changed its format to a 2-year event (i.e. 2000–01). In 2008, the tournament switched back to its one-year format. In 2011 it underwent another change when the Champions Cup was introduced for the first time.

The EuroFloorball Cup (EFC) is now for the national competition winners from the 5th and lower ranked nations. Qualification can be made via a number of processes. Firstly, the teams from the 5th, 6th &amp; 7th ranked nations receive automatic qualification. A team nominated by the local event organiser also gets automatic qualification, and then the last two spots are determined by qualification tournaments.

The winner of the EFC qualifies to play in the Champions Cup the following year. The reigning EuroFloorball Cup Champions as of October 2011, are Men: RTU/Inspecta (Latvia)and Women: RSU/Runway (Latvia).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.floorball.org/pages/EN/EFC-2011 |title=EuroFloorball Cup Final Round 2011 |website=Floorball.org |accessdate=7 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Indoor hockey]]

== Notes and references ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Floorball}}
* [https://floorball.sport/ International Floorball Federation]

{{IFF Member Nations}}
{{National floorball teams}}
{{Team Sport}}
{{Sports of the World Games program}}

[[Category:Floorball| ]]
[[Category:Team sports]]
[[Category:Indoor sports]]
[[Category:Ball games]]
[[Category:Variations of hockey]]
[[Category:Sports originating in Sweden]]</text>
      <sha1>3ug8vffs8e0sg6m2o0ehz394d756ups</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
