  <page>
    <title>Geodesy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12608</id>
    <revision>
      <id>935572009</id>
      <parentid>935278782</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-13T11:28:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>217.150.62.109</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Mathematical geodesists before 1900 */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|The science of the geometric shape, orientation in space, and gravitational field of Earth}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{More footnotes|date=February 2009}}
{{More citations needed|date=December 2018}}
{{Inadequate lead|date=June 2018}}}}
[[File:Geodetisch station1855.jpg|thumb|An old geodetic pillar (1855) at [[Ostend]], [[Belgium]]]]
{{Geodesy}}

'''Geodesy''' ({{IPAc-en|dʒ|iː|ˈ|ɒ|d|ɪ|s|i}})&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.lexico.com/en/definition/geodesy|title=geodesy {{!}} Definition of geodesy in English by Lexico Dictionaries|website=Lexico Dictionaries {{!}} English|language=en|access-date=2019-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; is the [[Earth science]] of accurately measuring and understanding [[Earth]]'s geometric shape, orientation in space and [[gravitational field]].&lt;ref name=&quot;noaa&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=What Is Geodesy|url=https://oceanservice.noaa.gov/facts/geodesy.html|website=[[National Ocean Service]]|accessdate=8 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The field also incorporates studies of how these properties change over time and equivalent measurements for other [[planet]]s (known as [[planetary geodesy]]). [[Geodynamical]] phenomena include [[crust (geology)|crustal]] motion, [[tide]]s and [[polar motion]], which can be studied by designing global and national [[control networks]], applying [[Space techniques|space]] and terrestrial techniques and relying on [[Geodetic datum|datums]] and [[coordinate system]]s.

== Definition ==
The word &quot;geodesy&quot; comes from the [[Ancient Greek]] word {{lang|grc|γεωδαισία}} ''geodaisia'' (literally, &quot;division of Earth&quot;).

It is primarily concerned with positioning within the [[time|temporally]] varying gravity field. Geodesy in the [[German language|German]]-speaking world is divided into &quot;higher geodesy&quot; (&quot;''Erdmessung''&quot; or &quot;''höhere Geodäsie''&quot;), which is concerned with measuring Earth on the global scale, and &quot;practical geodesy&quot; or &quot;engineering geodesy&quot; (&quot;''Ingenieurgeodäsie''&quot;), which is concerned with measuring specific parts or regions of Earth, and which includes [[surveying]]. Such geodetic operations are also applied to other astronomical bodies in the [[solar system]]. It is also the science of measuring and understanding Earth's geometric shape, orientation in space, and gravity field.

To a large extent, the shape of Earth is the result of [[Earth's rotation|rotation]], which causes its [[equatorial bulge]], and the competition of geological processes such as the [[Continental collision|collision of plates]] and of [[Volcano|volcanism]], resisted by Earth's [[gravity]] field. This applies to the solid surface, the liquid surface ([[dynamic sea surface topography]]) and [[Earth's atmosphere]]. For this reason, the study of Earth's [[gravity field]] is called [[physical geodesy]].

== History ==
{{main|History of geodesy}}

== Geoid and reference ellipsoid ==
{{see also|Geoid}}

The [[geoid]] is essentially the figure of Earth abstracted from its topographical features. It is an idealized equilibrium surface of [[sea water]], the [[mean sea level]] surface in the absence of [[Ocean current|currents]] and [[Atmospheric pressure|air pressure]] variations, and continued under the continental masses. The geoid, unlike the [[reference ellipsoid]], is irregular and too complicated to serve as the computational surface on which to solve geometrical problems like point positioning. The geometrical separation between the geoid and the reference ellipsoid is called the geoidal [[wiktionary:undulate|undulation]]. It varies globally between ±110&amp;nbsp;m, when referred to the GRS&amp;nbsp;80 ellipsoid.

A [[reference ellipsoid]], customarily chosen to be the same size (volume) as the geoid, is described by its semi-major axis (equatorial
radius) ''a'' and flattening ''f''. The quantity ''f''&amp;nbsp;= {{sfrac|''a'' − ''b''|''a''}}, where ''b'' is the semi-minor axis (polar radius), is a purely geometrical one. The mechanical ellipticity of Earth (dynamical flattening, symbol ''J''&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) can be determined to high precision by observation of satellite [[Orbital perturbation analysis|orbit perturbations]]. Its relationship with the geometrical flattening is indirect. The relationship depends on the internal density distribution, or, in simplest terms, the degree of central concentration of mass.

The 1980 Geodetic Reference System ([[GRS80|GRS&amp;nbsp;80]]) posited a 6,378,137&amp;nbsp;m semi-major axis and a 1:298.257 flattening. This system was adopted at the XVII General Assembly of the International Union of Geodesy and Geophysics ([[IUGG]]). It is essentially the basis for geodetic positioning by the [[Global Positioning System]] (GPS) and is thus also in widespread use outside the geodetic community. The numerous systems that countries have used to create maps and charts are becoming obsolete as countries increasingly move to global, geocentric reference systems using the GRS&amp;nbsp;80 reference ellipsoid.

The geoid is &quot;realizable&quot;, meaning it can be consistently located on Earth by suitable simple measurements from physical objects like a tide gauge. The geoid can, therefore, be considered a real surface. The reference ellipsoid, however, has many possible instantiations and is not readily realizable, therefore it is an abstract surface. The third primary surface of geodetic interest—the topographic surface of Earth—is a realizable surface.

== Coordinate systems in space ==
{{see also|Geodetic system}}

The locations of points in three-dimensional space are most conveniently described by three [[cartesian coordinate system|cartesian]] or rectangular coordinates, ''X'', ''Y'' and ''Z''. Since the advent of satellite positioning, such coordinate systems are typically [[geocentric]]: the ''Z''-axis is aligned with Earth's (conventional or instantaneous) rotation axis.

Prior to the era of [[satellite geodesy]], the coordinate systems associated with a geodetic [[datum (geodesy)|datum]] attempted to be [[geocentric]], but their origins differed from the geocenter by hundreds of meters, due to regional deviations in the direction of the [[plumbline]] (vertical). These regional geodetic data, such as [[ED50|ED&amp;nbsp;50]] (European Datum 1950) or [[North American Datum#North American Datum of 1927|NAD&amp;nbsp;27]] (North American Datum 1927) have ellipsoids associated with them that are regional &quot;best fits&quot; to the [[geoid]]s within their areas of validity, minimizing the deflections of the vertical over these areas.

It is only because [[Global Positioning System|GPS]] satellites orbit about the geocenter, that this point becomes naturally the origin of a coordinate system defined by satellite geodetic means, as the satellite positions in space are themselves computed in such a system.

Geocentric coordinate systems used in geodesy can be divided naturally into two classes:
# [[Inertial]] reference systems, where the coordinate axes retain their orientation relative to the [[fixed star]]s, or equivalently, to the rotation axes of ideal [[gyroscopes]]; the ''X''-axis points to the [[vernal equinox]]
# Co-rotating, also [[ECEF]] (&quot;Earth Centred, Earth Fixed&quot;), where the axes are attached to the solid body of Earth. The ''X''-axis lies within the [[Greenwich meridian|Greenwich]] observatory's [[Meridian (geography)|meridian]] plane.

The coordinate transformation between these two systems is described to good approximation by (apparent) [[sidereal time]], which takes into account variations in Earth's axial rotation ([[day|length-of-day]] variations). A more accurate description also takes [[polar motion]] into account, a phenomenon closely monitored by geodesists.

=== Coordinate systems in the plane ===
[[File:Litography archive of the Bayerisches Vermessungsamt.jpg|thumb|A [[Munich]] archive with [[lithography]] plates of maps of [[Bavaria]]]]
In [[surveying]] and [[map]]ping, important fields of application of geodesy, two general types of coordinate systems are used in the plane:

# Plano-polar, in which points in a plane are defined by a distance ''s'' from a specified point along a ray having a specified direction ''α'' with respect to a base line or axis;
# Rectangular, points are defined by distances from two perpendicular axes called ''x'' and ''y''. It is geodetic practice—contrary to the mathematical convention—to let the ''x''-axis point to the north and the ''y''-axis to the east.

Rectangular coordinates in the plane can be used intuitively with respect to one's current location, in which case the ''x''-axis will point to the local north. More formally, such coordinates can be obtained from three-dimensional coordinates using the artifice of a [[map projection]]. It is ''not'' possible to map the curved surface of Earth onto a flat map surface without deformation. The compromise most often chosen—called a [[conformal projection]]—preserves angles and length ratios, so that small circles are mapped as small circles and small squares as squares.

An example of such a projection is UTM ([[Universal Transverse Mercator]]). Within the map plane, we have rectangular coordinates ''x'' and ''y''. In this case, the north direction used for reference is the ''map'' north, not the ''local'' north. The difference between the two is called [[Transverse Mercator projection#Convergence|meridian convergence]].

It is easy enough to &quot;translate&quot; between polar and rectangular coordinates in the plane: let, as above, direction and distance be ''α'' and ''s'' respectively, then we have

:&lt;math&gt;\begin{align}
x &amp;= s \cos \alpha\\
y &amp;= s \sin \alpha
\end{align}&lt;/math&gt;

The reverse transformation is given by:

:&lt;math&gt;\begin{align}
s &amp;= \sqrt{x^2 + y^2}\\
\alpha &amp;= \arctan\frac{y}{x}.
\end{align}&lt;/math&gt;

== Heights ==
In geodesy, point or terrain ''[[height]]s'' are &quot;[[above sea level]]&quot;, an irregular, physically defined surface. 
Heights come in the following variants:

# [[Orthometric height]]s
# [[Normal height]]s
# [[Geopotential height]]s

Each has its advantages and disadvantages. Both orthometric and normal heights are heights in metres above sea level, whereas geopotential numbers are measures of potential energy (unit: m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;s&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt;) and not metric. Orthometric and normal heights differ in the precise way in which mean sea level is conceptually continued under the continental masses. The reference surface for orthometric heights is the [[geoid]], an equipotential surface approximating mean sea level.

''None'' of these heights is in any way related to '''geodetic''' or '''ellipsoidial''' heights, which express the height of a point above the [[reference ellipsoid]]. Satellite positioning receivers typically provide ellipsoidal heights, unless they are fitted with special conversion software based on a model of the [[geoid]].

== Geodetic data ==
Because geodetic point coordinates (and heights) are always obtained in a system that has been constructed itself using real observations, geodesists introduce the concept of a &quot;geodetic datum&quot;: a physical realization of a coordinate system used for describing point locations. The realization is the result of ''choosing'' conventional coordinate values for one or more datum points.

In the case of height data, it suffices to choose ''one'' datum point: the reference benchmark, typically a tide gauge at the shore. Thus we have vertical data like the NAP ([[Normaal Amsterdams Peil]]), the North American Vertical Datum 1988 (NAVD&amp;nbsp;88), the Kronstadt datum, the Trieste datum, and so on.

In case of plane or spatial coordinates, we typically need several datum points. A regional, ellipsoidal datum like [[ED50|ED&amp;nbsp;50]] can be fixed by prescribing the [[undulation of the geoid]] and the deflection of the vertical in ''one'' datum point, in this case the Helmert Tower in [[Potsdam]]. However, an overdetermined ensemble of datum points can also be used.

Changing the coordinates of a point set referring to one datum, so to make them refer to another datum, is called a ''datum transformation''. In the case of vertical data, this consists of simply adding a constant shift to all height values. In the case of plane or spatial coordinates, datum transformation takes the form of a similarity or ''Helmert transformation'', consisting of a rotation and scaling operation in addition to a simple translation. In the plane, a [[Helmert transformation]] has four parameters; in space, seven.

;A note on terminology

In the abstract, a coordinate system as used in mathematics and geodesy is called a &quot;coordinate system&quot; in [[International Organization for Standardization|ISO]] terminology, whereas the [[International Earth Rotation and Reference Systems Service]] (IERS) uses the term &quot;reference system&quot;. When these coordinates are realized by choosing datum points and fixing a geodetic datum, ISO says &quot;coordinate reference system&quot;, while IERS says &quot;reference frame&quot;. The ISO term for a datum transformation again is a &quot;coordinate transformation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;(ISO 19111: Spatial referencing by coordinates).&lt;/ref&gt;

== Point positioning ==
[[File:Geodetic Control Mark.jpg|250px|thumb|right|Geodetic Control Mark (example of a [[Benchmark (surveying)|deep benchmark]])]]

Point positioning is the determination of the coordinates of a point on land, at sea, or in space with respect to a coordinate system. Point position is solved by computation from measurements linking the known positions of terrestrial or extraterrestrial points with the unknown terrestrial position. This may involve transformations between or among astronomical and terrestrial coordinate systems. The known points used for point positioning can be [[triangulation]] points of a higher-order network or [[Global Positioning System|GPS]] satellites.

Traditionally, a hierarchy of networks has been built to allow point positioning within a country. Highest in the hierarchy were triangulation networks. These were densified into networks of [[traverse (surveying)|traverse]]s ([[polygons]]), into which local mapping surveying measurements, usually with measuring tape, [[Corner reflector|corner prism]], and the familiar{{where?|date=January 2017}} red and white poles, are tied.

Nowadays all but special measurements (e.g., underground or high-precision engineering measurements) are performed with [[Global Positioning System|GPS]]. The higher-order networks are measured with [[Global Positioning System|static GPS]], using differential measurement to determine vectors between terrestrial points. These vectors are then adjusted in traditional network fashion. A global polyhedron of permanently operating GPS stations under the auspices of the [[IERS]] is used to define a single global, geocentric reference frame which serves as the &quot;zero order&quot; global reference to which national measurements are attached.

For [[surveying]] mappings, frequently [[Real Time Kinematic]] GPS is employed, tying in the unknown points with known terrestrial points close by in real time.

One purpose of point positioning is the provision of known points for mapping measurements, also known as (horizontal and vertical) control.
In every country, thousands of such known points exist and are normally documented by national mapping agencies. Surveyors involved in real estate and insurance will use these to tie their local measurements.

== Geodetic problems ==
{{Main|Geodesics on an ellipsoid}}

In geometric geodesy, two standard problems exist—the first (direct or forward) and the second (inverse or reverse).

;First (direct or forward) geodetic problem

: Given a point (in terms of its coordinates) and the direction ([[azimuth]]) and [[distance]] from that point to a second point, determine (the coordinates of) that second point.

;Second (inverse or reverse) geodetic problem

: Given two points, determine the azimuth and length of the line (straight line, arc or [[geodesic]]) that connects them.

In plane geometry (valid for small areas on Earth's surface), the solutions to both problems reduce to simple [[trigonometry]].
On a sphere, however, the solution is significantly more complex, because in the inverse problem the azimuths will differ between the two end points of the connecting [[great circle]], arc.

On the ellipsoid of revolution, geodesics may be written in terms of elliptic integrals, which are usually evaluated in terms of a series expansion—see, for example, [[Vincenty's formulae]]. In the general case, the solution is called the [[geodesic]] for the surface considered. The [[differential equation]]s for the [[geodesic]] can be solved numerically.

== Observational concepts ==
Here we define some basic observational concepts, like angles and coordinates, defined in geodesy (and [[astronomy]] as well), mostly from the viewpoint of the local observer.

* '''[[Plumbline]]''' or '''vertical''': the direction of local gravity, or the line that results by following it.
* '''[[Zenith]]''': the point on the [[celestial sphere]] where the direction of the gravity vector in a point, extended upwards, intersects it. It is more correct to call it a '''direction''' rather than a point.
* '''[[Nadir]]''': the opposite point—or rather, direction—where the direction of gravity extended downward intersects the (obscured) celestial sphere.
* '''Celestial horizon''': a plane perpendicular to a point's gravity vector.
* '''[[Azimuth]]''': the direction angle within the plane of the horizon, typically counted clockwise from the north (in geodesy and astronomy) or the south (in France).
* '''[[Elevation]]''': the angular height of an object above the horizon, Alternatively [[zenith distance]], being equal to 90 degrees minus elevation.
* '''Local topocentric coordinates''': azimuth (direction angle within the plane of the horizon), elevation angle (or zenith angle), distance.
* '''North [[celestial pole]]''': the extension of Earth's ([[precession|precessing]] and [[nutation|nutating]]) instantaneous spin axis extended northward to intersect the celestial sphere. (Similarly for the south celestial pole.)
* '''Celestial equator''': the (instantaneous) intersection of Earth's equatorial plane with the celestial sphere.
* '''[[meridian (geography)|Meridian]] plane''': any plane perpendicular to the celestial equator and containing the celestial poles.
* '''Local meridian''': the plane containing the direction to the zenith and the direction to the celestial pole.

== Measurements ==
{{further|Satellite geodesy|Geodetic astronomy|Surveying|Gravimetry|Levelling}}

[[File:Stephen Merkowitz NASA's Space Geodesy Project.ogv|thumb|350px|A NASA project manager talks about his work for the [[Space geodesy|Space Geodesy]] Project, including an overview of its four fundamental techniques: GPS, [[very-long-baseline interferometry|VLBI]], [[Satellite laser ranging|SLR]], and [[DORIS (geodesy)|DORIS]].]]

The level is used for determining height differences and height reference systems, commonly referred to [[mean sea level]]. The traditional [[spirit level]] produces these practically most useful heights above [[sea level]] directly; the more economical use of GPS instruments for height determination requires precise knowledge of the figure of the [[geoid]], as GPS only gives heights above the [[GRS80]] reference ellipsoid. As geoid knowledge accumulates, one may expect the use of GPS heighting to spread.

The [[theodolite]] is used to measure horizontal and vertical angles to target points. These angles are referred to the local vertical. The [[tacheometer]] additionally determines, electronically or [[Electro-optics|electro-optically]], the distance to target, and is highly automated to even robotic in its operations. The method of [[free station position]] is widely used.

For local detail surveys, tacheometers are commonly employed although the old-fashioned rectangular technique using angle prism and steel tape is still an inexpensive alternative. Real-time kinematic (RTK) GPS techniques are used as well. Data collected are tagged and recorded digitally for entry into a [[Geographic information system|Geographic Information System]] (GIS) database.

Geodetic [[Global Positioning System|GPS]] receivers produce directly three-dimensional coordinates in a [[geocentric]] coordinate frame. Such a frame is, e.g., [[WGS84]], or the frames that are regularly produced and published by the International Earth Rotation and Reference Systems Service ([[IERS]]).

GPS receivers have almost completely replaced terrestrial instruments for large-scale base network surveys. For planet-wide geodetic surveys, previously impossible, we can still mention [[satellite laser ranging]] (SLR) and [[lunar laser ranging]] (LLR) and [[very-long-baseline interferometry]] (VLBI) techniques. All these techniques also serve to monitor irregularities in Earth's rotation as well as plate tectonic motions.

[[Gravity]] is measured using [[gravimeters]], of which there are two kinds. First, &quot;absolute gravimeters&quot; are based on measuring the acceleration of [[free fall]] (e.g., of a reflecting prism in a [[vacuum tube]]). They are used to establish the vertical geospatial control and can be used in the field. Second, &quot;relative gravimeters&quot; are spring-based and are more common. They are used in gravity surveys over large areas for establishing the figure of the geoid over these areas. The most accurate relative gravimeters are called &quot;superconducting&quot; gravimeters, which are sensitive to one-thousandth of one-billionth of Earth-surface gravity. Twenty-some superconducting gravimeters are used worldwide for studying Earth's [[tide]]s, [[rotation]], interior, and [[ocean]] and atmospheric loading, as well as for verifying the Newtonian constant of [[gravitation]].

In the future, gravity and altitude, will be measured by relativistic [[time dilation]] measured by [[Atomic clock#Strontium optical clocks|strontium optical clocks]].

== Units and measures on the ellipsoid ==
Geographical [[latitude]] and [[longitude]] are stated in the units degree, minute of arc, and second of arc. They are ''angles'', not metric
measures, and describe the ''direction'' of the local normal to the [[reference ellipsoid]] of revolution. This is ''approximately'' the same as the direction of the plumbline, i.e., local gravity, which is also the normal to the geoid surface. For this reason, astronomical position determination – measuring the direction of the plumbline by astronomical means – works fairly well provided an ellipsoidal model of the figure of Earth is used.

One geographical mile, defined as one minute of arc on the equator, equals 1,855.32571922 m. One [[nautical mile]] is one minute of astronomical latitude. The radius of curvature of the ellipsoid varies with latitude, being the longest at the pole and the shortest at the equator as is the nautical mile.

A metre was originally defined as the 10-millionth part of the length from equator to North Pole along the meridian through Paris (the target was not quite reached in actual implementation, so that is off by 200 [[Parts-per notation#ppm|ppm]] in the current definitions). This means that one kilometre is roughly equal to (1/40,000) * 360 * 60 meridional minutes of arc, which equals 0.54 nautical mile, though this is not exact because the two units are defined on different bases (the international nautical mile is defined as exactly 1,852 m, corresponding to a rounding of 1,000/0.54 m to four digits).

== Temporal change ==
In geodesy, temporal change can be studied by a variety of techniques. Points on Earth's surface change their location due to a variety of mechanisms:

* Continental plate motion, [[plate tectonics]]
* Episodic motion of tectonic origin, especially close to [[fault line]]s
* Periodic effects due to tides
* [[glaciation|Postglacial]] land uplift due to isostatic adjustment
* Mass variations due to hydrological changes
* Anthropogenic movements such as reservoir construction or [[petroleum]] or water extraction

The science of studying deformations and motions of Earth's crust and its solidity as a whole is called [[geodynamics]]. Often, study of Earth's irregular rotation is also included in its definition.

Techniques for studying geodynamic phenomena on the global scale include:

* Satellite positioning by [[Global Positioning System|GPS]]
* [[Very-long-baseline interferometry]] (VLBI)
* Satellite and lunar [[laser ranging]]
* Regionally and locally precise levelling
* Precise tacheometers
* Monitoring of gravity change
* [[Interferometric synthetic aperture radar]] (InSAR) using satellite images

== Notable geodesists ==
=== Mathematical geodesists before 1900 ===
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Pythagoras]] 580–490&amp;nbsp;BC, [[ancient Greece]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ngs.noaa.gov/PUBS_LIB/Geodesy4Layman/TR80003A.HTM|title=DEFENSE MAPPING AGENCY TECHNICAL REPORT 80-003|website=Ngs.noaa.gov|accessdate=8 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Eratosthenes]] 276–194&amp;nbsp;BC, ancient Greece
* [[Hipparchus]] {{circa}} 190–120&amp;nbsp;BC, ancient Greece
* [[Posidonius]] {{circa}} 135–51&amp;nbsp;BC, ancient Greece
* [[Claudius Ptolemy]] {{circa}} AD&amp;nbsp;83–168, [[Roman Empire]] ([[Roman Egypt]])
* [[Al-Ma'mun]] 786–833, [[Baghdad]] (Iraq/[[Mesopotamia]])
* [[Abu Rayhan Biruni]] 973–1048, [[Greater Khorasan|Khorasan]] ([[Persia|Iran]]/[[Samanid Dynasty]])
* [[Muhammad al-Idrisi]] 1100–1166, ([[Arabia]] &amp; Sicily)
* [[Regiomontanus]] 1436–1476, (Germany/Austria)
* [[Abel Foullon]] 1513–1563 or 1565, (France)
* [[Pedro Nunes]] 1502–1578 (Portugal)
* [[Gerardus Mercator|Gerhard Mercator]] 1512–1594 (Belgium &amp; Germany)
* [[Willebrord Snellius|Snellius]] (Willebrord Snel van Royen) 1580–1626, [[Leiden]] (Netherlands)
* [[Christiaan Huygens]] 1629–1695 (Netherlands)
* [[Pierre Bouguer]] 1698–1758, (France &amp; Peru)
* [[Pierre de Maupertuis]] 1698–1759 (France)
* [[Alexis Clairaut]] 1713–1765 (France)
* [[Johann Heinrich Lambert]] 1728–1777 (France)
* [[Roger Joseph Boscovich]] 1711–1787, ([[Rome]]/ [[Berlin]]/ [[Paris]])
* [[Ino Tadataka]] 1745–1818, ([[Tokyo]])
* [[Georg von Reichenbach]] 1771–1826, [[Bavaria]] (Germany)
* [[Pierre-Simon Laplace]] 1749–1827, [[Paris]] (France)
* [[Adrien-Marie Legendre|Adrien Marie Legendre]] 1752–1833, [[Paris]] (France)
* [[Johann Georg von Soldner]] 1776–1833, [[Munich]] (Germany)
* [[George Everest]] 1790–1866 (England and India)
* [[Friedrich Wilhelm Bessel]] 1784–1846, [[Königsberg]] (Germany)
* [[Heinrich Christian Schumacher]] 1780–1850 (Germany &amp; Russian Empire)
* [[Carl Friedrich Gauss]] 1777–1855, Göttingen (Germany)
* [[Friedrich Georg Wilhelm Struve]] 1793–1864, [[Tartu Observatory|Dorpat]] and [[Pulkovo Observatory|Pulkovo]] ([[Russian Empire]])
* [[J. H. Pratt]] 1809–1871, [[London]] (England)
* [[Friedrich H. C. Paschen]] 1804–1873, [[Schwerin]] (Germany)
* [[Johann Benedikt Listing]] 1808–1882 (Germany)
* [[Johann Jacob Baeyer]] 1794–1885, [[Berlin]] (Germany)
* Sir [[George Biddell Airy]] 1801–1892, [[Cambridge]] &amp; [[London]]
* [[Karl Maximilian von Bauernfeind]] 1818–1894, [[Munich]] (Germany)
* [[Wilhelm Jordan (geodesist)|Wilhelm Jordan]] 1842–1899, (Germany)
* [[Hervé Faye]] 1814–1902 (France)
* [[George Gabriel Stokes]] 1819–1903 (England)
* [[Carlos Ibáñez e Ibáñez de Ibero]] 1825–1891, [[Barcelona]] (Spain)
* [[Henri Poincaré]] 1854–1912, [[Paris]] (France)
* [[Alexander Ross Clarke]] 1828–1914, [[London]] (England)
* [[Charles Sanders Peirce]] 1839–1914 (United States)
* [[Friedrich Robert Helmert]] 1843–1917, [[Potsdam]] (Germany)
* [[Heinrich Bruns]] 1848–1919, [[Berlin]] (Germany)
* [[Loránd Eötvös]] 1848–1919 (Hungary)
{{div col end}}

===20th century geodesists===
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[John Fillmore Hayford]], 1868–1925, (US)
* [[Feodosy Krasovsky|Feodosy Nikolaevich Krasovsky]], 1878–1948, (Russian Empire, USSR)
* [[Alfred Wegener]], 1880–1930, (Germany and Greenland)
* [[William Bowie (engineer)|William Bowie]], 1872–1940, (US)
* [[Friedrich Hopfner]], 1881–1949, [[Vienna]], (Austria)
* [[Tadeusz Banachiewicz]], 1882–1954, (Poland)
* [[F.A. Vening Meinesz|Felix Andries Vening-Meinesz]], 1887–1966, (Netherlands)
* [[Martin Hotine]], 1898–1968, (England)
* [[Yrjö Väisälä]], 1889–1971, (Finland)
* [[Veikko Aleksanteri Heiskanen]], 1895–1971, (Finland and US)
* [[Karl Ramsayer]], 1911–1982, [[Stuttgart]], (Germany)
* [[Buckminster Fuller]], 1895–1983 (United States)
* [[Harold Jeffreys]], 1891–1989, [[London]], (England)
* [[Reino Antero Hirvonen]], 1908–1989, (Finland)
* [[Mikhail Molodenskii|Mikhail Sergeevich Molodenskii]], 1909–1991, (Russia)
* [[Maria Ivanovna Yurkina]], 1923-2010, (Russia)
* [[Guy Bomford]], 1899–1996, (India?)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bomford.net/IrishBomfords/Chapters/Chapter26/childpages/GuyBomfordTribute.htm|title=Guy Bomford tribute|website=Bomford.net|accessdate=8 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Antonio Marussi]], 1908–1984, (Italy)
* [[Hellmut Schmid]], 1914–1998, (Switzerland)
* [[William M. Kaula]], 1926–2000, [[Los Angeles]], (US)
* [[John A. O'Keefe (astronomer)|John A. O'Keefe]], 1916–2000, (US)
* [[Thaddeus Vincenty]], 1920–2002, (Poland)
* [[Willem Baarda]], 1917–2005, (Netherlands)
* [[Irene Fischer|Irene Kaminka Fischer]], 1907–2009, (US) 
* [[Arne Bjerhammar]], 1917–2011, (Sweden)
* [[Karl-Rudolf Koch]] 1935, [[Bonn]], (Germany)
* [[Helmut Moritz]], 1933, [[Graz]], (Austria)
* [[Petr Vaníček]], 1935, [[Fredericton]], (Canada)
* [[Erik Grafarend]], 1939, [[Stuttgart]], (Germany)
* [[Hans-Georg Wenzel]] (1949–1999), (Germany)
* [[Floyd Hough]], 1898-1976, (US) 
{{div col end}}

===Unlisted===
{{Expand list|date=July 2014}}
{{category see also|Geodesists}}

== See also ==
{{Portal|Earth sciences|Geophysics}}
{{div col}}
;Fundamentals: 
*[[Geodesics on an ellipsoid]]
*[[Physical geodesy]]
*[[Earth's circumference]]

;Governmental agencies:
*[[U.S. National Geodetic Survey]]
*[[National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency]]
*[[United States Geological Survey]]

;International organizations: 
*[[International Association of Geodesy]]
*[[International Federation of Surveyors]]
*[[International Geodetic Student Organisation]]

;Other: 
*[[EPSG Geodetic Parameter Dataset]]
*[[Surveying]]
*[[Meridian arc]]
{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* F. R. Helmert, [http://geographiclib.sf.net/geodesic-papers/helmert80-en.html ''Mathematical and Physical Theories of Higher Geodesy'', Part 1], ACIC (St. Louis, 1964). This is an English translation of ''Die mathematischen und physikalischen Theorieen der höheren Geodäsie'', Vol 1 (Teubner, Leipzig, 1880).
* F. R. Helmert, [http://geographiclib.sf.net/geodesic-papers/helmert84-en.html ''Mathematical and Physical Theories of Higher Geodesy'', Part 2], ACIC (St. Louis, 1964). This is an English translation of ''Die mathematischen und physikalischen Theorieen der höheren Geodäsie'', Vol 2 (Teubner, Leipzig, 1884).
* B. Hofmann-Wellenhof and H. Moritz, ''Physical Geodesy'', Springer-Verlag Wien, 2005. (This text is an updated edition of the 1967 classic by W.A. Heiskanen and H. Moritz).
* W. Kaula, ''Theory of Satellite Geodesy : Applications of Satellites to Geodesy'', Dover Publications, 2000. (This text is a reprint of the 1966 classic).
* Vaníček P. and E.J. Krakiwsky, ''Geodesy: the Concepts'', pp.&amp;nbsp;714, Elsevier, 1986.
* Torge, W (2001), ''Geodesy'' (3rd edition), published by de Gruyter, {{ISBN|3-11-017072-8}}. 
* Thomas H. Meyer, Daniel R. Roman, and David B. Zilkoski. &quot;What does ''height'' really mean?&quot; (This is a series of four articles published in ''Surveying and Land Information Science, SaLIS''.)
**[http://digitalcommons.uconn.edu/thmeyer_articles/2 &quot;Part I: Introduction&quot;] ''SaLIS'' Vol. 64, No. 4, pages 223–233, December 2004.
** [http://digitalcommons.uconn.edu/thmeyer_articles/3 &quot;Part II: Physics and gravity&quot;] ''SaLIS'' Vol. 65, No. 1, pages 5–15, March 2005.
** [http://digitalcommons.uconn.edu/nrme_articles/2 &quot;Part III: Height systems&quot;] ''SaLIS'' Vol. 66, No. 2, pages 149–160, June 2006.
** [http://digitalcommons.uconn.edu/nrme_articles/5 &quot;Part IV: GPS heighting&quot;] ''SaLIS'' Vol. 66, No. 3, pages 165–183, September 2006.

==External links==
{{Wikibooks-inline|Geodesy}}
{{commons category-inline|Geodesy}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20150924055300/http://www.ogp.org.uk/pubs/373-01.pdf Geodetic awareness guidance note, Geodesy Subcommittee, Geomatics Committee, International Association of Oil &amp; Gas Producers]
*{{cite EB1911|wstitle=Geodesy|volume=11|pages=607–615|short=1}}

{{Geology}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Geodesy| ]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]</text>
      <sha1>5612ak3kw3wl5436wybff5m4ik0cbh9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
