  <page>
    <title>Ghatampur</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23535978</id>
    <revision>
      <id>933229543</id>
      <parentid>920874783</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-30T18:21:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Uziel302</username>
        <id>13037279</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>India.Observer-&gt;India. Observer - [[Wikipedia:Correct typos in one click|Fix a typo in one click]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2018}}
{{Use Indian English|date=August 2018}}
{{Cleanup rewrite|date=January 2012}}
&lt;!-- See [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Indian cities]] for details --&gt;{{Infobox settlement
| name                    = Ghatampur
| native_nae             = 
| native_name_lang        = 
| other_name              = 
| nickname                = 
| settlement_type         = city
| image_skyline           = 
| image_alt               = 
| image_caption           = 
| pushpin_map             = India Uttar Pradesh
| pushpin_label_position  = right
| pushpin_map_alt         = 
| pushpin_map_caption     = Location in Uttar Pradesh, India
| coordinates             = {{coord|26.17|N|80.17|E|display=inline,title}}
| subdivision_type        = Country
| subdivision_name        = {{flag|India}}
| subdivision_type1       = [[States and territories of India|State]]
| subdivision_name1       = [[Uttar Pradesh]]
| subdivision_type2       = [[List of districts of India|District]]
| subdivision_name2       = [[Kanpur Nagar district|Kanpur Nagar]]
| established_title       = &lt;!-- Established --&gt;
| established_date        = 
| founder                 = 
| named_for               = 
| government_type         = 
| governing_body          = 
| unit_pref               = Metric
| area_footnotes          = 
| area_rank               = 
| area_total_km2          = 
| elevation_footnotes     = 
| elevation_m             = 122
| population_total        = 40623
| population_as_of        = 2011
| population_rank         = 
| population_density_km2  = auto
| population_demonym      = 
| population_footnotes    = 
| demographics_type1      = Languages
| demographics1_title1    = Official
| demographics1_info1     = [[Hindi language|Hindi]]
| timezone1               = [[Indian Standard Time|IST]]
| utc_offset1             = +5:30
| postal_code_type        = [[Postal Index Number|PIN]]
| postal_code             = 209206
| registration_plate      = UP78
| website                 = 
| footnotes               = 
}}
'''Ghatampur''' (Gautampur) is a city and a [[municipal board]] in [[Kanpur Nagar district]] in the state of [[Uttar Pradesh]], [[India]].

==History==

About 15&amp;nbsp;km North-East of Ghatampur is a small town named [[Bhitargaon]] which has a historical temple of the Gupta Period. Ghatampur was part of Kanpur district but was put with Kanpur Nagar after bifurcation of district into Kanpur Nagar and Kanpur Dehat.

Earlier Ghamatpur was both [[Ghatampur (Assembly constituency) | Vidhan Sabha]] and Lok Sabha constituency for election process. During restructuring of seats by [[Delimitation Commission of India]] lead to creation of a new Akbarpur Lok Sabha constituency in 2008 election.Town is dominated by majority of the Population from Sachan (Kurmi) Community.

==Geography==
Ghatampur is located at {{Coord|26.17|N|80.17|E|}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fallingrain.com/world/IN/36/Ghatampur.html Falling Rain Genomics, Inc - Ghatampur]&lt;/ref&gt; It has an average elevation of 122&amp;nbsp;metres (400&amp;nbsp;feet)
Ghatampur is situated about 30–40&amp;nbsp;km from southwest from [[Kanpur]] Downtown and about 130&amp;nbsp;km from [[Lucknow]] (State Capital).

==Festivals==

Kushmanda or Kudaha temple is one of the famous worship place of Ghatampur. It is believed to be one of its own kind in the country. People celebrate &quot;Deepdan&quot; on the fourth day of Navaratri. Navaratri is best time to visit Ghatampur. Post navaratri a five-day Ramleela and Krishna Leela is held in the city.

The second biggest festival of Ghatampur is &quot;&lt;span style=&quot;font-color:red;&quot;&gt;Kartik Purnima&lt;/span&gt;&quot; ( say Katki )on this day Ghatampur Municipality holds a fair on the grounds of the [[Kushmanda]] Mata Temple.
This town has three government inter colleges to boast of, one of them being  Shri Gandhi vidya peeth, Janta inter college and Islamia Inter college and one government girls inter college (GGIC).the third biggest festival in ghatam pur is Adbhut baraat on the day of shivratri.

==Demographics==
The Ghatampur city is divided into 25 wards for which elections are held every 5 years. The Ghatampur Nagar Palika Parishad has population of 40,623 of which 21,334 are males while 19,289 are females as per report released by Census India 2011. 

Population of Children with age of 0-6 is 5244 which is 12.91 % of total population of Ghatampur (NPP). In Ghatampur Nagar Palika Parishad, Female Sex Ratio is of 904 against state average of 912. Moreover Child Sex Ratio in Ghatampur is around 928 compared to Uttar Pradesh state average of 902. Literacy rate of Ghatampur city is 75.51 % higher than state average of 67.68 %. In Ghatampur, Male literacy is around 80.03 % while female literacy rate is 70.49 %. 

Ghatampur Nagar Palika Parishad has total administration over 7,407 houses to which it supplies basic amenities like water and sewerage. It is also authorize to build roads within Nagar Palika Parishad limits and impose taxes on properties coming under its jurisdiction.

==Popular places==
Ghatampur is not popular tourist destination but it has many popular old time temples like Kushmanda Devi Temple in the town, Gupta-era temple in Bhitargaon village and Brick Temple in  Nibiakhera village.

Ghatampur is progressively developing area regarding education and other facilities.

==Transportation==
Ghatampur is well connected with other parts of country by Rail and Road Transport. It is situated between junction of [[National Highway 34 (India)]] (connectiong Uttarakhand to Madhya Pradesh via Kanpur City) and UP State Highway 46 (bypass for NH 19).

CNG buses are run between Kanpur and Ghatampur as part of Kanpur City Transport Service Ltd. UPSRTC Buses going to Hamirpur and Mahoba from Kanpur also have stopover. There is one direct bus to [[Delhi]] from bus station.

Ghatampur town also has a Railway Station under Northern Central zone. There are daily trains with connectivity to [[Kanpur Central railway station]], [[Lucknow]], [[Chitrakoot division|Chitrakoot]] and [[Jabalpur]]. This station has two plateforms and is served by Express, Intercity and Passenger type of trains.

Nearest airport is Kanpur Chakeri Airport for domestic flights to Kolkata, Delhi and Mumbai. For other places and international flights, people need to travel to Lucknow.

==Health Services==

Ghatampur is growing tremendously in health sector areas. Ghatampur has Community health centre which provides health services to rural and poor communities in and around the city. Ghatampur is also home to the national JALMA institute of leprosy and other mycobacterial disease, which majorly concentrates on diseases like leprosy, tuberculosis, filariasis &amp; other mycobacterial diseases.

==Power Plant Project==

The government, recently has come up with constructing 3 x 660 total 1980 MW NUPPL (Neyveli Uttar Pradesh Power Limited) thermal power plant in Ghatampur area District Kanpur Nagar in Uttar Pradesh India. Observer Mr. Ajay Mehrotra Mob No.+91-9839100876.

==Popular culture==
The Uttar Pradesh government on Saturday entered into a joint venture agreement with Neyveli Lignite Corporation Limited for setting up a 1980-MW thermal power plant in Ghatampur of Kanpur Nagar. Proposed at a cost of around Rs 11,130 crore, the power plant was scheduled to be commissioned in three stages beginning December 2016. Chief minister Akhilesh Yadav, who presided over the meeting, asked the officials to ensure timely completion of the project.

According to the agreement, UP and Neyveli Lignite Corporation Limited (NLCL) will have a share of 49% and 51% of the total cost. The state will be getting at least 64.39% of the total generation, and the state government will be releasing its share according to this ratio. Principal secretary (energy), Anil Kumar Gupta said that keeping in view the demand of power in the state, the government has demanded a share of 75% of the total generation. &quot;This way UP will add between 1,275 Mw to 1,350 Mw of power, depending upon the share of the generation,&quot; he said. While UP Rajya Vidyut Utpadan Nigam Limited (UPRVUNL) was represented by managing director, Dheeraj Sahu, Neyveli Lignite Corporation Limited was represented by its chairman and managing director B Sundar Mohan.

==External links==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20110903013316/http://www.upelections.co.in/ Uttar Pradesh Assembly Elections 2012]
*[http://www.upelections.co.in/uttar-pradesh-assembly-constituencies/ghatampur GhatampurAssembly Elections 2012]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Kanpur district}}

[[Category:Cities and towns in Kanpur district]]</text>
      <sha1>d404ls730z7cqkaefx8q72tt0qju9v7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
