  <page>
    <title>Giannitsa</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4982600</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938529250</id>
      <parentid>934896152</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-31T19:36:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2A02:214B:8159:7200:994:1A3:1F2F:B4B6</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Notable people */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Yenice (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox Greek Dimos
 |name = Giannitsa 
 |name_local = Γιαννιτσά
|image_map = DE Giannitson.svg 
|map_caption = Location within the regional unit
| periph = [[Central Macedonia]]
| periphunit         = [[Pella (regional unit)|Pella]]
|municipality = [[Pella (municipality)|Pella]]
 |pop_municipality = 63122 
 |pop_municunit = 33775
 |population_as_of = 2011
 |area_municunit = 208.1 
 |pop_community = 29789
 |elevation = 42
 |coordinates = {{coord|40|47|N|22|24|E|format=dms|display=inline,title}}
 |postal_code = 581 00
 |area_code = 23820-2
 |licence = EE
 |website = [http://www.giannitsa.gr/ www.giannitsa.gr/]
 |image_skyline      = Pezodromos Giannitsa.jpg
 |caption_skyline    = 
 |city_flag          = 
 |city_seal          = 
 |districts          = 
}}

'''Giannitsa''' ({{lang-el|Γιαννιτσά}} {{IPA-el|ʝaniˈt͡sa|}}, in English also '''Yannitsa''', '''Yenitsa''') is the largest city in the [[regional units of Greece|regional unit]] of [[Pella (regional unit)|Pella]] and the capital of the [[Pella (municipality)|Pella municipality]], in the region of [[Central Macedonia]] in northern [[Greece]].&lt;ref name=Kallikratis&gt;[http://www.kedke.gr/uploads2010/FEKB129211082010_kallikratis.pdf Kallikratis law] Greece Ministry of Interior {{in lang|el}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The municipal unit Giannitsa has an area of 208.105 km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;ref name=stat01&gt;{{cite web |url=http://dlib.statistics.gr/Book/GRESYE_02_0101_00098%20.pdf |publisher=National Statistical Service of Greece |title=Population &amp; housing census 2001 (incl. area and average elevation) |language=el |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150921212047/http://dlib.statistics.gr/Book/GRESYE_02_0101_00098%20.pdf |archivedate=2015-09-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Its population is 31,983 people (2011 census). It includes a few outlying villages (Mesiano, Melissi, Pentaplatanos, Archontiko, Ampelies and [[Damiano, Pella|Damiano]]). The municipality Pella as a whole includes many villages and has 63,122 inhabitants. The city is located in the center of Macedonia between [[Mount Paiko]] and the plain of Giannitsa, and is the economic, commercial and industrial center of the [[Pella (regional unit)|Pella regional unit]]. [[European route E86]] ([[Greek National Road 2]]) runs along the south of the city.

The former shallow, swampy, and variable-sized [[Giannitsa Lake]] or (ancient) Loudias Lake, fed by the [[Loudias River]] and south of the city, was drained in 1928-1932 by the New York Foundation Company..&lt;ref&gt;Eugene N. Borza, ''In the shadow of Olympus: the emergence of Macedon'' (1992) {{ISBN|0-691-00880-9}}, p. 289; Matthieu Ghilardi ''et al.'', &quot;Human occupation and geomorphological evolution of the Thessaloniki Plain (Greece) since mid Holocene&quot;, ''Journal of Archaeological Science'' '''35''':1:111-125 (January 2008)&lt;/ref&gt; It or the surrounding marshland were sometimes called '''Borboros''' 'slime' or '''Borboros Limen'''.&lt;ref&gt;Ghilardi; Théophile Alphonse Desdevises-du-Dezert, ''Géographie ancienne de la Macédoine'' (A. Durand, 1863)&lt;/ref&gt;

About {{convert|7|km|0|abbr=on}} from Giannitsa are the ruins of ancient [[Pella]], birthplace of [[Alexander the Great]] and capital of [[ancient Macedonia]]. The city is {{convert|48|km|0|abbr=on}} from [[Thessaloniki]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.macedonia.info/pellis.htm|title=Macedonia - Perfecture of Pella|publisher=|accessdate=13 January 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304223433/http://www.macedonia.info/pellis.htm|archive-date=4 March 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Name==
[[File:Enidje-kula.JPG|thumb|The famous clocktower in the city's centre]]

The city was founded as  ''Yenice-i Vardar'' [[Ottoman Turkish language|Ottoman Turkish]] يڭيجۀ واردار 'new (town) of Vardar' in around 1372. It was sometimes called ''Evrenos Beg yöresi'' '[[Evrenos Bey]]'s town'.&lt;ref&gt;[[Encyclopedia of Islam]], 2nd edition, ''s.v.'' [http://referenceworks.brillonline.com/entries/encyclopaedia-of-islam-2/ewrenos-SIM_2214 Ewrenos]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Turkish name, in the form Γενιτσά, was used until February 1926 when its name was Hellenized as Yannitsa/Γιαννιτσά.&lt;ref&gt;Institute for Neohellenic Research, &quot;Name Changes of Settlements in Greece&quot; [http://pandektis.ekt.gr/dspace/handle/10442/170067 Genitsa/Giannitsa]&lt;/ref&gt; In other languages, the city is called: [[Ottoman Turkish language|Ottoman Turkish]] ''Yenice-i Vardar'' ('new-town of Vardar', as opposed to ''Yenice-i Karasu'', modern [[Genisea]], near [[Xanthi]] and known for tobacco), [[Turkish language|Turkish]] ''Yenice'' or ''Vardar Yenicesi'', {{lang-bg|Енидже Вардар}}, ''Enidže Vardar''.

==Population==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Year!! Population
|-
| 2011 || 31.983
|-
| 2001 || 29.364
|-
| 1991 || 22.504
|-
| 1981 || 23.966
|-
| 1971 || 21.188
|-
| 1961 || 23.555
|-
| 1951  || 20.187
|-
| 1940 || 16.401
|-
| 1928 || 12.785
|-
| 1913 || 7.167
|}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.e-demography.gr/ElstatPublications/censuses/index.cfm?year=1928|title=Εργαστήριο Δημογραφικών και Κοινωνικών Αναλύσεων Πανεπιστημίου Θεσσαλίας - Εργο e-Demography - Εκδόσεις ΕΛΣΤΑΤ - Απογραφές - 1928|author=Anastassios Hadjicrystallis - Consultant and developer of Internet and cell phone technology services.|publisher=|accessdate=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Prehistoric===
In the area of &quot;Old Market&quot;, on the southern hill of the city, there was an Early Neolithic settlement (late 7th to early 6th millennium BC). Giannitsa was also inhabited through the Bronze and Iron Ages. Incidental findings, such as coins, inscriptions, and sculptures indicate that the area was inhabited during the Hellenistic period (323-30BC). In ancient times, the area was called [[Bottiaea]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hellinon.net/NeesSelides/GianitsaNeolithika.htm|title=Ο ΝΕΟΛΙΘΙΚΟΣ ΟΙΚΙΣΜΟΣ ΤΩΝ ΓΙΑΝΝΙΤΣΩΝ|publisher=|accessdate=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ottoman===
[[File:Mosque and Clocktower in Enice Vardar Old Postcard.jpg|thumb|Postcard of Yenice-i Vardar, around 1900]]

Though there was probably a pre-existing Byzantine castle in the vicinity, the importance of the city of Yenije begins with its foundation by [[Gazi Evrenos]] in around 1372. Yenije became the base of the [[ghazi (warrior)|ghazi]] followers of Evrenos who took Macedonia and later Albania. The city was an important Ottoman cultural center and sacred area in the 15th and 16th centuries. Starting in the mid-15th century, Yenice became a center of literature and the arts. Under Ahmet Bey, a descendant of [[Gazi Evrenos]], many mosques, schools, workhouses and charitable projects were founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pellanet.gr/index.php?com=page&amp;item=20|title=Ιστορία Γιαννιτσών|work=PellaNet Online|accessdate=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 20th century, Yenije was a battleground between [[Macedonian Bulgarians|Bulgarian]] and Greek-Macedonian partisans in the [[Macedonian struggle]]. [[Penelope Delta]]'s novel ''Secrets of the Swamp'' (referring to the shores of Giannitsa Lake) is a romanticised account of this from the Greek point of view.{{cn|date=March 2017}}

[[File:Giannitsa.png|thumb|left|Map of the [[Battle of Yenidje|Battle of Yenice]]]]

===Balkan wars===
[[File:TiradoresGriegosEnElLagoYeniye--balkancockpitpol00pric 0091.png|thumb|Greek soldiers at the lake during the [[Balkan Wars]] (1912–3)]]
[[File:Enidje-pametnik.JPG|thumb|Monument to the [[Balkan Wars]]]]

Yenice &quot;retained its emphatically Turkish character up to 1912&quot; and members of the Evrenos family lived in the city in a large palace in the center of town until then.&lt;ref name=&quot;hist&quot;/&gt; In the [[First Balkan War]], the [[Battle of Yenidje|Battle of Yenice]]  (20 October 1912) was one of the most important battles the Greek army fought.

===German occupation===
The German army invaded Giannitsa on April 11, 1941 . On April 20, 1941, some Austrian forces arrived. The municipal registry of Giannitsa confirms four random killings in various parts of the city. On 16 September 1943, the Municipality of Giannitsa, headed by the Mayor, Thomas Magriotis and the help of local soccer teams organized a demonstration in the city and indulge{{clarify|date=August 2014}} in German commandant a text against the intention of the Germans to surrender [[Central Macedonia]] to the Bulgarians. According to oral testimony on November 13, 1943, the Germans arrested around 50 people, whom they transferred to the camp of Pavlos Melas at [[Thessaloniki]] and they killed thirteen. At the same time, the Germans invaded for the first time the village Eleftherohori {{convert|7|km|0|abbr=on}} away from the city, steal and destroy. In this attack there were no casualties. On 23 March 1944, the village was burned, and the place deserted. Eleftherohori lost 19 lives. On 5 August 1944, the Austrian soldier Otmar Dorne left the German occupation army and joined the 30th Constitution of the [[Greek People's Liberation Army|E.L.A.S]], based in [[Mount Paiko]]. The defection of Dorne, and the presence of the SS sergeant [[Friedrich Schubert|Schubert]], led to mass reprisals on 14 September 1944 in Giannitsa: about 120 residents of Giannitsa were executed by forces of the Jagdkommando Schubert with the collaboration of Greek units under the command of [[Georgios Poulos|G. Poulos]]. Among those executed was the Mayor, Thomas Mangriotis. The Swedish ambassador Timberg indicated that one third of the city was destroyed by fire. The citizens left the city. Emile Wenger visited Giannitsa few days after the mass execution, as a representative of the [[International Red Cross]] and wrote &quot;Giannitsa is already a dead city&quot;. On 20 September 1944, a citizens' committee sent a message to the National Government stating the facts and asking for weapons. The Germans left Giannitsa on November 3, 1944.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.24grammata.com/?p=4216|title=24grammata.com Culture e-Magazine – Free eBooks – WebRadio  » Τα Γιαννιτσά στα χρόνια της κατοχής / Eλευθεροχώρι, 23 Μαρτίου 1944|publisher=|accessdate=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Landmarks==
===Monuments===
[[File:Giannitsa, Gazi Evrenos 2.jpg|thumb|Mausoleum of [[Gazi Evrenos]]]]

Yenice was an important center in the [[Ottoman Greece|Ottoman]] period, and several important monuments survive, such as the ''Tombs of [[Gazi Evrenos]]'' (built in 1417) and ''Gazi Ahmed Bey'', the ''Kaifoun Baths,'' the ''Great Mosque'', the ''Army Mosque'', the ''[[Turkish bath|hammam]] of Evrenos'', and the ''Clock Tower'', built from 1667 to 1668 by the Ottomans. (The choice of location was made with military criteria because they wanted to control the commercial activity that took place across the city and throughout central Macedonia.) These monuments have been declared historical monuments by the Greek Archaeological Service.&lt;ref name=&quot;hist&quot;&gt;Vasilis Demetriades, &quot;The Tomb of Ghāzī Evrenos Bey at Yenitsa and Its Inscription&quot;, ''Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies'' (University of London) '''39''' (1976), 2: 328–332; Eleni Kanetaki, &quot;The Still Existing Ottoman ''Hamams'' in the Greek Territory&quot;, ''Middle East Technical University Journal of the Faculty of Architecture'' '''21''' (2005), 1-2: 81–110, citing M. Kiel, &quot;Yenice-i Vardar. A forgotten Turkish cultural center in Macedonia of the 15th and 16th century&quot;, ''Studia Byzantina et Neohellenica Neerlandica'' '''3''' (1971): 300–329.&lt;/ref&gt;

Points of interest include also the Cathedral Church of Giannitsa (achieved in 1860), the Neoclassical Multicenter, the Filippeio tourist center, the Macedonian tombs, and the prehistoric settlement of Archontiko.

[[File:Macedonian Museums-47-Laografiko Giannitsvn-210.jpg|thumb|Traditional Costumes at the [[Folklore Museum of Giannitsa]]]]

===Museums===
* The ''[[Folklore Museum of Giannitsa]]'' (opened in October 1977) by the &quot;Philippos&quot; History and Folklore Association to promote local history and traditions.
* The ''Military museum of Giannitsa'' (opened 24 February 2012), displays photographs, texts, weapons, uniforms, medals and other materials, with a particular emphasis on the Battle of the Swamp and the Balkan Wars 1912–1913.

===Statues===
[[File:Φίλλιπος B - Γιαννιτσά.jpg|thumb|[[Philip II of Macedon]] statue at Phillipio hill]]

* ''Black Statue - The Memorial of Giannitsà'', erected at the eastern entrance to the town in 1926 in honor and remembrance of the battle of Giannitsà (Sculptor: Gregory Zevgolis).
* ''Mass Grave'', a list of the residents who were executed at the 1st Primary School on 14 September 1944 by German troops.
* ''[[Alexander the Great]]'',  near the Cultural Center, unveiled on 20 October 2009, the anniversary of the liberation of the city and the Day of the [[Macedonian Struggle]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://macedonian-news.blogspot.gr/2009/10/statue-of-alexander-great-in-giannitsa.html|title=Macedonian News M-N        Μακεδονικά Νέα|author=ioakim-makedonas (macedonian)|publisher=|accessdate=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Philip II of Macedon]]'', located in the park of the &quot;Filippio&quot; tourist center.  Near the statue, there is a relief depicting the Macedonian phalanx.

===Aravyssos===
[[File:Aravissos Giannitsa Pella Πηγές Αραβησσού.JPG|thumb|Aravyssós park]]

About {{convert|10|km|0|abbr=on}} northwest of the city is the spring of Aravyssos, which produces drinking water. The surrounding grove and creek include a popular park.

==Economy==
Giannitsa is predominantly a rural area. The draining of the Lake Giannitsà left fertile soil for agriculture, leading to population growth in the region.

==Entertainment==
The focus of the social life of the city is at the central pedestrian street, where people gather to eat and drink or to take a walk. Giannitsa was one of the first cities that founded Open Theatre (3000&amp;nbsp;seats) and became an institution for cultural events and big names in theater and music, every year, the last month of summer giving a culture festival character . Also various theatrical and musical events take place in a closed theater located internally of the Cultural Centre which has a modern architecture. In the first days of September there is a big market for about a week. The DI.&amp;nbsp;K.&amp;nbsp;E.&amp;nbsp;P.&amp;nbsp;A.&amp;nbsp;P. (ΔΗ.&amp;nbsp;Κ.&amp;nbsp;Ε.&amp;nbsp;Π.&amp;nbsp;Α.&amp;nbsp;Π) is a charitable non-profit cultural organization founded in 1996 that develops music, visual arts, dance, film and other arts.

[[File:Loudias River 2.jpg|thumb|Loudias river]]

==Loudias river==
Seven kilometers ({{convert|7|km|abbr=off|disp=output only}}) south of the center is the [[Loudias River]], which has a sailing center. The Nautical Club of Giannitsa (NOG) teaches canoeing, kayaking, and rowing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.freewebs.com/nog-1/history.htm |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2014-03-24 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140324185113/http://www.freewebs.com/nog-1/history.htm |archivedate=2014-03-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Districts==
[[File:Saint George Church in Giannitsa.jpg|thumb|Saint George church]]

* Center
* St. George
* Ayía Paraskeví
* Sfageia
* Sinoikismos
* Mitropoli
* St. Konstantinos
* Tsali (Nea Trapezounta)
* Filippeio
* Kapsali
* Palaia agora

==Local Media==
[[File:Alexander the Great Statue Giannitsa.jpg|thumb|A statue of Alexander the Great]]

===Newspapers===
* ''O Logos tis Pellas'' (weekly; [[Greek language|Greek]] ''Ο λόγος της Πέλλας'')
* ''Giannitsa'' (daily; [[Greek language|Greek]] ''Γιαννιτσά'')

===TV station===
* [[List of Greek-language television channels|''Pella TV'']] ([[Greek language|Greek]] ''Πέλλα τηλεόραση'')

===Online Newspapers===
* ''Pella24''
* ''Pellanet''
* ''Giannitsa City news''
* ''Logos Pellas''

==Sports==
The most popular team is the [[Anagennisi Giannitsa]] football team which plays at the Municipal Stadium.

There is a [[motocross]] track northwest of the city, in the foothills of Mount Paiko, where local, Greek, and European races are run.

At the river Loudias, there are rowing races in which the Nautical Club participates.

==Twin towns and sister cities==
Giannitsa is [[Twin towns and sister cities|twinned]] with three cities:
* {{flagicon|CYP}} [[Larnaca]], [[Cyprus]], since 2003&lt;ref&gt;http://www.larnaka.org.cy/el/page/adelfopoiiseis#.XEMWylUzbX4&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|ITA}} [[Crotone]], Italy, since 2010&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arealocale.com/default.asp?action=article&amp;ID=4699 Grecia e Magna Grecia: incontro Giannitsa e Crotone]{{in lang|it}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|USA}} [[New Britain, Connecticut|New Britain]], [[Connecticut]], United States, since 2010&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://events.ct.com/events/view/35451/new_britain_sister_city_announces_a_trip_to_northern_greece.html|title=-  -  - CTNow.com|publisher=|accessdate=13 January 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131224111813/http://events.ct.com/events/view/35451/new_britain_sister_city_announces_a_trip_to_northern_greece.html|archive-date=24 December 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{See also|List of twin towns and sister cities in Greece}}

==Notable people==
* [[Gazi Evrenos]] (died 1417), founder of the Ottoman city, whose mausoleum is in the center of town
* [[K̲h̲ayālī]] (died 1556), Ottoman poet
* [[Āgehī]] (died 1577/8), Ottoman poet and historian
* Georgios [[Gonos Giotas]] (1880–1911), revolutionary in the [[Greek struggle for Macedonia|Macedonian Struggle]]
* [[Ahmet Derviş]] (1883–1932), military officer in the Ottoman and Turkish armies
* [[Elisavet Mystakidou]] (born 1977), Greek Olympic silver medalist in taekwondo
* [[Dimitris Pelkas]] (born 1993), soccer player playing as an [[attacking midfielder]] for [[PAOK FC]]
* [[Andreas Varsakopoulos]] (born 1990), [[Television personality]], [[personal trainer]], Lecturer currently living in [[South Korea]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.giannitsa.gr/ Δήμος Πέλλας], official site of the municipality of Pella
* [https://www.google.com/maps/@40.691764,22.3286115,29244m/data=!3m1!1e3?hl=en Google Earth view of Giannitsa and the drained lakebed]

{{Pella div}}
{{Greek Macedonia}}
{{Kallikratis-Central Macedonia}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Populated places in Pella (regional unit)]]
[[Category:Municipalities of Central Macedonia]]
[[Category:Macedonia under the Ottoman Empire]]
[[Category:1372 establishments in Europe]]</text>
      <sha1>9ymlx8ffvbyrrnn4t5o7ldklyq6g1um</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
