  <page>
    <title>Golf</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19568112</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936323399</id>
      <parentid>931804854</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-18T02:21:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>KingSkyLord</username>
        <id>30529645</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* top */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Golfer|other uses|Golf (disambiguation)|and|Golfer (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2018}}
{{Infobox sport
| name       
| image      = Golfer swing.jpg
| imagesize  = 250px
| caption    = A golfer in the finishing position after hitting a tee shot
| union      = [[The Royal and Ancient Golf Club of St Andrews|R&amp;A]]&lt;br /&gt;[[United States Golf Association|USGA]]&lt;br /&gt;[[International Golf Federation|IGF]]
| nickname   =
| first      = [[Kingdom of Scotland|15th century, Kingdom of Scotland]]
| registered =
| contact    = No
| team       =
| equipment  = [[golf ball|Ball]], [[golf club|clubs]], [[tee]]
| mgender    =
| rules      = USGA's [[Rules of Golf]]
| category   = Outdoor
| ball       = [[Golf club]]s, [[golf ball]]s, and others
| glossary   = [[Glossary of golf]]
| olympic    = [[1900 Summer Olympics|1900]], [[1904 Summer Olympics|1904]], [[2016 Summer Olympics|2016]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.olympic.org/uk/sports/past/index_uk.asp| title=Olympic sports of the past| publisher=Olympic Movement| accessdate=29 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[2020 Summer Olympics|2020]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Associated Press file |url=http://www.cleveland.com/sports/index.ssf/2009/10/golf_rugby_make_olympic_roster.html |title=Golf, rugby make Olympic roster for 2016, 2020 |publisher=cleveland.com |date=9 October 2009 |accessdate=23 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

'''Golf''' is a club-and-ball [[sport]]&lt;!--consensus is that golf is a sport, not a &quot;game&quot; or &quot;form of sport&quot; or similar so please do not modify this opening line--&gt;&lt;!--Golf, unlike fishing or checkers, is, of course, both a sport AND a game--&gt; in which players use various [[Golf club|clubs]] to hit [[Golf ball|balls]] into a series of holes on a [[golf course|course]] in as few strokes as possible.

Golf, unlike most [[ball game]]s, cannot and does not utilize a standardized playing area, and coping with the varied terrains encountered on different courses is a key part of the game. The game at the usual level is played on a course with an arranged progression of 18 holes, though recreational courses can be smaller, often having nine holes. Each hole on the course must contain a [[Teeing ground|tee box]] to start from, and a [[putting green]] containing the actual hole or cup {{convert|4+1/4|in|cm}} in diameter. There are other standard forms of terrain in between, such as the fairway, rough (long grass), bunkers (or &quot;sand traps&quot;), and various hazards (water, rocks) but each hole on a course is unique in its specific layout and arrangement.

Golf is played for the lowest number of strokes by an individual, known as [[stroke play]], or the lowest score on the most individual holes in a complete round by an individual or team, known as [[match play]]. Stroke play is the most commonly seen format at all levels, but most especially at the elite level.

The modern game of golf [[Golf in Scotland|originated in 15th century Scotland]]. The 18-hole round was created at the [[Old Course at St Andrews|Old Course]] at [[St Andrews]] in 1764. Golf's first major, and the world's oldest tournament in existence, is [[The Open Championship]], also known as the British Open, which was first played in 1860 in Ayrshire, Scotland. This is one of the four [[Men's major golf championships|major championships]] in men's professional golf, the other three being played in the United States: [[The Masters]], the [[U.S. Open (golf)|U.S. Open]], and the [[PGA Championship]].

==Origin and history==
{{Main|History of golf}}
[[File:The MacDonald boys playing golf.jpg|thumb|''The MacDonald boys playing golf'', attributed to William Mosman. 18th century, [[National Galleries of Scotland]].]]
While the modern game of golf originated in [[15th-century]] [[Scotland]], the game's ancient origins are unclear and much debated.

Some historians&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Brasch, Rudolph |title=How did sports begin?: A look at the origins of man at play |publisher=McKay |year=1970}}&lt;/ref&gt; trace the sport back to the Roman game of [[wikt:paganica|paganica]], in which participants used a bent stick to hit a stuffed leather ball. One theory asserts that paganica spread throughout Europe as the Romans conquered most of the continent, during the first century BC, and eventually evolved into the modern game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/438170/paganica |title=paganica (game) – Britannica Online Encyclopedia |publisher=Britannica.com |accessdate=23 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Others cite [[chuiwan]] (捶丸; &quot;chui&quot; means striking and &quot;wan&quot; means small ball)&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/883334381|title=When china rules the world : the end of the western world and the birth of a new global order|last=Jacques, Martin.|first=|date=2014|publisher=Penguin Books|year=|isbn=9781101151457|location=|pages=503–504|oclc=883334381}}&lt;/ref&gt; as the progenitor, a [[China|Chinese]] game played between the eighth and fourteenth centuries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://kaleidoscope.cultural-china.com/en/141Kaleidoscope598.html |title=Golf (Chui wan) – China culture |publisher=Kaleidoscope.cultural-china.com |date=25 September 2009 |accessdate=23 September 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6GWJYtVdw?url=http://kaleidoscope.cultural-china.com/en/141Kaleidoscope598.html |archivedate=10 May 2013  }}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Ming dynasty|Ming Dynasty]] scroll by the artist Youqiu dating back to 1368 entitled &quot;The Autumn Banquet&quot; shows a member of the Chinese Imperial court swinging what appears to be a golf club at a small ball with the aim of sinking it into a hole.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; The game is thought to have been introduced into Europe during the Middle Ages.&lt;ref name=&quot;TUGB54&quot; /&gt;

Another early game that resembled modern golf was known as [[wikt:cambuca|cambuca]] in England and chambot in France.&lt;ref name=&quot;TUGB54&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=McGrath |first1=Charles |last2=McCormick |first2=David|last3=Garrity|first3=John|title=The ultimate golf book |url=https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=QGvBn-wOy4EC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=lob+wedge+history&amp;ots=W9oxyaUmSP&amp;sig=6ojRy1wz353wbgt2i1xwop7PdRc#PPP1,M1|accessdate=4 May 2009 |year=2006|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|page=13|isbn=978-0-618-71025-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Persian game [[wikt:chaugán|chaugán]] is another possible ancient origin. In addition, [[kolven]] (a game involving a ball and curved bats) was played annually in Loenen, Netherlands, beginning in 1297, to commemorate the capture of the assassin of [[Floris V, Count of Holland|Floris V]], a year earlier.

[[File:Four gentlemen golfers on the tee of a golf course (5014828806).jpg|thumb|Four gentlemen golfers on the tee of a golf course, 1930s]]
[[File:Competición de golf femenino en Lasarte (2 de 2) - Fondo Car-Kutxa Fototeka.jpg|thumb|Female golfer in a competition in Spain in 1915.]]
The modern game [[Golf in Scotland|originated in Scotland]], where the first written record of golf is [[James II of Scotland|James II]]'s banning of the game in 1457, as an unwelcome distraction to learning archery.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.golf-information.info/history-of-golf.html History Of Golf] Golf Information.info.&lt;/ref&gt; [[King James IV of Scotland|James IV]] lifted the ban in 1502 when he became a golfer himself, with golf clubs first recorded in 1503–1504: &quot;For golf clubbes and balles to the King that he playit with&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Leibs (2004). ''Sports and Games of the Renaissance''. p. 69. Greenwood Publishing Group&lt;/ref&gt; To many golfers, the [[Old Course at St Andrews|Old Course]] at [[St Andrews]], a [[Links (golf)|links course]] dating to before 1574, is considered to be a site of pilgrimage.&lt;ref&gt;Cochrane, Alistair (ed) Science and Golf IV: proceedings of the World Scientific Congress of Golf. Page 849. Routledge&lt;/ref&gt; In 1764, the standard 18-hole golf course was created at St Andrews when members modified the course from 22 to 18 holes.&lt;ref&gt;Forrest L. Richardson (2002). ''Routing the Golf Course: The Art &amp; Science That Forms the Golf Journey''. p. 46. John Wiley &amp; Sons&lt;/ref&gt; Golf is documented as being played on [[Musselburgh Links]], East Lothian, Scotland as early as 2 March 1672, which is certified as the oldest golf course in the world by Guinness World Records.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/edinburgh_and_east/7949045.stm Links plays into the record books] BBC. Retrieved 24 September 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pgatour.com/2009/tourlife/travel/03/23/course_of_week/index.html |title=Recognition for the world's oldest links, at last |publisher=PGA Tour |date=24 March 2009 |accessdate=24 September 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090402071632/http://www.pgatour.com/2009/tourlife/travel/03/23/course_of_week/index.html |archivedate=2 April 2009  }}&lt;/ref&gt; The oldest surviving [[rules of golf]] were compiled in March 1744 for the Company of Gentlemen Golfers, later renamed [[The Honourable Company of Edinburgh Golfers]], which was played at [[Leith Links|Leith]], Scotland.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ruleshistory.com/ &quot;Historical Rules of Golf&quot;]. ruleshistory.com. Retrieved 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The world's oldest golf tournament in existence, and golf's first major, is [[The Open Championship]], which was first played on 17 October 1860 at Prestwick Golf Club, in Ayrshire, Scotland, with [[Men's major golf championships#Major championship winners|Scottish golfers winning the earliest majors]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pgatour.com/2007/travel/07/16/trans_071607/index.html The Open Championship – More Scottish than British] PGA Tour. Retrieved 23 September 2011 {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121002214520/http://www.pgatour.com/2007/travel/07/16/trans_071607/index.html |date=2 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two Scotsmen from [[Dunfermline]], John Reid and Robert Lockhart, first demonstrated golf in the U.S. by setting up a hole in an orchard in 1888, with Reid setting up America's first golf club the same year, [[Saint Andrew's Golf Club]] in Yonkers, New York.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-scotland-tayside-central-29310735 &quot;Ryder Cup: Painting celebrates Dunfermline links to American golf&quot;]. BBC. Retrieved 29 December 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

==Golf course==
[[File:Golf course Golfplatz Wittenbeck Mecklenburg Ostsee Baltic Sea Germany.jpg|thumb|Aerial view of the ''Golfplatz [[Wittenbeck]]'' in [[Mecklenburg]], [[Germany]]]]
{{Main|Golf course}}
A golf course consists of either 9 or 18 holes, each with a [[teeing ground]] that is set off by two markers showing the bounds of the legal tee area, [[Fairway (golf)#Fairway and rough|fairway]], [[Fairway (golf)#Fairway and rough|rough]] and other [[Hazard (golf)|hazards]], and the [[putting green]] surrounded by the fringe with the pin (normally a flagstick) and cup.

The levels of grass are varied to increase difficulty, or to allow for putting in the case of the green. While many holes are designed with a direct line-of-sight from the teeing area to the green, some holes may bend either to the left or to the right. This is commonly called a &quot;dogleg&quot;, in reference to a dog's knee. The hole is called a &quot;dogleg left&quot; if the hole angles leftwards and &quot;dogleg right&quot; if it bends right. Sometimes, a hole's direction may bend twice; this is called a &quot;double dogleg&quot;.

A regular golf course consists of 18 holes, but nine-hole courses are common and can be played twice through for a full round of 18 holes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encarta&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761570500/Golf.html#p2 |title=Golf |publisher=[[Encarta]] |accessdate=20 December 2007 |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/5kwq81UW4?url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761570500/Golf.html |archivedate=1 November 2009 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hildenpark.co.uk/golf/golfcourse.html |title=Hill den Park – 9 Hole Golf Course |publisher=hilden park.co.uk |accessdate=20 December 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071222001759/http://www.hildenpark.co.uk/golf/golfcourse.html |archivedate=22 December 2007 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early Scottish golf courses were primarily laid out on links land, soil-covered sand dunes directly inland from beaches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?search=links&amp;searchmode=none |title=Online Etymology Dictionary definition of the word Links |publisher=Etymonline.com |accessdate=23 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This gave rise to the term &quot;golf links&quot;, particularly applied to seaside courses and those built on naturally sandy soil inland.

The first 18-hole golf course in the United States was on a sheep farm in [[Downers Grove, Illinois]], in 1892. The course is still there today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nbcchicago.com/news/sports/golf-good-question-93041254.html |title=Why Does Golf Have 18 Holes? |accessdate=6 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Play of the game==
[[File:Golf field.svg|thumb|right|upright|1=teeing ground, 2=water hazard, 3=rough, 4=out of bounds, 5=[[Hazard (golf)#Bunker|sand bunker]], 6=water hazard, 7=fairway, 8=putting green, 9=flagstick, 10=hole]]
Every round of golf is based on playing a number of holes in a given order. A &quot;round&quot; typically consists of 18 holes that are played in the order determined by the course layout. Each hole is played once in the round on a standard course of 18 holes. The game can be played by any number of people, although a typical group playing will have 1-4 people playing the round. The typical amount of time required for pace of play for a 9-hole round is two hours and four hours for an 18-hole round.

Playing a hole on a golf course is initiated by putting a ball into play by striking it with a club on the [[teeing ground]] (also called the tee box, or simply the tee). For this first shot on each hole, it is allowed but not required for the golfer to place the ball on a [[Tee#Golf tee|tee]] prior to striking it. A tee is a small peg that can be used to elevate the ball slightly above the ground up to a few centimetres high. Tees are commonly made of wood but may be constructed of any material, including plastic. Traditionally, golfers used mounds of sand to elevate the ball, and containers of sand were provided for the purpose. A few courses still require sand to be used instead of peg tees, to reduce litter and reduce damage to the teeing ground. Tees help reduce the interference of the ground or grass on the movement of the club making the ball easier to hit, and also places the ball in the very centre of the striking face of the club (the &quot;sweet spot&quot;) for better distance.

When the initial shot on a hole is intended to move the ball a long distance, typically more than {{convert|225|yd|-1}}, the shot is commonly called a &quot;drive&quot; and is generally made with a long-shafted, large-headed [[wood (golf)|wood]] club called a &quot;driver&quot;. Shorter holes may be initiated with other clubs, such as higher-numbered woods or [[Iron (golf)|irons]]. Once the ball comes to rest, the golfer strikes it again as many times as necessary using shots that are variously known as a &quot;lay-up&quot;, an &quot;approach&quot;, a &quot;pitch&quot;, or a &quot;[[Golf stroke mechanics#Chip|chip]]&quot;, until the ball reaches the green, where he or she then &quot;[[Golf stroke mechanics#Putt|putt]]s&quot; the ball into the hole (commonly called &quot;sinking the putt&quot; or &quot;holing out&quot;). The goal of getting the ball into the hole (&quot;holing&quot; the ball) in as few strokes as possible may be impeded by obstacles such as areas of longer grass called &quot;rough&quot; (usually found alongside fairways), which both slows any ball that contacts it and makes it harder to advance a ball that has stopped on it; &quot;doglegs&quot;, which are changes in the direction of the fairway that often require shorter shots to play around them; [[Hazard (golf)#Bunker|bunkers]] (or sand traps); and [[Hazard (golf)#Water hazard|water hazards]] such as ponds or streams.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encarta&quot;/&gt;

In stroke play competitions played according to [[strict rules]], each player plays his or her ball until it is holed no matter how many strokes that may take. In match play it is acceptable to simply pick up one's ball and &quot;surrender the hole&quot; after enough strokes have been made by a player that it is mathematically impossible for the player to win the hole. It is also acceptable in informal stroke play to surrender the hole after hitting three strokes more than the &quot;par&quot; rating of the hole (a &quot;triple bogey&quot; - see below); while technically a violation of Rule 3-2, this practice speeds play as a courtesy to others, and avoids &quot;runaway scores&quot;, excessive frustration and injuries caused by overexertion.

The total distance from the first tee box to the 18th green can be quite long; total yardages &quot;through the green&quot; can be in excess of {{convert|7000|yd|km}}, and when adding in the travel distance between the green of one hole and the tee of the next, even skilled players may easily travel {{convert|5|mi|km|0|spell=in}} or more during a round. At some courses, electric [[golf carts]] are used to travel between shots, which can speed-up play and allows participation by individuals unable to walk a whole round. On other courses players generally walk the course, either carrying their bag using a shoulder strap or using a &quot;golf trolley&quot; for their bag. These trolleys may or may not be battery assisted. At many amateur tournaments including U.S. high school and college play, players are required to walk and to carry their own bags, but at the professional and top amateur level, as well as at high-level private clubs, players may be accompanied by [[caddies]], who carry and manage the players' equipment and who are allowed by the rules to give advice on the play of the course.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|url=http://encarta.msn.com/dictionary_1861593951/caddie.html |title=Caddie |publisher=[[Encarta]] |accessdate=24 December 2007 |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/5kwq7UVSG?url=http://encarta.msn.com/dictionary_1861593951/caddie.html |archivedate=1 November 2009 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt; A caddie's advice can only be given to the player or players for whom the caddie is working, and not to other competing players.

==Rules and regulations==
{{Main|Rules of golf}}
[[File:ArnoldPalmerCoastGuard1953.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Arnold Palmer]] in 1953]]
The rules of golf are internationally standardised and are jointly governed by The R&amp;A, spun off in 2004 from [[The Royal and Ancient Golf Club of St Andrews]] (founded 1754), and the [[United States Golf Association]] (USGA).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usga.org/playing/rules/rules_of_golf.html# |title=The Rules of Golf |publisher=[[United States Golf Association]] |accessdate=7 November 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071011003259/http://www.usga.org/playing/rules/rules_of_golf.html |archivedate=11 October 2007 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ROG&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.randa.org/flash/rules/PDF/RoG2004.pdf |title=Rules of Golf |publisher=[[The Royal and Ancient Golf Club of St Andrews]] |accessdate=7 November 2007 |format=PDF |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071031100139/http://www.randa.org/flash/rules/PDF/RoG2004.pdf |archivedate=31 October 2007 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The underlying principle of the rules is fairness. As stated on the back cover of the official rule book:
:''Play the ball as it lies, play the course as you find it, and if you cannot do either, do what is fair.''

There are strict regulations regarding the amateur status of golfers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usga.org/playing/amateur_status/amateur_status.html |title=Amateur Status |publisher=[[United States Golf Association]] |accessdate=7 November 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071001153253/http://www.usga.org/playing/amateur_status/amateur_status.html |archivedate=1 October 2007 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Essentially, anybody who has ever received payment or compensation for giving instruction, or played golf for money, is not considered an amateur and may not participate in competitions limited solely to amateurs. However, amateur golfers may receive expenses that comply with strict guidelines and they may accept non-cash prizes within the limits established by the Rules of Amateur Status.

In addition to the officially printed rules, golfers also abide by a set of guidelines called [[golf etiquette]]. Etiquette guidelines cover matters such as safety, fairness, pace of play, and a player's obligation to contribute to the care of the course. Though there are no penalties for breach of etiquette rules, players generally follow the rules of golf etiquette in an effort to improve everyone's playing experience.

===Penalties===
{{main|Penalty (golf)}}
Penalties are incurred in certain situations. They are counted towards a player's score as if there were extra swing(s) at the ball. Strokes are added for rule infractions or for hitting one's ball into an unplayable situation.

A lost ball or a ball hit out of bounds result in a penalty of one stroke and distance (Rule 27–1). A one-stroke penalty is assessed if a player's equipment causes the ball to move or the removal of a loose impediment causes the ball to move (Rule 18–2). A one-stroke penalty is assessed if a player's ball results into a red or yellow staked hazard (Rule 26). If a golfer makes a stroke at the wrong ball (Rule 19–2) or hits a fellow golfer's ball with a putt (Rule 19–5), the player incurs a two-stroke penalty. Most rule infractions lead to stroke penalties but also can lead to disqualification. Disqualification could be from cheating, signing for a lower score, or from rule infractions that lead to improper play.&lt;ref name=&quot;rules&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Rules of Golf (free download)|url=https://golfwithasmile.com/rules-of-golf/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Equipment==
{{Main|Golf equipment}}
[[File:Golf ball resting near fairway wood.jpg|thumb|right|A [[Wood (golf)|wood]] positioned ready to be swung and to strike a [[golf ball]]]]
[[Golf club]]s are used to hit the [[golf ball]]. Each club is composed of a shaft with a lance (or &quot;grip&quot;) on the top end and a club head on the bottom. Long clubs, which have a lower amount of degree loft, are those meant to propel the ball a comparatively longer distance, and short clubs a higher degree of loft and a comparatively shorter distance. The actual physical length of each club is longer or shorter, depending on the distance the club is intended to propel the ball.

Golf clubs have traditionally been arranged into three basic types. [[Wood (golf)|Woods]] are large-headed, long-shafted clubs meant to propel the ball a long distance from relatively &quot;open&quot; lies, such as the tee box and fairway. Of particular importance is the ''driver'' or &quot;1-wood&quot;, which is the lowest lofted wood club, and in modern times has become highly specialized for making extremely long-distance tee shots, up to {{convert|300|yd}}, or more, in a professional golfer's hands. Traditionally these clubs had heads made of a hardwood, hence the name, but virtually all modern woods are now made of metal such as titanium, or of composite materials. [[Iron (golf club)|Irons]] are shorter-shafted clubs with a metal head primarily consisting of a flat, angled striking face. Traditionally the clubhead was forged from iron; modern iron clubheads are investment-cast from a steel alloy. Irons of varying loft are used for a variety of shots from virtually anywhere on the course, but most often for shorter-distance shots approaching the green, or to get the ball out of tricky lies such as sand traps. The third class is the [[putter]], which evolved from the irons to create a low-lofted, balanced club designed to roll the ball along the green and into the hole. Putters are virtually always used on the green or in the surrounding rough/fringe. A fourth class, called [[hybrid (golf)|hybrids]], evolved as a cross between woods and irons, and are typically seen replacing the low-lofted irons with a club that provides similar distance, but a higher launch angle and a more forgiving nature.

A maximum of 14 clubs is allowed in a player's bag at one time during a stipulated round. The choice of clubs is at the golfer's discretion, although every club must be constructed in accordance with parameters outlined in the rules. (Clubs that meet these parameters are usually called &quot;conforming&quot;.) Violation of these rules can result in disqualification.

The exact shot hit at any given time on a golf course, and which club is used to accomplish the shot, are always completely at the discretion of the golfer; in other words, there is no restriction whatsoever on which club a golfer may or may not use at any time for any shot.

[[Golf ball]]s are spherical, usually white (although other colours are allowed), and minutely pock-marked by dimples that decrease aerodynamic drag by increasing air turbulence around the ball in motion, which delays &quot;boundary layer&quot; separation and reduces the drag-inducing &quot;wake&quot; behind the ball,
thereby allowing the ball to fly farther.&lt;ref name=&quot;ClubHist&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.home.aone.net.au/~byzantium/golf/ghistory.html|title=History of the Golf Club |accessdate=5 November 2007 |author=Nicholls, David|date=February 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; The combination of a soft &quot;boundary layer&quot; and a hard &quot;core&quot; enables both distance and spin.

A [[Tee#Golf tee|tee]] is allowed only for the first stroke on each hole, unless the player must hit a provisional tee shot or replay his or her first shot from the tee.

Many golfers wear [[Golf equipment#Shoes|golf shoes]] with metal or plastic spikes designed to increase traction, thus allowing for longer and more accurate shots.

A [[golf bag]] is used to transport golf clubs and the player's other or personal equipment. Golf bags have several pockets designed for carrying equipment and supplies such as tees, balls, and gloves. Golf bags can be carried, pulled on a trolley or harnessed to a motorized [[golf cart]] during play. Golf bags usually have both a hand strap and shoulder strap for carrying, others may be carried over both shoulders like a backpack, and often bags have retractable legs that allow the bag to stand upright when at rest.

==Stroke mechanics==
[[File:Lady golfer.jpg|thumb|right|A golfer takes an approach shot on the fairway.]]
{{Main|Golf stroke mechanics}}

The golf swing is outwardly similar to many other motions involving swinging a tool or playing implement, such as an axe or a baseball bat. However, unlike many of these motions, the result of the swing is highly dependent on several sub-motions being properly aligned and timed. These ensure that the club travels up to the ball in line with the desired path; that the clubface is in line with the swing path; and that the ball hits the centre or &quot;sweet spot&quot; of the clubface. The ability to do this consistently, across a complete set of clubs with a wide range of shaft lengths and clubface areas, is a key skill for any golfer, and takes a significant effort to achieve.

===Stance===
Stance refers to how the golfer positions themselves in order to play a stroke; it is fundamentally important in being able to play a stroke effectively. The stance adopted is determined by what stroke is being played. All stances involve a slight crouch. This allows for a more efficient striking posture whilst also [[Isometric exercise#Isometric presses as preparation for explosive power movements|isometrically preloading]] the muscles of the legs and core; this allows the stroke to be played more dynamically and with a greater level of overall control. When adopting their stance golfers start with the non-dominant side of the body facing the target (for a right-hander, the target is to their left). Setting the stance in regard to the position of the ball, and placing the clubhead behind the ball, is known as being at address; when in this position the player's body and the centerline of the club face are positioned parallel to the desired line of travel, with the feet either perpendicular to that line or slightly splayed outward. The feet are commonly shoulder-width apart for middle irons and putters, narrower for short irons and wider for long irons and woods. The ball is typically positioned more to the &quot;front&quot; of the player's stance (closer to the leading foot) for lower-lofted clubs, with the usual ball position for a drive being just behind the arch of the leading foot. The ball is placed further &quot;back&quot; in the player's stance (toward the trailing foot) as the loft of the club to be used increases. Most iron shots and putts are made with the ball roughly centered in the stance, while a few mid- and short-iron shots are made with the ball slightly behind the centre of the stance to ensure consistent contact between the ball and clubface, so the ball is on its way before the club continues down into the turf.

===Strokes===
The golfer chooses a golf club, grip, and stroke appropriate to the distance:
* The &quot;drive&quot; or &quot;full swing&quot; is used on the teeing ground and fairway, typically with a wood or long iron, to produce the maximum distance capable with the club. In the extreme, the windup can end with the shaft of the club parallel to the ground above the player's shoulders.
* The &quot;approach&quot; or &quot;3/4 swing&quot; is used in medium- and long-distance situations where an exact distance and good accuracy is preferable to maximum possible distance, such as to place the ball on the green or &quot;lay up&quot; in front of a hazard. The windup or &quot;backswing&quot; of such a shot typically ends up with the shaft of the club pointing straight upwards or slightly towards the player.
* The &quot;chip&quot; or &quot;half-swing&quot; is used for relatively short-distance shots near the green, with high-lofted irons and wedges. The goal of the chip is to land the ball safely on the green, allowing it to roll out towards the hole. It can also be used from other places to accurately position the ball into a more advantageous lie. The backswing typically ends with the head of the club between hip and head height.
* The &quot;putt&quot; is used in short-distance shots on or near the green, typically made with the eponymous &quot;putter&quot;, although similar strokes can be made with medium to high-numbered irons to carry a short distance in the air and then roll (a &quot;bump and run&quot;). The backswing and follow-through of the putt are both abbreviated compared to other strokes, with the head of the club rarely rising above the knee. The goal of the putt is usually to put the ball in the hole, although a long-distance putt may be called a &quot;lag&quot; and is made with the primary intention of simply closing distance to the hole or otherwise placing the ball advantageously.

Having chosen a club and stroke to produce the desired distance, the player addresses the ball by taking their stance to the side of it and (except when the ball lies in a hazard) grounding the club behind the ball. The golfer then takes their backswing, rotating the club, their arms and their upper body away from the ball, and then begins their swing, bringing the clubhead back down and around to hit the ball. A proper golf swing is a complex combination of motions, and slight variations in posture or positioning can make a great deal of difference in how well the ball is hit and how straight it travels. The general goal of a player making a full swing is to propel the clubhead as fast as possible while maintaining a single &quot;plane&quot; of motion of the club and clubhead, to send the clubhead into the ball along the desired path of travel and with the clubhead also pointing that direction.

Accuracy and consistency are typically stressed over pure distance. A player with a straight drive that travels only {{convert|220|yd}} will nevertheless be able to accurately place the ball into a favourable lie on the fairway, and can make up for the lesser distance of any given club by simply using &quot;more club&quot; (a lower loft) on their tee shot or on subsequent fairway and approach shots. However, a golfer with a drive that may go {{convert|280|yd}} but often doesn't fly straight will be less able to position their ball advantageously; the ball may &quot;hook&quot;, &quot;pull&quot;, &quot;draw&quot;, &quot;fade&quot;, &quot;push&quot; or &quot;slice&quot; off the intended line and land out of bounds or in the rough or hazards, and thus the player will require many more strokes to hole out.

===Musculature===

A golf stroke uses the muscles of the [[Core (anatomy)|core]] (especially [[erector spinae muscles]] and [[latissimus dorsi muscle]] when turning), [[hamstring]], [[shoulder]], and [[wrist]]. Stronger muscles in the wrist can prevent them from being twisted during swings, whilst stronger shoulders increase the turning force. Weak wrists can also transmit the force to elbows and even neck and lead to injury. (When a muscle contracts, it pulls equally from both ends and, to have movement at only one end of the muscle, other muscles must come into play to stabilize the bone to which the other end of the muscle is attached.) Golf is a unilateral exercise that can break body balances, requiring exercises to keep the balance in muscles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Jack Welch's 6 Ways Exercise | author = [[John Sitaras]] | publisher = [[Golf Digest]] (Korean edition) | date = 14 November 2013 | url = http://www.golfdigest.co.kr/gd/Magazine/textyle/749478 | accessdate = 7 December 2013 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20141210203559/http://www.golfdigest.co.kr/gd/Magazine/textyle/749478 | archive-date = 10 December 2014 | url-status = dead | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = George Soros' Exercise| author= [[John Sitaras]]| publisher = [[Golf Digest]] (Korean edition) | date = 21 November 2013 | url = https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OWaDpV0VdPg | accessdate = 7 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Types of putting===
Putting is considered to be the most important component of the game of golf. As the game of golf has evolved, there have been many different putting techniques and grips that have been devised to give golfers the best chance to make putts. When the game originated, golfers would putt with their dominate hand on the bottom of the grip and their weak hand on top of the grip. This grip and putting style is known as &quot;conventional&quot;. There are many variations of conventional including overlap, where the golfer overlaps the off hand index finger onto off the dominant pinky; interlock, where the offhand index finger interlocks with the dominant pinky and ring finger; double or triple overlap and so on.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Dave Pelz: Your best way to putt|url = http://www.golf.com/instruction/dave-pelz-your-best-way-putt|website = Golf.com|accessdate = 23 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recently, &quot;cross handed&quot; putting has become a popular trend amongst professional golfers and amateurs. Cross handed putting is the idea that the dominant hand is on top of the grip where the weak hand is on the bottom. This grip restricts the motion in your dominant hand and eliminates the possibility of wrist breakdowns through the putting stroke.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Cross Handed Putting Grip, How It Can Improve Your Stroke|url = http://golf-info-guide.com/putters/how-a-cross-handed-grip-can-improve-your-putting/|website = golf-info-guide.com|accessdate = 20 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other notable putting styles include &quot;the claw&quot;, a style that has the grip directly in between the thumb and index finger of the dominant hand while the palm faces the target.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = 4. Controlling the Yips - PGA Digital Golf Academy|url = http://golfacademy.pga.com/video/002932_4-controlling-the-yips/|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140602162049/http://golfacademy.pga.com/video/002932_4-controlling-the-yips/|url-status = dead|archive-date = 2 June 2014|website = golfacademy.pga.com|accessdate = 23 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The weak hand placed normally on the putter. Anchored putting, a style that requires a longer putter shaft that can be anchored into the player's stomach or below the chin; the idea is to stabilize one end of the putter thus creating a more consistent pendulum stroke. This style has been banned on professional circuits since 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.usga.org/content/dam/usga/images/rules/anchoring/082715USGA-UNDERSTANDINGANCHOREDSTROKES-Finaluse.pdf|title = Anchored putting|date = |accessdate = |website = |publisher = United States Golf Association|last = USGA|first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Scoring and handicapping==

===Par===
{{Main|Par (score)}}[[File:The Phoenician-Canyon.jpg|thumb|A par-3 hole in Phoenician Golf Club, [[Scottsdale, Arizona|Scottsdale]], [[Arizona]]]]
[[File:Grand Cypress New Course 15th hole.jpg|thumb|A marker stone indicating that this hole is a par-5 hole]]
A hole is classified by its par, which gives an indication of the number of strokes a skilled golfer may be expected to need to complete play of the hole.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encarta&quot;/&gt; The primary factor for classifying the par of a relatively straight, hazard-free hole is the distance from the tee to the green, and calculates the number of strokes a skilled golfer is expected to require to reach the [[Putting green|green]] with an additional allowance of 2 putts. As such, the minimum par of any hole is 3; one stroke for the tee shot and two putts. Par 3, 4 and 5 holes are commonplace on golf courses; far more rarely, courses may feature par-6 and even par-7 holes.

For men, a typical par-3 hole is less than {{convert|250|yd|m}} in length, with a par-4 hole ranging between {{convert|251|-|450|yd|m}}, and a par-5 hole being longer than {{convert|450|yd|m}}; for women these boundaries are lower, and for professionals they are much increased. The rare par-6s can stretch well over {{convert|650|yd}}. These distances are based on the typical scratch golfer's drive distance of between {{convert|240|and|280|yd}}. Although length is the primary factor in calculating par, other factors are taken into account; however the number of strokes a scratch golfer should take to make the green remains foremost. Factors affecting the calculation include altitude, gradient of the land from the tee to green, and forced &quot;[[Glossary of golf#Lay-up|lay-ups]]&quot; due to dog-legs (sharp bends) or obstacles (e.g. bunkers, water hazards).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://golf.about.com/od/handicaps/f/faq_parlengths.htm |title=Golf FAQ – What are the Yardage Guidelines for Par-3s, Par-4s and Par-5s? |publisher=About.com |author=Kelley, Brent |accessdate=8 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Getting the ball onto the green in two strokes less than par, and hence meeting the par calculation criteria, is called making &quot;green in regulation&quot; or GIR.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://golf.about.com/cs/golfterms/g/bldef_par.htm |title=Definition of Par |publisher=[[About.com]] |author=Kelley, Brent |accessdate=8 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Missing a GIR does not necessarily mean a golfer will not make par, but it does make doing so more difficult as it reduces the number of putts available; conversely, making a GIR does not guarantee a par, as the player might require three or more putts to &quot;hole out&quot;. Professional golfers typically make between 60% and 70% of greens in regulation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.pgatour.com/stats/stat.103.html|title=Stat – Greens in Regulation Percentage|newspaper=PGATour|access-date=20 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eighteen-hole courses typically total to an overall par score of 70 to 72 for a complete round; with most holes having a par of 4, and a smaller number of par-3 and par-5 holes. Additionally, courses may be classified according to their play difficulty, which may be used to calculate a golfer's [[Handicap (golf)|handicap]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://golf.about.com/cs/rulesofgolf/a/hfaq_sloperate.htm |title=Golf FAQ: What is Slope Rating? |author=Kelley, Brent |publisher=About.com |accessdate=8 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The two primary difficulty ratings in the U.S. are the Course Rating, which is the expected score for a zero-handicap &quot;scratch golfer&quot;, and the Slope Rating, which is a measure of how much worse a &quot;bogey golfer&quot; (handicap around 20) would be expected to play than a &quot;scratch golfer&quot; relative to their handicap.

====Scoring====
The goal is to play as few strokes per round as possible. A golfer's number of strokes in a hole, course, or tournament is compared to its respective par score, and is then reported either as the number that the golfer was &quot;under-&quot; or &quot;over-par&quot;, or if it was &quot;equal to par&quot;. A [[hole in one]] (or an &quot;ace&quot;) occurs when a golfer sinks their ball into the cup with their first stroke from the tee. Common scores for a hole also have specific terms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encarta&quot;/&gt;

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!  style=&quot;background:#dfdfdf; text-align:center;&quot;|Numeric term
!  style=&quot;background:#dfdfdf; text-align:center;&quot;|Name
!  style=&quot;background:#dfdfdf; text-align:center;&quot;|Definition
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|  style=&quot;background:#efefef; &quot;|−4
|| Condor
|| four strokes under par
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|  style=&quot;background:#efefef; &quot;|−3
|| Albatross (Double Eagle)
|| three strokes under par
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|  style=&quot;background:#efefef; &quot;|−2
|| Eagle
|| two strokes under par
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|  style=&quot;background:#efefef; &quot;|−1
|| Birdie
|| one stroke under par
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|  style=&quot;background:#efefef; &quot;|E
|| [[Par (score)|Par]]
|| equal to par
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|  style=&quot;background:#efefef; &quot;|+1
|| Bogey
|| one stroke over par
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|  style=&quot;background:#efefef; &quot;|+2
|| Double bogey
|| two strokes over par
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|  style=&quot;background:#efefef; &quot;|+3
|| Triple bogey
|| three strokes over par
|}

In a typical professional tournament or among &quot;scratch&quot; amateur players, &quot;birdie-bogey&quot; play is common; a player will &quot;lose&quot; a stroke by bogeying a hole, then &quot;gain&quot; one by scoring a birdie. Eagles are uncommon but not rare; however, only [[List of albatrosses in important tournaments#Major championships|18 players have scored an albatross]] in a men's major championship. One of the rarest feats in golf is the condor, which has never occurred in a professional tournament. Only four condors have been verified to have ever occurred: all of them involved hitting a hole in one on a par-5 hole, although none of the courses involved were professionally accredited.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://golftoday.co.uk/golf-a-to-z-the-condor/|title=Golf A to Z - The 'Condor'|date=2018-07-20|website=Golf Today|language=en-US|access-date=2019-12-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Basic forms of golf===
There are two basic forms of golf play, match play and stroke play. Stroke play is more popular.

====Match play====
Two players (or two teams) play each hole as a separate contest against each other in what is called [[match play]]. The party with the lower score wins that hole, or if the scores of both players or teams are equal the hole is &quot;halved&quot; (or tied). The game is won by the party that wins more holes than the other. In the case that one team or player has taken a lead that cannot be overcome in the number of holes remaining to be played, the match is deemed to be won by the party in the lead, and the remainder of the holes are not played. For example, if one party already has a lead of six holes, and only five holes remain to be played on the course, the match is over and the winning party is deemed to have won &quot;6 &amp; 5&quot;. At any given point, if the lead is equal to the number of holes remaining, the party leading the match is said to be &quot;dormie&quot;, and the match is continued until the party increases the lead by one hole or ties any of the remaining holes, thereby winning the match, or until the match ends in a tie with the lead player's opponent winning all remaining holes. When the game is tied after the predetermined number of holes have been played, it may be continued until one side takes a one-hole lead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encarta&quot;/&gt;

====Stroke play====
The score achieved for each and every hole of the round or tournament is added to produce the total score, and the player with the lowest score wins in [[stroke play]]. Stroke play is the game most commonly played by professional golfers. If there is a tie after the regulation number of holes in a professional tournament, a playoff takes place between all tied players. Playoffs either are sudden death or employ a pre-determined number of holes, anywhere from three to a full 18. In sudden death, a player who scores lower on a hole than all of his opponents wins the match. If at least two players remain tied after such a playoff using a pre-determined number of holes, then play continues in sudden death format, where the first player to win a hole wins the tournament.

===Other formats of play===
{{main|Variations of golf}}
There are many variations in scoring and playing formats in the game of golf, some officially defined in the Rules of Golf. Variations include the popular Stableford scoring system, and various team formats. Some common and popular examples are listed below.

There are also variations on the usual starting procedure where everyone begins from the first tee and plays all holes in order, though to the eighteenth. In large field tournaments, especially on professional tours, a two tee start is commonplace, where the field will be split between starting on the first tee and the tenth tee (sometimes the eighth or eleventh depending on proximity to the clubhouse). [[Shotgun start]]s are mainly used for amateur tournament or society play. In this variant, each of the groups playing starts their game on a different hole, allowing for all players to start and end their round at roughly the same time. For example a group starting on hole 5 will play through to the 18th hole and continue with hole 1, ending their round on hole 4.

====Bogey or Par competition====
{{main|Par (golf scoring format)}}
A bogey or par competition is a scoring format sometimes seen in informal tournaments. Its scoring is similar to match play, except each player compares their hole score to the hole's par rating instead of the score of another player. The player &quot;wins&quot; the hole if they score a birdie or better, they &quot;lose&quot; the hole if they score a bogey or worse, and they &quot;halve&quot; the hole by scoring par. By recording only this simple win-loss-halve score on the sheet, a player can shrug off a very poorly-played hole with a simple &quot;-&quot; mark and move on. As used in competitions, the player or pair with the best win-loss &quot;differential&quot; wins the competition.

====Stableford====
{{main|Stableford}}
The [[Stableford]] system is a simplification of stroke play that awards players points based on their score relative to the hole's par; the score for a hole is calculated by taking the par score, adding 2, then subtracting the player's hole score, making the result zero if negative. Alternately stated, a double bogey or worse is zero points, a bogey is worth one point, par is two, a birdie three, an eagle four, and so on. The advantages of this system over stroke play are a more natural &quot;higher is better&quot; scoring, the ability to compare Stableford scores between plays on courses with different total par scores (scoring an &quot;even&quot; in stroke play will always give a Stableford score of 36), discouraging the tendency to abandon the entire game after playing a particularly bad hole (a novice playing by strict rules may score as high as an 8 or 10 on a single difficult hole; their Stableford score for the hole would be zero, which puts them only two points behind par no matter how badly they played), and the ability to simply pick up one's ball once it is impossible to score any points for the hole, which speeds play.

The USGA and R&amp;A sanction a &quot;Modified Stableford&quot; system for scratch players, which makes par worth zero, a birdie worth 2, eagle 5 and double-eagle 8, while a bogey is a penalty of −1 and a double-bogey or worse −3. As with the original system, the highest score wins the game, and terrible scores on one or two holes won't wreck an entire game, but this system rewards &quot;bogey-birdie&quot; play more than the original, encouraging golfers to try to make the riskier birdie putt or eagle chipshot instead of simply parring each hole.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encarta&quot;/&gt;

====Basic pairs formats====
[[File:Junín Golf Club 20101031 001.jpg|thumb|right|Junín Golf Club, in [[Junín, Buenos Aires|Junín]], Argentina]]
* [[Foursomes]] (also known as Alternate Shot): defined in Rule 22, this is played in pairs, in which each team has only one ball and players alternate playing it. For example, if players &quot;A&quot; and &quot;B&quot; form a team, &quot;A&quot; tees off on the first hole, &quot;B&quot; will play the second shot, &quot;A&quot; the third, and so on until the hole is finished. On the second hole, &quot;B&quot; will tee off (regardless who played the last putt on the first hole), then &quot;A&quot; plays the second shot, and so on. Foursomes can be played as match play or stroke play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://golf.about.com/cs/golfterms/g/bldef_foursomes.htm |title=Definition of Foursomes |publisher=About.com |author=Kelley, Brent |accessdate=25 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Greensomes (also known as Scotch Foursomes): also called modified alternate shot, this is played in pairs; both players tee off, and then pick the best shot. The player who did not shoot the best first shot plays the second shot. The play then alternates as in a foursome.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://golf.about.com/cs/golfterms/g/bldef_greensome.htm |title=Definition of Greensome |publisher=About.com |author=Kelley, Brent |accessdate=25 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; A variant of greensome is sometimes played where the opposing team chooses which of their opponent's tee shots the opponents should use.
* [[Four-ball golf|Four-ball]]: defined in Rules 23, this is also played in pairs, but every each plays their own ball and for each team, the lower score on each hole counts. Four-ball can be played as match play or stroke play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://golf.about.com/cs/golfterms/g/bldef_fourball.htm |title=Definition of Fourball |publisher=About.com |author=Kelley, Brent |accessdate=25 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Team formats====
* Scramble: also known as ambrose or best-shot; each player in a team tees off on each hole, and the players decide which shot was best. Every player then plays their second shot from within a clublength of where the best shot has come to rest (and no closer to the hole), and the procedure is repeated until the hole is finished. This system is very common at informal tournaments such as for charity, as it speeds play (due to the reduced number of shots taken from bad lies), allows teams of varying sizes, and allows players of widely varying skill levels to participate without profoundly affecting team score.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://golf.about.com/cs/golfterms/g/bldef_scramble.htm |title=Definition of Scramble |publisher=About.com |author=Kelley, Brent |accessdate=25 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Best-ball: like four-ball, each player plays the hole as normal, but the lowest score of all the players on the team counts as the team's score for the hole.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://golf.about.com/cs/golfterms/g/bldef_betterbal.htm |title=Better Ball |publisher=About.com |author=Kelley, Brent |accessdate=17 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are many variations on this format, which count a different number of scores on each hole.

===Handicap systems===
{{Main|Handicap (golf)}}
A handicap is a numerical measure of a golfer's potential scoring ability over 18 holes. It is used to enable players of widely varying abilities to compete against one another. Better players are those with the lowest handicaps, and someone with a handicap of 0 or less is often referred to as a ''scratch golfer''. Handicap systems vary throughout the world and use different methods to assess courses and calculate handicaps. In order to address difficulties in translating between these systems the USGA and The R&amp;A, working with the various existing handicapping authorities, devised a new ''World Handicap System'' which is set to be introduced globally starting in 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.golfdigest.com/story/usga-randa-unveil-new-world-handicap-system-set-to-debut-in-2020 |title=USGA/R&amp;A unveil new World Handicap System set to debut in 2020 |website=Golf Digest |first=Ryan |last=Herrington |date=February 20, 2018 |accessdate=December 4, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Golf courses are assessed and rated according to the average good score of a scratch golfer, taking into account a multitude of factors affecting play, such as length, obstacles, undulations, etc. A player's handicap gives an indication of the number of strokes above this [[course rating]] that the player will make over the course of an &quot;average best&quot; round of golf, i.e. scoring near their potential, above average.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.nationalclubgolfer.com/news/usga-course-rating-system-work/ |title=How does the USGA course rating system work? |website=National Club Golfer |first=Steve |last=Carroll |date=March 7, 2018 |accessdate=December 6, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lower handicap players are generally the most consistent, so can be expected to play to this standard or better more often than higher handicappers. Some handicap systems also account for differences in scoring difficulty between low and high handicap golfer. They do this by means of assessing and rating courses according to the average good score of a &quot;bogey golfer&quot;, a player with a handicap of around 20. This is used with the course rating to calculate a [[slope rating]], which is used to adjust golfer's handicap to produce a ''playing handicap'' for the course and set of tees being used.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.popeofslope.com/courserating/system.html |title=The Slope System |first=Tom |last=Dellner |website=The Pope of Slope |accessdate=December 15, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Handicap systems have potential for abuse by players who may intentionally play badly to increase their handicap ([[Glossary of cue sports terms#sandbag|sandbagging]]) before playing to their potential at an important event with a valuable prize. For this reason, handicaps are not used in professional golf, but they can still be calculated and used along with other criteria to determine the relative strengths of various professional players. Touring professionals, being the best of the best, have negative handicaps; they can be expected, more often than not, to score lower than the Course Rating on any course.

==Popularity==
[[File:Golfveld.jpg|thumb|right|Part of a golf course in western India]]
[[File:Golf course, Italy - 20070620.jpg|thumb|An aerial view of a golf course in Italy]]
In 2005 ''[[Golf Digest]]'' calculated that the countries with most golf courses per capita, in order, were: Scotland, New Zealand, Australia, Ireland, Canada, Wales, United States, Sweden, and England (countries with fewer than 500,000 people were excluded).

The number of courses in other territories has increased, an example of this being the expansion of [[golf in China]]. The first golf course in China opened in 1984, but by the end of 2009 there were roughly 600 in the country. For much of the 21st century, development of new golf courses in China has been officially banned (with the exception of the island province of [[Hainan]]), but the number of courses had nonetheless tripled from 2004 to 2009; the &quot;ban&quot; has been evaded with the government's tacit approval simply by not mentioning golf in any development plans.&lt;ref name=&quot;China golf&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/golf/columns/story?id=4618648 |title=Olympics makes China major player |first=Dan |last=Washburn |publisher=ESPN  |date=6 November 2009 |accessdate=7 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, the number of people who play golf twenty-five times or more per year decreased from 6.9&amp;nbsp;million in 2000 to 4.6&amp;nbsp;million in 2005,&lt;ref name=NYT/&gt; according to the [[National Golf Foundation]]. The NGF reported that the number who played golf at all decreased from 30 to 26 million over the same period.&lt;ref name=NYT&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/21/nyregion/21golf.html?em&amp;ex=1203829200&amp;en=9c9070c4064e72a7&amp;ei=5087%0A |title=More Americans Are Giving up Golf|author=Paul Vitello|work=The New York Times|date=21 February 2008 |publisher=[[The New York Times Company]]|accessdate=7 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 1971, [[astronaut]] [[Alan Shepard]] became the first person to golf anywhere other than [[Earth]]. He smuggled a golf club and two golf balls on board [[Apollo 14]] with the intent to golf on the [[Moon]]. He attempted two drives. He shanked the first attempt, but it is estimated his second went more than {{convert|200|yd|m}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pga.com/news/golf-buzz/feb-6-1971-alan-shepard-plays-golf-moon|title=Feb. 6, 1971: Alan Shepard plays golf on the moon|website=PGA.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Golf courses worldwide===
Number of golf courses by country in 2015. Below are the top 18 countries that have the most golf courses.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.scottishgolfhistory.org/news/how-many-golf-holes-are-there-in-the-world/|title=How many Golf Holes are there in the World? Answer 576,534 - Scottish Golf History|website=www.scottishgolfhistory.org|access-date=22 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|'''Country'''
|'''Number of  courses'''
|'''%'''
|-
|USA
|15,372
|45%
|-
|Japan
|2,383
|7%
|-
|Canada
|2,363
|7%
|-
|England
|2,084
|6%
|-
|Australia
|1,628
|5%
|-
|Germany
|747
|2%
|-
|France
|648
|2%
|-
|Scotland
|552
|2%
|-
|South Africa
|512
|2%
|-
|Sweden
|491
|1%
|-
|China
|473
|1%
|-
|Ireland
|472
|1%
|-
|South Korea
|447
|1%
|-
|Spain
|437
|1%
|-
|New Zealand
|418
|1%
|-
|Argentina
|319
|1%
|-
|Italy
|285
|1%
|-
|India
|270
|1%
|-
|Rest of the world
|4,110
|12%
|-
|Total
|34,011
|
|}

==Professional golf==
{{Main|Professional golfer}}
The majority of [[professional golfer]]s work as club or teaching professionals (&quot;pros&quot;), and only compete in local competitions. A small elite of professional golfers are &quot;tournament pros&quot; who compete full-time on international &quot;tours&quot;. Many club and teaching professionals working in the golf industry start as [[caddies]] or with a general interest in the game, finding employment at [[golf course]]s and eventually moving on to certifications in their chosen profession. These programs include independent institutions and universities, and those that eventually lead to a Class A golf professional certification. Touring professionals typically start as amateur players, who attain their &quot;pro&quot; status after success in major tournaments that win them either prize money and/or notice from corporate sponsors. [[Jack Nicklaus]], for example, gained widespread notice by finishing second in the 1960 [[U.S. Open (golf)|U.S. Open]] to champion [[Arnold Palmer]], with a 72-hole score of 282 (the best score to date in that tournament by an amateur). He played one more amateur year in 1961, winning that year's [[United States Amateur Championship (golf)|U.S. Amateur Championship]], before turning pro in 1962.

===Instruction===
[[File:Indoor Putting Green.JPG|thumb|right|upright|Indoor [[Golf course#Putting green|putting green]] for practice and instruction]]
{{Main|Golf instruction}}

Golf instruction involves the teaching and learning of the game of golf. Proficiency in teaching golf instruction requires not only technical and physical ability but also knowledge of the rules and etiquette of the game. In some countries, golf instruction is best performed by teachers certified by the [[Professional Golfers Association]]. Some top instructors who work with professional golfers have become quite well known in their own right. Professional golf instructors can use physical conditioning, mental visualization, classroom sessions, club fitting, driving range instruction, on-course play under real conditions, and review of videotaped swings in slow motion to teach golf to prepare the golfer for the course.

===Golf tours===
{{Main|Professional golf tours}}
There are at least twenty professional golf tours, each run by a [[Professional Golfers Association|PGA]] or an independent tour organization, which is responsible for arranging events, finding sponsors, and regulating the tour. Typically a tour has &quot;members&quot; who are entitled to compete in most of its events, and also invites non-members to compete in some of them. Gaining membership of an elite tour is highly competitive, and most professional golfers never achieve it.

[[File:All Black.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Gary Player]] is widely regarded as one of the greatest players in the history of golf.]]
Perhaps the most widely known tour is the [[PGA Tour]], which tends to attract the strongest fields, outside the four Majors and the four World Golf Championships events. This is due mostly to the fact that most PGA Tour events have a first prize of at least 800,000 [[USD]]. The [[PGA European Tour|European Tour]], which attracts a substantial number of top golfers from outside North America, ranks second to the PGA Tour in worldwide prestige. Some top professionals from outside North America play enough tournaments to maintain membership on both the PGA Tour and European Tour. Since 2010, both tours' money titles have been claimed by the same individual three times, with [[Luke Donald]] doing so in 2011 and [[Rory McIlroy]] in 2012 and 2014. In 2013, [[Henrik Stenson]] won the [[FedEx Cup]] points race on the PGA Tour and the European Tour money title, but did not top the PGA Tour money list (that honour going to [[Tiger Woods]]).

The other leading men's tours include the [[Japan Golf Tour]], the [[Asian Tour]] (Asia outside Japan), the [[PGA Tour of Australasia]], and the [[Sunshine Tour]] (for southern Africa, primarily South Africa). The Japan, Australasian, Sunshine, PGA, and European Tours are the charter members of the trade body of the world's main tours, the International Federation of PGA Tours, founded in 1996. The Asian Tour became a full member in 1999. The [[PGA Tour Canada|Canadian Tour]] became an associate member of the Federation in 2000, and the [[Tour de las Américas]] (Latin America) became an associate member of the Federation in 2007. The Federation underwent a major expansion in 2009 that saw eleven new tours become full members&amp;nbsp;– the Canadian Tour, Tour de las Américas, China Golf Association, the Korea Professional Golfers' Association, [[Professional Golf Tour of India]], and the operators of all six major women's tours worldwide. The [[OneAsia Tour]], founded in 2009, is not a member of the Federation, but was founded as a joint venture of the Australasia, China, Japan, and Korean tours. In 2011, the Tour de las Américas was effectively taken over by the PGA Tour, and in 2012 was folded into the new [[PGA Tour Latinoamérica]]. Also in 2012, the Canadian Tour was renamed [[PGA Tour Canada]] after it agreed to be taken over by the PGA Tour. All men's tours that are Federation members, except the India tour, offer points in the [[Official World Golf Ranking]] (OWGR) to players who place sufficiently high in their events. The OneAsia Tour also offers ranking points.

Golf is unique in having lucrative competition for older players. There are several senior tours for men aged fifty and over, arguably the best known of which is the U.S.-based [[PGA Tour Champions]].

There are six principal tours for women, each based in a different country or continent. The most prestigious of these is the United States-based [[LPGA|LPGA Tour]]. All of the principal tours offer points in the [[Women's World Golf Rankings]] for high finishers in their events.

All of the leading professional tours for under-50 players have an official developmental tour, in which the leading players at the end of the season will earn a tour card on the main tour for the following season. Examples include the [[Web.com Tour]], which feeds to the PGA Tour, and the [[Challenge Tour]], which is the developmental tour of the European Tour. The Web.com and Challenge Tours also offer OWGR points.

===Men's major championships===
[[File:Lee Westwood bunker.jpg|thumb|right|[[Lee Westwood]] pictured making a bunker shot at the [[2008 Open Championship|2008 Open]]]]
{{Main|Men's major golf championships}}

The major championships are the four most prestigious men's tournaments of the year. In chronological order they are: [[Masters Tournament|The Masters]], the [[U.S. Open (golf)|U.S. Open]], [[The Open Championship]] (referred to in North America as the British Open) and the [[PGA Championship]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.supersport.com/golf/golf-globe/future-venues-dates-golf-majors|title=Future Men`s Major Championships - dates and venues - SuperSport - Golf|website=www.supersport.com|access-date=20 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The fields for these events include the top several dozen golfers from all over the world. The Masters has been played at [[Augusta National Golf Club]] in Augusta, Georgia, since its inception in 1934. It is the only major championship that is played at the same course each year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sporting-world.co.uk/masters-golf-tournament.php |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060917081123/http://www.sporting-world.co.uk/masters-golf-tournament.php |url-status=dead |archive-date=17 September 2006 |title=Golf Majors: The Masters Golf Tournament |publisher=Sporting-World.co.uk |accessdate=17 December 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. Open and PGA Championship are played at courses around the United States, while the Open Championship is played at courses around the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.theopen.com/Heritage/OpenVenues|title=The Open - Open Venues|website=www.theopen.com|access-date=20 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to the advent of the PGA Championship and The Masters, the four Majors were the U.S. Open, the U.S. Amateur, the Open Championship, and the [[The Amateur Championship|British Amateur]].

===Women's major championships===
[[File:2007 LPGA Championship - Lorena Ochoa (1).jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Lorena Ochoa]], a retired number one female golfer, pictured here in 2007]]
{{Main|Women's major golf championships}}
Women's golf does not have a globally agreed set of majors. The list of majors recognised by the dominant women's tour, the [[LPGA|LPGA Tour]] in the U.S., has changed several times over the years, with the most recent changes occurring in 2001 and 2013. Like the PGA Tour, the (U.S.) LPGA&lt;ref&gt;There are several bodies known as the &quot;LPGA&quot;, each based in a different country or continent. The U.S. LPGA is the only one without a geographic identifier in its name, as it was the first to be founded. Typically, if the term &quot;LPGA&quot; is used without an identifier, it refers to the U.S. body.&lt;/ref&gt; tour long had four majors, but now has five: the [[ANA Inspiration]] (previously known by several other names, most recently the Kraft Nabisco Championship), the [[Women's PGA Championship]] (previously known as the LPGA Championship),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.pga.com/pga-america/pga-feature/pga-america-lpga-kpmg-join-forces-kpmg-womens-pga-championship |publisher=PGA of America |title=PGA of America, LPGA, KPMG join forces for KPMG Women's PGA Championship |date=29 May 2014 |accessdate=18 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[United States Women's Open Championship (golf)|U.S. Women's Open]], the [[Women's British Open]] (which replaced the [[Canadian Women's Open|du Maurier Classic]] as a major in 2001) and [[The Evian Championship]] (added as the fifth major in 2013). Only the last two are also recognised as majors by the [[Ladies European Tour]]. However, the significance of this is limited, as the LPGA is far more dominant in women's golf than the PGA Tour is in mainstream men's golf. For example, the [[BBC]] has been known to use the U.S. definition of &quot;women's majors&quot; without qualifying it. Also, the [[Ladies' Golf Union]], the governing body for women's golf in Great Britain and Ireland, stated on its official website that the Women's British Open was &quot;the only Women's Major to be played outside the U.S.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lgu.org/championships/women__s_british_open/ |title=Women's British Open breaks new ground at St Andrews |publisher=Ladies' Golf Union |accessdate=12 August 2007 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070815190852/http://www.lgu.org/championships/women__s_british_open/ |archivedate=15 August 2007  }}&lt;/ref&gt; (this was before the elevation of The Evian Championship to major status). For many years, the Ladies European Tour tacitly acknowledged the dominance of the LPGA Tour by not scheduling any of its own events to conflict with the three LPGA majors played in the U.S., but that changed beginning in 2008, when the LET scheduled an event opposite the LPGA Championship. The second-richest women's tour, the [[LPGA of Japan Tour]], does not recognise any of the U.S. LPGA or European majors as it has its own set of majors (historically three, since 2008 four). However, these events attract little notice outside Japan.

===Senior major championships ===
{{Main|Senior major golf championships}}
Senior (aged fifty and over) men's golf does not have a globally agreed set of majors. The list of senior majors on the U.S.-based [[PGA Tour Champions]] has changed over the years, but always by expansion. PGA Tour Champions now recognises five majors: the [[Senior PGA Championship]], [[The Tradition]], the [[Senior Players Championship]], the [[United States Senior Open]], and [[Senior Open Championship|The Senior (British) Open Championship]].

Of the five events, the Senior PGA is by far the oldest, having been founded in 1937. The other events all date from the 1980s, when senior golf became a commercial success as the first golf stars of the television era, such as [[Arnold Palmer]] and [[Gary Player]], reached the relevant age. The Senior Open Championship was not recognised as a major by PGA Tour Champions until 2003. The [[European Senior Tour]] recognises only the Senior PGA and the two Senior Opens as majors. However, PGA Tour Champions is arguably more dominant in global senior golf than the U.S. LPGA is in global women's golf.

===Olympic Games===
{{main|Golf at the 2016 Summer Olympics}}
After a 112-year absence from the Olympic Games, golf returned for the [[Golf at the 2016 Summer Olympics|2016 Rio Games]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.golf.com/tour-and-news/golf-returns-2016-olympics-rio|title=Golf returns to Olympics in 2016, but many questions remain|access-date=16 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;  41 different countries were represented by 120 athletes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.rio2016.com/en/golf |title=Golf |website=Rio 2016 |access-date=16 September 2016 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160921082103/https://www.rio2016.com/en/golf |archivedate=21 September 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Controversy ==

=== Women ===
It wasn't until 1552 that the first woman golfer played the game. [[Mary, Queen of Scots|Mary Queen of Scots]] commissioned [[St Andrews Links|St. Andrew's Links]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.livestrong.com/article/367790-when-were-women-allowed-to-play-golf/ |title=When Were Women Allowed to Play Golf? |last=Leviticus |first=Jill |website=LiveStrong.con |access-date=21 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it wasn't until the 20th century that women were taken seriously and eventually broke the &quot;Gentlemen Only, Ladies Forbidden&quot; rule. Many men saw women as unfit to play the sport due to their lack of strength and ability.

In the United States, 1891 was a pivotal year for ladies golf because the [[Shinnecock Hills Golf Club|Shinnecock Hills]] nine-hole course was built in Southampton, New York, for women and was the first club to offer membership to women golfers. Four years later, in 1895, The U.S. Golf Association held the first Women's Amateur Championship tournament.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://nancyberkley.com/774892.html |title=Timeline – Important Events in the History of Women's Golf |website=nancyberkley.com |access-date=21 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Just like professional golfer [[Bobby Jones (golfer)|Bobby Jones]], [[Joyce Wethered]] was considered to be a star in the 1920s.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://womensgolfjournal.com/golf/no-women-allowed/ |title=Gentlemen Only, Ladies Forbidden - a history |date=11 April 2016 |work=Women's Golf Journal |access-date=21 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jones praised Wethered in 1930 after they had played an exhibition against each other. He doubted that there had ever been a better golfer, man or woman.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1997/11/25/sports/joyce-wethered-96-top-golfer-of-the-20-s.html |title=Joyce Wethered, 96, Top Golfer of the 20's |last=Litsky |first=Frank |date=25 November 1997 |work=The New York Times |access-date=21 December 2017 |issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Bobby Jones' comment wasn't enough for others to change their views on women golfers.

The [[Royal Liverpool Golf Club|Royal Liverpool']]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s club refused entry of [[Henry Cotton (golfer)|Sir Henry Cotton]]'s wife into the clubhouse in the late 1940s. The secretary of the club released a statement saying, &quot;No woman ever has entered the clubhouse and, praise God, no woman ever will.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; However, American golfer and all-around athlete, [[Babe Zaharias]] didn't have to enter the clubhouse. She was able to prove herself on the course, going on to become the first American to win the British Women's Amateur title in 1947. The following year she became the first woman to attempt to qualify for the [[U.S. Open (golf)|U.S. Open]], but her application was rejected by the [[United States Golf Association|USGA]]. They stated that the event was intended to be open to men only.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=K01hAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=2nQNAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2239,1001149&amp;dq=los-angeles+zaharias+golf&amp;hl=en |title=Men Only—Answer To Mrs. Zaharias Golf Entry |newspaper=The Telegraph-Herald |first=Ben |last=Phlegar |agency=Associated Press |date=7 April 1948 |page=11 |location=Dubuque, Iowa |via=news.google.com |access-date=21 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[LPGA|Ladies Professional Golf Association]] was formed in 1950 as a way to popularize the sport and provide competitive opportunities for golfers.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; The competitions were not the same for the men and women. It wasn't until 1972 that [[United States Congress|U.S. Congress]] passed the [[Title IX|Title IX of the Education Amendments]]. &quot;No person in the United States shall, on the basis of sex, be excluded from participation in, be denied the benefits of, or be subject to discrimination under any education program or activities receiving Federal financial assistance.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.justice.gov/crt/overview-title-ix-education-amendments-1972-20-usc-1681-et-seq |title=Overview Of Title IX Of The Education Amendments Of 1972, 20 U.S.C. A§ 1681 Et. Seq. |publisher=Department of Justice |access-date=21 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; American [[Renee Powell]] moved to the UK in the 1970s to further her career, and became the first woman to play in a British men's tournament in 1977.&lt;ref name=hennessy&gt;{{cite news|first=John|last=Hennessy|title=Golf|newspaper=The Times|location=London|date=September 7, 1977|p=8|accessdate=September 18, 2018|url=http://find.galegroup.com/ttda/infomark.do?&amp;source=gale&amp;prodId=TTDA&amp;userGroupName=kccl&amp;tabID=T003&amp;docPage=article&amp;searchType=BasicSearchForm&amp;docId=CS134578471&amp;type=multipage&amp;contentSet=LTO&amp;version=1.0|url-access=subscription }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, women golfers are still fighting and working hard to have the same opportunities as men golfers. There is still a big pay gap in the USGA. The USGA has a long history of writing bigger checks to winners of the men's U.S. Open than the U.S. Women's Open.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.espn.com/espnw/sports/article/15160220/big-gap-earnings-men-women-professional-golfers |title=Big gap in earnings between men and women professional golfers |work=espnW |first=Max |last=Saffer |date=8 April 2016 |access-date=21 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==International events==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Golf at the Asian Games]]
* [[Golf at the Pan American Games]]
* [[Golf at the Summer Olympics]]
* [[Golf at the Summer Universiade]]
* [[Ryder Cup]]
* [[Presidents Cup]]
* [[Solheim Cup]]
* [[International Crown]]
* [[Seve Trophy]]
* [[EurAsia Cup]]
* [[Walker Cup]]
* [[Curtis Cup]]
{{div col end}}

==See also==
* [[Glossary of golf]]
* [[Outline of golf]]
* [[Lists of golfers]]
* [[List of golf courses in the United Kingdom]]
* [[Professional Golfers' Association of America]]
* [[Variations of golf]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links |d=Q5377|wikt=golf |commons=Category:Golf |b=Golf |n=Category:Golf |q=no |s=Category:Golf |v=Golf |voy=Golf |species=no |m=no|mw=no}}
* [http://www.randa.org/ The R&amp;A, St Andrews]
* [http://www.usga.org/ USGA: United States Golf Association]
* [http://www.golf.org.au/ Golf Australia, national governing body of Australia]
* [https://www.igfgolf.org/ International Golf Federation (IGF)]

{{Golf}}
{{Golf at multi-sport events}}
{{Summer Olympic sports}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Golf| ]]
[[Category:Precision sports]]
[[Category:Ball and bat games]]
[[Category:Sports originating in Scotland]]
[[Category:Leisure activities]]
[[Category:Summer Olympic sports]]
[[Category:Scottish games]]
[[Category:15th-century introductions]]</text>
      <sha1>s5snuc8eoahly4lqzup2ihfb5m1divf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
