  <page>
    <title>Groundskeeping</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2079855</id>
    <revision>
      <id>912764574</id>
      <parentid>908579910</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-08-27T18:31:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rtkat3</username>
        <id>275202</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Garden pool in Filoli, Woodside, California.jpg|thumb|right|260px|A mansion garden landscape.]]
'''Groundskeeping''' is the activity of tending an area of land for aesthetic or functional purposes; typically in an institutional setting. It includes mowing grass, trimming hedges, pulling weeds, planting flowers, etc. The U.S. Department of Labor estimated that more than 900,000 workers are employed in the [[landscape maintenance]] and groundskeeping services industry in the United States in 2006. Of these over 300,000 workers were [[greenskeeper]]s for [[golf course]]s, schools, resorts, and public parks.&lt;ref&gt;The National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health. [https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/docs/2008-144/ &quot;Fact Sheet: Fatal Injuries Among Landscape Services Workers&quot;]. DHHS Publication 2008-144. October 2008. Accessed 10-22-2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Compare [[gardener]].

==Groundskeepers==
A '''groundskeeper''' is a person who maintains landscaping, gardens or sporting venues (and their vegetation where appropriate) for appearance and functionality. In [[United Kingdom|Britain]] the word '''groundsman''' (occasionally '''groundswoman''' if appropriate) or '''park-keeper''' is used much more commonly.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/groundskeeper groundskeeper] in [[Oxford Dictionaries Online]]: &quot;North American term for groundsman.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/park-keeper park-keeper] in [[Oxford Dictionaries Online]]: &quot;The caretaker of a park.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
In [[Australia]], the word '''curator''' is often used for a person undertaking this job, especially those involving [[cricket pitch]]es.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}} At university campuses, groundskeepers are often called [[horticulturists]]. The equivalent on a golf course is a [[greenskeeper]].{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}

The U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics (BLS) estimated in May 2015 that statistical group 37-3011 &quot;Landscaping and Groundskeeping Workers&quot; numbered 895,600 with a median annual wage of $25,030.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bls.gov/oes/current/oes373011.htm |title=Occupational Employment and Wages, May 2015 |publisher=bls.gov |date=2015-05-01 |accessdate=2016-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; The BLS describes the functions of this group as &quot;Workers typically perform a variety of tasks, which may include any combination of the following: sod laying, mowing, trimming, planting, watering, fertilizing, digging, raking, sprinkler installation, and installation of mortarless segmental concrete masonry wall units&quot;.

[[File:20120801 Wrigley Field groundscrew.JPG|thumb|[[Wrigley Field]] Grounds crew smooths the infield dirt.]]
{{unreferenced section|date=January 2011}}
A groundskeeper's job requires a wide range of knowledge of horticulture, pest control, and weed abatement. As many institutions (especially schools) are moving away from the use of chemical pesticides and toward [[integrated pest management]] the experience, knowledge and scholastic requirements of top groundskeepers are increasing. While groundskeepers usually follow a site plan created by a [[landscape architecture|landscape architect]], there can be many opportunities for creativity in detailed design and presentation.

==Groundskeeping equipment==
{{see also|Equipment manager}}
'''Groundskeeping equipment''' comprise [[tool|implement]]s and [[vehicle]]s used in groundskeeping, including:

* [[mower]]s
* [[lawn mower]]s
* [[tractor]]s
* [[string trimmer]]s
* [[snow blower]]s
* [[snow plow]]s
* [[edger]]s
* [[string trimmer|rotary brushe]]s
* [[Rake (tool)|rake]]s
* [[leaf blower]]s
* [[shovel]]s
* [[trowel]]s
* [[irrigation sprinkler|sprinkler]]s
* [[garden tool]]s
* [[watering can]]s or truck mounted watering system (polyethylene tank and hoses)
* [[line marker (sports)|line markers]]

==Environmental impact==
Pollution from gas-powered groundskeeping equipment is a significant source of air pollution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.epa.gov/air/community/details/yardequip.html Lawn Equipment | Improving Air Quality in Your Community | US EPA&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090428102707/http://www.epa.gov/air/community/details/yardequip.html |date=2009-04-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[US emission standard]]s specifically limit emissions from small engines.  Electric models produce no emissions at the point of use, but may shift pollution to power plants.  Emissions may still be reduced by the use of [[renewable energy]] in grid generation, or because central power plants generally must have stricter emissions control equipment installed.

==Groundskeepers in fiction==
{{unreferenced section|date=January 2011}}
Groundskeepers have appeared occasionally as minor characters in fiction and moving images. They are usually presented as comic or peculiar characters, often exhibiting a compulsive or obsessive personality defect.

Some examples of fictional groundskeepers include:

* On [[Cartoon Network]]'s animated series ''[[Regular Show]]'', Mordecai, Rigby, Skips, Muscle Man, High Five Ghost and Thomas are groundskeepers at a local park.
* [[Groundskeeper Willie]] is a gruff speaking Scot in the television animated series ''[[The Simpsons]]''. He is both a groundskeeper and a [[janitor]].
* Ben Weatherstaff in ''[[The Secret Garden]]'', is the only adult in the story to have some idea of the children's doings.
* Carl Spackler is an assistant groundskeeper played by actor [[Bill Murray]] in the movie ''[[Caddyshack]]'', who obsessively pursues the destruction of a [[gopher (animal)|gopher]] on the [[golf|golf course]] that he maintains.
* [[Boothby (Star Trek)|Boothby]] is the longtime [[Starfleet Academy]] groundskeeper and grandfatherly figure to many cadets in the ''[[Star Trek]]'' series ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation|The Next Generation]]'', ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|Deep Space Nine]]'', and ''[[Star Trek: Voyager|Voyager]]''.
* Chauncey Gardiner, played by [[Peter Sellers]] in ''[[Being There]]''. In this case the character is central to the plot. Although of limited intelligence (from our viewpoint) he uniquely mirrors all who interact with him and so becomes a popular persona, even to the point of being suggested by others as a possible United States presidential candidate.
* In the ''[[Harry Potter]]'' book series, [[Rubeus Hagrid]] is the [[Half-giant|Half-Giant]] groundskeeper at Hogwarts.

==See also==
* [[Organic horticulture]]
* [[List of organic gardening and farming topics]]
* [[:Category:American gardeners|American gardeners]]
* [[Turf management]]
* [[Professional Grounds Management Society]]

==References==
; Notes
{{reflist|30em}}

[[Category:Horticulture and gardening]]
[[Category:Lawn care]]
[[Category:Equipment|&gt;]]
[[Category:Baseball field]]
[[Category:Playing field surfaces|*]]</text>
      <sha1>l0111mprcn6iik40fjq5obkhy3slh8q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
