  <page>
    <title>Jaisinghpur</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22966238</id>
    <revision>
      <id>925379568</id>
      <parentid>922176036</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-09T19:12:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sun Creator</username>
        <id>5663757</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WP:AWB/GF|General fixes]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: ’s → 's</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Distinguish|Jaysingpur}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2017}}
{{Use Indian English|date=February 2017}}
{{Infobox settlement
| name                    = Jaisinghpur
| other_name              = 
| nickname                = 
| settlement_type         = city
| image_skyline           = 
| image_alt               = 
| image_caption           = 
| pushpin_map             = India Himachal Pradesh#India
| pushpin_label_position  = right
| pushpin_map_alt         = 
| pushpin_map_caption     = Location in Himachal Pradesh, India
| coordinates             = {{coord|31.898615|N|76.598931|E|display=inline,title}}
| subdivision_type        = Country
| subdivision_name        = {{flag|India}}
| subdivision_type1       = [[States and territories of India|State]]
| subdivision_name1       = [[Himachal Pradesh]]
| subdivision_type2       = [[List of districts of India|District]]
| subdivision_name2       = [[Kangra district|Kangra]]
| established_title       = &lt;!-- Established --&gt;
| established_date        = 
| founder                 = 
| named_for               = 
| government_type         = 
| governing_body          = 
| unit_pref               = Metric
| area_footnotes          = 
| area_rank               = 
| area_total_km2          = 
| elevation_footnotes     = 
| elevation_m             = 592
| population_total        = 1273
| population_as_of        = 2005
| population_rank         = 
| population_density_km2  = auto
| population_demonym      = 
| population_footnotes    = 
| demographics_type1      = Languages
| demographics1_title1    = Official
| demographics1_info1     = [[Hindi language|Hindi]]
| timezone1               = [[Indian Standard Time|IST]]
| utc_offset1             = +5:30
| postal_code_type        = [[Postal Index Number|PIN]]
| postal_code             = 176095
| area_code_type          = Telephone code
| area_code               = 911894xxxxxx
| registration_plate      = HP-56
| website                 = 
| footnotes               = 
}}
'''Jaisinghpur''' is a small town and [[Sub-Division]] in [[Kangra district]] of [[Himachal Pradesh]], [[India]]. There is only one tehsil under Sub-Division Jaisinghpur, which is situated at Jaisinghpur itself. Population of Jaisinghpur Town is 1,273 and overall population of Jaisinghpur Sub-Division is 58,623. It was named after the name of [[Katoch]] king of Princely ordered state Kangra-[[Lambagraon]], Maharaja Jai Singh. It is situated on the bank of river [[Beas River|Beas]]. It is known for its &quot;[[chaugan]].&quot; There are several notable temples in the town such as Janaki Nath temple, Radhey Krishan temple near Bus Adda,Laxmi Narayan temple, Baba Mani Ram Temple, Neel Kanth Mahadev Temple, Dhudu Mahadev Mandir, Guga temple (Called Gangoti near [[Shitala]] Mata Mandir), [[Shitala]] Mata temple, a Dargah midtown, popularly known as Baba Shah Mast Ali Dargah and a [[Gurudwara]] on Jaisinghpur Lambagoan road. [[Shitala]] Mata temple is famous temple of the town on Tinbar-Palampur road. Another famous temple is [[Jankinath temple]].One of the famous tourist place is Naguli Naag, there is swimming pool where you will enjoy in summer days.And also one more place is Basanti da patan near the beas river where you will enjoy the boating at very minimal cost.

==Festival and fair==
Jaisinghpur has been also known as the first place in Kangra or perhaps in entire Himachal for staging Ramlila festival. Ramlila of Jaisinghpur started some 90 years ago and almost all the actors were Brahmin, mainly from Awasthi community. [[Pandit Balkishan Awasthi]], a native of Jaisinghpur who lived in Mumbai for his work and also associated with theatre there, have brought all the Drama items required for Ramlila from Mumbai and started Ramlila festival single-handedly at Jaisinghpur. He used to play the role of Ravana in the Ramlila and become very popular because of his dialogue delivery in strong deep voice and due to his tall, handsome personality. The uniqueness of the Ramlila was the [[Sanskrit language]] used at that time, most Ramlilas in [[North India]] are based on the 16th century [[Avadhi]] version of [[Ramayana]], [[Ramcharitmanas]], written by [[Gosvami Tulsidas]] entirely in verse, thus used as dialogues in most traditional versions.

Jaisinghpur is also famous for its annual fair also known as holian which are celebrated in the month of march during the colour festival of holi. The Holian of Jaisinghpur is famous for its mouth watering aalu chholey and Jalebi and continues for almost a week. Holding of Kushti (wrestling) at Dargah during Holis is an annual affair watched by several visitors.

==Nature and agriculture==
There are  many natural water resources in the town.'Baayein' near PWD Rest House and 'Naoun' is favorite place for all boys to have fun by swimming in summer, however it serves the major water need of people. Jaisinghpur is also famous for its vegetable production on the banks of Beas river the spot is popularly known as Bhuare ke Bagh. Once Jaisinghpur was also famous for  vegetable growing on the banks of river Beas i.e. popularly known as bhuaray ka bagh. But nowadays the growing of crops including vegetables has been stopped in Jainsinghpur and entire adjoining area  because of the increase of stray animals, monkeys, wild pigs, rabbits, deer's (Kakkar, Barahsinga and neel gaye), which spoil crops completely.

The menace of wild and stray animals has increased nowadays manifold probably because tigers/leopards which were responsible for keeping such animals under control have been killed by local poachers.

[[File:Jaisinghpur Chougan.JPG|right|thumb|250px|Jaisinghpur Chougan]]
[[File:Beas jaisinghpur.jpg|right|thumb|250px|View of the river Beas from Jaisinghpur]]
[[File:Sukad Khad bridge.JPG|right|thumb|250px|Sukad Khad bridge]]
[[File:Jaisinghpur Bus Stand.JPG|right|thumb|250px|Jaisinghpur Bus Stand]]

==[[Geography]]==
Jaisinghpur is located at {{coord|31.898615|N|76.598931|E|}}. It has an average elevation of 558&amp;nbsp;metres (1,831&amp;nbsp;feet).

==Demographics==
According to the 2001 India census,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.censusindia.gov.in/ Census of India] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070514045222/http://www.censusindia.gov.in/ |date=14 May 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the population of Jaisinghpur town is 1,273 and overall population of Jaisinghpur tehsil is 58,623. This number represents 26,666 are males and 31,957 females.

==Schools in Jaisinghpur==
1. Pathshala, the primary school near Sheetla Mata Mandir was the oldest school of Jaisinghpur. Initially it was a private school only and students had to join high school at Lambagaon after finishing their primary education. Since approx. 2005-2010 this school has been closed.

2. At the present time (early 21st century) the Govt. Sr. Secondary School conducting science as well as humanity classes is the biggest school of the area. This was a middle school up to 1969 and high school up to 1986 after which it was upgraded to Sr. Secondary School.

3 Beside now there are some private schools opened in recent years which are B.K Public Sr. Sec. School, Aim Academy Sr. Sec School, The Lawrence International School (first [[Central Board of Secondary Education|CBSE]])

==Colleges in Jaisinghpur==
*Government Degree College Jaisinghpur
*The Lawrence College Jaisinghpur
*Jaggi Institute of Technology
*PR Education Point (Tinbar-Majhera) Tehsil Jaisinghpur, Kangra HP 176076

== Places of tourism in Jaisinghpur and adjoining area ==

The temples of Bijapur, JanakiNath, and Baba Mani Ram temple are made up of similar design indicating their construction in same era (approx. 500 years old) are religious places of Jaisinghpur to visit.
Bijapur is the adjoining village of Jaisinghpur which is famous as the birthplace of Maharaja Sansar Chand, the 18Th century King of erstwhile Kangra State. There are still the remains of three storey Mahal of Maharaj which have turned into ruins now but one can just judge how prosperous people of that time lived in this Palace. On one marble stone is engraved &quot;Birth Place of Mahraja Sansar Chand-1765 A.D.&quot; Maharani Tara Devi the fourth wife of Maharaja Hari Singh of Jammu &amp; Kashmir and the mother of Scholar, Congress M.P. Karan Singh is also from this royal family of Bijapur. The other major attraction of Bijapur is more than 500 years Sita Ram Mandir. The statues of god Rama, Laxman and Sita and Hanuman outside temple are worth seeing and worshipping. The broken arm of Shri Hanuman Ji which is reported to have broken by the then Muslim invadors but who couldn't broke the temple is still lying on the feet of Hanuman statue. There are small structures of concrete all around this village which tell how fortified the village would have been for the security of the then Kings.
One can enjoy boat riding which at Basanti which is the source of crossing river Beas. A number of migratory water birds such Siberian Crayons (saras) etc. can be seen near river all around.
There is Ardaa Baba Mandir near the forests of Sandalwood in Netru village, which is very very old and people pay respect to Baba on every occasion. The other attractions are forests of sandalwood of Netru (4&amp;nbsp;km from Jaisinghpur) which are being stolen by local thieves nowadays are worth seeing. If you are lucky, you can also see the likely to be extinct breed of animal i.e. Pengulin in the dense forests of Netru. If you are interested in adventures, the trip from Netru to Chadhiar Via Salehra through dense forests and parallel to Ganoonu ki khad is so enjoyful.
 
Kunjeshwar Mahadev Temple which is another very old temple and Palace of King (saradkhana) are other attractions in Lower Lambagaon. 
Ashapuri temple is a religious place of area and scenic view of whole Changer area from the heights of this temple is worth watching.

For staying in Jaisinghpur the only place is the Govt Rest house which may be booked through local Executive Engineer of PWD at very nominal rates.

== Cities and villages in Jaisinghpur Tehsil ==

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot;  style=&quot;margin:auto; width:560px; margin:0 0 1em 1em; background:#f4f5f6; border:#c6c7c8 solid; font-size:90%;&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;8&quot;  style=&quot;background:#c2d6e5; text-align:center;&quot;| '''Cities and villages in Jaisinghpur Tehsil
|-
| Alampur || Amb  || Ambal Tappa || Ambotu || Andrana || Anirudh || Aranda || Arath
|-
| Ashapuri || Bag Kuljan || Bagh || Baghetar || Bagrena || Bajot || Bakarag || Balah
|-
| Ban Baghetar || Ban Banjar || Ban Chambi || Bandahu Khas || Bansu || Bar || Baralu || Barla
|-
| Barram Kalan || Barram Khurd || Behru || Bhagaina || Bhaglal || Bhagun || Bhalundar || Bhati
|-
| Bhatwara || Bhaudi || Bheri Nichli || Bheri Uparli || Bhuhara || Bijapur || Bir || Chambe Da Lahr
|-
| Chambi || Chandraun || Chaunsaral Pat || Chhainti || Chhatter || Chohla || Dabla || Dadu
|-
| Dagoh Khas || Dali || Daliana || Dalu || Dandel || Daraman Khas || Daslon || Dehru
|-
| Dehru || Dhaneri || Dhar Brahmpuri || Dhar Darumka Kalan || Dhar Darumka Khurd || Dhar Lahar Langha || Dibb || Dol
|-
| Drup Kayara || Dugruhi || Gadiara || Gahli || Galehr || Gandar || Ganguhi || Garh 
|-
| Ghar Chandi || Gharun || Guga || Gughrar|| Guhan || Gujrera || Gulana || Gungari 
|-
| Haler || Halon Kalan || Halon Khurd || Har || Har Balak Rupi || Hardon || Harsi || Inder Nagar
|-
| Jagat || Jagni Jar || Jagrup Nagar || Jaisinghpur || [[Jalari]] || Jaleht || Jamhun || Jamula
|-
| Jandera || Jangal || Jarehr || Jaryal Lahr || Jol || Julah Pat || Kachhal Bhadarian || Kachhal Jagian
|-
| Kachhehra || Kalhera || Kalhun || Kaluhi || Kamand || Karan Ghat || Karonthi || Kasehda
|-
| Kathaun || Kathla || Kelan || Khajurnun || Khalta || Kharjar || Kheri || Koal
|-
| Kohala || Koru || Kosri Khas || Kotahan || Kotlu || Kotlu Khas || Kudana || Kuhn Khas
|-
| Kuhn Uparli || Kutwalla || Lahat Khas || Lahr || Lahri || Lahru || Lanot || Liunda
|-
| Lower Lamba Graon || Luggat || Maharaj Nagar || Maila || Maiser Gujrehra || Majehar || Majhera || Malehr
|-
| Malodhan || Maniar || Manjhoti || Marera || Mashwar || Molag Jhikla || Molag Uparla || Mongal
|-
| Nagban Buhla || Nagban Uparla || Nagpuri || Nahlna || Nakthori || Netru || Nihara || Nin
|-
| Och Kalan || Och Khurd || Odri || Palat || Paleta || Pandehr || Panjlehr || Panti II Pharer
|-
| Paplah || Paprola || Parman || Pat || Ramnagar || Rana Nagar || Rirkal || Rit
|-
| Ropa || Ropri || Sadda || Sai || Sandroa || Sanghol || Santal || Sari
|-
| Saul Banehr || Shakoh || Siara || Spehr || Suan || Talwar || Tambar  || Tambru
|-
| Tandar || Tarhela || Tatrola || Thanpal || Theru Buhla || Theru Uparla || Tikkar Jihan || Tikri
|-
| Tikri Ghamarrnun || Tikru || Tina Nagaitar || Trefar || Umar || Umri || Uppar Lamba Graon || Utrapur
|-
| Gopalpur (uttrapur) || Harot
|-
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot;  style=&quot;margin:auto; width:560px; margin:0 0 1em 1em; background:#f4f5f6; border:#c6c7c8 solid; font-size:90%;&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;9&quot;  style=&quot;background:#c2d6e5; text-align:center;&quot;| '''Pin Codes of Jaisinghpur
|-
| Ashapuri&lt;br /&gt;176094 || Bachhwai&lt;br /&gt;176107 || Balahra&lt;br /&gt;176098 || Balakrupi&lt;br /&gt;176082 || Bandahu (Kalhun)&lt;br /&gt;176073 || Barram Khurd&lt;br /&gt;176097 || Bhatwan&lt;br /&gt;176098 || Bheri&lt;br /&gt;176082 || Dagera&lt;br /&gt;176107
|-
| Dhupkiara&lt;br /&gt;176096 || Dhar Brahmpuri&lt;br /&gt;176082 II Draman&lt;br /&gt;176094 || Galoti&lt;br /&gt;176107 || Haler&lt;br /&gt;176091 || Harrot&lt;br /&gt;176095 || Harsi&lt;br /&gt;176091 || Jagrup Nagar&lt;br /&gt;176082 || Jaisinghpur&lt;br /&gt;176095 || Jalag&lt;br /&gt;176094 
|-
| Jangal&lt;br /&gt;176082 || Karanghat&lt;br /&gt;176095 || Khera&lt;br /&gt;176086 || Kona&lt;br /&gt;176107 || Kosri&lt;br /&gt;176096 || Kotlu&lt;br /&gt;176096 || Kuhan&lt;br /&gt;176098 || Lahru&lt;br /&gt;176098 || Maharajnagar&lt;br /&gt;176096
|-
|Maila&lt;br /&gt;176089 || Majhoti&lt;br /&gt;176089 || Marera&lt;br /&gt;176097 || Molag&lt;br /&gt;176089 || Nahlana&lt;br /&gt;176094 || Netru&lt;br /&gt;176095 || Rananagar&lt;br /&gt;176089 || Sadun&lt;br /&gt;176107 || Sai&lt;br /&gt;176107
|-
|Sakoh&lt;br /&gt;176082 || Salan&lt;br /&gt;176107 || Sanghole&lt;br /&gt;176091 || Sari&lt;br /&gt;176089 || Suan&lt;br /&gt;176094 || Talwar&lt;br /&gt;176096 || Tammber&lt;br /&gt;176095 || Thural&lt;br /&gt;176107 || Uttrapur&lt;br /&gt;176095
|-
|Vijaypur&lt;br /&gt;176095  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  || 
|-
|}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://jaisinghpur-kangra.blogspot.com/ Detailed '''BLOG''' on JAISINGHPUR.]
* {{Wikivoyage-inline}}
{{Commons category|Jaisinghpur}}

[[Category:Cities and towns in Kangra district]]</text>
      <sha1>ivc7ejw439g4jtpppgh2q170cnmer6y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
