  <page>
    <title>Kabaddi</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16926</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938654205</id>
      <parentid>938654162</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-01T16:24:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Arjayay</username>
        <id>5718152</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/103.250.44.172|103.250.44.172]] ([[User talk:103.250.44.172|talk]]) to last version by Piyush Khandelwal 199</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about||the circle style kabaddi|Punjabi kabaddi|the films|Kabaddi (2009 film)|and|Kabaddi (2013 film)}}
{{Use Indian English|date=October 2017}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2016}}
{{short description|Team sport popular in South Asia}}
{{Infobox sport
| name           = Kabaddi
| image          = Iran men's national kabaddi team 13970602000432636707284535394012 98208.jpg
| caption        = A kabaddi match during the [[2018 Asian Games]].
| union          = [[International Kabaddi Federation]]
| nickname       = Kaudi, Pakaada, Ha-du-du, Bhavatik, Saadukuda, Hu-Tu-Tu, Himoshika
| region         = [[Indian Subcontinent]], [[Asia]]
| registered     = Arbadi Bad
| clubs          = none
| contact        = Permitted
| team           = 7 (per side)
| mgender        = No, there are separate competitions for male and female
| category       =[[Team sport]], [[Contact sport]]
| equipment      = None
| venue          = Kabaddi court
| olympic        = [[Demonstration sport]]: [[1936 Summer Olympics|1936 Olympics]]
}}
 
'''Kabaddi''' is a [[contact sport|contact]] [[team sport]], played between two teams of seven players each. The objective of the game is for a single player on offence, referred to as a &quot;raider&quot;, to run into the opposing team's half of a court, tag out as many of their defenders as possible, and return to their own half of the court, all without being tackled by the defenders, and in a single breath. Points are scored tagged by the raider, while the opposing team earns a point for stopping the raider. Players are taken out of the game if they are tagged or tackled, but are brought back in for each point scored by their team from a tag or tackle.

It is popular in [[South Asia]] and other surrounding [[Asia]]n countries. Although accounts of kabaddi appear in the histories of [[ancient India]], the game was popularised as a competitive sport in the 20th century. It is the [[national sport]] of [[Bangladesh]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Dhaka Tribune&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.dhakatribune.com/sport/other-sports/2016/12/15/tale-kabaddi-bangladeshs-national-sport/|title=A tale of kabaddi, Bangladesh’s national sport|work=Dhaka Tribune|accessdate=31 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bpedia/&gt; It is the state game of the [[Indian state]]s of [[Andhra Pradesh]], [[Bihar]], [[Haryana]], [[Karnataka]], [[Kerala]], [[Maharashtra]],[[Odisha]], [[Punjab, India|Punjab]], [[Tamil Nadu]], [[Telangana]], and [[Uttar Pradesh]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://sportycious.com/introduction-kabaddi-history-rules-information-91452|title=Kabaddi Introduction, Rules, Information, History &amp; Competitions|last=siddharth|date=2016-12-31|website=Sportycious|language=en-US|access-date=2020-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are two major disciplines of Kabaddi: so-called [[Punjabi kabaddi]], also referred to as &quot;circle style,&quot; comprises traditional forms of the sport that are played on a circular field outdoors, while the &quot;standard style,&quot; played on a rectangular court indoors, is a discipline played in major professional leagues and international competitions such as the [[Asian Games]].

The game is known by numerous names in different parts of South Asia, such as: ''kabaddi '' or ''chedugudu'' in [[Andhra Pradesh]]; ''kabaddi'' in [[Maharashtra]], [[Karnataka]], [[Kerala]] and [[Telangana]]; ''kabadi'' or ''ha-du-du'' in [[Bangladesh]]; ''bhavatik'' in [[Maldives]], ''kauddi'' or ''kabaddi'' in the [[Punjab region]]; ''hu-tu-tu'' in Western India, ''hu-do-do'' in Eastern India; ''chadakudu'' in South India; ''kapardi'' in [[Nepal]]; and ''kabadi'' or ''sadugudu'' in [[Tamil Nadu]].

==History of the game==
Although unverified, theories from religious believers state that Kabaddi originated from either the [[Vedic period]] of [[ancient India]], or the [[Sistan]] region of present-day Iran. The game was said to have been popular among the [[Yadava]] people; an [[abhang]] by [[Tukaram]] stated that the god [[Krishna]] played the game in his youth, while the [[Mahabharata]] contains an account of [[Arjuna]] being able to sneak into hostile areas also take out enemies unscathed, which they are claiming that parallels the gameplay of kabaddi.

There are also accounts of [[Gautama Buddha]] having played the game recreationally.{{Citation needed|date= December 2019}}

Despite these conflicting claims, India has been credited with having helped to popularize kabaddi as a competitive sport, with the first organized competitions occurring in the 1920s, their introduction to the programme of the [[National Games of India|Indian Olympic Games]] in 1938, the establishment of the All-India Kabaddi Federation in 1950, and it being played as a [[demonstration sport]] at the [[1951 Asian Games|inaugural 1951 Asian Games]] in [[New Delhi]]. These developments helped to formalize the sport, which had traditionally been played in villages, for legitimate international competition.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.espn.com/kabaddi/story/_/id/17854768/the-kabaddi-question-game-anyway|title=The kabaddi question - whose game is it anyway?|work=ESPN.com|access-date=2018-08-20|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=O5mACgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA219&amp;lpg=PA219&amp;dq=%22Vedic%22+%22kabaddi%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=a0cu-rN3Qm&amp;sig=re-A8huBsvqMQMHiDYQ3QgDWr_A&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjAko_o4vzcAhUB74MKHVi6AUk4ChDoATAEegQIBhAB#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Vedic%22%20%22kabaddi%22&amp;f=false|title=Nation at Play: A History of Sport in India|last=Sen|first=Ronojoy|date=2015-10-27|publisher=Columbia University Press|isbn=9780231539937|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dhaka Tribune&quot;/&gt;

After being demonstrated again at the [[1982 Asian Games]] in Delhi, Kabaddi was added to the Asian Games' programme beginning in [[1990 Asian Games|1990]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.dailypioneer.com/sunday-edition/sunday-pioneer/sports-feature/kabaddi-goes-international.html|title=Kabaddi goes international|last=Pioneer|access-date=2018-08-23|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variations of Kabaddi==

===Standard style===
[[File:A Kabaddi match at 2006 Asian Games.jpg|thumb|A kabaddi court at the [[2006 Asian Games]].]]
In the international team version of kabaddi, two teams of seven members each occupy opposite halves of a court of {{convert|10|x|13|m|ft}} in case of men and {{convert|8|x|12|m|ft}} in case of women. Each has five supplementary players held in reserve, i.e. for substitution. The game is played with 20-minute halves with a 5-minute half break in which the teams exchange sides. During each play, known as a &quot;raid&quot;, a player from the attacking side, known as the &quot;raider&quot;, runs into the opposing team's side of the court and attempts to tag as many of the seven defending players as far as possible for a raider. For a raid to be eligible for points, the raider must cross the baulk line in the defending team's territory, and return to their half of the field without being tackled (note that if an attacker touches a defender and hasn't yet reached the baulk line, they don't need to reach the baulk line to score points and may return to their half of the court&lt;ref&gt;https://www.prokabaddi.com/prokabaddi-rules&lt;/ref&gt;). While doing so, the raider must also loudly chant the word &quot;kabaddi&quot;, confirming to referees that their raid is done on a single breath without inhaling. A 30-second [[shot clock]] is also enforced on each raid.&lt;ref name=&quot;kabaddiikf&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;indianexpress-everything&quot; /&gt;

A point is scored for each defender tagged. If the raider steps beyond the bonus line marked in the defending team's territory, they earn an additional point known as a bonus point. If the raider is successfully stopped, the opposite team to earns a point instead. All players tagged are taken out of the game, but one is &quot;revived&quot; for each point a team scores from a subsequent tag or tackle (bonus points do not revive players). Players who step out of the boundary or lobbies are also out. A raid where no points are scored by the raider is referred to as an &quot;empty raid&quot;. By contrast, a play where the raider scores three or more points is referred to as a &quot;super raid&quot;. If a team gets all seven players on the opposing team out at once (&quot;All Out&quot;), they earn two additional points and the players are placed back in the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;kabaddiikf&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;indianexpress-everything&quot; /&gt;

Additional rules are used in the [[Pro Kabaddi League]]: if a team has two empty raids in a row, the next raider must score a point on their next raid, because the next raid is a &quot;do-or-die&quot; raid. In this raid, the player must either get a point or be out. If the raider does not get a point then the opposite team will get a point and the raider will be declared out. Additionally when fewer than four players left on the field, tackles are worth 2 points (&quot;super tackle&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;kabaddiikf&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kabaddiikf.com/RULES_Regularikf.doc|title=Rules of Kabaddi|publisher=International Kabaddi Federation (IKF)|access-date=26 August 2014|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304070523/http://kabaddiikf.com/RULES_Regularikf.doc|archivedate=4 March 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.firstpost.com/sports/kabaddi-world-cup-2016-a-handy-guide-to-the-format-rules-and-how-the-sport-works-3034132.html|title=Kabaddi World Cup 2016: A handy guide to the format, rules and how the sport works|date=2016-10-05|work=Firstpost|access-date=2017-10-29|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.espn.com/kabaddi/story/_/id/20169474/all-need-know-pro-kabaddi-league-2017|title=Kabaddi 101: Raid, defend, revive, repeat|work=ESPN.com|access-date=2017-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;indianexpress-everything&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://indianexpress.com/article/blogs/sports-blogs/everything-you-need-to-know-about-kabaddi/|title=Everything you need to know about Kabaddi|date=2016-01-30|work=The Indian Express|access-date=2017-10-29|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Circle style===
[[File:Kabaddi Match (Bhimber).jpg|thumb|right|A circle kabaddi match being played in [[Bhimber]].]]
There are four major forms of Indian kabaddi recognised by the amateur federation. In Sanjeevani kabaddi, one player is revived against one player of the opposite team who is out. The game is played over 40 minutes with a five-minute break between halves. There are seven players on each side and the team that outs all the players on the opponent's side scores four extra points. In Gaminee style, seven players play on each side and a player put out has to remain out until all his team members are out. The team that is successful in outing all the players of the opponent's side secures a point. The game continues until five or seven such points are secured and has no fixed time duration. Amar style resembles the Sanjeevani form in the time frame rule, but a player who is declared out stays inside the court while play continues. For every player of the opposition touched &quot;out&quot;, a team earns a point.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sportskeeda.com/kabaddi/kabaddi-india-origins-success-current-pitiable-state|title=Kabaddi In India: Origins, success and current pitiable state|work=Sportskeeda.com|date=7 March 2014|access-date=17 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Punjabi Kabaddi|Punjabi kabaddi]] is a variation that is played on a circular pitch of a diameter of {{convert|22|m}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Kissa 2 Kabaddi da|publisher=Sarwan Singh Sangam Publications|isbn=93-83654-65-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==International competitions==
The following competitions are played in standard format, for that of circle style kabaddi, see [[Punjabi Kabaddi|Punjabi kabaddi]].{{Citation needed|date= December 2019}}

===Kabaddi World Cup===
{{Main|Kabaddi World Cup (Standard style)}}
The standard style Kabaddi World Cup is an outdoor international kabaddi competition conducted by the International Kabaddi Federation (IKF), contested by men's and women's national teams. The competition has been previously contested in 2004, 2007 and 2016. All the tournaments have been won by [[India]]. India defeated Iran by 38-29 in the final of the championship game to clinch the title of 2016.{{Citation needed|date= December 2019}}

After the establishment of a new kabaddi organization named [[World Kabaddi Federation]], a world cup in 2019 at [[Malacca]], [[Malaysia]] will be organized. It will be the largest world cup in kabaddi history, consisting of 32 men teams.{{Citation needed|date= December 2019}}

===Asian Games===
{{Main|Kabaddi at the Asian Games}}
[[File:Kabaddi-japan-2015-10-4.webm|thumb|(video) Kabaddi being played in [[Japan]], 2015]]
Kabaddi has been played at the [[Asian Games]] since 1990.{{Citation needed|date= December 2019}} The [[India national kabaddi team|Indian national team]] had won every men's and women's kabaddi competition in the Asian Games from 1990 through 2014. At the [[2018 Asian Games]], [[Iran national kabaddi team|Iran]] became the first country outside of India to win gold medals in Kabaddi, with India's men's team winning bronze, and India's women's team being beaten by Iran to win silver.{{Citation needed|date= December 2019}}

===Pro Kabaddi League===
{{Main|Pro Kabaddi League}}
The [[Pro Kabaddi League]] was established in 2014. The league modeled its business upon that of the [[Indian Premier League]] of [[Twenty20]] [[cricket]], with a large focus on marketing, the backing of local broadcaster [[Star Sports]], and changes to the sport's rules and its presentation to make it more suitable for a television audience.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc-kabaddiipl&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Kabaddi gets the IPL treatment|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/business-28660432|website=BBC News|accessdate=22 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Pro Kabaddi League quickly became a ratings success on Indian television; the [[2014 Pro Kabaddi League season|2014 season]] was watched by at least 435 million viewers over the course of the season, and the inaugural championship match was seen by 98.6 million viewers.&lt;ref name=&quot;thehindu-pklratings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Pro Kabaddi league viewership second only to IPL|url=http://www.thehindu.com/sport/other-sports/pro-kabaddi-league-viewership-second-only-to-ipl/article6413148.ece|website=The Hindu|accessdate=22 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian-kabaddiwc&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Simple, visceral, fun: why the ancient sport of kabaddi is enjoying a resurgence|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/oct/10/kabaddi-world-cup-india-resurgence|work=The Guardian|accessdate=21 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Indo International Premier Kabaddi League===
{{Main|Indo International Premier Kabaddi League}}
The Inaugural edition of the IIPKL was on 13 May at the Pune, India.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.iipkl.com/press-releases/indo-international-premier-kabaddi-league-grand-opening|title=Indo International Premier Kabaddi League Grand Opening|website=IIPKL|language=en|access-date=2019-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The title for the inaugural season was won by the Bangalore Rhinos&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.kabaddiadda.com/news/bangalore-rhinos-become-champions-indo-international-premier-kabaddi-league|title=Bangalore Rhinos become Champions in the Indo International Premier Kabaddi League|website=Kabaddi Adda|language=en|access-date=2019-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Super Kabaddi League===
{{Main|Super Kabaddi League}}
In May 2018, the [[Super Kabaddi League]] was first held in Pakistan, as part of a larger push to promote renewed interest in the sport in Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://tns.thenews.com.pk/importance-professional-leagues/|title=The importance of professional leagues|date=2018-11-25|website=The News on Sunday|language=en-US|access-date=2018-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.newindianexpress.com/sport/other/2018/jun/26/beleaguered-no-more-kabaddi-gains-popularity-in-pakistan-1833688.html|title=Beleaguered no more: Kabaddi gains popularity in Pakistan|website=The New Indian Express|access-date=2018-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://tribune.com.pk/story/923696/kabaddi-league-pakistanis-axed-from-roster-2/|title=Kabaddi league: Pakistanis axed from roster|date=2015-07-21|work=The Express Tribune|language=en-US|access-date=2018-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women's Kabaddi Challenge===
{{Main|Women's Kabaddi Challenge}}
Women's Kabaddi Challenge is a women's kabaddi league. The first season was played from 28 June to 31 July 2016 and was broadcast by [[Star Sports]] in India. Three teams took part and the league played across seven cities in India{{Citation needed|date= December 2019}}. The final was played alongside the men's version on 31 July.  The Storm Queens produced a last-second turnaround to defeat the Fire Birds 24-23.{{Citation needed|date= December 2019}}

===Asian Kabaddi Championship===
[[Kabaddi Asia Cup|AKC]]'s tenth season was played in [[Gorgan]], [[Iran]] in 2017 in which India won its tenth gold by defeating Pakistan in the finals.{{Citation needed|date= December 2019}}

===Kabaddi Masters===
The inaugural edition of the Kabaddi Masters was held in Dubai from 22 to 30 June 2018. It was the first Kabaddi tournament to be held in the UAE. It featured 6 teams. India won the tournament by defeating Iran in the final with a scoreline of 44-26, with the Indian Defense out performing the Iran Defense.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.kabaddiadda.com/dubai-kabaddi-masters-2018/match15-india-vs-iran|title=Kabaddi Masters Dubai 2018 - Match 15 - INDIA vs IRAN|website=Kabaddi Adda|language=en|access-date=2019-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Junior World Kabaddi championship===
The inaugular junior Kabaddi world championship was held in [[Kish island]], [[Iran]] From 11 to 14 November 2019.It featured 13 teams.
Iran won the tournament by defeating Kenya in the final with a final scoreline 42-22.

Note:- Team [[India]] did not participated in this tournament

===Kabaddi premier League===
It is the professional Kabaddi league held in [[Iran]]

===European Kabaddi championship===
First edition of European Kabaddi championship was held in [[Scotland]] in 2019 .Final match was between [[Poland]] and [[Holland]].[[Poland]] won the final with score line 47-27

==Popularity==
Kabaddi is a popular sport in the [[Indian subcontinent]]. The Kabaddi Federation of India (KFI) was founded in 1950, and it compiled a standard set of rules. The governing body for Kabaddi in Pakistan is Pakistan Kabaddi Federation.

In [[Bangladesh]], there is a variation of Kabaddi called Ha-du-du, going back to ancient times. Ha-du-du has no definite rules and is played with different rules in different areas. Kabaddi is the [[national sport]] of Bangladesh, given official status in 1972.&lt;ref name=bpedia&gt;{{cite book|title=Banglapedia: National Encyclopedia of Bangladesh|first=Gofran|last=Faroqi|chapter-url=http://en.banglapedia.org/index.php?title=Kabadi|chapter=Kabadi|publisher=[[Asiatic Society of Bangladesh]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Amateur Kabaddi Federation of Bangladesh was formed in 1973.

In Iran, the Community of Kabaddi was formed in 1996 (the same year they joined the Asian Kabaddi Federation) and in 2001 they joined the International Kabaddi Federation. The Iran Amateur Kabaddi Federation was formed in 2004.

Kabaddi is one of the national sports of Nepal. Kabaddi is played and taught at a very early age in most primary schools beginning in the third grade or so in most Nepali schools. Kabaddi was also played by the [[British Army]] for fun, to keep fit and as an enticement to recruit soldiers from the British Asian community. Kabaddi was brought to the United Kingdom by [[Non-resident Indian and person of Indian origin|Indian]], [[Bangladeshi]] and [[Pakistani immigrant]]s. The governing body for Kabaddi in the United Kingdom is the [[England Kabaddi Federation UK]].

==In popular culture==
;Films depicting kabaddi
* ''[[Gunga Jumna]]'' (1961)
* ''[[Kudumba Thalaivan]]'' (1962)
* ''[[Ganga Ki Saugandh]]'' (1978)
* ''[[Naseeb (1981 film)|Naseeb]]'' (1981)
* ''[[Little Buddha]]'' (1993)
* ''[[Pardes (film)|Pardes]]'' (1997)
* ''[[Hu Tu Tu]]'' (1999)
* ''Kabaddi Kabaddi'' (2003)
* ''[[Okkadu]]'' (2003)
* ''[[Ghilli]]'' (2004)
* ''[[Ajay (2006 film)|Ajay]]'' (2006)
* ''[[Kabaddi (2009 film)|Kabaddi]]'' (2009)
* ''[[Vennila Kabadi Kuzhu]]'' (2009)
* ''[[Bheemli Kabadi Jattu]]'' (2010)
* ''[[Chal Dhar Pakad]]'' (2010)
* ''Kabaddi Ik Mohabbat'' (2010)
* ''[[Kabaddi Once Again]]'' (2012)
* ''[[Badlapur Boys]]'' (2014)
* ''[[Tevar]]'' (2015)
* ''[[Thoppil Joppan]]'' (2016)
* ''[[Georgettan's Pooram]]'' (2017)
*&quot;bathhi kabaddi league &quot;(2017)
* ''[[Student of the Year 2]]'' (2019)
* &quot;[[Panga (film)]]&quot; (2020)
;Anime and manga depicting kabaddi
* ''[[Full Metal Panic? Fumoffu]]'' (2003)
* ''[[Gintama]]'' (2006)
* ''[[Teekyu]]'' (2013)
* ''[[Durarara!!|Durarara!!×2 Shō]]'' (2015)
* ''[[Chio's School Road]]'' (2016, manga; 2018, anime)
* ''Uwagaki'' (2009)

;Dramas depicting kabaddi
* ''[[Bitter Sweet (TV series)|Bitter Sweet]]'' (2015)
* ''[[Azhagiya Tamil Magal]]'' (2017)
*&quot;Varanasi kabbadi league &quot;(2017)
* Super Kabaddi League Pakistan (2017)

==See also==
*[[Punjabi Kabaddi]]
*[[Kabaddi in India]]
*[[Boli Khela]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{commons category}}
* [http://worldkabaddi.org/ World Kabaddi]
* {{Official website|http://www.kabaddiikf.com|International Kabaddi Federation official website}}
* {{Official website|http://www.asiankabaddi.org|Asian Amateur Kabaddi Federation official website}}
* {{Official website|http://www.indiankabaddi.org|Amateur Kabaddi Federation of India (AKFI) official website}}
* [https://www.nytimes.com/slideshow/2010/09/20/nyregion/20200920KABBADI.html A Game Called Kabbadi] – slideshow by ''[[The New York Times]]''

{{International Kabaddi}}
{{Indian martial arts}}
{{Team Sport}}
{{Symbols of Bangladesh}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Kabaddi| ]]
[[Category:Traditional sports of India]]
[[Category:Traditional sports of Pakistan]]
[[Category:Sports originating in South Asia]]
[[Category:National symbols of Bangladesh]]
[[Category:Traditional sports of Bangladesh]]</text>
      <sha1>q7hma5boqkgtnkq3dyzotgqbklnjl1a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
