  <page>
    <title>Khuiratta</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13316678</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937081962</id>
      <parentid>936701682</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-22T21:02:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>YahyA</username>
        <id>31895678</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Gohra,pathan-&gt;Gohra, pathan - [[Wikipedia:Correct typos in one click|Fix a typo in one click]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
{{refimprove|date=September 2015}}
{{cleanup|date=April 2010}}
}}
{{Infobox settlement
| name                   = Khuiratta 
| other_name             = Khoi ratta
| native_name            = {{Nastaliq| کھوئی رٹہ}}
| subdivision_type        = Country
| subdivision_name        = [[Pakistan]]
| subdivision_type1       = [[States of Pakistan|State]]
| subdivision_name1       = [[Azad Kashmir]]
| subdivision_type2       = [[Districts of Pakistan|District]]
| subdivision_name2       = [[Kotli District|Kotli]]
| area_footnotes         =
| area_total_km2         = 
| leader_title1          = [UCs]
| leader_name1           = 05
| coordinates             = {{coord|33.360|74.027|region:PK_type:city|display=inline}}
| pushpin_map             = Azad Kashmir
| pushpin_label_position  = &lt;!-- left, right, top, bottom, none --&gt;
| pushpin_map_alt         = 
| pushpin_mapsize         = 
| pushpin_map_caption     =
&lt;!-- Elevation --------------------------&gt;
| elevation_max_m        = 
| elevation_max_ft       =
| elevation_min_m        =
&lt;!-- Population   -----------------------&gt;
| population_footnotes   =&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tiptopglobe.com/city?n=Khuiratta%20Loharan&amp;p=21462&lt;/ref&gt;
| population_total       = 1,00,000
| population_as_of       = 2014
| population_density_km2 =
&lt;!-- General information  ---------------&gt;
| population_note        =
| timezone               = [[Pakistan Standard Time|PST]]
| utc_offset             = +5
| postal_code_type       = Postal Code
| postal_code            = 11200
| area_code              = 0092-5826
| website                = [http://www.ajk.gov.pk/site/index.php District Website]
}}

'''Khuiratta''' ({{lang-ur|{{Nastaliq|کھوئی رٹہ}}}}) or '''Khoi ratta''' is the chief town of the [[Kotli District]], in Pakistan-administered [[Azad Jammu and Kashmir]].  

==Location==
Khuiratta lies 29&amp;nbsp;km southeast of [[Kotli]] and 165&amp;nbsp;km from [[Islamabad]], to the east. Khuiratta is approximately 7 kilometres from the Line Of Control (LOC). It is the second largest town of District Kotli after Kotli City. It has an elevation of 2570 feet above sea-level. Khuiratta is situated on the western side of Rajouri (IHK), with Tehsile Charhoi to the west, Rajouri to the east, Noshehra (IHK) to the south, Tehsile Nakyal to the north east and Kotli to the north west.

Khuiratta is connected to [[Kotli]] and [[Nakyal]] by a circular road and to [[Mirpur, Azad Kashmir|Mirpur]] (80&amp;nbsp;km) with two links, one via Dhongi-[[Charhoi]] and the other via Darghoti-[[Charhoi]]. 
Khuiratta is also connected to Seri, [[Battal]] , Ghaian and Khor Gumbi Bhera (via Manjwal and Dheri Sahibzadian), Khuiratta used to be connected to [[Rajouri]] in [[Indian-administered Kashmir]] via Seri but this road is now closed at the point Janjoot Bhadar and is separated by the [[Line of Control]].

==Tourism==
Khuiratta and its surrounding areas are very popular among [[Tourism|tourists]]. At approximately a distance of 4 kilometres from Khuiratta is a shrine of &quot;Mai Totti Sahiba&quot; also known as Darbar Mai Toti. Another known shrine of Baba Ali Lashkar is located at Dheri Sahibzadian. Both the locations are visited by hundreds of people daily. Late Sardar Aziz Ahmed started the construction of one of the biggest hospitals of Azad Kashmir in Khuiratta.
Khuiratta is known for the annual [[Basakhi]] (Mela Maveshian).{{fact|date=January 2019}} Thousands of people from the Kotli and other adjoining districts and Pakistan attend the festival in spring to watch sports, animal parades and horticultural displays. For many years this mela was being held in Dheari Bagh Ground. Lately{{when|date=January 2019}} it has been moved to Sihoor Beelaa Cricket Stadium as it caused much disturbance to the local residents. This mela lasts for three days; activities include , Neza bazi, Bazu giri, bull racing, wrestling, football and other form of traditional entertainment.{{Citation needed|date=September 2017}}

Khuiratta is in an area with a number of natural springs and waterfalls.{{fact|date=January 2019}} Several springs emerge from the mountains at Bahees Naraha (Bahee Narrah means 22 natural water springs). In ancient times this was an important [[Hindu]] place of worship. Close to Khui Ratta are the Bagh Fatehpur Dehari and Bagh Sain Hazuri. Thousands of people come to the Mai-ka-Makam Shrine (Mai Toti Sahiba), some 4 km from Khui Ratta city, to pay homage to Mai Toti Sahiba.{{fact|date=January 2019}}

Tourism is restricted to locals or inhabitants of Pakistan. In order for foreigners to visit they have to obtain a No Objection Certificate (NOC) which if granted is only valid for 4 days. The whole of the Azad Kashmir area is similarly restricted by the armed forces of Pakistan and entrance to the area is marked by signs stating &quot;Foreigners Not Allowed&quot;. Before the cease-fire agreement between Pakistan and India, there were military and civilian casualties.

==Health==
There is dearth of specialized health care services in the urban community of Khuiratta. However, general medical care services are being provided through Aziz Welfare Trust Hospital, four hospitals (Younis Medical Centre, Mehrban Hospital, Ishaq Hospital, Shifa Hospital) in private sector and RAHMA Health Centre (NGO). Tehsil Heqaquarter Hospital is the only hospital in public sector. However, the gap of specialized health care services availability has been abridged by weekly visits of consultants of various specialties in different hospitals.  The population of peripheral areas of Khuiratta city is deprived of even basic health facilities. 
The Aziz Welfare Trust Hospital is a huge modern building located in the heart of the city. Birmingham UK based Sardar Abdul Aziz (Late) in the year 2003 goal was to provide healthcare to the poor by building a hospital. The objectives to provide specialised health care services to local communities and especially to the underprivileged population of the area. 


 The Aziz Welfare Hospital was operationalized in the year 2013, 

Besides, General Outdoor medical services, Aziz Welfare Hospital is providing Dialysis, Dental, Laboratory, and Radio Diagnostics, Maternal and Child Health and emergency services to roughly 150 patients daily on subsidized rates to all and free to the poors.

Ambulance services are available at Aziz Welfare Hospital , THQH, Younis Medical Centre and Rehma Hospital but other emergency services like Fire brigade, Blood Bank , 1122 are not available in the area. Qureshi Medical Store is the only facility in Khuiratta you can buy variety of medicines.

==Villages and community==
Darkalla is in a valley known as Wadi e Banah.
Smaller villages located in Khuiratta have mosques. They are also home to shrines of some religious scholars like Mian Imam Baksh of Hujra near Tokahn.  There is also a shrine of Hazarat Baba Ali Lashkar of Dheri Sahibzadian and Pir Haider Shah of Dehari Bagh and Sheikh Alai Jee at khuiratta. There is also a shrine of Hazarat Mai toti  known as darbar mai toti sahiba.
There is also a shrine of Hazarat baba ghorai shah badshah. There is also a shrine of Hazarat RAHAMAN BABA. There is also a shrine of Hazarat OF MEERAY Aahiq ali badshah. There is also a shrine of Hazarat SAIN Sadiq

==Geography==
Khuiratta has mountaineous terrain and is  situated very close to the Line Of Control (LOC), only 8 km away, the temporary border between Indian-administered Kashmir and Azad Kashmir. It has some notable small towns and villages namely,Dehari Baagh,Damandah, Bindian, Dheri Sahibzadian, Gurah, Gitran, Hujra, Merah, Biyal, Manjwaal, Gheyaien,Karjai, Broat Gala, Anderla Kotehra, Phalni, Seri, Manjwar, Bandli, Saidpur, Darkala, Bain Thalla,Sehore, Phehan, Khajorla, Thill, Hill Mughalan, Banni Bannah, Khore bhera, Dhaana,Roshan Abad(formerly Andha), Gohra, pathan mohrha, Barooth, Katasery, Chirri,Battal, Barie, Samlaar, Plaana, Darbar Mai Toti, taeen, Darkoti, darkoti bala,maraal, Dharaa, khore kalla chamber, Nidi Sohana. Khore Rachalla, Khore Graan, Morah Bakhshiyan, Ruknabad, Sarootiyan, Gangal, Chirri, Batal, Barahi, Gajiyari, Bandali, Mohajar Colony, Hilla Ghair and chakranda 

Khuiratta is connected with Kotli via road through Manila.
 
Few years back Aziz welfare trust constructed a huge hospital, which was considered to be a mega project. However the Hospital could not get into its 2nd phase due to death of Mr. Abdul Aziz (Chairman of Aziz Welfare Trust) therefore it is just a building. These days an International level community health center (RAHMA Basic Health Center) is providing basic health &amp; lab facilities to needy and poor people in the area of Khuiratta and surroundings. This hospital is the great achievement of Mr.Muhammad Saghir Qamar (Chairman  RAHMA Islamic Relief, Pakistan) and gift from friends of Norway, which is providing free medical consultation, medicine and lab facilities to poor people of khuiratta.

Khuiratta is connected to kotli on one side, nakyal on west LOC on east and on south is charoi.

Khuiratta is connected to main road to Jammu.

Needi Sohana is the union council of Khuiratta and the highest point of the Kotli district and the [[Khui Forest]] is located in this union council this fores see on google earth.

==Population==
Its population is over 100,000 which is mostly educated. The Jarral, Gujjar, Rajput, Jaat, Hashmi, Khokhar, Chauhan,Malik and Mughal tribes form the majority. List of registered voters 89000 at an estimation of 2004 of this constituency i.e., 22000 Gujjars, 18000 Rajput, 16000 Jatt, 7000 Jarrals, 6000 Khokhar, 13000 Mughal &amp; Malik, 31700 other tribes, Khuiratta is in the Azad Kashmir Assembly constituency, LA 12 Kotli 5. Name of constituency main areas are following Patwar Circles of Kotli Tehsil/ Tehsil Khuiratta:
1. Khor, 2.Sarhotta, 3.Dheri Sahibzadian, 4.Seri Manjwar, 5.Khui-Ratta, 6.Bihal, 7.Dhanna, 8.Andarla Koterra, 9.Samlar, 10.Manjwal, 11.Sarhuta, 12.[[Nidi Sohana]], 13.Daraha sehoor,  14. Battal Barehi, 15. Andha, 15. Darbaar Mai Totti

==Education==
Literacy rate is 90%.
Khuiratta has two Govt. degree colleges for both boys and girls and four private colleges. There are also two high school for both boys and girls and some English medium schools, of which notable are Pasban Science School &amp; College, The Holy Public School &amp; College, Stars Academy, Pasban School, Suffa Academy &amp; Science College, National science college, Pakland School, Ideal Public School, Allama Iqbal Public School &amp; College, Unique Reformer Public School and Stars Academy. One of the earliest and only government school is the &quot;Government High School Khuiratta&quot;. Army Public School is an addition and contribution of Pak Army in uplifting the standard of education in Khuiratta Azad Kashmir.

Khuiratta is also renowned for [[pir (Sufism)|pir]]s and [[faqir]]s and the most revered - Mai Toti Sahiba, Baba Ali Lashkar Sahib,Sangan Darbar, Sain Rukan Deen Sahib, Sain Sakhi Sahib, Chamby Wali Darbar (hujra sharif).

==Politics==
Recently in July 2016 Raja Nisar Ahmed Khan, who belongs to the Pakistan Muslim League (N) Azad Kashmir,Elected as MLA and Minister Law, Parliamentarian affairs, Justice and Human Rights, Electricity .He was elected MLA in the Azad Kashmir Assembly General Election held in 2006 for five years, Ch. Muhammad Rafiq Nayyer Ex. Minister of Health &amp; Transport &amp; Muhammad Matloob Inkalabi Ex member of Kashmir Council &amp; Elected MLA in 2011 election and Joined AJK Legislative Assembley first time as Minister Higher Education IT/TEVTA AJ&amp;K Govt.

==History==
Before the independence of Pakistan and India in 1947, it was used as a trade corridor between [[Rajouri]] and [[Mirpur, Azad Kashmir|Mirpur]].

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

{{Kotli District}}
{{Tehsils of Azad Kashmir}}
[[Category:Populated places in Kotli District]]
[[Category:Tehsils of Kotli District]]</text>
      <sha1>fgag5v72f1lknkkkwlfmkzzu0dm6pq3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
