  <page>
    <title>Kloofing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>652760</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938336525</id>
      <parentid>921793993</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-30T15:52:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Muonmo</username>
        <id>4381570</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Origin of the word */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=August 2008}}

'''Kloofing''' is an [[adventure]] activity that typically involves the descent of a deep [[ravine]] or watercourse that may be dry or wet. The defining factor is usually that the ravine is several times deeper than it is wide. All manner of [[walking]], [[scrambling]], [[climbing]], [[human swimming|swimming]], plunging, [[jumping]], [[bumslide]]s or [[abseiling]] ([[rappelling]]) could be involved.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} 

A kloofing trip usually combines [[hiking]] with the descent of a watercourse.  Some of the more &quot;interesting&quot; kloofing involves long [[abseil]]s or high jumps into pools from varying heights, up to as high as 20 or more metres (for example the popular 'Suicide Gorge' in [[South Africa]]).  Kloofing trips can take from as short as a few hours up to multi-day kloofing trips that would require a party to overnight in a [[ravine]].

Depending on the nature of a particular trail a kloofer (noun) might require specialised technical equipment such as a [[rope]], [[belay device]], [[wetsuit]], [[rock climbing]] anchors, etc. Every year a number of kloofers get injured or need rescue and hence kloofers need to take great care and preferably be accompanied by an experienced kloofer. 

The recommended technique for jumping into water is the 'pin drop', which involves hitting the water with your body as straight as possible and your hands held firmly by your sides.  Closing your mouth completely is a good idea (to avoid biting your tongue) and pointing your toes is optional.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

==Origin of the word==
'''Kloofing''' is derived from the [[Afrikaans language|Afrikaans]] word 'kloof', meaning 'gorge' or 'ravine'.  It has been adopted by [[English language|English]]-speaking people (mostly in southern [[Africa]]), to mean the activity described above. The word is used in a similar sense to [[canyoning]] and [[canyoneering]]. The word (and activity) has been in use in [[South Africa]] since about the 1920s and probably earlier.&lt;ref&gt;1922 Journal of [[The Mountain Club of South Africa]], p5&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist}}
* [http://www.govertical.co.za  South Africa kloofing]

[[Category:Outdoor recreation]]


{{Climbing-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>kjtsuqe58q2ytby73cvvgdv7i0knsth</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
