  <page>
    <title>Leiria</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>307625</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932800997</id>
      <parentid>929030124</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-28T08:12:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Monkbot</username>
        <id>20483999</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* International relations */[[User:Monkbot/task 15: normalize lang icon templates|Task 15]]:  language icon template(s) replaced (1×);</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Portuguese subdivision
| type            = municipality
| official_name   = Leiria
| image_flag      = Pt-lra1.png
| image_shield    = LRA.png
| image_skyline           = {{Photomontage
| photo1a                 = Leiria (25746536508) (cropped).jpg
| photo1b                 = Enjoying the afternoon (39430537200).jpg
| photo2a                 = Castelo de Leiria visto da Encarnacao (cropped).jpg
| photo3a                 = Sé de Leiria - Portugal (40317072481) (cropped).jpg
| photo3b                 = Castelo de Leiria - Portugal (28003610998).jpg
| spacing                 = 2
| position                = center
| color_border            = white
| color                   = white
| size                    = 280
| foot_montage            =
}}
|coordinates             = {{coord|39|45|N|8|48|W|type:adm1st_region:PT_dim:100000|display=inline,title}}
| image_map       = LocalLeiria.svg
|region             = [[Centro Region, Portugal|Centro]]
|CIM                = [[Região de Leiria]]
|district           = [[Leiria District|Leiria]]
| leader_party            = [[Socialist Party (Portugal)|PS]]
| leader_name             = Raul Castro
| area_total_km2          = 565.09
| population_total        = 126,879
| population_as_of        = 2011
| parishes     = 18
| holiday        = Our Lady of the Assumption&lt;br /&gt;May 22
| website                 = {{url|http://www.cm-leiria.pt}}
}}
'''Leiria''' ({{IPA-pt|lɐjˈɾi.ɐ|-|Pt-pt Leiria FF.ogg}}; {{lang-cel-x-proto|ɸlāryo}}) is a city and a municipality in the [[Centro Region]] of [[Portugal]] and in the historical [[Provinces of Portugal|province]] of [[Beira Litoral Province|Beira Litoral]]. 
It is the capital of [[Leiria District]]. The population in 2011 was 126,879,&lt;ref name=ine&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ine.pt/xportal/xmain?xlang=en&amp;xpid=INE&amp;xpgid=ine_indicadores&amp;indOcorrCod=0005889&amp;contexto=pi&amp;selTab=tab0|title=Statistics Portugal|website=www.ine.pt|accessdate=24 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; in an area of {{convert|565.09|km2}}.&lt;ref name=dgt&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.dgterritorio.pt/cartografia_e_geodesia/cartografia/carta_administrativa_oficial_de_portugal_caop_/caop__download_/carta_administrativa_oficial_de_portugal___versao_2017__em_vigor_/ |title=Áreas das freguesias, concelhos, distritos e país |access-date=2018-11-05 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181105172426/http://www.dgterritorio.pt/cartografia_e_geodesia/cartografia/carta_administrativa_oficial_de_portugal_caop_/caop__download_/carta_administrativa_oficial_de_portugal___versao_2017__em_vigor_/ |archive-date=2018-11-05 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the seat of the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Leiria-Fátima]].

==History==

The region around Leiria has been inhabited for a long time, although its early history is obscure. The first evident inhabitants were the [[Turduli Oppidani]], a [[Celtiberians|Celtiberian]] tribe (akin to the [[Lusitanians]]), who established a settlement near (around 7&amp;nbsp;km) present-day Leiria. This settlement was later occupied by the [[Ancient Rome|Romans]], who expanded it under the original [[Celtiberian language|Celtiberian]] name ''Collippo''. The stones of the ancient Roman town were used in the Middle Ages to build much of Leiria.

[[File:LEIRIA E CASTELO.jpg|thumb|left|Leiria and [[Castle of Leiria|its Castle]].]]

The name &quot;Leiria&quot; in Portuguese derives from 'leira' (from the medieval [[Galician-Portuguese]] form 'laria', from [[proto-Celtic]] *ɸlār-yo-, 'high&lt;-&gt;ground'/'yon&lt;-&gt;floor' akin to [[English language|English]] 'floor(ing)', [[Old Irish]] 'làr' 'ground, floor', [[Breton language|Breton]] 'leur' 'ground', [[Welsh language|Welsh]] 'llawr' 'floor') meaning an area with small farming plots.
It was occupied for a short time by the [[Suebi]] in 414 until they were forced by the Romans to retreat to Galicia and later incorporated by Leovigild into the [[Visigoths]] kingdom in 585 A.D.
Later the [[Moors]] occupied the area until it was re-captured by the first King of Portugal, [[Afonso I of Portugal|Afonso Henriques]] in 1135, during the [[Reconquista]].  South of Leiria in that period was the so-called &quot;no-man's land&quot;, until regions further south (like [[Santarém, Portugal|Santarém]] and [[Lisbon]]) were permanently taken and re-populated by the [[Christians]]. In 1142 Afonso Henriques gave Leiria its first ''[[foral]]'' (compilation of feudal rights) to stimulate the colonisation of the region.

[[File:LeiriaSquare.jpg|thumb|left|Main square and [[Leiria Castle]] uphill.]]
Both [[Afonso Henriques|Afonso I of Portugal]] and [[Sancho I of Portugal|Sancho I]] rebuilt the walls and the [[Leiria Castle]] to avoid new enemy incursions. Most of the population lived inside the protective city walls, but already in the 12th century part of the population lived outside the walls. The oldest church of Leiria, the Church of Saint Peter (''Igreja de São Pedro''), built in [[Romanesque architecture|romanesque]] style in the last quarter of the 12th century, served the parish located outside the walls.

During the [[Middle Ages]] the importance of the village increased, and it was the setting of several ''[[Portuguese Cortes|cortes]]'' (feudal parliaments). The first of the ''cortes'' held in Leiria took place in 1245, under [[Afonso II of Portugal|King Afonso II]]. In the early 14th century, [[Denis of Portugal|King Dinis I]] restored the [[keep]] tower of the [[citadel]] of the castle, as can be seen in an inscription in the tower. He also built a royal residence in Leiria (now lost), and lived for long periods in the town, which he donated as feud to his wife, [[Elizabeth of Portugal|Isabel]]. The King also ordered the plantation of the famous Pine Forest of Leiria (''Pinhal de Leiria'') near the coast. Later, the wood from this forest would be used to build the ships used in the [[Age of Discovery|Portuguese Navigations]] of the 15th and 16th centuries.

In the late 14th century, [[John I of Portugal|King John I]] built a royal palace within the walls of the [[Leiria Castle|castle of Leiria]]. This palace, with elegant [[Gothic architecture|gothic]] galleries that offered wonderful views of the town and surrounding landscape, was totally in ruins but was partially rebuilt in the 20th century. John I also sponsored the rebuilding in late gothic style of the old Church of Our Lady of the Rock (''Igreja de Nossa Senhora da Pedra''), located inside the castle.

[[File:CASTELO DE LEIRIA.jpg|thumb|[[Leiria Castle]].]]
Towards the end of the 15th century the town continued to grow, occupying the area from the castle hill down to the river Lis. [[Manuel I of Portugal|King Manuel I]] gave it a new [[foral]] in 1510, and in 1545 it was elevated to the category of city and became see of a [[Diocese]]. The Cathedral of Leiria was built in the second half of the 16th century in a mix of late [[manueline]] and [[mannerist]] styles.

Compared to the Middle Ages, the subsequent history of Leiria is of relative decay. The city was stormed by the [[Peninsular War]], namely in 1808 (the killing of Portela, by the troops of [[:fr:Pierre Margaron|Gen. Margaron]]) and the Great Fire of 1811, caused by the [[Napoleonic wars|Napoleonic]] troops retreating from the [[Lines of Torres Vedras]]. In the 20th century, however, its strategic position in the Portuguese territory favoured the development of a diversified industry.

==Geography and location==
Leiria is located in the [[Centro Region]] and sub region of [[Pinhal Litoral]], about halfway between [[Lisbon]] and [[Porto]]. The distance to Lisbon is {{convert|137|km|0|abbr=off}}, to [[Coimbra]] {{convert|70|km|0|abbr=off}} and to [[Porto]] {{convert|177|km|0|abbr=off}}. The historic city centre spreads between the castle hill and the river Lis.

Leiria is also included in the [[Região de Leiria]]. As the main city in this community, the area of influence of Leiria spreads over the cities of [[Marinha Grande]], [[Ourém]], [[Fátima, Portugal|Fátima]], [[Pombal, Portugal|Pombal]] as well the municipalities/town seats of [[Batalha, Portugal|Batalha]] and [[Porto de Mós]] located nearby.

==Parishes==
Administratively, the municipality is divided into 18 civil parishes (''[[freguesia (Portugal)|freguesias]]''):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Law nr. 11-A/2013, page 552 61|url=http://dre.pt/pdf1sdip/2013/01/01901/0000200147.pdf |accessdate=24 July 2014|author=Diário da República |author-link=Diário da República |language=Portuguese|format=pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* Amor
* Arrabal
* Bajouca
* Bidoeira de Cima
* [[Caranguejeira]]
* Coimbrão
* Colmeias e Memória
* Leiria, Pousos, Barreira e Cortes
* Maceira
* Marrazes e Barosa
* Milagres
* [[Monte Real e Carvide]]
* Monte Redondo e Carreira
* Parceiros e Azoia
* Regueira de Pontes
* Santa Catarina da Serra e Chainça
* Santa Eufémia e Boa Vista
* Souto da Carpalhosa e Ortigosa
{{div col end}}

== Demographics ==
{| class=&quot;wikitable center&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;20&quot; | Demographic evolution of Leiria 
|-  style=&quot;background:silver; text-align:center; text-align:center;&quot;
|| 1801 
|| 1849 
|| 1900 
|| 1930
|| 1960
|| 1981
|| 1991
|| 2001
|| 2011
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
|| 37,930
|| 29,803
|| 54,422
|| 55,234
|| 82,988
|| 96,517
|| 102,762
|| 119,847
|| 126,879
|}
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=UMA POPULAÇÃO QUE SE URBANIZA|url=http://www.igeo.pt/atlas/Cap2/Cap2d_2.html|accessdate=16 October 2012|language=Portuguese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Climate==
The city of Leiria is located near the western coast, in the central region of Portugal, with a mainly Mediterranean climate (Csa) with Atlantic oceanic influence.
So it has cool and wet winters, relying on average 40 days of rain (330&amp;nbsp;mm) versus 50 dry days and 5 hours of sun per day. The average temperatures range between {{convert|15|°C|0|abbr=on}} and {{convert|7|°C|0|abbr=on}} and can lower the minimum at {{convert|-3|°C|0|abbr=on}} colder days, favoring the onset of frost or ice.
The springs are quite nice, being very rainy during the month of April. This season has an average of 43 days of rain {{convert|273|mm|0|abbr=on}} to 47 dry days and 7 hours of sunshine per day. The average temperatures range between {{convert|20|°C|0|abbr=on}} and {{convert|11|°C|0|abbr=on}}.
The summers bring high temperatures and sunshine, counting on average 18 days of rain {{convert|77|mm|0|abbr=on}} compared with 82 dry days and 9 hours of sunshine per day. Average temperatures range between {{convert|27|°C|0|abbr=on}} and {{convert|15|°C|0|abbr=on}}, the maximum can reach {{convert|35|°C|0|abbr=on}} on the hottest days.
The autumn, although mild, sometimes plagues the city with rain and wind and has on average 39 days of rain {{convert|339|mm|0|abbr=on}} compared to 51 dry days and 6 hours of sun per day. Average temperatures range between {{convert|21|°C|0|abbr=on}} and {{convert|12|°C|0|abbr=on}}.

Snowfalls in the city of Leiria typically occur once every 20 to 30 years. The last time it snowed in Leiria was on the 29th of 2006's January in a clammy Sunday between 10 and 12 am, during which the temperature peaked at {{convert|-3|°C|0|abbr=on}}.

==Culture==
In addition to being a site of historical interest, the castle of Leiria provides a venue for cultural events. Nearby is the Church of Saint Peter (''Igreja de São Pedro''), the site of the city's annual music festival. Leiria is home to the ''Museu da imagem em movimento'' (Museum of the Moving Image)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cm-leiria.pt/pages/722 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2015-06-26 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150627053914/http://www.cm-leiria.pt/pages/722 |archivedate=2015-06-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as Portugal's restored first paper mill, ''Moinho do Papel'' (The Paper Mill),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cm-leiria.pt/pages/311|title=Moinho do Papel - C.M. Leiria|website=www.cm-leiria.pt|accessdate=24 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Theatre Miguel Franco in the ''Mercado de Sant'Ana'' (Saint Anne's Market)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cm-leiria.pt/pages/604|title=Mercado de Sant'Ana - C.M. Leiria|website=www.cm-leiria.pt|accessdate=24 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Theatre José Lúcio da Silva&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.teatrojlsilva.pt/|title=Teatro José Lúcio da Silva|website=Teatro José Lúcio da Silva|accessdate=24 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; are venues for theatrical, musical, cinematic and dance performances.

Today the central square, ''Praça Francisco Rodrigues Lobo'', named after the Portuguese poet [[Francisco Rodrigues Lobo]], is home to a thriving café culture, regularly used for cultural events. The city was the principal residence of the Portuguese king, [[Denis of Portugal|Denis]], who wrote [[Trovadorismo|lyric poetry]] in the troubadour tradition, and the birthplace of the modern realist writer [[Eça de Queiroz]], whose first novel, [[O Crime do Padre Amaro]] (&quot;Father Amaro's Sin&quot;), published in 1875, is set in the city.

In October 2012, Leiria opened the city's &quot;Centro Cívico&quot;, a modern architecture building, designed to have social impact on the community. This building has the life of Eça de Queiroz as a theme. In here, there's senior classes and ''Associação Fazer Avançar'' runs SPEAK, with support from EDP and Calouste Gulbenkian Fundations, among others.

The city has several cultural entities like Leiria's Public Library Afonso Lopes Vieira, Arquivo, Ateneu, Leirena and O Nariz (theatre groups), Associação Fazer Avançar, FADE IN, Metamorfose, ECO and many others that make Leiria a culturally vibrant city, offering the busiest calendars of events.

In recent years, Leiria has seen much redevelopment on the banks of the river Liz, with the creation of several new parks, public spaces, children's play areas and a series of themed bridges. A long riverside promenade was built which is popular with walkers and joggers.

Since 2010, Associação FADE IN organizes ENTREMURALHAS, one of the most important gothic festivals in the world ([[List of gothic festivals]]).

===Gastronomy===

Leiria's gastronomy offers a good variety of Portuguese dishes including fresh fish dishes and the famous &quot;Leitão&quot; da Boavista (barbecued piglet/ [[suckling pig]]). 
The nearby village of Cortes is known for &quot;[[Migas]]&quot;, a dish of corn bread with spinach, garlic and olive oil which is eaten as an accompaniment to fish or meat.

'''Typical Dishes''': Morcela de Arroz; Negritos; Lentriscas; Bacalhoada com migas; Bacalhau com feijão frade; Ossinhos; Fritada; Cabrito; [[Feijoada]]; Leitão; Chanfana; Fritada dos peixinhos; Bacalhau com Chícharos.

'''Traditional sweet pastry''': [[Brisas do Lis]]; Lampreia de Ovos; Ovos Folhados; Bolinhos de [[Pine nut|Pinhão]]; Tarte de [[Lathyrus sativus|Chícharos]] (Alvaiázere); Canudos de Leiria; Doce de amêndoa; Broas Doces de Batata; Merendeiras dos Santos; Filhós de abóbora.

'''Wines of the region''' : Caves Vidigal, S.A./ Vale da Mata, Cortes / Quinta da Serrinha (Vin Bio), Barreira / Santos &amp; Santos, Torres Vedras / Quinta da Sapeira, Serra d'Aire / Paço Côrtes, Lda. IGP Lisboa, Sub-região Alta Estremadura. These wines are labeled D.O.C. ([[Denominação de Origem Controlada]]) which secures a superior quality. Also parte of the Portuguese wine region [[Encostas d'Aire DOC|Encostas de Aire (DOC)]].

===Panoramic view===
[[File:LEIRIA PANORAMICA.jpg|thumb|1000px|center|Panorama of Leiria.]]

==Economy==
Leiria has an economy concentrated on services and light industries. It has several industries related with plastics and moulds, as well as animal food, milling, cement, and civil construction, among other light industries. Agriculture, tourism, and state-run public services, such as education (including the [[Polytechnical Institute of Leiria]]), health (the [[district hospital]] ''Hospital de Santo André''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hsaleiria.min-saude.pt/ |title=Hospital de Santo André, EPE |publisher=Hsaleiria.min-saude.pt |date= |accessdate=2013-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;) and general public administration, are an important part of Leiria's economy.

[[Monte Real Air Base]], a major [[Military airbase]] of the [[Portuguese Air Force]] in [[Monte Real]], where all Portuguese [[General Dynamics F-16 Fighting Falcon|F16]] fighter squadrons are stationed, is also notable employer in the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Base Aérea Nº 5|url=http://www.emfa.pt/www/unidade-18-ba5|accessdate=16 October 2012|language=Portuguese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Castelo de Leiria 8.jpg|thumb|[[Gothic architecture|Gothic]] gallery in the Castle of Leiria.]]

==Transport==
Leiria is connected to its suburbs and the rest of Portugal by a motorway network. There are four motorways passing the city; 
* [[A1 - Auto-estrada do Norte]] linking [[Porto]] to [[Lisbon]], passing by Leiria.
* [[A8 motorway (Portugal)|A8]] linking Leiria to Lisbon.
* [[A17 motorway (Portugal)|A17]] linking [[Marinha Grande]] to [[Aveiro, Portugal|Aveiro]]. 
* [[A19 motorway (Portugal)|A19]], linking Leiria and Batalha, using part of the IC2.

There is a railway ''Linha do Oeste'' (west railway line linking Cacém ([[Sintra]]/Lisbon area) to [[Figueira da Foz]]) which serves the central western coast of Portugal. Leiria railway station is a few km from the city centre (about 2&amp;nbsp;km).

The main bus station service is in the city centre. The bus service, called Mobilis, is composed by 9 lines connecting surrounding neighbourhoods and parishes of Leiria with the city centre. This includes two bus loops and a specific line (uMob) that connects the city centre with Campus 1 and 2 of the [[Polytechnic Institute of Leiria|Instituto Politécnico de Leiria]]. 

There is a small [[airfield]] (''Aérodromo de Leiria''), used for sports and recreation.

==Leiria-based newspapers==

* Região de Leiria – Weekly
* Jornal de Leiria – Weekly
* Diário de Leiria – Daily
* O Mensageiro – Monthly

==Education==
Leiria hosts a national public [[polytechnic (Portugal)|polytechnic]] institution of [[higher education]], the [[Instituto Politécnico de Leiria]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=IP Leiria|url=http://www.ipleiria.pt/|accessdate=16 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; which has 5 campuses, 3 of them located in Leiria.
* Campus 1 - School of Education and Social Sciences (ESECS).
* Campus 2 - School of Technology and Management (ESTG) and the School Of Health Sciences (ESS)
* Campus 5 - Institute for Research, Development and Advanced Studies (INDEA), the Training Centre for the Courses of Technology Specialization (FOR.CET) with around 900 students, the Centre of New Opportunities (CNO), a Transfer Technology and Information Center (OTIC) and an E-Learning Unit (UED).
There is also a private institution, o Instituto Superior de Línguas e Administração (ISLA).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Instituto Superior de Línguas e Administração|url=http://www.leiria.unisla.pt/|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121108172629/http://leiria.unisla.pt/|archivedate=2012-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
 
In [[Secondary education]], Leiria has the following schools, the first two in the center, the last in the outskirts.
* Escola Secundária de Francisco Rodrigues Lobo (former Liceu)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Escola Secundária de Francisco Rodrigues Lobo (ESFRL)|url=http://www.esfrl.edu.pt/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Escola Secundária de Domingos Sequeira (former Escola Comercial)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Escola Secundária Domingos Sequeira|url=http://www.esds.edu.pt/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Escola Secundária de Afonso Lopes Vieira, in Gândara dos Olivais, Marrazes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Escola Secundária Afonso Lopes Vieira|url=http://esalv.pt/|url-status=dead|archiveurl=http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20120120232801/http%3A//esalv.pt/|archivedate=2012-01-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Primary education]], Leiria has the following schools, teaching from the 5th grade until 9th grade. 
* Escola D. Dinis&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Escola D. Dinis|url=http://aeddinis.ccems.pt/}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Escola Correia Mateus (with 1st cycle)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Escolas Dr. Correia Mateus|url=http://agcorreiamateus-m.ccems.pt/}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Escola José Saraiva&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cm-leiria.pt/pages/191|title=Escolas do Concelho de Leiria|website=www.cm-leiria.pt|language=pt-PT|access-date=2019-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Escola de Marrazes&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Escola Marrazes|url=http://eb23marrazes-m.ccems.pt/}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Colégio Dinis de Melo&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Colégio Dinis de Melo|url=http://www.cl-dinis-melo.pt/}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Colégio Senhor dos Milagres&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Colégio Senhor dos Milagres|url=http://www.colegiosenhormilagres.pt/}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Besides this there are multiple schools in the Municipality for the 1st cycle, from 1st grade until 4th grade.

==Sport==
[[File:Estadio de Leiria.jpg|thumb|[[Estádio Dr. Magalhães Pessoa|Stadium Dr. Magalhães Pessoa]]]]
The city of Leiria has its own [[Association football|football]] team, the [[UD Leiria|União Desportiva de Leiria]], commonly called just '''União de Leiria'''. It currently plays at the third level of [[Portugal|Portuguese]] football, in the [[Campeonato Nacional de Seniores]], but recently spent 16 seasons in the [[Primeira Liga]].

An important facility is the ''[[Estádio Dr. Magalhães Pessoa]]'', situated close to Leiria castle. The modern stadium has a capacity for 23,000 people and was built for the [[UEFA Euro 2004]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Venues Guide – Leiria |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport2/hi/football/euro_2004/venues_guide/3513299.stm |publisher=BBC Sport (British Broadcasting Corporation) |accessdate=17 June 2012 |date=25 May 2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Efforts were made to sell it, as its debt (nearly €50M) overburdens the city finances,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Câmara de Leiria admite vender estádio construído para o Euro 2004|url=http://www.publico.pt/desporto/noticia/camara-de-leiria-admite-vender-estadio-construido-para-o-euro-2004-1415650|accessdate=10 May 2015|work=Público|date=29 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Estádio de Leiria custa 16.750 euros por dia à Câmara|url=https://economico.sapo.pt/noticias/estadio-de-leiria-custa-16750-euros-por-dia-a-camara_195211.html|accessdate=10 May 2015|work=Sapo.pt|date=9 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  União de Leiria rents the stadium, but played the [[2011–12 Primeira Liga|2011-12]] season in [[Estádio Municipal da Marinha Grande]] due to a rent dispute.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Leiria constrói três relvados sintéticos na Marinha Grande|url=http://www.sol.pt/noticia/24401|accessdate=10 May 2015|work=Sol|date=18 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Leiria District|district]] football in Leiria is managed by the [[Leiria Football Association]], overseeing the regional leagues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Factos Históricos da A.F. Leiria|url=http://afleiria.fpf.pt/Associa%C3%A7%C3%A3o/Hist%C3%B3ria.aspx|work=afleiria.fpf.pt}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Regarding other sports, Leiria has a notable women's handball team, [[Juve Lis]], which plays in the [[1ª Divisão de Andebol Feminino|Women's Handball League]], and also participated in [[European Handball Federation|EHF]] competitions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=História|url=http://www.juvelis.pt/?m=pages&amp;page=juvelis&amp;id=6|work=juvelis.pt|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150416224937/http://juvelis.pt/?m=pages&amp;page=juvelis&amp;id=6|archivedate=2015-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=POR Juve Lis|url=http://www.eurohandball.com/ec/chc/women/2014-15/clubs/006506/Juve+Lis|work=EHF.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 2013 Leiria has had a chess academy (Academia de Xadrez) offered as an activity for young people by the Corvos do Lis. Enrolled students have won titles in National Competitions: second place by teams under 12 years old in 2014 and 2015 and a National Champion, (Blitz, 2013, Under 8) and (Super Rapid play, 2015, under 10). They work with many primary schools in the region teaching chess, considering it a useful complement to developing intellectual skills.&lt;ref name=Corvosdolis2015&gt;{{cite web|title=Clube Cultural e Desportivo Corvos do Lis|url=http://www.corvosdolis.com/xadrez/5a-etapa-mimo/|website=Corvosdolis.com|publisher=CorvosdoLis|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151218131209/http://www.corvosdolis.com/|archivedate=December 18, 2015|language=Portuguese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==International relations==
{{See also|List of twin towns and sister cities in Portugal}}
[[File:Friendshipcitiesleiria.jpg|thumb|Monument of the twin cities in Leiria|alt=|249x249px]]

According to the National Association of Portuguese Municipalities&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.anmp.pt/anmp/pro/mun1/gem101l0.php?cod_ent=M2400|title=Consulta|website=www.anmp.pt|access-date=2019-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;, Leiria is [[Twin towns and sister cities|twinned]] with:

*{{flagicon|JPN}} [[Tokushima]], Japan (since 1969)
*{{flagicon|POR}} [[Setúbal District|Setúbal]], Portugal (since 1982)&lt;ref name=&quot;São Paulo twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www3.prefeitura.sp.gov.br/cadlem/secretarias/negocios_juridicos/cadlem/integra.asp?alt=11072007L%20144710000|title=Pesquisa de Legislação Municipal - No 14471|work=Prefeitura da Cidade de São Paulo [Municipality of the City of São Paulo]|language=Portuguese|trans-title=Research Municipal Legislation - No 14471|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111018123138/http://www3.prefeitura.sp.gov.br/cadlem/secretarias/negocios_juridicos/cadlem/integra.asp?alt=11072007L%20144710000|archivedate=2011-10-18|accessdate=2013-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;São Paulo WikiSource&quot;&gt;[http://pt.wikisource.org/wiki/Lei_Municipal_de_S%C3%A3o_Paulo_14471_de_2007 Lei Municipal de São Paulo 14471 de 2007] WikiSource {{in lang|pt}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|FRA}} [[Saint-Maur-des-Fossés]], France (since 1982)
*{{flagicon|BRA}} [[Maringá]], Brazil (since 1982)&lt;ref name=&quot;Leiria Town Hall&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cm-leiria.pt/PageGen.aspx?WMCM_PaginaId=30748|title=Câmara Municipal de Leiria|publisher=Cm-leiria.pt|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131109045038/http://www.cm-leiria.pt/PageGen.aspx?WMCM_PaginaId=30748|archivedate=2013-11-09|accessdate=2013-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|ESP}} [[Olivenza]], Spain (since 1984)
*{{flagicon|ARG}} [[Olavarría, Argentina|Olavarría]], Argentina (since 1992)&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cm-leiria.pt/pages/890|title=Geminações|website=www.cm-leiria.pt|language=pt-PT|access-date=2019-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|CPV}} [[São Filipe, Cape Verde|São Filipe]], Cape Verde (since 1994)
*{{flagicon|GER}} [[Rheine]], Germany (since 1996)
*{{flagicon|UK}} [[Borough of Halton|Halton]], United Kingdom (since 1997)
*{{flagicon|China}} [[Tongling]], China (since 1999)
*{{flagicon|Mozambique}} [[Nampula]], Mozambique (since 2002)
*{{flagicon|FRA}} [[Quint-Fonsegrives]], France (since 2013)
*{{flagicon|China}} [[Penglai, Shandong|Penglai]], China (since 2014)&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

== See also ==
{{portal|Portugal}}
* [[Centro Region, Portugal]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*{{cite EB1911|wstitle=Leiria |volume=16 |short=x}}
* [http://www.cm-leiria.pt Municipality of Leiria]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090922222942/http://www.cm-leiria.pt/pagegen.asp?SYS_PAGE_ID=835308 Mobilis Municipal Bus (in Portuguese)]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090306183754/http://portaldeleiria.com/ Portal of Leiria (Business and Social Network)]
* [https://www.flickr.com/photos/vitor107/sets/1444890/ Photos from Leiria]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090705221419/http://www.leiria2009.com/ 2009 European Team Championships]

{{Municipalities of Leiria}}

[[Category:Municipalities of Portugal]]
[[Category:Populated places in Leiria District]]
[[Category:Leiria| ]]
[[Category:Cities in Portugal]]
[[Category:Municipalities of Leiria District]]</text>
      <sha1>ragda43x3555pxdnwwoigstqezt9u4k</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
