  <page>
    <title>Luge</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>37779</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931051423</id>
      <parentid>929703154</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-16T17:21:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>71.224.248.19</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{for|the wheeled vehicle|Street luge}}
{{More citations needed|date=February 2010}}
{{Infobox sport
|name       = '''Luge'''
|image      = Départ d'un lugeur.jpg
|imagesize  = 250px
|caption    = Departing German luger at the 2010 Olympics
|union      = ''[[Fédération Internationale de Luge de Course]]''
|nickname   =
|first      = 1870s
|registered = 
|clubs      = 
|contact    = No
|team       = Teams of 1 or 2
|mgender    = Yes, but usually in separate competitions
|category   = Winter sport, Time trial
|equipment  = Sled, helmet, suit, visor, gloves, finger spikes, booties
|venue      = [[List of bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton tracks|Luge tracks]]
|obsolete   =
|olympic    = Part of Winter Olympic program in 1964 to 2026
}}
A '''luge''' {{IPAc-en|l|uː|ʒ}} is a small one- or two-person [[sled]] on which one sleds [[Supine position|supine]] (face up) and feet-first. A luger steers by using their [[Calf (leg)|calf]] muscles to flex the sled's runners or by exerting opposite shoulder pressure to the seat. Racing sleds weigh {{convert|21|–|25|kg|lb|abbr=on}} for singles and {{convert|25|–|30|kg|lb|abbr=on}} for doubles.&lt;ref name=&quot;usaluge2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.teamusa.org/~/media/USA_Luge/Documents/IRO_2014_AT_English.pdf|title=Rules of Artificial Track Luge|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Luge is also the name of an Olympic sport.

Lugers can reach speeds of 140&amp;nbsp;km/h (87&amp;nbsp;mph). [[Austrians|Austrian]] [[Manuel Pfister]] reached a top speed of 154&amp;nbsp;km/h (96&amp;nbsp;mph) on a [[The Whistler Sliding Centre|track in Whistler]], [[Canada]], prior to the [[2010 Winter Olympics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.xinhuanet.com/english2010/sports/2010-02/13/c_13174368.htm |title=Whistler's fast luge track poised risky |publisher=News.xinhuanet.com |date=2010-02-13 |accessdate=2011-11-25 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100216130157/http://news.xinhuanet.com/english2010/sports/2010-02/13/c_13174368.htm |archivedate=2010-02-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Lugers compete against a timer in one of the most precisely timed sports in the world—to one one-thousandth of a second on artificial tracks.

The first recorded use of the term &quot;luge&quot; dates to 1905 and derives from the [[Savoy]]/[[Switzerland|Swiss]] dialect of the [[French language|French]] word ''luge'', meaning &quot;small coasting sled.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=luge |title=Online Etymology Dictionary |publisher=Etymonline.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.motionvideo.co.nz/kjhkj/extreme-sport-articles/extreme-sports-disicplines/293-lugel.html|title=Luge, extreme sport disciplines|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160611010017/http://www.motionvideo.co.nz/kjhkj/extreme-sport-articles/extreme-sports-disicplines/293-lugel.html|archivedate=2016-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Luge sled.jpg|thumb|left|Luge sled, with steel runners removed.]]
[[File:Young luger.jpg|thumb|left|A young luger on the start ramp at the Utah Olympic track.]]
The  very practical use of sleds is ancient and widespread. The first recorded sled races took place in Norway sometime during the 15th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;usaluge1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://usaluge.org/aboutluge/history.php/ |title=United States Luge Association |publisher=Usaluge.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The sport of luge, like the [[Skeleton (sport)|skeleton]] and the [[bobsleigh]], originated in the health-spa town of [[St Moritz]], [[Switzerland]], in the mid-to-late 19th century, through the endeavours of hotel entrepreneur [[Caspar Badrutt]]. Badrutt successfully sold the idea of winter resorting, as well as rooms with food, drink, and activities. His more adventurous English guests began adapting delivery boys' sleds for recreation, which led to collisions with pedestrians as they sped down the lanes and alleys of the village.

The first organized meeting of the sport took place in 1883 in [[Switzerland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fil-luge.org/ |title=International Luge Federation |publisher=Fil-luge.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1913, the Internationale Schlittensportverband or International Sled Sports Federation was founded in [[Dresden]], [[Germany]]. This body governed the sport until 1935, when it was incorporated in the [[Fédération Internationale de Bobsleigh et de Tobogganing]] (FIBT, International Bobsleigh and Tobogganing Federation). After it had been decided that luge would replace the sport of [[Skeleton (sport)|skeleton]] at the [[Olympic Games]], the first [[FIL World Luge Championships|World Championships]] in the sport were held in [[FIL World Luge Championships 1955|1955]] in [[Oslo]] ([[Norway]]). In 1957, the [[Fédération Internationale de Luge de Course]] (FIL, International Luge Federation) was founded. Luge events were first included in the [[Olympic Winter Games]] in [[Luge at the 1964 Winter Olympics|1964]].

Americans were slow to adopt the sport of luge. The first luge run in North America was built at [[Lolo Hot Springs, Montana]], in 1965.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Delta Sky Mag|date=January 2011|pages=124}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
| last = Briggeman
| first = Kim
| title = Lolo Hot Springs was home to first, 'pretty crude' American luge run
| work = [[Missoulian]]
| accessdate = 2014-02-07
| date = 2014-02-06
| url = http://missoulian.com/news/state-and-regional/lolo-hot-springs-was-home-to-first-pretty-crude-american/article_1f7f3830-8f93-11e3-830f-0019bb2963f4.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the United States competed in every Olympic luge event from 1964 through 1976, it was not until 1979 that the United States Luge Association was founded. The first artificial American track was completed in that year for use in the 1980 XIII Winter Olympic Games at Lake Placid, New York.&lt;ref name=&quot;usaluge1&quot;/&gt;
Since that time the United States luge program has greatly improved. A second artificial track was constructed near [[Park City, Utah]], for the 2002 XIX Olympic Winter Games at Salt Lake City.

Caitlin Nash and Natalie Corless, both of Canada, became the first all-female team to compete in a World Cup doubles race in luge in 2019.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.thestar.com/sports/2019/12/14/canadian-lugers-caitlin-nash-and-natalie-corless-become-the-first-female-team-to-compete-in-a-world-cup-doubles-race.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Artificial tracks==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-C0223-0007-003, Friedrichroda, Deutsche Meisterschaften, Rennrodeln.jpg|thumb|right|German luger [[Thomas Köhler]] in 1964]]
[[File:Mortensen and Griffall.jpg|thumb|Matt Mortensen (top) and Preston Griffall (bottom) are clocked at 80 miles per hour on a run at Sanki Sliding Centre in Krasnaya Polyana, Russia.]]

[[File:Utah Olympic track.jpg|thumb|Curves 11 and 12 on the Utah Olympic track near Park City, Utah.]]
{{Details|List of bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton tracks}}

Artificial luge tracks have specially designed and constructed banked curves plus walled-in straights. Most tracks are artificially refrigerated, but artificial tracks without artificial cooling also exist (for example, in [[St. Moritz]]). Tracks tend to be very smooth.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

The athletes ride in a flat, aerodynamic position on the sled, keeping their heads low to minimize air resistance. They steer the sled mainly with their calves by applying pressure on the runners—right calf to turn left, left calf to turn right. It takes a precise mix of shifting body weight, applying pressure with calves and rolling the shoulders. There are also handles for minor adjustments. A successful luger maintains complete concentration and relaxation on the sled while traveling at high speeds. Most lugers &quot;visualize&quot; the course in their minds before sliding.{{citation needed|date=October 2012}} Fastest times result from following the perfect &quot;line&quot; down the track. Any slight error, such as brush against the wall, costs time. Track conditions are also important. Softer ice tends to slow speeds, while harder ice tends to lead to faster times. Lugers race at speeds averaging {{convert|120|–|145|km/h|mph|abbr=on}} around high banked curves while experiencing a centripetal acceleration of up to 5g. Men's Singles have their start locations near where the [[bobsled]] and [[skeleton(sport)|skeleton]] competitors start at most tracks, while both the Doubles and Women's Singles competition have their starthouse located farther down the track. Artificial track luge is the fastest and most agile sledding sport.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

==Natural track luge==
{{Details|List of natural luge tracks}}
Natural tracks are adapted from existing mountain roads and paths. Artificially banked curves are not permitted.&lt;ref name=&quot;NTRules2014&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Rules of Natural Track Luge|url=http://www.fil-luge.org/fileadmin/user_upload/Documents/IRO/IRO_2014_NB_English_komplett_web.pdf|website=FIL}}&lt;/ref&gt; The track's surface should be horizontal. They are naturally iced. Tracks can get rough from the braking and steering action. Athletes use a steering rein and drag their hands and use their legs in order to drive around the tight flat corners. Braking is often required in front of curves and is accomplished by the use of spikes built on the bottom of the shoes.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

Most of the tracks are situated in Austria and Italy, with others in Germany, Poland, Russia, Slovenia, Canada, Switzerland, Croatia, Liechtenstein, Turkey, Sweden, Finland, Norway, Bulgaria, Romania, New Zealand and the United States. The Upper Peninsula Luge Club&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://upluge.org/ |title= The Upper Peninsula Luge Club |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2015-03-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Negaunee, Michigan]], is home to one of only five lighted natural track luge runs in the world, and the only natural track in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first =  Sarah |last = O'Neill |title=Negaunee Luge Hill Open for Public Use|url=http://www.thenorthwindonline.com/negaunee-luge-hill-open-for-public-use/|accessdate=2015-03-03|work=The North Wind |location= Northern Michigan University |date=2009-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; The over 800 meter (half-mile) track features 29 curves along its {{convert|88|m|ft|adj=on|sp=us}} vertical drop. The club hosts international luge events and offers luge instruction to the public during the winter months.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

[[FIL World Luge Natural Track Championships|World championships]] have been held since [[FIL World Luge Natural Track Championships 1979|1979]] while [[FIL European Luge Natural Track Championships|European championships]] have been held since [[FIL European Luge Natural Track Championships 1970|1970]].

==Events==
There are five luge disciplines.
*Men's singles
*Men's doubles
*Women's singles
*Women's doubles
*Team relay (Olympic discipline starting in 2014)
These are further broken into several age classes - multiple youth and junior classes that cover the range of age 7–20, and general class (ages 21 and older).&lt;ref name=&quot;usaluge2&quot;/&gt;  Older competitors may enjoy the sport in masters (age 30–50), and senior masters (age 51+) classes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.teamusa.org/USA-Luge |title= United States Luge Association |publisher=usaluge.org |date= |accessdate=2015-03-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In a team relay competition, one man, one woman, and a doubles pair form a team. A touchpad at the bottom of the run is touched by a competitor signaling a teammate at the top of the run to start.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

Rules and procedures for races are very precise:
* A drawing is held to determine start order for the race. Athletes are assigned a number which is displayed on a bib. During major national and international events, men's singles consists of four runs. Women's singles and doubles competitions consist of two runs. The cumulative time of all runs is used to determine finish order. In all three events, the start order after the first run is determined by the outcome of the previous run, with the last-place slider sliding first, the next-to-last place slider sliding second, and so forth, with the leader of the previous run sliding last.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;
* Physical measurements of the sled are taken, and the temperature of the sled's steel blades is checked and may not be more than {{convert|5|°C}} above that of a previously established control temperature. Additionally, for artificial track races, the athlete must first be weighed. This is to determine whether the athlete is entitled to carry extra weight on their body while sliding. Men may use additional weight amounting to 75% of the difference between body weight and a base weight of {{convert|90|kg}}. Women may use additional weight amounting to 50% of the difference between body weight and a base weight of {{convert|70|kg}}. Doubles athletes may use additional weight amounting to 50% of the difference between body weight and a base weight of {{convert|90|kg}}. Additional weight is not allowed if the body weight of the front person and back person together exceeds {{convert|180|kg}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; If one of the partners weighs more than {{convert|90|kg}}, the weight exceeding the {{convert|90|kg}} mark is added to the lighter partner. If there should still be a difference between the partner's weight and the {{convert|90|kg}} mark, the difference can be compensated according to an official weight table.&lt;ref name=&quot;usaluge2&quot;/&gt; Between runs, athletes are randomly selected for additional weight checks. Before each run, the sled (with the athlete, for artificial track races) is weighed at the start ramp.
* Once an athlete is on their sled, they are audibly notified that the track is clear. At this point, a tone sounds and the athlete has thirty seconds to begin their run. A run becomes official when an athlete and their sled, in contact with one another, crosses the finish line. If an athlete and sled are not within contact of one another, the athlete is disqualified from further competition. Disqualifications may also take place for any violation of rules and regulations. Certain disqualifications may be appealed.&lt;ref name=&quot;usaluge2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

==Training==
The sport of luge requires an athlete to balance mental and physical fitness. Physically, a luger must have strong neck, upper body, abdominal, and thigh muscles. Athletes also use Wind Tunnels to train&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://freshwater-and-saltwater.webnode.com/title=Rules to play Luge|last=|first=|date=|website=|publisher=|access-date=|title=Freshwater-and-saltwater}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Strength training]] is essential to withstand the extreme G-forces of tight turns at high speeds. Since lugers have very little protection other than a visor and helmet, they must be able to endure the physical pounding administered by the track when mistakes are made.

==Risks==
As with many [[extreme sports]], luging has risks. Though most injuries involve bumps, bruises, broken bones and concussions, fatalities do occasionally occur. [[Georgia (country)|Georgian]] luger [[Nodar Kumaritashvili]] suffered a fatal crash during his final practice run for the [[2010 Winter Olympics]] on the [[Whistler Sliding Centre]] in [[Whistler, British Columbia]], [[Canada]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2010/SPORT/02/12/olympic.luge.crash/index.html|title=Olympic Luger Dies on Track Where Speed Caused Concern|last=|first=|date=|website=|publisher=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hours later, the [[International Luge Federation]] concluded that the accident was caused by a steering error and not a track error; nevertheless, changes to the track were made before the re-opening.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vancouver2010.com/olympic-news/n/news/fil-statement-on-mens-luge-competition_274462nE.html |title=Joint VANOC/FIL statement |publisher=Vancouver2010.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kumaritashvili was the fourth athlete to die while in preparation for a Winter Olympics competition, following speed skier [[Nicolas Bochatay]], aged 27, who died while preparing for the [[Albertville 1992]] games; and [[United Kingdom|British]] luger [[Kazimierz Kay-Skrzypecki]] and skier [[Ross Milne]], aged 19, who both died in the run-up to the [[Innsbruck 1964]] games.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;

==Governing body==
The sport of luge is governed by the FIL, Fédération International de Luge de Course. The FIL is located in [[Berchtesgaden]], Germany, and includes 53 member nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fil-luge.org/index.php?id=402 |title=Member Countries – International Luge Federation |publisher=Fil-luge.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is traditionally dominated by German representatives, however.

The following persons have been president of the FIL:
* [[Bert Isatitsch]], [[Austria]] (1957–1994)
* [[Josef Fendt]], [[Germany]] (1994–current)

==Olympic medal table==
[[File:Rodel-Weltcup-2005-Oberhof-Hackl.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A man with a goatee wears a red-white-and-yellow tight jumpsuit, with a red-and-white vest over it, and a red helmet with a raised full-faced visor. He shows a concentrated look. Partially hidden behind him is another man, wearing a black tracksuit jacket and winter cap.|[[Georg Hackl]] of [[Germany at the Olympics|Germany]] is the most successful Olympic luger, having won five medals, of which three are gold medals attained in three consecutive Olympics.]]
[[File:Rodel-Weltcup-2005-Oberhof-Zoeggeler cropped.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A man with a soul patch wears a red-and-white tight jumpsuit, with a red-and-white vest over it, and a metallic silver helmet with a raised full-faced visor. He is sat on the ground with his arms resting upon his legs.|[[Armin Zöggeler]] is an [[Italy at the Olympics|Italian]] luger, and is [[List of multiple Olympic medalists in one event|the first]] - and so far the only - athlete to have won one medal in six consecutive Olympics.]]
[[File:Rodel-WM2008-Herren-Sieger2.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Three smiling men stand side-by-side in front of a crowd of photographers. Each holds up a flower bouquet with their right arm, and wears the same tight black-and-white jumpsuit with some yellow and red stripes. The man on the left wears a white cap, while the one in the middle wears a red headband.|German lugers [[Felix Loch]] (''center'') and [[David Möller]] (left) occupied the first and second places, respectively, of the men's singles at the [[2010 Winter Olympics]].]]
[[File:NodarKumaritashvili-AccidentLocation-WhistlerSlidingCentre-20100215.jpg|thumb|left|Spectators at the [[Whistler Sliding Centre]] watching lugers pass the point on the track where Kumaritashvili crashed and died.]]

{{Main|Luge at the Winter Olympics}}
{{Details|List of Olympic medalists in luge}}

===Men's singles===

up to: 2014
{{Medals table
 | caption        = 
 | host           = 
 | flag_template  = flagIOC
 | event          = 
 | team           = 
 | gold_GER = 10 | silver_GER = 7 | bronze_GER = 6
 | gold_ITA = 3 | silver_ITA = 2 | bronze_ITA = 3
 | gold_AUT = 1 | silver_AUT = 2 | bronze_AUT = 2
 | gold_RUS = 0 | silver_RUS = 3 | bronze_RUS = 2
 | gold_LAT = 0 | silver_LAT = 0 | bronze_LAT = 1
}}

===Doubles===

up to: 2014
{{Medals table
 | caption        = 
 | host           = 
 | flag_template  = flagIOC
 | event          = 
 | team           = 
 | gold_GER = 10 | silver_GER = 4 | bronze_GER = 6
 | gold_AUT = 3 | silver_AUT = 3 | bronze_AUT = 2
 | gold_ITA = 2 | silver_ITA = 2 | bronze_ITA = 3
 | gold_USA = 0 | silver_USA = 2 | bronze_USA = 2
 | gold_LAT = 0 | silver_LAT = 1 | bronze_LAT = 1
 | gold_RUS = 0 | silver_RUS = 1 | bronze_RUS = 0
}}

===Women's singles===

up to: 2014
{{Medals table
 | caption        = 
 | host           = 
 | flag_template  = flagIOC
 | event          = 
 | team           = 
 | gold_GER = 10 | silver_GER = 12 | bronze_GER = 9
 | gold_ITA = 2 | silver_ITA = 0 | bronze_ITA = 0
 | gold_AUT = 1 | silver_AUT = 2 | bronze_AUT = 3
 | gold_RUS = 1 | silver_RUS = 0 | bronze_RUS = 1
 | gold_USA = 0 | silver_USA = 0 | bronze_USA = 1
}}

===Team relay===

up to: 2014
{{Medals table
 | caption        = 
 | host           = 
 | flag_template  = flagIOC
 | event          = 
 | team           = 
 | gold_GER = 1 | silver_GER = 0 | bronze_GER = 0
 | gold_RUS = 0 | silver_RUS = 1 | bronze_RUS = 0
 | gold_LAT = 0 | silver_LAT = 0 | bronze_LAT = 1
}}

===Total Olympic ranking===

up to: 2014
{{Medals table
 | caption        = 
 | host           = 
 | flag_template  = flagIOC
 | event          = 
 | team           = 
 | gold_GER = 31 | silver_GER = 23 | bronze_GER = 21 | note_GER = {{ref|a|[a]}}
 | gold_ITA = 7 | silver_ITA = 4 | bronze_ITA = 6
 | gold_AUT = 5 | silver_AUT = 7 | bronze_AUT = 7
 | gold_RUS = 1 | silver_RUS = 5 | bronze_RUS = 3 | note_RUS = {{ref|b|[b]}}
 | gold_USA = 0 | silver_USA = 2 | bronze_USA = 3
 | gold_LAT = 0 | silver_LAT = 1 | bronze_LAT = 3
}}
* {{note|a|[a]}} including East Germany and West Germany
* {{note|b|[b]}} including Soviet Union

==Fatal accidents==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 85%;&quot;
|-
! Competitor
! Year
! Track
! Race
! Event
|-
| {{flagicon|UK}} [[Kazimierz Kay-Skrzypeski]]
| 1964
| {{flagicon|AUT}} [[Olympic Sliding Centre Innsbruck|Innsbruck]]
| Training run
| [[1964 Winter Olympics]]
|-
| {{flagicon|POL}} [[Stanisław Paczka]]
| 1969
| {{flagicon|GER}} [[Königssee bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|Königssee]]
| First run
| [[FIL World Luge Championships 1969]]
|-
| {{flagicon|GEO}} [[Nodar Kumaritashvili]]
| 2010
| {{flagicon|CAN}} [[The Whistler Sliding Centre|Whistler]]
| Training run
| [[2010 Winter Olympics]]
|}

==See also==
{{Portal|Sports}}
*[[FIL World Luge Championships|World Luge Championships]]
*[[FIL World Luge Natural Track Championships|World Luge Natural Track Championships]]
*[[List of Luge World Cup champions]]
*[[FIL European Luge Championships|European Luge Championships]]
*[[FIL European Luge Natural Track Championships|European Luge Natural Track Championships]]
*[[Bobsleigh]]
*[[Skeleton (sport)|Skeleton]]
*[[Toboggan]]
*[[Street luge]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Luge}}
*[http://www.fil-luge.org/ International Luge Federation]
*[http://www.bsd-portal.de/ Bob- und Schlittenverband für Deutschland/German Luge Federation]
*[http://www.rodel-austria.at/ Österreichischer Rodelverband/Austrian Luge Federation]
*[http://www.usaluge.org/ United States Luge Association]
*[http://upluge.org/ Natural Track: Upper Peninsula Luge Club of Michigan, USA]
*[http://www.cbdg.org.br/ Brazilian Luge Federation]
*[http://www.gbla.org.uk/ British Luge Association]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090122070119/http://sanjkanje.hr/ Croatian Luge Federation]
*{{YouTube|cG1uWOVn2Jo|POV Lake Placid Olympic track}}
*{{YouTube|i5Ln-hUAC_w|POV Utah Olympic track}}
*{{YouTube|-emRB_DJjjk|POV Whistler Olympic track}}
*{{YouTube|wFvTaATElf4|POV Oberhof track}}
*{{YouTube|mEI26CnBD-w|POV Calgary Olympic track}}
*{{YouTube|Xvc5LhPzEgY|POV Altenberg track}}
*{{YouTube|t4QvvA7o4wU|Mark Grimmette describes doubles luge}}

{{Bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton}}
{{Winter Olympic sports}}
{{Extreme sports}}

[[Category:Luge| ]]
[[Category:Winter Olympic sports]]
[[Category:Racing vehicles]]
[[Category:Racing]]
[[Category:Sledding]]
[[Category:Winter sports]]
[[Category:Human-powered vehicles]]
[[Category:Sliding vehicles]]
[[Category:Sports originating in Switzerland]]</text>
      <sha1>8qt99a3z1326bf6enhsnw3ms7ryx082</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
