  <page>
    <title>Mashkan-shapir</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21944604</id>
    <revision>
      <id>925621423</id>
      <parentid>902890967</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-11T07:41:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BHGbot</username>
        <id>5737366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WP:BRFA/BHGbot 4|BHGbot 4]]: replace links to deleted portals: [[Portal:Mesopotamia]] (aka [[Portal:Ancient Near East]]) → [[Portal:Asia]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Hammurabi's Babylonia 1.svg|300px|right|thumb|[[Babylonia]] at the time of [[Hammurabi]], [[circa|ca.]] 1792-1750 BC]]
{{Coord|32|13|42.7|N|45|18|24.5|E|display=title}}
'''Mashkan-shapir''' (modern '''Tell Abu Duwari''', [[Al Qadisyah Governorate]],  [[Iraq]]) was an ancient  ''[[Tell (archaeology)|tell]]'' (hill city)  in the [[Ancient Near East]] roughly {{convert|30|km}} north
of [[Nippur]] and around {{convert|90|mi}} southeast of [[Baghdad]].

The city god of Mashkan-shapir was [[Nergal]] and a temple named Meslam dedicated to him was built there.

==History==
Though occupied during the [[Uruk period]], the town's first epigraphic appearance was during the [[Akkadian Empire|Akkadian]] period in a minor context, and then during the [[Ur III period]] as a location for royal shepherds. A brick of [[Amar-Sin]] was also found at the site. Mashkan-shapir achieved prominence during the [[First Babylonian dynasty|Old Babylonian]] period. This time of occupation is considered to begin with the construction of the city walls by [[Sin-Iddinam]] of [[Larsa]]. The city was abandoned during the reign of [[Samsu-iluna]], successor to [[Hammurabi]] of the [[First Babylonian dynasty]] and not re-occupied until late in the first millennium. The city's demise was part of a general collapse and abandonment of sites in the region at that time.

After rising to importance under the Larsa city-state, Mashkan-shapir became part of the Babylonian empire after the defeat of Larsa by Hammurabi following a long siege. At the time, Babylon and Larsa were engaged in a struggle for dominance in the region.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=tiHwDe7JmCEC&amp;printsec=frontcover] Wolfgang Heimpel, Letters to the King of Mari: A New Translation, with Historical Introduction, Notes, and Commentary, Eisenbrauns, 2003, {{ISBN|1-57506-080-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Note that the modern name of the site is in some doubt. Other possible names are Ishan Chebir and Tell Naim. The Tell Abu Duwari identification was the first and is used in archaeological publications.

==Archaeology==
The site of Mashkan-shapir covers about 56 hectares and is divided into
a number of sections by the beds of ancient canals and rivers. It is
especially important from an archaeological standpoint because it is
a single level site. Most cities in the Ancient Near East have been
built and rebuilt many times over history, obscuring our understanding
of individual time periods.

Tell Abu Duwari was first noted, as site 639, in the Nippur survey of Robert McCormick Adams of the [[University of Chicago Oriental Institute|Oriental Institute]] at the [[University of Chicago]].
&lt;ref&gt;Robert M. Adams, Heartland of Cities. Surveys of Ancient Settlement and Land Use on the Central Floodplain of the Euphrates, University of Chicago Press, pp. 256-257, 1981, {{ISBN|0-226-00544-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The site was excavated for a total of five months in three seasons between 1987 and 1990 by an [[American Schools of Oriental Research]] and [[National Geographic Society]] team led by Elizabeth Stone and Paul Zimansky.
&lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth C. Stone, The Tell Abu Duwari Project, Iraq, 1987,
Journal of Field Archaeology, vol. 17, no. 2, pp. 141-162, 1990&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth C. Stone and Paul Zimansky, The Tell Abu Duwari Project, 1988-1990, Journal of Field Archaeology, vol. 21, no. 4, pp. 437-455, 1994&lt;/ref&gt;
A key find was that of foundation deposits commemorating the city walls
being built by Sin-Iddinam, which allowed the city to be identified. As part
of the work, satellite images were taken and a complete surface
mapping was made using a kite lofted camera and coordinate markers.

Excavations at Mashkan-shapir ended with the invasion of [[Kuwait]] by
[[Iraq]] in 1990, interrupting a planned long term research program.
Subsequently, the site has been heavily looted to the point where any
further archaeological work would probably be pointless.

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Asia}}
* [[Cities of the ancient Near East]]
* [[Tell (archaeology)]]
* [[Short chronology timeline]]

==References==
*Elizabeth C. Stone and Paul Zimansky, The Tapestry of Power in a Mesopotamian City, Scientific American, vol. 15, no. 1, 2005
*Elizabeth C. Stone and Paul Zimansky, Mashkan-shapir and the Anatomy of an Old Babylonian City, The Biblical Archaeologist, vol. 55, no. 4, pp.&amp;nbsp;212–218, 1992
*[https://books.google.com/books?id=5iSSBg8lq-0C&amp;printsec=frontcover] Elizabeth Caecilia Stone, Paul E. Zimansky, Piotr Steinkeller, Vincent C. Pigott, The Anatomy of a Mesopotamian City: Survey and Soundings at Mashkan-shapir, Eisenbrauns, 2004, {{ISBN|1-57506-082-5}}
*Elizabeth C. Stone, The Ur III-Old Babylonian Transition: An Archaeological Perspective, Iraq, vol. 64, pp.&amp;nbsp;79–84, 2002

==External links==
*[http://cdli.ucla.edu/tools/yearnames/HTML/T12K7.htm Year Named of Samsu-iluna at CDLI]
*[https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1D81639F932A25757C0A96F948260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all New York Times article on the discovery of Mashkan-Shapir]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mashkan-Shapir}}
[[Category:Al-Qādisiyyah Governorate]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites in Iraq]]
[[Category:Former populated places in Iraq]]</text>
      <sha1>ah9ognxy79qyiz6ckqqekg003j6dzqj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
