  <page>
    <title>Mehsi</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22162687</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936215337</id>
      <parentid>928376683</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-17T12:03:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>122.182.236.49</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Location */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2018}}
{{Use Indian English|date=July 2018}}
{{cleanup|reason=Grammar needs improving|date=October 2016}}
{{Infobox settlement
| name                    = Mehsi
| native_name             = 
| native_name_lang        = 
| other_name              = 
| nickname                = 
| settlement_type         = city
| image_skyline           = 
| image_alt               = 
| image_caption           = 
| pushpin_map             = India Bihar
| pushpin_label_position  = right
| pushpin_map_alt         = 
| pushpin_map_caption     = Location in Bihar, India
| coordinates             = {{coord|26.35|N|85.11|E|display=inline,title}}
| subdivision_type        = Country
| subdivision_name        = {{flag|India}}
| subdivision_type1       = [[States and territories of India|State]]
| subdivision_name1       = [[Bihar]]
| subdivision_type2       = [[List of districts of India|District]]
| subdivision_name2       = [[East Champaran district|East Champaran]]
| established_title       = &lt;!-- Established --&gt;
| established_date        = 
| founder                 = 
| named_for               = 
| government_type         = 
| governing_body          = 
| unit_pref               = Metric
| area_footnotes          = 
| area_rank               = 
| area_total_km2          = 
| elevation_footnotes     = 
| elevation_m             = 51
| population_total        = 
| population_as_of        = 
| population_rank         = 
| population_density_km2  = auto
| population_demonym      = 
| population_footnotes    = 
| demographics_type1      = Languages
| demographics1_title1    = Official
| demographics1_info1     = [[Maithili language|Maithili]], [[Hindi language|Hindi]] , Bhojpuri
| timezone1               = [[Indian Standard Time|IST]]
| utc_offset1             = +5:30
| postal_code_type        = [[Postal Index Number|PIN]]
| postal_code             = 845426
| area_code_type          = Telephone code
| area_code               = +91-6257
| registration_plate      = 
| blank1_name_sec1        = Coastline
| blank1_info_sec1        = {{Convert|0|km|mi}}
| blank2_name_sec1        = Nearest city
| blank2_info_sec1        = Muzaffarpur, Motihari and Chakia
| blank3_name_sec1        = [[Lok Sabha]] constituency
| blank3_info_sec1        = Motihari
| blank1_name_sec2        = Avg. summer temperature
| blank1_info_sec2        = {{convert|42|°C|°F}}
| website                 = {{URL|eastchamparan.bih.nic.in/}}
| footnotes               = 
}}

'''Mehsi''' is a town located in [[East Champaran district]] in the Indian state of [[Bihar]]. Mehsi is an entry point of East Champaran when traveling from [[Patna]], [[Muzaffarpur]] to [[Chakia, Bihar|Chakia]], [[Raxaul]], connected both by rail and road. There are many smaller factories manufacturing buttons for the clothing industry, although most of the population depends upon commercial business and agriculture. &lt;!--Mehsi was the birthplace of the writer and intellectual, Rajkamal Chaudhary. The last sentence about the birthplace of Rajkamal Chaudhary is not at Mehsi of District East Champaran, but it is at Saharsa district of Bihar.--&gt;

==LocationMehsi is located {{convert|114|km|mi|0}} north of [[Patna]] and {{convert|41.2|km|mi|0}} north of [[Muzaffarpur]] and{{convert|43.2|km|mi|0}} south of [[Motihari]]  and [[Chakia, Bihar|chakia]] 10 km .&lt;ref name=&quot;I9&quot; /&gt; The [[National Highway 28 (India)|National Highway 28]] passes through Mehsi. The nearest airport is [[Patna Airport]]. The nearest village is Sulsabad(Barharwa) which is 1&amp;nbsp;km north of Mehsi railway station. The nearest village is [[Rampurwa-Mirzapur]] which is 1&amp;nbsp;km east of the railway station and Chak Laloo is a village located near the bus stand and 1&amp;nbsp;km from the railway station. This village is the birthplace of the scholar Moulana Zahirul Haque and his elder son Haider Imam Anzar.==
==Nagar Panchayat Mehsi==
Kaswa Mehsi Gram Panchayat was upgraded to Mehsi Nagar Panchayat in the year 2009 under the Bihar Municipal Bill,2007. Chairman of Nagar Panchayat Mehsi is Anita Gupta &amp; Dy.Chairman of Nagar Panchayat Mehsi is Sanjay Kumar. 
Ward-1- Indu Devi
Ward-2- Nasima Khatoon
Ward-3- Chawal Mishra
Ward-4- Shailendra Srivastav
Ward-5-Lalbabu Thakur
Ward-6-Nazma Khatoon
Ward-7-Babulal Ram
Ward-8-Rumi Tabassum
Ward-9-Subodh Thakur
Ward-10-Anita Devi(Chairman) 
Ward-11-Urmila Devi
Ward-12-Satrudhan Mahto and ruplal mahto runerup
Ward-13-Sanjay Kumar(Dy.Chairman) 
Ward-14-Priti Kumari
Ward-15-Manoj Chowrasiya.

'''&lt;u&gt;&lt;big&gt;Important Personalities of MEHSI NAGAR PANCHAYAT -&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/u&gt;''' 

1.'''&lt;code&gt;&lt;u&gt;Shatrudhan Prasad Chaudhary&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/code&gt;'''- He was a well known renowned leader &amp; social activist of Mehsi Block. He served for more than two decades as the active politician of this block. He served for 23 years as the '''Mukhiya''' of Kaswa Mehsi Gram Panchayat ( now Mehsi Nagar Panchayat). He also graced the Mehsi Block '''Uppramukh''' post for 23 years. This place suffered a great loss by his death in January,2006. His ideology &amp; social deeds are still inspiration to the young generation.

2.'''&lt;code&gt;&lt;u&gt;Pawan Kumar Jaiswal-&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/code&gt;''' He is a well famed personality of Mehsi Block. He is a renowned businessman,dynamic social activist &amp; powerful political personality.He is the elder son of Late Shatrudhan Prasad Chaudhary .He is  an eminent person of&quot; Kalwaar Samaj &quot;of Mehsi . 

3.Ram Avtar Shah-He was a freedom fighter &amp; participated in Indian Independence Aandolan.
----
4. Mr.Radhakant prasad yadav from village tajpur bara. He do work in the field of Medical in Local people of villages. He help many people in medical field.

==Industry==
Mehsi industry includes zip buttons while other resources harvested are [[Lychee|Litchi]] and [[Mango]] fruits. Mehsi is the major producer of these fruits in India.&lt;ref name=&quot;I9&quot;&gt;&quot;Mehsi in India&quot;, India9.com, 30 June 2005, web: [http://www.india9.com/i9show/Mehsi-74380.htm i9-Mehsi].&lt;/ref&gt;

== River ==
The [[Budhi Gandak]] river flows near the town of Mehsi which is one branch from the Gandak river.

==Demographics==
Mehsi is one of the 27 blocks in Purbi Champaran district. {{As of|2001}} India [[census]] the total population of the Mehsi to 232,159. There are 30 villages in this block. The literacy rate is 61.53% whereas for females it its 55.03% and 85.91% for males.

==Tourism and places of interest==
This small community has a number of places of interest at the east side of railway station. These include :
* A 700 hundred yeared old mazar known as '''Mirza Halim Shah Mazar dargah''' situated at ward no. 10. near chowk bazar. 
* A very old library 'Nagrik Pustakalaya'.
* An old High School (Tirhut Vidyalaya) of the English government
* Orchards of lichi and mango trees.
* An old inter college named &quot;Mahatma Gandhi Inter College&quot;.
* An old Girls High school (Land donated by Bhagwan Sah.)
* A New Building office of nagar panchayat mehsi (Land Donated by Sanjay Kumar)
* A '''10 yeared old NGO''' named as '''&quot;May I Help You&quot;''' ,registered under ''F.C.R.A'' , is present in Mehsi.
* It is situated in Chaklaloo region near bus stand.
* It is working for skill development under '''N.S.D.C''' AND '''P.M.K.V.Y''' (Pradhan Mantri Kaushal Vikas Yogna).
* It is working under the presidency of late '''Er. Md. Yaseen Ansari'''.
*  Presently it is being functioned under '''Md.Ashraf Ansari''' (C.E.O. Of May I Help You).And the Secretary General, '''Aasia Perween'''.
° Late Ram Avtar Shah was great freedom fighter belong to Mehsi.
° 70 years old Tea stall Vendor situated in railway station plat form 01.passengers of trains enjoy their with samosha and Famous KALA JAAMUN.
°

In Mehsi, there is now a place called Litchipuram named after the fruit. This was highlighted recently when Deputy chief minister Sushil Kumar Modi inaugurated a 3-day Litchi Utsav at a local school in Mehsi. According to the government’s own data, East Champaran has been the highest producer of litchi in recent years. Along with Mehasi, Muzaffarpur, Vaishali and Samastipur districts, Bihar produces 40 per cent of the country’s litchi crop.&lt;ref name=&quot;I7&quot;&gt;.
   &quot;Litchipuram, Mehsi, East Champaran&quot;, bihardays.com, web:
   [http://www.bihardays.com/3bhr/litchipuram-mehsi-east-champaran-celebrates-litchi-utsav-inaugurated-sushil-modi/ Litchipuram].
&lt;/ref&gt;

Litchi is grown in over 15,000 hectares in the whole district but in Mehsi region alone [[litchi]] is grown by farmers in over 11,000 acres – thus the moniker Litchipuram. The name was given in 2003 by the then district magistrate S. Sheo Kumar who discovered that litchi production in the region is far greater than the neighboring Muzaffarpur, which hogs all the fame due to earlier association.&lt;ref name=&quot;I7&quot;/&gt;

Mehsi is also known for litchi honey, produced in hives maintained in the orchards during the flowering season. It is indeed the rarest of rarities. Apart from boosting pride among the local farmers, the litchi festival is also hosting seminars with participants such as professors, scientists and specialists from Rajendra Agriculture University, Pusa, and National Horticulture Mission.  As for the demand by the locals for a Litchi Research Institute, it can only be set up with the assistance of the National Council Agriculture Research, New Delhi.&lt;ref name=&quot;I7&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- I couldn't make sense of this: nagar panchayat mehsi office land donate late Radhakant prasad.smt.shanti devi is presant chairman in nagar panchayat mehsi.smt shanti devi is wife of sanjay kumar.sanjay kumar is son of late Radhakant prasad. --&gt;in mehsi it has been started by some businessman ,it may include tahir, abdul qayyum khanand so many people. There is a forest which name is Bhimalpur jungal; this is good place for celebrate picnic &amp; move and seen many types of animal like nilgaya &amp;  Sahi. There is beautiful morning &amp; evening time ; because behind these forest passes a river which is budi gandak.

Mehsi is also famous for button industries. 30% peoples are emloyed in this field.

== Geography ==

The summer, April–July is extremely hot and humid (28/42 deg C,90% Max.) and winter is pleasantly cold, around 06/20 deg C. The region of the city is filled with the orchards of [[lichi]] and [[mango]] trees. The river and the orchards creates a pleasant climate around the city.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.india9.com/i9show/Mehsi-74380.htm About Mehsi]
* [http://eastchamparan.bih.nic.in.html District Administration Website]
* [http://www.allaboutbihar.com/districts/purba_champaran/mehsi.php All about Bihar]
{{Tirhut Division}}

[[Category:Cities and towns in East Champaran district]]</text>
      <sha1>ggkkth6q9lcofzjblk6oalvewg29kuj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
