  <page>
    <title>Parasailing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24208</id>
    <revision>
      <id>933896968</id>
      <parentid>933896946</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-03T16:31:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ifnord</username>
        <id>470876</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/2401:4900:188C:D213:83B9:E503:3D40:F0F6|2401:4900:188C:D213:83B9:E503:3D40:F0F6]] ([[User talk:2401:4900:188C:D213:83B9:E503:3D40:F0F6|talk]]) to last revision by Parafacts ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Parasail|the programming language|ParaSail (programming language)}}
{{distinguish|kiteboating|Paragliding}}

{{disputed|date=April 2017}}
[[File:Serie de fotografías en Playa del Carmen 39.jpg|thumb|Parasailing in [[Playa del Carmen]], [[Quintana Roo]], [[México]].]]
'''Parasailing''', also known as '''parascending''' or '''parakiting''', is a recreational [[Kite types|kiting]] activity where a person is towed behind a vehicle (usually a boat) while attached to a specially designed canopy wing that resembles a [[parachute]], known as a parasail wing. The [[manned kite]]'s moving anchor may be a car, truck, or boat. The harness attaches the pilot to the parasail, which is connected to the boat, or land vehicle, by the tow rope. The vehicle then drives off, carrying the parascender (or wing) and person into the air. If the boat is powerful enough, two or three people can parasail behind it at the same time. The parascender has little or no control over the parachute. The activity is primarily a fun ride, not to be confused with the sport of [[paragliding]].

There are commercial parasailing operations all over the world. Land-based parasailing has also been transformed into a competition sport in Europe. In land-based competition parasailing, the parasail is towed to maximum height behind a 4-wheel-drive vehicle. The driver then releases the tow line; the parasailer flies down to a target area in an accuracy competition.

The sport was developed in the early 1980s and has been very popular ever since. The first international competitions were held in the mid-1980s and continue annually to this day. Over the years, the competitions have grown in scope as well as the number of participants.
  
== Terminology ==

===Parachute versus parasailing===
Both the parachute and parasail can ascend and glide. The primary difference between the two is that the parasail is more stable and efficient during the ascent mode when being towed aloft with minimum or zero steering control by the parasailor. The parachute is not efficient when towed and is primarily used for skydiving where the parachutist can fully control the direction. In the descent mode, both are designed to slow the fall of a person during said descent at any given altitude.

=== Kite color ===
The parachute/kite part is normally brightly colored to match to beach area in which it is used. Some people have kites with colors matching their favorite sports team or alma mater. Many parasail canopies that are designed for commercial use offering rides to tourists on vacation are bright in color and have designs ranging from flags, logos, [[Smiley|smiley faces]], and multiple color patterns.

== History ==

===Early years of parasailing ===
The first ascending-gliding parachute was developed by Pierre-Marcel Lemoigne in 1962.{{&lt;ref&gt;cite web|url=http://www.parasail.org/ |title=Welcome to the Parasail Safety Council - Mark McCulloh|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alohasurfguide.com/parasailing/|title=Parasailing - Aloha Surf Guide|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.discovery.com/adventure/extreme-sports/parasailing-what-you-need-to-know-before-you-go.htm|title=Parasailing: What You Need to Know Before You Go|first=Talal|last=Al-Khatib|date=5 December 2011|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same year, Lemoigne established an Aeronautical Training Center to introduce his new ascending-gliding parachute as a training tool for parachutists. The technique allows parachutists to train more efficiently by towing the parachutist to a suitable altitude, then releasing them to practice landings. This training method proved cheaper than—and just as effective as—an airplane. In 1963 Jacques-André Istel from Pioneer Parachute Company bought a license from Lemoigne to manufacture and sell the 24-gore ascending-gliding parachute which was trade-named &quot;parasail.&quot;{{citation needed|date=April 2019}}

In 1974, Mark McCulloh invented the first self-contained parasail launch and recovery vessel that incorporated a hydraulic winch and canopy assist mast that collectively launched and retrieved the parasail canopy and parasailors to and from the vessel flight deck. McCulloh's invention was patented in 1976 and later referred to as a &quot;WINCHBOAT&quot; which the set the first parasail equipment industry standard that is utilized by all commercial parasail operations around the world.{{&lt;ref&gt;cite web|url=http://www.parasail.org/ |title=Welcome to the Parasail Safety Council - Mark McCulloh|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In early 1976, Brian Gaskin designed, created, and tested the first 16-gore canopy design which he named &quot;Waterbird&quot;. The Waterbird was revolutionary in its canopy design, its unique tow yoke harness arrangement, its construction, and the use of zero porosity fabrics which allowed it to be used over water safely. The majority of commercial parasail operators then moved to the 16-gore canopy arrangement. In 1976 Gaskin founded his company, Waterbird Parakites, which is still in operation today, producing commercial and recreational 16-gore parasails.{{citation needed|date=April 2019}}

In April 2013, the first ASTM parasail weather standard was approved. With the help of the WSIA, and the chair of the parasail committee, Matthew Dvorak, owner and operator of Daytona Beach Parasail, Inc. the new standard was implemented. This is the first standard in the parasail industry with three more in the works to be approved later this year. This standard was the first step in bringing the otherwise unregulated industry into a more uniformed and safe industry!{{citation needed|date=April 2019}}
[[File:Max methode.JPG|thumb|right|Example of parakiting]]

=== Improved parasail canopy designs ===
In recent years, operators have moved from small (20-foot range) parachutes to large (30–40 feet) parachutes that utilize high-lift, low-drag designs enabling operators to fly higher payloads in lower (typically safer) winds. Most operators now offer double and triple flights using an adjustable side by side bar arrangement. The side-by-side bar is aluminum attached to the yoke of the chute, allowing two or three passenger harnesses to be attached side by side.

In the late 1990s, Waterbird Parakites &lt;code&gt;waterbird.co.uk&lt;/code&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.waterbird.co.uk|title=Waterbird - the home of parasailing|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Custom Chutes Inc,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.customchutes.com|title=Home - Custom Chutes|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; redesigned the original Gaskin design to allow parasails to carry more weight (double rides and triple rides), but still ensure they could operate in the same operating conditions.  As a result, a completely new design, much larger in diameter but with much smaller increased air resistance, was born.

===Criticism ===
In 2014, the  [[National Transportation Safety Board]] issued a press release in which it found the parasailing industry to be largely unregulated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://miami.cbslocal.com/2014/07/01/ntsb-parasailing-accidents-frequently-caused-by-faulty-equipment/|title=NTSB: Parasailing Accidents 'Frequently Caused By Faulty Equipment'|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The report identified a number of safety concerns which included vessel operators who continued to operate despite hazardous wind conditions, use of inadequate equipment and unserviceable gear, and compromised strength of rope tied to the parasail. In a period from 1998 to the third of July 2013, there were six parasailing fatalities in the Florida area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/US/parasailing-safety-questioned-accident-florida/story?id=19567438|title=Parasailing Safety Questioned After Accident|work= ABC News|date=8 July 2013|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The great majority of deaths in parasail incidents have occurred when riders were unable to get out of their harness support system after an unplanned landing in water during high winds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.swoperodante.com/parasailing-accident-statistics/|title=Parasailing Accident Statistics &amp; Info - Swope, Rodante, P.A.|date=8 May 2014|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to the release of the NTSB report, Florida passed the [[White-Miskell Act]] which added strict regulations parasailing companies must follow including obtaining an insurance policy, and restrictions on parasailing in inclement weather.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Wet-n-Wild Parasailing Destin|url=http://destinflboatrentals.com/attractions/parasailing/|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170207142323/http://destinflboatrentals.com/attractions/parasailing/|url-status=dead|archive-date=2017-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Parasailing associations ==
[[File:2017 Sarasota Crescent Beach Airplane Ad Banner 4 FRD 9257 (cropped).jpg|thumb|Banner towing by parasailing at [[Crescent Beach, Sarasota County, Florida|Crescent Beach]] on [[Siesta Key, Florida|Siesta Key]]]]

The leading trade associations for parasailing are:
*Commercial Winchboat Operators Association (CWOA)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cwoa.net|title=CWOA.net|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Parasail Safety Council&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parasail.org|title=Welcome to the Parasail Safety Council|first=Mark|last=McCulloh|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*PAPO (Professional Association of Parasail Operators)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.teampapo.org|title=低金利キャッシング※おすすめの銀行・消費者金融一覧|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Water Safety Industry Association &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wsia.net WSIA.net]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Kite line]]
*[[Kite mooring]]
*[[Kite types]]
*[[Kitesurfing]]
*[[Paragliding]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Kites}}
{{Extreme sports}}

[[Category:Parachuting]]
[[Category:Water sports]]
[[Category:Kites]]</text>
      <sha1>jf725jy4e3ix3vd4tu2tbucrng7xw28</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
