  <page>
    <title>Parkour</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>223199</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938587350</id>
      <parentid>938587205</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-01T03:31:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Apparition11</username>
        <id>6046731</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/Hidayatgul12|Hidayatgul12]] ([[User talk:Hidayatgul12|talk]]): Spam using [[WP:TWINKLE|TW]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2017}}
{{Infobox Martial art
| image           = Parkour speed vault portrait.jpg
| imagecaption    = A ''traceur'' performing a speed vault
| imagesize       = 197px
| name            = Parkour
| aka             = PK&lt;ref name =&quot;Nacho&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://davidbelle.com/biography-eng/ |title=Actor David Belle Biography |publisher=David Belle |accessdate=22 May 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20141020053729/http://davidbelle.com/biography-eng/ |archivedate=20 October 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.3run.co.uk/story |title=3RUN Story |publisher=3run.co.uk |date=6 December 2012 |accessdate= 22 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://learnmoreparkour.com/about-the-tapps.htm |title=About the Tapp Brothers |website= LearnMoreParkour.com |accessdate=22 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| focus           = Obstacle passing
| difficulty      = Non-competitive
| country         = France 
| creator         = [[David Belle]]
| formation       = 1995–1996
| famous pract    = {{plainlist|
* [[Storror]]
* [[Sébastien Foucan]]
* David Belle
* [[Yamakasi]]
}}
| descendant arts = [[Freerunning]]
| olympic         = No
| martialart      =
}}
'''Parkour''' ({{IPA-fr|paʁkuʁ|lang}}) is a [[Training#Physical training|training]] discipline using movement that developed from military [[obstacle course]] training.&lt;ref name=&quot;CineP20&quot;&gt;[[#Angel|Angel]], pp. 17–20&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pkgen-history&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://parkourgenerations.com/parkour-history/ |title=Parkour History |date=22 August 2014 |publisher=Parkour Generations |accessdate=2 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YYwQLvIkQ88 |title=Interview with David Belle |accessdate=2 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Practitioners, called tracers or traceurs, aim to get from one point to another in a complex environment, without assistive equipment and in the fastest and most efficient way possible. Parkour includes [[running]], [[climbing]], [[:wikt:swinging|swinging]], [[vault (urban movement)|vaulting]], jumping, [[plyometrics]], [[roll (gymnastics)|rolling]], [[crawling (human)|quadrupedal movement]] (crawling) and other movements as deemed most suitable for the situation (not to be confused with [[freerunning]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Ferrari&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.flowjournal.org/2010/05/from-%E2%80%9Cplay-to-display%E2%80%9D-parkour-as-media-mimetics-or-nature-reclamation-matthew-ferrari-university-of-massachusetts-amherst/|title=From 'Play to Display': Parkour as Media-Mimetics or Nature Reclamation?|last=Ferrari|first=Matthew|date=7 May 2010|work=FlowTV, vol 11, lokaliseret den 01-04-2011 på|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Freitas&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=De Feitas |first=Elizabeth |title=Parkour and the Built Environment: Spatial Practices and the Plasticity of School Buildings |year=2011 |journal=Journal of Curriculum Theorizing |issue=3|volume=27|url=http://journal.jctonline.org/index.php/jct/article/view/126 |page=209}}&lt;/ref&gt; Parkour's development from military training gives it some aspects of a non-combative [[Martial arts|martial art]].

Parkour is an activity that can be practiced alone or with others and is usually carried out in urban spaces, though it can be done anywhere.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Rawlinson |first1=Christopher |last2=Guaralda |first2=Mirko |date=11 September 2012 |contribution=Chaos and creativity of play: designing emotional engagement in public spaces| title=In Out of Control: 8th International Conference on Design and Emotion| location=Central Saint Martins College of Arts and Design, London |url=http://eprints.qut.edu.au/51313/ |accessdate=16 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1007/s00146-010-0294-2| title = Nice-looking obstacles: Parkour as urban practice of deterritorialization| journal = AI &amp; Society| volume = 26| issue = 2| pages = 143–152| year = 2010| last1 = Brunner | first1 = C. | url = http://doc.rero.ch/record/312807/files/146_2010_Article_294.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Parkour involves seeing one's environment in a new way, and imagining the potential for navigating it by movement around, across, through, over and under its features.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last1=Rawlinson |first1=Christopher |last2=Guaralda |first2=Mirko |date=27 April 2011 |contribution=Play in the city: Parkour and architecture| title=The First International Postgraduate Conference on Engineering, Designing and Developing the Built Environment for Sustainable Wellbeing |location=Queensland University of Technology, Brisbane, Australia |url=http://eprints.qut.edu.au/42506/ |accessdate=16 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last1=Ameel |first1=L. |last2=Tani |first2=S. |year=2012 |title=Everyday aesthetics in action: Parkour Eyes and the beauty of concrete walls |journal=Emotion, Space and Society |volume=5 |issue=3|pages=164–173 |doi=10.1016/j.emospa.2011.09.003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Parkour as a type of movement was established by David Belle in the late 1980s, therefore many consider its origin to be France, however this type of movement has also been practiced by people in other European countries like Latvia and Russia during the same period of time.{{citation needed|date=January 2020}} The discipline was popularised in the late 1990s and 2000s through films, documentaries, video games and advertisements featuring the [[Yamakasi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CineP20&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview|last=Belle|first=David|title=Entrevista com David Belle (OSRAM 2006)|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YYwQLvIkQ88|accessdate=10 February 2013|year=2006|trans-title=Interview with David Belle (OSRAM 2006)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Atkinson|first1=M.|year=2009|title=Parkour, Anarcho-Environmentalism, and Poiesis|journal=Journal of Sport &amp; Social Issues|volume=33|issue=2|pages=169–194|doi=10.1177/0193723509332582}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology ==
The word ''parkour'' derives from ''parcours du combattant'' (obstacle course), the classic obstacle course method of military training proposed by [[Georges Hébert]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PAWA-Welcome&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Russell |first=Matthew |url=http://www.pawa.fr/Welcome/welcome.html |title=English welcome&amp;nbsp;— Parkour Worldwide Association |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050508021450/http://www.pawa.fr/Welcome/welcome.html |archivedate=8 May 2005 |accessdate=12 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=23 February 2006 |url=http://parkour.net/forum/index.php?showtopic=3937 |title=PAWA statement on Freerunning |accessdate=12 May 2007 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927193626/http://parkour.net/forum/index.php?showtopic=3937 |archivedate=27 September 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927193447/http://parkour.net/forum/index.php?showtopic=5481 |archivedate=27 September 2007 |url-status=dead |url=http://parkour.net/forum/index.php?showtopic=5481 |title=The name Parkour, simple question |accessdate=12 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Raymond Belle used the term &quot;''les parcours''&quot; to encompass all of his training including climbing, jumping, running, balancing, and the other methods he undertook in his personal athletic advancement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parkour-DB2&quot;&gt;[[#Belle2|Belle]], pp.&amp;nbsp;31–70&lt;/ref&gt; His son, David, further developed his father's methods and achieved success as a stuntman, and one day on a film set showed his 'Speed Air Man' video to [[Hubert Koundé]]. Koundé suggested he change the &quot;c&quot; of &quot;''parcours''&quot; to a &quot;k&quot; because it was stronger and more dynamic, and to remove the silent &quot;s&quot; for the same reason, forming &quot;''parkour''&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;CineP37&quot;&gt;[[#Angel|Angel]], p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt;

A practitioner of parkour is called a ''traceur'', with the feminine form being ''traceuse''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ferrari&quot; /&gt; They are [[noun substantive|nouns]] derived from the French verb ''[[:fr:wikt:tracer|tracer]]'', which normally means &quot;to trace&quot;, as in &quot;tracing a path&quot;, in reference to drawing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cnrtl.fr/lexicographie/tracer? |title=Portail lexical&amp;nbsp;— Définition de tracer |language=French|accessdate=28 August 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The verb ''tracer'' used familiarly means: &quot;to hurry up&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[wikt:fr:tracer#populaire|(Populaire) Filer, se dépêcher.]] or to run (go) fast (to leave in a hurry) → [[wikt:filer#Verb|(intransitive, informal) to leave, to get going]], [[wikt:dépêcher#Verb|(reflexive) to haste, to hurry up]] → [[wikt:buck up#Interjection|(idiomatic, dated) Hurry up; make haste.]]&lt;/ref&gt; The term ''traceur'' was originally the name of a parkour group headed by David Belle which included [[Sébastien Foucan]] and Stéphane Vigroux.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_d1AxUPPcF8 |title=An Interview With Stephane Vigroux |publisher=YouTube |date=27 January 2009 |accessdate=22 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A ''jam'' refers to a meeting of traceurs, involving training lasting anywhere from hours to several days, often with people from different cities. The first parkour jam was organised in July 2002 by Romain Drouet, with a dozen people including [[Sébastien Foucan]] and Stéphane Vigroux.

== History ==
===Georges Hébert===
In Western Europe, a forerunner of parkour was developed by French naval officer [[Georges Hébert]], who before [[World War I]] promoted athletic skill based on the models of indigenous tribes he had met in Africa.&lt;ref name=HerbertUFF&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.urbanfreeflow.com/articles/methode_naturelle.htm |title=Georges Hebert and the Natural Method of Physical Culture |accessdate=2 July 2013 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050323090031/http://www.urbanfreeflow.com/articles/methode_naturelle.htm |archivedate=23 March 2005 |author=Artful Dodger }}&lt;/ref&gt; He noted, &quot;their bodies were splendid, flexible, nimble, skillful, enduring, and resistant but yet they had no other tutor in gymnastics but their lives in nature.&quot;&lt;ref name=HerbertUFF/&gt; His rescue efforts during the 1902 eruption of [[Mount Pelée]] on [[Saint-Pierre, Martinique]], reinforced his belief that athletic skill must be combined with courage and altruism.&lt;ref name=HerbertUFF/&gt; Hébert became a physical education tutor at the college of [[Reims]] in France. Hébert set up a &quot;méthode naturelle&quot; (''natural method'') session consisting of ten fundamental groups: walking, running, jumping, quadrupedal movement, climbing, balancing, throwing, lifting, self-defence and swimming. These were intended to develop &quot;the three main forces&quot;: energetic (willpower, courage, coolness, and firmness), moral (benevolence, assistance, honour, and honesty) and physical (muscles and breath).&lt;ref name=HebertINSEP&gt;{{cite web |title=Georges Hébert&amp;nbsp;— la methode naturalle |url=http://perso.orange.fr/le.parkour/france/medias/page3.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060718150740/http://perso.orange.fr/le.parkour/france/medias/page3.html |archivedate=18 July 2006 |format=JPG |publisher=INSEP&amp;nbsp;— Musée de la Marine |language=French |accessdate=22 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; During World War I and World War II, teaching continued to expand, becoming the standard system of French military education and training. Inspired by Hébert, a Swiss architect developed a &quot;''parcours du combattant''&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;No Obstacles&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=No Obstacles |url=http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2007/04/16/070416fa_fact_wilkinson?currentPage=all |date=16 April 2007 |first=Alec |last=Wilkinson |work= [[The New Yorker]] |accessdate=14 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;—military obstacle course—the first of the courses that are now standard in military training and which led to the development of civilian [[fitness trail]]s and confidence courses.&lt;ref name=HerbertUFF/&gt;

===Raymond and David Belle===
Born in 1939 in [[Vietnam]], Raymond Belle was the son of a French physician and Vietnamese mother. During the [[First Indochina War]], his father died and he was separated from his mother, after which he was sent to a military orphanage in [[Da Lat]] at the age of 7. He took it upon himself to train harder and longer than everyone else in order never to be a victim. At night, when everyone else was asleep, he would be outside running or climbing trees. He would use the military [[obstacle course]]s in secret, and also created courses of his own that tested his endurance, strength, and flexibility. Doing this enabled him not only to survive the hardships he experienced during his childhood, but also eventually to thrive. After the [[Battle of Dien Bien Phu]] in 1954, he returned to France and remained in military education until the age of 19, when he joined the [[Paris Fire Brigade]], a French Army unit.&lt;ref name=&quot;CineP20&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Parkour-DB1&quot;&gt;[[#Belle2|Belle]], p. 23–30&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Raymond Belle Bio&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://parkour.net/modules/articles/item.php?itemid=3 |title=Raymond Belle's biography |date=17 February 2006 |work=Original French biography sourced from 'Allo Dix-Huit', the magazine of the Parisian pompiers. |publisher=Parkour.NET |accessdate=29 November 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060217200929/http://parkour.net/modules/articles/item.php?itemid=3 |archivedate=17 February 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:David Belle NewYorker.jpg|thumb|[[David Belle]] is considered the founder of parkour.]]
Raymond's son, [[David Belle]], was born in 1973. He experimented with [[gymnastics]] and [[Athletics (sport)|athletics]] but became increasingly disaffected with both school and the [[sports club]]s. As he got older, he started to read the newspaper clippings{{which|date=March 2016}} that told of his father's exploits and was increasingly curious about what had enabled his father to accomplish these feats. Through conversations with his father, he realised that what he really wanted was a means to develop skills that would be useful to him in life, rather than just training to kick a ball or perform moves in a padded, indoor environment.&lt;ref name=&quot;CineP20&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Parkour-DB2&quot;/&gt;

Through   conversations with his father, David learned about this way of training that his father called &quot;''parcours''&quot;. He heard his father talk of the many repetitions he had done in order to find the best way of doing things. He learned  that for his father, training was not a game but something vital which enabled him to survive and to protect the people he cared about. David realised that this was what he had been searching for, and so he began training in the same way. After a time, he found it far more important to him than schooling and he gave up his other commitments to focus all his time on his training.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parkour-DB2&quot;/&gt;

===Yamakasi===
{{main|Yamakasi}}
David initially trained on his own, and after moving to [[Lisses]], found other young men (including his cousins) who had similar desires, and they began to train together.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nacho&quot; /&gt; The group eventually included David Belle, [[Sébastien Foucan]], Châu Belle Dinh, Williams Belle, Yann Hnautra, Laurent Piemontesi, Guylain N'Guba Boyeke, Malik Diouf, and Charles Perrière.

====Discipline====
The group put themselves through challenges that forced them to find the physical and mental strength to succeed. Examples included training without food or water, or sleeping on the floor without a blanket, to learn to endure the cold.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Angel|Angel]], p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; For example, no one in the group was permitted to be late for training, as it would hold back the whole group. If any member completed a challenge, everyone else had to do the same thing.&lt;ref name=&quot;David Belle p.43&quot;&gt;[[#Belle|Belle and Perriére]], p. 43&lt;/ref&gt; During their training no one was allowed to complain or be negative. Few excuses were allowed. For instance, if someone claimed that his shoes were too worn out in order to make a jump, he had to do it anyway, even if it meant doing the jump barefoot.&lt;ref name=&quot;David Belle p.42&quot;/&gt; At the same time, everyone was required to have knowledge of their own limits.&lt;ref name=&quot;David Belle p.46&quot;&gt;[[#Belle|Belle and Perriére]], p. 46&lt;/ref&gt;

Respecting one's health and physical well-being was one of the foundations of the group. If any member hurt himself during or after the execution of a movement, the movement was deemed a failure. A movement executed only once was not considered an achievement; only with repetition was the challenge complete. Every movement had to be repeated at least ten times in a row without the traceur having to push his limits or sustaining any injury. If any mistake was made by any traceur in the group everyone had to start all over again.&lt;ref name=&quot;David Belle p.43&quot;/&gt;

Humility was an important principle.&lt;ref name=&quot;David Belle p.46&quot;/&gt; No traceur was allowed to feel superior over someone else, for example by executing a movement only to show off in front of someone who could not perform the movement. If any traceur in the group claimed that he had completed a difficult and dangerous challenge that should not be attempted unaided, he had to prove his claims by doing the challenge again. Anyone who lied violated the principle of humility.&lt;ref name=&quot;David Belle p.43&quot;/&gt;

To join the group, new members had to be recommended by an existing member and then pass tests to evaluate their motivation for joining.&lt;ref name=&quot;David Belle p.42&quot;&gt;[[#Belle|Belle and Perriére]], p. 42&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the huge emphasis on the collective, each traceur had to progress and develop independently — &quot;to create the means to be yourself&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Belle|Belle and Perriére]], p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; — and there was a complete trust within the group.&lt;ref name=&quot;David Belle p.46&quot;/&gt; Every traceur was to encourage the others and show confidence through their behaviour.&lt;ref name=&quot;David Belle p.47&quot;&gt;[[#Belle|Belle and Perriére]], p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; If a member violated the principles, the group could meet without the offending person to discuss various punishments. Anyone deemed unsuitable could be temporarily or even permanently banned from the group in order to uphold its disciplines and values.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Belle|Belle and Perriére]], p. 44&lt;/ref&gt;

The group also drew influence from Asian cultures, notably the acrobatic antics of [[Jackie Chan]] in his [[Hong Kong action films]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Stratford |first1=Elaine |title=Geographies, Mobilities, and Rhythms over the Life-Course: Adventures in the Interval |date=2014 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=9781135117429 |page=79 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=d4yLBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA79}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hunt |first1=Leon |last2=Wing-Fai |first2=Leung |title=East Asian Cinemas: Exploring Transnational Connections on Film |date=2010 |publisher=[[I.B. Tauris]] |isbn=9780857712271 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pzgBAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA229}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the philosophy of [[Bruce Lee]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Parkour History |url=https://parkourgenerations.com/parkour-history/ |accessdate=13 March 2019 |work=Parkour Generations}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Name and split====
In 1997, David Belle's brother Jean-François invited the group to perform for the public in a firefighter show in Paris.&lt;ref name=&quot;CineP35&quot;&gt;[[#Angel|Angel]], p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; For the performance, the group named themselves ''[[Yamakasi]]'', from the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo|Congolese]] [[Lingala language|Lingala]] ''ya makási'', meaning strong in one's person, or &quot;strong man, strong spirit&quot;. Sébastien Foucan also invented a name for what they were doing: &quot;''l'art du déplacement''{{-&quot;}} (French for &quot;the art of movement&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;CineP35&quot;/&gt; The firefighter performance caused both positive and negative attention. Some members of the group were concerned how the public would view their discipline since the performance did not demonstrate all aspects of it, such as their hard training and their values and ethics. Jean-François also sent pictures and video of the group to a French TV programme, and the popularity of parkour began to increase. A series of television programmes in various countries subsequently featured video footage of the group, and they began to get more requests for performances. During this time, conflicting interests arose within the group. Sébastien Foucan wanted to teach more rather than to train more, and David Belle had the ambition to become an actor. David and Sébastien chose to leave the group, and used the name &quot;parkour&quot; to describe their activity (see [[Parkour#Etymology|§ Etymology]] above). The seven remaining Yamakasi members continued to use the term ''l'art du déplacement''&lt;ref name=&quot;CineP20&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Parkour-DB3&quot;&gt;[[#Belle2|Belle]], pp. 71–79&lt;/ref&gt; (see [[Parkour#Derivative terminologies and disciplines|§ Derivative terminologies and disciplines]] below).

==Organizations==
National parkour organizations include the [[World Freerunning and Parkour Federation]], established in 2007, who have worked with [[MTV]] to produce Parkour related shows.&lt;ref&gt;[https://wfpf.com/history-wfpf/ History of WFPF] wfpf.com&lt;/ref&gt;

[[International Gymnastics Federation]] (FIG) added parkour as one of their disciplines in 2017, receiving lots of opposition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.accessparkour.com/fig-gate-the-story-so-far/|title=Fig-Gate: The Great Parkour Scandal|date=11 May 2017|publisher=accessparkour.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.insidethegames.biz/articles/1051013/denmark-add-voice-to-opposition-of-figs-move-into-parkour|title=Denmark add voice to opposition of FIG's move into parkour|publisher=insidethegames.biz|date=1 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.insidethegames.biz/articles/1053647/parkour-earth-officially-becomes-sports-international-federation-as-fig-row-continues|title=Parkour Earth officially launches as FIG row continues|publisher=insidethegames.biz|date=4 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Programme includes Speed-Run (Sprint) and Freestyle. They launched FIG Parkour World Cup in 2018, first event was held on 6–8 April 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gymnastics.sport/site/news/displaynews.php?idNews=2017|title=7 days to go till first FIG Parkour World Cup|publisher=[[International Gymnastics Federation]]|date=30 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[2020 Parkour World Championships|1st Parkour World Championships]] is scheduled to take place at [[Hiroshima]], [[Japan]], on 3–5 April 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gymnastics.sport/site/news/displaynews.php?idNews=2057|title=Main decisions from the 18th FIG Council in Istanbul|publisher=[[International Gymnastics Federation]]|date=14 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.gymnastics.sport/site/news/displaynews.php?idNews=2586|title=Hiroshima to host 1st Parkour World Championships in 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Parkour will also make its [[World Games]] debut at the [[2021 World Games]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theworldgames.org/sports/Gymnastics-59 Gymnastics at the World Games] theworldgames.org&lt;/ref&gt;

== Philosophy ==
According to Williams Belle, the philosophies and theories behind parkour are an integral aspect of the art, one that many non-practitioners have never been exposed to. Belle says he trains people because he wants it &quot;to be alive&quot; and &quot;for people to use it&quot;.&lt;ref name=GYamakasi&gt;{{cite video |people=Belle, Châu; Belle, Williams; Hnautra, Yann and Daniels, Mark (director) |title=Generation Yamakasi
|medium=TV-Documentary |language=French |publisher=[[France 2]] |location=France |url=http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=-3773384792923323349 |accessdate=25 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Châu Belle explains it is a &quot;type of freedom&quot; or &quot;kind of expression&quot;; that parkour is &quot;only a state of mind&quot; rather than a set of actions, and that it is about overcoming and adapting to mental and emotional obstacles as well as physical barriers.&lt;ref name=GYamakasi/&gt; Traceur Dylan Baker says, &quot;Parkour also influences one's thought processes by enhancing self-confidence and critical thinking skills that allow one to overcome everyday physical and mental obstacles&quot;.&lt;ref name=GYamakasi/&gt;&lt;ref name=TheLantern&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thelantern.com/2.1347/students-on-campus-are-mastering-parkour-an-art-of-self-awareness-and-body-control-1.74990 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100925061659/http://www.thelantern.com/2.1347/students-on-campus-are-mastering-parkour-an-art-of-self-awareness-and-body-control-1.74990 |archivedate=25 September 2010 |first=Jeffy |last=Mai |date=14 April 2008 |title=Students on campus are mastering parkour, an art of self-awareness and body control |accessdate=19 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;parkour-journeys&quot;&gt;{{cite video |first=Andreas |last=Kalteis |title=Parkour Journeys&amp;nbsp;— Training with Andi |medium=DVD |publisher=Catsnake Studios |location=London, UK |year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study by ''Neuropsychiatrie de l'Enfance et de l'Adolescence'' (Neuropsychiatry of Childhood and Adolescence) in France found traceurs seek more excitement and leadership situations than gymnasts do.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1016/j.neurenf.2007.02.001| title = La pratique du parkour chez les adolescents des banlieues: Entre recherche de sensation et renforcement narcissique| journal = Neuropsychiatrie de l'Enfance et de l'Adolescence| volume = 55| issue = 3| pages = 154–159| year = 2007| last1 = Cazenave | first1 = N.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Academic research on parkour has tended to describe how parkour provides a novel way of interacting with the urban environment that challenges the use and meaning of urban space, metropolitan life, and embodiment.&lt;ref name=&quot;new-media-technologies&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=New Media Technologies in Lifestyle Sport |author1=Gilchrist, Paul |author2=Wheaton, Belinda |conference=Digital Media Sport: Technology and Power in the Network Society |editor=Hutchins/Rowe |date=30 July 2012 |url=https://www.academia.edu/1821623 |accessdate=8 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A newer convention of parkour philosophy has been the idea of &quot;human reclamation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;two-theories&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Two Theories on Parkour Philosophy |publisher=Parkour North America |url=http://parkournorthamerica.com/plugins/content/content.php?content.17 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120712091605/http://parkournorthamerica.com/plugins/content/content.php?content.17 |archivedate=12 July 2012 |date=7 September 2007 |accessdate=16 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Andy Tran of Urban Evolution clarifies it as &quot;a means of reclaiming what it means to be a human being. It teaches us to move using the natural methods that we should have learned from infancy. It teaches us to touch the world and interact with it, instead of being sheltered by it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;two-theories&quot;/&gt; Another traceur{{who|date=January 2016}} writes, &quot;It is as much as a part of truly learning the physical art as well as being able to master the movements, it gives you the ability to overcome your fears and pains and reapply this to life as you must be able to control your mind in order to master the art of parkour.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Parkour History |work=Urban discipline |url=http://www.urban-discipline.com/parkourhistory.htm |accessdate=5 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Competition===
A campaign was started on 1 May 2007 by the Parkour.NET portal to preserve parkour's philosophy against sports competition and rivalry.&lt;ref name=&quot;rivalry-free&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Keeping parkour rivalry-free : JOIN IN ! |publisher=Parkour.NET |url=http://parkour.net/forum/index.php?showtopic=9539 |date=1 May 2007 |accessdate=11 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title='Jumped-up' plan to stage world competition sees free runners falling out |first1=Paul |last1=Bignell |first2=Rob |last2=Sharp |work=The Independent |url=http://news.independent.co.uk/uk/this_britain/article2472154.ece |date=22 April 2007 |location=London |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080101230324/http://news.independent.co.uk/uk/this_britain/article2472154.ece |archivedate=1 January 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the words of [[Erwan Le Corre]]: &quot;Competition pushes people to fight against others for the satisfaction of a crowd and/or the benefits of a few business people by changing its mindset. Parkour is unique and cannot be a competitive sport unless it ignores its altruistic core of self-development. If parkour becomes a sport, it will be hard to seriously teach and spread parkour as a non-competitive activity. And a new sport will be spread that may be called parkour, but that won't hold its philosophical essence anymore.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;rivalry-free&quot;/&gt; Red Bull's sponsored athlete for parkour, Ryan Doyle, has said, &quot;Sometimes people ask, 'Who is the best at parkour?' and it is because they don't understand what Parkour is; 'Who is the best?' is what you would say to a sport, and parkour is not a sport, it is an art, it's a discipline. That's like saying, 'What's the best song in the world?'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z1NzOqfW7z4 |title=Ryan Doyle – Parkour Training Jam |publisher=YouTube |accessdate=22 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; This seems to be a highly consensual opinion of many professional traceurs who view parkour as a style of life more than a set of tricks, as has been popularised by YouTube and most media exposure. {{citation needed|date=September 2013}}

===David Belle===
In his 2009 book &quot;Parkour&quot;, David Belle stressed that the most important aspect of parkour is not the physical movements, but rather the practitioner's mentality and understanding of its principles. &quot;When young trainees come to see me and give me videos telling me to check out what they are doing, I just take the tape and throw it away. What I'm interested in is what the guy's got in his head, if he has self-confidence, if he masters the technique, if he has understood the principles of parkour. I just can't deal with guys who do Parkour because they saw videos on the Internet and thought it was kinda cool and want to do even better.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Belle2|Belle]], p. 58&lt;/ref&gt; Further, he states the importance of traceurs being aware of their abilities and limitations, and developing in their own way. &quot;When a young person asks me: 'Can you show me how to do this?' I simply answer: &quot;No, I am going to show you how ''I'' do it. Then, you'll have to learn with your own technique, your own way of moving, your style, your abilities and your limitations. You are going to learn to be yourself, not someone else.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;David Belle, Parkour, p.59&quot;/&gt;

The philosophy of parkour has been compared to that of martial arts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruce Lee and the Philosophy of parkour&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Bruce Lee and the Philosophy of Parkour | first= Rob | last= Green |publisher= WorldWideJam.tv |url=http://www.worldwidejam.tv/db.bl.jam.parkour.html |accessdate=1 February 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In an interview with ''The New Yorker'', David Belle acknowledges the influence: &quot;There's a quote by [[Bruce Lee]] that's my motto: 'There are no limits. There are plateaus, but you must not stay there, you must go beyond them. A man must constantly exceed his level.' If you're not better than you were the day before, then what are you doing—what's the point?&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;No Obstacles&quot; /&gt; In an interview with the press, Belle explained that parkour is a training method for warriors. &quot;So many people try to train easy 'Come do parkour! It's really cool!' But if tomorrow I made you do real training, you would end up crying. That's what you need to know: you are going to cry, you are going to bleed and you are going to sweat like never before.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cine parkour, p.22&lt;/ref&gt; In his book, Belle also quotes his father Raymond: &quot;If two roads open up before you, always take the most difficult one. Because you know you can travel the easy one.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Belle2|Belle]], p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;

Belle is an influential proponent of discipline and control in parkour, saying, &quot;Precision is all about being measured,&quot; and going on to describe parkour as an art that requires huge amounts of repetition and practice to master.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JUeHrPazTtY |title=David Belle – Parkour |publisher=YouTube |date=16 July 2011 |accessdate=22 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;With parkour, I often say, 'Once is never'. In other words, someone can manage a jump one time but it does not mean anything. It can be luck or chance. When you make a jump, you have to do it at least three times to be sure you can actually do it. It's an unavoidable rule. Do it the hard way and stop lying to yourself. When you come for training, you have to train. Even if it means doing the same jump fifty or a hundred times.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;David Belle, Parkour, p.59&quot;&gt;[[#Belle2|Belle]], p. 59&lt;/ref&gt; To its founder, parkour is a method of self-refinement, used for learning to control and focus oneself.

== Practice ==
=== Movement ===
[[File:Parkour - climb stairs.ogv|thumb|A practitioner climbing a wall]]
While there is no official list of &quot;moves&quot; in parkour, the style in which practitioners move often sets them apart from others,&lt;ref name=&quot;Freitas&quot; /&gt; and there are a number of movements considered fundamental.&lt;ref name=&quot;pkgen-history&quot; /&gt; Some examples of common movements are:&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Murray |first=Joseph B |year=2010 |title=Knowing Obstacles: Urban Dialogues in Parkour Practice |type=Doctoral dissertation |location=Central European University |url=http://www.etd.ceu.hu/2010/murray_joseph.pdf |accessdate=16 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mclean&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1016/j.injury.2006.04.119| pmid = 16806217| title = Paediatric fractures sustained in Parkour (free running)| journal = Injury| volume = 37| issue = 8| pages = 795–797| year = 2006| last1 = McLean | first1 = C. R. | last2 = Houshian | first2 = S.| last3 = Pike | first3 = J.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Vault (urban movement)|Vaulting]] over obstacles.
* &quot;Precision&quot; Jumping and landing accurately with the feet on small or narrow obstacles.
* &quot;Arm Jumps&quot; Jumping and landing feet-first on a vertical surface, catching the horizontal top with the hands.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1386/jdsp.2.2.143_1| title = Parkour and the critique of ideology: Turn-vaulting the fortresses of the city| journal = Journal of Dance and Somatic Practices| volume = 2| issue = 2| pages = 143–154| year = 2010| last1 = Chow | first1 = B. D. V. }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Using a rolling motion to help absorb impacts from larger drops.
* Running towards a high wall and then jumping and pushing off the wall with a foot to reach the top of the wall.
* Moving from a position hanging from a wall-top or ledge, to standing on the top or over to the other side.

=== Equipment ===
[[File:Parkour - Poliana.jpg|thumb|A ''traceuse'' vaults an obstacle.]]
Parkour is practiced without equipment of any kind. Practitioners normally train wearing light, non-restrictive casual clothing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090203212658/http://www.americanparkour.com/content/view/50/237/
|url=http://www.americanparkour.com/content/view/50/237/ |title=What Should I Wear for parkour? |date=6 November 2005 |archivedate=3 February 2009 |publisher=americanparkour.com
|accessdate=21 April 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://parkourvisions.org/resources/parents-faq.pdf |title=Is there any equipment cost, membership fee, or exclusive conditions required for my child to do Parkour? |year = 2008 |publisher=washingtonparkour.com |accessdate=4 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Traceurs who wear gloves are rare—bare hands are considered better for grip and tactile feedback.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.herald-mail.com/2009-09-28/news/25176213_1_parkour-cross-country-jfk-50-mile |title=Parkour: All in a day's training |last=Arnold |first=Tiffany |date=28 September 2009 |work=[[Herald Mail]] |accessdate=25 July 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140203143705/http://articles.herald-mail.com/2009-09-28/news/25176213_1_parkour-cross-country-jfk-50-mile |archivedate=3 February 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thenational.ae/article/20090223/LIFE/125121212/-1/SPORT |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090226064531/http://www.thenational.ae/article/20090223/LIFE/125121212/1196/TRAVEL |archivedate=26 February 2009 |title=You might as well jump |last=Money-Coutts |first=Sophia |date=23 February 2009 |work=[[The National (Abu Dhabi)|The National]]|publisher=Abu Dhabi Media Company |accessdate=25 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Light running shoes with good grip and flexibility are encouraged because they allow for more natural and fluid movements. Practitioners often use [[minimalist shoes]], sometimes as a progression to bare feet, for better sensitivity and balance, while others prefer more cushioning for better absorption of impacts from large jumps.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://parkourshoesguide.com/|title=10 Best Parkour Shoes (2020) – Freerunning Shoes Reviewed|last=|first=|date=2017-06-11|work=ParkourShoesGuide|access-date=2017-06-19|url-status=live|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Barefoot training is done by some for movement competency without gear—David Belle noted that &quot;bare feet are the best shoes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QMw3q3NjqRk |title=David Belle&amp;nbsp;— Parkour simples |date= 16 March 2007 |publisher=YouTube |accessdate=7 July 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Various [[sneakers|sneaker]] manufacturers have developed shoes specifically for parkour and [[freerunning]]. Many other companies around the world have started offering clothing targeted at parkour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Know Obstacles|url=http://www.knowobstacles.com|accessdate=12 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Risks ===
==== Trespassing ====
[[File:Wiki parkour leavenotrace.jpeg|thumb|Traceurs in [[Lisses]] re-painting a wall, repairing shoe scuff marks from parkour.]]
[[File:Wiki parkour ban.jpg|thumb|A notice on a wall of the [[Strasbourg Museum of Modern and Contemporary Art]] in 2012 prohibiting parkour (removed in 2018).]]
Parkour is not widely practiced in dedicated public facilities. Although efforts are being made to create places for it, many traceurs do not like the idea, as it is contradictory to parkour's values of adaptation, creativity, and freedom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090414060418/http://www.miramar.usmc.mil/newspage175.htm|title=American Parkour HotSpots Contest |date=21 May 2008 |accessdate=13 June 2008|archivedate=14 April 2009|url=http://www.miramar.usmc.mil/newspage175.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Traceurs practice parkour in both rural and urban areas such as gyms, parks, playgrounds, offices, and abandoned structures. Concerns have been raised regarding trespassing, damage of property,&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCArr&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/gloucestershire/7220380.stm Gloucestershire&amp;nbsp;– Rooftop-jumping youths arrested]. [[BBC]]. 31 January 2008. Retrieved 15 March 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and use of inappropriate places such as cemeteries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/2079539/Gravestone-vaulting-teenagers-condemned-over-YouTube-stunt.html |title=Gravestone vaulting teenagers condemned over YouTube stunt |date=6 May 2008 |last=Gammell |first=Caroline |accessdate=13 June 2008 | work=The Daily Telegraph | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many parkour organizations around the globe support the ''Leave No Trace'' initiative, an urban version of the [[Leave No Trace|outdoor conservation ethic]] created by the Seattle [[Nonprofit organization|nonprofit]] ''Parkour Visions'' in 2008, promoting safety, respect for the spaces used and their other users, and sometimes includes picking up rubbish to leave areas in better condition than they were found.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://parkourvisions.org/projects/leave-no-trace/ |title=Leave No Trace Campaign (practice policy) |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120929092640/http://parkourvisions.org/projects/leave-no-trace/ |archivedate=29 September 2012 |accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Without a Trace |work=Vertical Floor Magazine |last=Bafford |first=Tenedra |date=June 2013 |url=http://verticalfloormag.com/?p=72 |accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=New Zealand Parkour Vision and Values |last=Puddle |first=Damien |date=23 July 2014 |url=http://nzparkour.co.nz/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/NZ-Parkour-Vision-and-Values.pdf |accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://parkour.uga.edu/ |title=Parkour at UGA |first=Jimmy | last=Hansen |date=1 March 2011 |accessdate=6 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=American Parkour leaves Meridian Park when asked during national jam |url=http://americanparkour.com/component/content/6562?task=view |website=American Parkour |accessdate=7 November 2015 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130927125033/http://americanparkour.com/component/content/6562?task=view |archivedate=27 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Injuries and deaths ====
Concerns have been raised by law enforcement and fire and rescue teams of the risk in jumping off high buildings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1607235,00.html |title=Student Stuntmen |date=5 April 2008 |last=Rawe | first=Julie |work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |accessdate=13 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; They argue that practitioners are needlessly risking damage to both themselves and rooftops by practicing at height, with police forces calling for practitioners to stay off the rooftops.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCArr&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=ULGuardian&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yourlocalguardian.co.uk/news/suttonnews/display.var.2166130.0.youths_on_roofs.php |title=Youths on Roofs |work=Your Local Guardian |date=2 April 2008 |accessdate=9 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.schriever.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123100262 |title=Parkour growing by leaps and bounds |first=Don | last=Branum |date=2 June 2008 |accessdate=27 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some practitioners of Parkour agree that such behaviour should be discouraged.&lt;ref name=ULGuardian/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080612003334/http://www.americanparkour.com/content/view/2364/1/|archivedate=12 June 2008|title=Terrible Representation of Parkour and Freerunning |date=13 June 2008 |accessdate=13 June 2008|url=http://www.americanparkour.com/content/view/2364/1/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Jacob |last=Comenetz |url=http://www.dw.com/en/running-through-life-the-parkour-way/a-1701098 |title=Running Through Life the Parkour Way |publisher=Deutsche Welle  |date= 9 June 2005 |accessdate=9 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://datingthin.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/parents-faq.pdf Parkour FAQ for Parents] (PDF). Pacific Northwest Parkour Association. 20 September 2008. Retrieved 17 August 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

Because parkour philosophy is about learning to control oneself in interaction with the environment, {{clarify span|text=many parkour experts tend to view serious physical injury as a deviation from true parkour |explain=interpretation of beachcombermb.com source?|date=July 2019}}. Daniel Ilabaca, co-founder of the World Parkour and Freerunning Federation, said &quot;Thinking you're going to fail at something gives you a higher risk of doing just that. Committing to something you're thinking or knowing you will land gives you a higher chance of landing or completing the task.&quot;&lt;ref name=beachcombermb&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.beachcombermb.com/opinions/2012/01/27/parkour-legends-daniel-ilabaca-tim-shieff-and-oleg-vorslov/ |title=The Beachcomber : Parkour Legends: Daniel Ilabaca, Tim Shieff, and Oleg Vorslov |publisher=Beachcombermb.com |date=17 March 2013 |accessdate=22 May 2014|url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130807001610/http://www.beachcombermb.com/opinions/2012/01/27/parkour-legends-daniel-ilabaca-tim-shieff-and-oleg-vorslov/ |archivedate=7 August 2013 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; On [[Sports biomechanics|biomechanical]] grounds, a single study found that certain parkour landing techniques may lead to lower landing forces and loads in comparison with traditional sport technique.&lt;ref name=&quot;Puddle&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal| pmid = 24149735| pmc = 3761764| year = 2013| last1 = Puddle| first1 = D. L.| title = Ground reaction forces and loading rates associated with parkour and traditional drop landing techniques| journal = Journal of Sports Science &amp; Medicine| volume = 12| issue = 1| pages = 122–9| last2 = Maulder| first2 = P. S.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a [[Survey methodology|survey]] of parkour-related emergency department visits in the United States between 2009 and 2015, most injuries were reportedly caused by landing or from striking objects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Rossheim |first1=ME |last2=Stephenson |first2=CJ |title=Parkour injuries presenting to United States emergency departments, 2009-2015. |journal=The American Journal of Emergency Medicine |date=October 2017 |volume=35 |issue=10 |pages=1503–1505 |doi=10.1016/j.ajem.2017.04.040 |pmid=28455090}}&lt;/ref&gt;

American traceur Mark Toorock said injuries are rare &quot;because participants rely not on what they can't control&amp;nbsp;– wheels or the icy surfaces of snowboarding and skiing&amp;nbsp;– but their own hands and feet,&quot; but Lanier Johnson, executive director of the [[American Sports Medicine Institute]], noted that many of the injuries are not reported.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Jump First, Ask Questions Later |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/01/08/AR2008010803471_4.html | date=8 January 2008 |first=Colin |last=Bane |work=[[The Washington Post]] |accessdate=19 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Impact ==
Initially featured in films of French director/producer [[Luc Besson]], parkour was first introduced to the British public by the [[BBC One]] TV channel trailer ''Rush Hour'' in April 2002. It featured David Belle leaping across London's rooftops from his office to home, in an attempt to catch his favourite BBC programme,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Unmissable new campaign for BBC ONE |work=BBC Press Office |date=11 April 2002 |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/pressoffice/pressreleases/stories/2002/04_april/11/rush_hour.shtml |accessdate=2 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and captured the imagination of many viewers, especially when they learned no special effects or wires were used.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=BBC film's rooftop stunts 'real' |work=BBC News |date=19 April 2002 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/1939106.stm |accessdate=2 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; This advertisement, along with others for [[Coca-Cola]], [[Nike, Inc.|Nike]], and [[Toyota]], had a large-scale impact on public awareness of parkour.&lt;ref name=&quot;pkgen-history&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Urban Free Flow: A Poetics of Parkour |last=Geyh |first=Paula |journal=M/C Journal |volume=9 |issue=3 |date=July 2006 |url=http://journal.media-culture.org.au/0607/06-geyh.php |accessdate=2 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The creation of parkour show-reels and documentaries has always been crucial to the spread of parkour, and is common in the parkour community.&lt;ref name=&quot;CineP20&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Parkour-DB3&quot;/&gt; ''[[Jump London]]'' is a 2003 documentary explaining some of the background of parkour, culminating with [[Sébastien Foucan]], Johann Vigroux, and [[Jérôme Ben Aoues]] demonstrating their parkour skills. ''Jump London'' changed the presence of parkour in the UK almost overnight and is widely credited for inspiring a new generation of traceurs.&lt;ref name=&quot;new-media-technologies&quot; /&gt; It was followed by ''[[Jump Britain]]'' in 2005. Both Jump films were shown in over 80 countries exposing the discipline and its philosophy to an unprecedented global audience and are cited by numerous practitioners as their motivation for taking up the discipline.

The Australian version of ''[[60 Minutes (Australian TV program)|60 Minutes]]'' broadcast a segment about parkour on 16 September 2007, featuring Foucan and Stephane Vigroux.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Go Jump|url=http://sixtyminutes.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=295676| authorlink=Liz Hayes|first=Liz|last=Hayes|work=[[60 Minutes (Australian TV program)|60 Minutes]]|date=16 September 2007|accessdate=3 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Parkour is not defined by a set of rules or guidelines, which has been particularly attractive to young people, allowing them to explore and engage in the activity on their own terms. It can be easily accepted by all cultures as a means of personal expression and recreation.&lt;ref name=Thorpe1&gt;{{cite book|title=International Review for the Sociology of Sport |last=Thorpe |first=Holly |year=2013 |publisher=SAGE Publications Inc |page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in 2010 ''[[The New York Times]]'' published a short video featuring three young men from the Gaza Strip who were active members of the parkour community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Palestinian Parkour |last=Sorcher |first=Sara |work=The New York Times |date=13 October 2010 |type=video |url=https://www.nytimes.com/video/world/middleeast/1248069141234/palestinian-parkour.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, the [[BBC]] covered youth parkour participation in [[Jammu and Kashmir]]. Zahid Shah founded the Kashmir Freerunning and Parkour Federation, finding hope in the non-violent discipline of parkour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Kashmir freerunning: Finding freedom in the art of parkour |date=7 December 2014 |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-30347099/ |accessdate=1 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Entertainment ===
&lt;!-- Please do not add anything uncited.--&gt;
Parkour has become a popular element in action sequences, with film directors hiring parkour practitioners as [[stunt performer]]s. The first director to do so was [[Luc Besson]], for the film ''[[Taxi 2]]'' in 1998, followed by ''[[Yamakasi (film)|Yamakasi]]'' in 2001 featuring members of the original [[Yamakasi]] group, and its sequel ''[[Les fils du vent]]'' in 2004. Also in 2004, Besson wrote ''[[District 13]]'', another feature film involving advanced parkour chase sequences, starring [[David Belle]] and [[Cyril Raffaelli]],&lt;ref name=LADailyNews/&gt;&lt;ref name=TimesOnline/&gt; followed by the sequel ''[[District 13: Ultimatum]]'' in 2009 and remade in English as ''[[Brick Mansions]]'' in 2014. In 2006 the film ''[[Casino Royale (2006 film)|Casino Royale]]'' featured Sébastien Foucan in a chase taking place early in the movie, sparking renewed media interest in parkour.&lt;ref name=&quot;No Obstacles&quot;/&gt; Along with ''[[The Bourne Ultimatum (film)|The Bourne Ultimatum]]'' (2007), ''Casino Royale'' is credited with starting a new wave of Parkour-inspired stunts in [[Western world|Western]] film and television.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollywood Reporter&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title= Fremantle Pacts to Bring Parkour to TV Screens|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/televisionNews/idUSTRE57R0OZ20090828|date= 28 August 2009|first=Georg|last=Szalai|agency=[[Reuters]]|accessdate=23 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Parkour was prominent in ''[[Live Free or Die Hard]]'' (2007),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title='Look, Ma, no hands' — or feet |url=https://www.usatoday.com/life/lifestyle/2007-12-03-parkour_N.htm |last=Kornblum |first=Janet |date=3 December 2007 |newspaper=[[USA Today]] |accessdate=7 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; again with stuntman/actor Cyril Raffaelli, and ''[[Prince of Persia: The Sands of Time (film)|Prince of Persia: The Sands of Time]]'' (2010), choreographed by David Belle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.emanuellevy.com/comment/prince-of-persia-tackling-stunts-and-parkour-1/ |first=Emanuel |last=Levy |title=Prince of Persia: Tackling Stunts and Parkour |year=2010 |accessdate=10 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several films besides ''Yamakasi'' are about thieves who use parkour, such as ''[[Breaking and Entering (film)|Breaking and Entering]]'' (2006),&lt;ref name=LADailyNews&gt;{{cite news|title=Parkour: Leaps of faith|url=http://www.dailynews.com/entertainment/ci_4937806| first=Sandra|last=Barrera|date=2 January 2007|newspaper=[[Los Angeles Daily News]]|accessdate=11 December 2007|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070224231820/http://www.dailynews.com/entertainment/ci_4937806|archivedate=24 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TimesOnline&gt;{{cite news|title=Focus: Look Mum, watch this!|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2087-2262412,00.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080829131418/http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2087-2262412,00.html|archivedate=29 August 2008|first1=Yuba|last1=Bessaoud|first2=Alex|last2=Delmar-Morgan|date=9 July 2006|work=[[The Times]]|accessdate=3 January 2008|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Run'' (2013),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Run (2013) |work=IMDb |url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2215457/ |accessdate=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Tracers (film)|Tracers]]'' (2015). The 2011 film ''[[Freerunner (film)|Freerunner]]'' is about eight [[freerunning|freerunners]] racing through a city for survival. Parkour also featured in ''[[Dhoom 3]]'' (2013)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Lalwani|first=Vickey|title=Aamir Khan learns French technique of Parkour|url= http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/entertainment/bollywood/news-interviews/Aamir-Khan-learns-French-technique-of-Parkour/articleshow/10778399.cms|accessdate=24 November 2011|newspaper=[[Mumbai Mirror]]; [[The Times of India]]|date=18 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Aadhi]]'' (2018).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=George|first=Vijay|title='Aadhi' packs a punch with parkour|url=http://www.thehindu.com/entertainment/movies/jeethu-joseph-on-his-film-aadhi-which-introduces-pranav-mohanlal/article22503604.ece|accessdate=30 January 2018|work=[[The Hindu]]|date=25 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2019 [[Netflix]] film ''[[6 Underground (film)|6 Underground]]'' featured several parkour scenes choreographed and performed by team [[Storror]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.looper.com/179374/the-truth-about-those-parkour-scenes-in-6-underground/|title=The truth about those parkour scenes in 6 Underground|last=Gates|first=Christopher|website=Looper.com|language=en-US|access-date=2020-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.metro.us/entertainment/movies/Ben-Hardy-talks-6-underground-and-Michael-Bay|website=www.metro.us|access-date=2020-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[MTV]]'s show ''Ultimate Parkour Challenge'' premiered as a one-hour special in October 2009 starring the athletes of the [[World Freerunning &amp; Parkour Federation]]. This was followed in May 2010 with a six-episode series of the same name. The athletes were [[Daniel Ilabaca]], [[Tim Shieff]], [[Ryan Doyle]], Michael Turner, Oleg Vorslav, Ben Jenkin, Daniel Arroyo, Pip Andersen and King David. The programme format was a two-part weekly competition in different Southern California locations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Ultimate Parkour Challenge |publisher=[[MTV]] |url=http://www.mtv.com/shows/parkour/series.jhtml |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131207235230/http://www.mtv.com/shows/parkour/series.jhtml |archivedate=7 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Actor [[Stephen Amell]] learned parkour at Tempest Academy in preparation for his role as Oliver Queen in the television series ''[[Arrow (TV series)|Arrow]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Wickline, Dan (18 June 2014). [http://www.bleedingcool.com/2014/06/18/stephen-amell-back-in-training-for-arrow-season-3/ &quot;Stephen Amell Back In Training For Arrow Season 3&quot;]. ''Bleeding Cool Comic Book, Movie, TV News''.&lt;/ref&gt; and co-star [[Caity Lotz]] is also a practitioner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.daemonstv.com/2011/07/21/caity-lotz-interview/ |title=Exclusive Interview: Kick Ass Caity Lotz From MTV's DEATH VALLEY Talks About Zombies, Parcour and Twilight's Jackson Rathbone |accessdate=27 May 2016|publisher=Daemon's TV}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Modern video games frequently include aspects of parkour as major game-play elements. The [[Assassin's Creed|''Assassin's Creed'' series]] makes heavy use of parkour movement (called freerunning in the game).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Assassin's Creed (Xbox 360) |url=http://www.gamesxtreme.net/x360/game/assassins-creed/review.shtml |date=28 November 2007 |accessdate=11 December 2007 |quote=It's a good start, an excellent free-roaming adventure with some of the best use of parkour yet.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Review: 'Assassin's Creed' Not Quite Perfect |url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,311973,00.html |first=Ryan |last=Pearson |publisher=[[Fox News Channel]] |quote=Leave it to the French to bring us the first parkour video game |date=16 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Andrew |last=P. |title=Review of ''Assassin's Creed'' |journal=Electronic Gaming Monthly |issue=224 |date=January 2008 |page=89 |quote=...&amp;nbsp;the game features 'a challenging parkour path of escape&amp;nbsp;...'}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Mirror's Edge]]'' games are heavily inspired by parkour, consisting entirely of efficiently moving around buildings, rooftops, and other obstacles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesunion.com/local/article/Mysterious-gift-puts-to-rest-1903-deaths-of-three-608191.php | work=Wired | first=Chris | last=Baker | title=Review: Mirror's Edge, the First-Person Parkour Game You Must Play | date=11 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Mirror's Edge puts grace of parkour at fingertips |url=http://www.timesunion.com/AspStories/story.asp?storyID=744129&amp;category=ARTS |first=Doug |last=Elfman |date=28 November 2008 |accessdate=23 September 2009 }}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Brink (video game)|Brink]]'' introduced a parkour mechanic into a realistic [[first person shooter]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=GDC Europe: Perfecting The SMART Parkour Traversal System In ''Brink'' |date=15 August 2011 |last=Nutt |first=Christian |work=Gamasura |url=http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/126533/GDC_Europe_Perfecting_The_SMART_Parkour_Traversal_System_In_Brink.php |accessdate=29 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Prince of Persia]]'' and ''[[Dying Light]]'' include a central parkour mechanic,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.twinfinite.net/2014/06/13/e3-dying-light-hands-preview/|title=E3 – Dying Light Hands-On Preview|first=Alissa|last=Mcaloon|work=twinfinite.com|date=13 June 2014|accessdate=13 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/2867562/dying-light-preview-zombies-are-even-more-stomach-churning-in-virtual-reality.html|title=Dying Light preview: Zombies are even more stomach-churning in virtual reality|first=Hayden|last=Dingman|work=PCWorld|date=1 March 2015|accessdate=1 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; while ''[[Crackdown]]'' and ''[[Crackdown 2]]'' include an emphasis on gripping and vaulting from ledges and protruding objects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=10 Reasons to Play Crackdown |url=http://xbox360.ign.com/articles/754/754563p1.html |first=Cam |last=Shea |date=10 January 2007 |accessdate=3 January 2008 |quote=It's part super hero (think Hulk or Neo), part Jumping Flash and part parkour.}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Tony Hawk's American Wasteland]]'' allows the character to use several freerunning techniques while not on the skateboard.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Tony Hawk's American Wasteland&amp;nbsp;— Xbox 360 |url=http://hexus.net/gaming/reviews/xbox-360/4583-tony-hawks-american-wasteland-xbox-360/ |first=Steven |last=Williamson |date=8 February 2006 |accessdate=10 February 2013 |quote=Later on in story mode, you'll even get the chance to learn some parkour skills!}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Tron Evolution]]''{{'}}s basic movements and combat were based on parkour and [[capoeira]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview|title=Tron Evolution Pre-E3 Hands-On Interview: Alex Peters |first=Darren |last=Hedges |url=http://www.gamespot.com/tron-evolution/videos/tron-evolution-pre-e3-hands-on-interview-alex-peters-6263033/ |date=18 May 2010 |publisher=GameSpot |interviewer=Ricardo Torres |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130518191251/http://www.gamespot.com/tron-evolution/videos/tron-evolution-pre-e3-hands-on-interview-alex-peters-6263033/ |archivedate=18 May 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Military training ===
Although parkour itself grew out of military obstacle-course training,&lt;ref name=&quot;CineP20&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Parkour-DB1&quot;/&gt; it has become a separate discipline. After the attention that parkour received following the 2006 film ''[[Casino Royale (2006 film)|Casino Royale]]'', military forces around the world began looking for ways to incorporate elements from parkour into military training. A physical trainer with the Royal Marines trained with parkour practitioners with hopes of introducing some of their techniques to his own students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2008/jan/12/military.uknews4 |title=Freerunning goes to war as marines take tips from EZ, Livewire and Sticky |work=The Guardian |date= 12 January 2008 |accessdate=9 August 2009 | location=London | first=Robert | last=Booth}}&lt;/ref&gt; Colorado Parkour began a project to introduce elements from parkour into the U.S. military&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.coloradoparkour.com/projects.html |title=Projects |publisher=Colorado Parkour |accessdate=9 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and one [[Miramar, San Diego|San Diego]] staff sergeant trained [[United States Marine Corps|US Marines]] in parkour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090414060418/http://www.miramar.usmc.mil/newspage175.htm |title=Parkour: Getting over the wall |publisher=US Marine Corps |date=23 January 2009 |accessdate=9 August 2009 |archivedate=14 April 2009|url=http://www.miramar.usmc.mil/newspage175.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Robotics ===

In October 2018, [[WIRED]] magazine issued a report (&quot;Watch Boston Dynamics' Humanoid Robot Do Parkour&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
| url           = https://www.wired.com/story/watch-boston-dynamics-humanoid-robot-do-parkour/ 
| title         = Watch Boston Dynamics' Humanoid Robot Do Parkour 
| last          = Simon 
| first         = Matt 
| date          = 11 October 2018 
| publisher     = [[WIRED]] magazine 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; that included some videos showing a humanoid robot doing parkour. (&quot;See also&quot; the later article,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
| url           = https://www.wired.com/story/how-boston-dynamics-robot-videos-became-internet-gold/ 
| title         = How Boston Dynamics' Robot Videos Became Internet Gold 
| last          = Simon 
| first         = Matt 
| date          = 30 October 2018 
| publisher     = [[WIRED]] magazine 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; by the same author, called ''&quot;How Boston Dynamics' Robot Videos Became Internet Gold&quot;''.)

== Derivative terminologies and disciplines ==
In September 2003, Mike Christie's documentary ''[[Jump London]]'', starring [[Sébastien Foucan]], was released. In the documentary, the term &quot;[[freerunning]]&quot; was used as an attempt to translate &quot;parkour&quot;, in order to make it more appealing to the English-speaking audience.&lt;ref&gt;Edwardes, Dan (2009) ''The Parkour &amp; Freerunning Handbook''. It Books. {{ISBN|0-06-178367-6}}. p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; Foucan decided to keep using the term &quot;freerunning&quot; to describe his discipline, to distinguish it from David Belle's methods.&lt;ref name=&quot;FreerunningSF&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Free Running |last=Foucan |first=Sébastien |authorlink=Sébastien Foucan |year=2008  |isbn=978-1-56975-652-2 |pages=8–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CineP39&quot;&gt;[[#Angel|Angel]], p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;

The remaining seven ''Yamakasi'' members continued to use the term &quot;''l'art du déplacement''{{-&quot;}}, also not wanting to associate it too closely with parkour. Similar to Sébastien's freerunning, ''l'art du déplacement'' was less about the hard discipline from the original ''Yamakasi'' group, more a participatory approach focused on making the teaching more accessible. David Belle kept the term &quot;parkour&quot;, saying the group contributed to the development of it, but that his father was the source of his motivation, who had verbally communicated this method only to him.&lt;ref name=&quot;CineP39&quot;/&gt;

Both parkour and freerunning encompass the ideas of overcoming obstacles and self-expression; in freerunning, the greater emphasis is on self-expression.&lt;ref name=&quot;FreerunningSF&quot;/&gt; Although the differences between the disciplines are often hard to discern, practitioners tend to aspire to parkour and describe themselves as traceurs rather than as freerunners.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kidder1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1111/j.1540-6040.2012.01406.x| title = Parkour, the Affective Appropriation of Urban Space, and the Real/Virtual Dialectic| journal = City &amp; Community| volume = 11| issue = 3| pages = 229–253| year = 2012| last1 = Kidder | first1 = J. L. | citeseerx = 10.1.1.645.395}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Anan Anwar]]
* [[Bruce Lee]]
* [[Buildering]]
* [[Buster Keaton]] - Silent film actor and producer
* [[Dérive]] - a philosophy and technique of rapid, serendipitous movement through mostly urban environments
* [[Freerunning]]
* [[Jackie Chan]]
* [[Jet Li]]
* [[Obstacle course]]
* [[Obstacle racing]]
* [[Plyometrics]] - Exercises to develop muscles for jumping
* [[Qinggong]] - Chinese martial arts techniques
* [[Tony Jaa]]
* [[Urban exploration]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
{{Sister project links |wikt=parkour |commons=Parkour |n=no |q=Parkour |s=no |b=Parkour |voy=no |v=Parkour and Freerunning |d=no}}
* {{cite book |ref=Angel|title=Ciné Parkour |last=Angel |first=Julie |year=2011 |isbn=978-0-9569717-1-5}}
* {{cite book|ref=Belle|author1=Belle, David  |author2=Perriére, Charles  |lastauthoramp=yes |title=PARKOUR – From the origins to the practise}}
* {{cite book|ref=Belle2|title=Parkour |last=Belle |first=David |authorlink=David Belle |year=2009 |publisher=Intervista |isbn=978-2-35756-025-3}}

{{Parkour and Freerunning}}

[[Category:Parkour| ]]
[[Category:Sports originating in France]]
[[Category:Acrobatic sports]]
[[Category:Outdoor recreation]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Jumping sports]]
[[Category:Games and sports introduced in the 1980s]]</text>
      <sha1>4wwe0e6ou12okif3n5i1b0tqrxbojsn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
