  <page>
    <title>Petra</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>45008</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938654849</id>
      <parentid>937901081</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-01T16:30:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>82.213.237.170</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Music and musical videos */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the ancient Jordanian city of Petra}}
{{short description|Ancient historical site in Jordan}}
{{Infobox historic site
| name       = Petra&lt;br /&gt;Raqmu
| image      = Petra Jordan BW 21.JPG
| image_size = 200px
| caption    = Tourists in front of [[Al Khazneh]] (The Treasury) at Petra
| location   = [[Ma'an Governorate]], [[Jordan]]
| coordinates= {{coord|30|19|43|N|35|26|31|E|region:JO-MN_type:landmark|display=inline,title}}
| locmapin   = Jordan
| built      = possibly as early as 5th century BC &lt;ref&gt;Browning, Iain (1973, 1982), ''Petra'', Chatto &amp; Windus, London, p. 15, {{ISBN|0-7011-2622-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| elevation  = {{convert|810|m|abbr=on|0}}
| beginning_label =
| beginning_date = 
| architect    =
| architecture =
| area       = {{convert|264|km2}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Petra National Trust site&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Management of Petra|url=http://petranationaltrust.org/UI/ShowContent.aspx?ContentId=207|publisher=Petra National Trust|accessdate=14 April 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150419110653/http://petranationaltrust.org/UI/ShowContent.aspx?ContentId=207|archive-date=19 April 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| visitation_num = 1,135,300
| visitation_year = 2019
| governing_body = Petra Region Authority
| embedded = 
  {{Infobox UNESCO World Heritage Site
|child    = yes
|ID       = 326
|Year     = 1985
|Criteria = Cultural: i, iii, iv
}}
| website = {{URL|http://www.visitpetra.jo|www.visitpetra.jo}}
}}

'''Petra''' ({{lang-ar|ٱلْبَتْرَاء|Al-Batrāʾ}}; {{lang-grc|Πέτρα}}, &quot;Stone&quot;), originally known to its inhabitants as '''Raqmu''',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.jo/books?id=bpWGAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA14|title=Men on the Rocks: The Formation of Nabataean Petra|accessdate=14 November 2019|year=2013|author=Stephan G. Schmid and Michel Mouton}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a historical and archaeological city in southern [[Jordan]]. Petra lies around [[Jebel al-Madhbah|Jabal Al-Madbah]] in a [[Depression (geology)|basin]] surrounded by mountains which form the eastern flank of the [[Arabah]] valley that runs from the [[Dead Sea]] to the [[Gulf of Aqaba]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot; /&gt; The area around Petra has been inhabited as early as 7,000&amp;nbsp;BC,&lt;ref name=&quot;PNF&quot;/&gt; and the [[Nabataeans]] might have settled in what would become the capital city of their [[Nabataean Kingdom|kingdom]], as early as the 4th century BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;lost kingdom&quot;/&gt; However, archaeological work has only discovered evidence of Nabataean presence dating back to the second century BC,&lt;ref name=&quot;NGlost&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Petra. The &quot;Lost City&quot; still has secrets to reveal: Thousands of years ago, the now-abandoned city of Petra was thriving. |author= Mati Milstein |work= National Geographic |date= |url= https://www.nationalgeographic.com/history/archaeology/lost-city-petra/ |access-date=27 December 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; by which time Petra had become their capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;PNF&quot;/&gt; The Nabataeans were nomadic [[Arabs]] who invested in Petra's proximity to the [[Incense Route|trade routes]] by establishing it as a major regional trading hub.&lt;ref name=&quot;PNF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author= Jack D. Elliott, Jr. |title= The Nabatean Synthesis of Avraham Negev: A Critical Appraisal |editor= Joe D. Seger |work= Retrieving the Past: Essays on Archaeological Research and Methodology in Honor of Gus W. Van Beek |year= 1996 |publisher= Eisenbrauns |isbn= 9781575060125 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=2PWC98JLn7QC&amp;pg=PA56 |page= 56 |access-date=27 December 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The trading business gained the Nabataeans considerable revenue and Petra became the focus of their wealth. The Nabataeans were accustomed to living in the barren deserts, unlike their enemies, and were able to repel attacks by taking advantage of the area's mountainous terrain. They were particularly skillful in [[Rainwater harvesting|harvesting rainwater]], [[agriculture]] and [[stone carving]]. Petra flourished in the 1st century AD, when its famous [[Khazneh]] structure – believed to be the [[mausoleum]] of Nabataean king [[Aretas IV Philopatris|Aretas IV]] – was constructed, and its population peaked at an estimated 20,000 inhabitants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nationalgeographic.com/archaeology-and-history/magazine/2016/01-02/petra/|title=Petra Lost and Found|work=National Geographic|date=2 January 2016|accessdate=8 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the Nabataean kingdom became a client state of the [[Roman Empire]] in the first century BC, it was only in 106 AD that it lost its independence. Petra fell to the Romans, who annexed Nabataea and renamed it as [[Arabia Petraea]]. Petra's importance declined as sea trade routes emerged, and after an [[Galilee earthquake of 363|earthquake in 363]] destroyed many structures. In the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine era]] several Christian churches were built, but the city continued to decline, and by the early Islamic era it was abandoned except for a handful of nomads. It remained unknown to the world until it was rediscovered in 1812 by [[Johann Ludwig Burckhardt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/17/arts/art-review-rose-red-city-carved-from-the-rock.html|title=ART REVIEW; Rose-Red City Carved From the Rock|first=Grace|last=Glueck|date=17 October 2003|publisher=|newspaper=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Access to the city is through a {{convert|1.2|km|mi|adj=mid|-long}} gorge called the [[Siq]], which leads directly to the Khazneh. Famous for its [[rock-cut architecture]] and water conduit system, Petra is also called the 'Rose City' because of the colour of the stone from which it is carved.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jordan Tourism board&quot;&gt;[http://www.visitjordan.com/Default.aspx?Tabid=63 Major Attractions: Petra], Jordan tourism board&lt;/ref&gt; It has been a [[UNESCO]] [[World Heritage Site]] since 1985. UNESCO has described Petra as &quot;one of the most precious cultural properties of man's cultural heritage&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;unesco&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://whc.unesco.org/archive/advisory_body_evaluation/326.pdf |title=UNESCO advisory body evaluation |accessdate=2011-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, Al-Khazneh was voted one of the [[New7Wonders of the World]]. Petra is a symbol of Jordan, as well as Jordan's most-visited tourist attraction. Tourist numbers peaked at 918,000 in 2010, but there followed a temporary slump during the political instability generated by the [[Arab Spring]], which affected countries surrounding Jordan.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20111117043619/http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2011/01/2011128125157509196.html Thousands protest in Jordan], January 28, 2011. Retrieved May 20, 2019.&lt;/ref&gt; Visitor numbers subsequently increased and reached a record-breaking 1.1 million tourists in 2019, marking the first time that the figure rose above the 1 million mark.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.jordantimes.com/news/local/rose-red-city-petra-wraps-2019-record-breaking-1135300-visitors|title=Rose-red city of Petra wraps up 2019 with record-breaking 1,135,300 visitors|work=The Jordan Times|accessdate=6 January 2020|date=6 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Importance in Antiquity==
[[Pliny the Elder]] and other writers identify Petra as the capital of the [[Nabataean Kingdom]] and the centre of their [[camel train|caravan]] trade. Enclosed by towering rocks and watered by a [[perennial stream]], Petra not only possessed the advantages of a fortress, but controlled the main commercial routes which passed through it to [[Gaza City|Gaza]] in the west, to [[Bosra]] and [[Damascus]] in the north, to [[Aqaba]] and Leuce Come on the [[Red Sea]], and across the desert to the [[Persian Gulf]].&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;

==Description==
[[File:Karta Petra.PNG|thumb|upright=1.55|Map of Petra]]
===Water control===
Excavations have demonstrated that it was the ability of the Nabataeans to control the water supply that led to the rise of the desert city, creating an artificial [[oasis]]. The area is visited by [[flash flood]]s, but archaeological evidence shows that the Nabataeans controlled these floods by the use of [[dam]]s, [[cistern]]s and water conduits. These innovations stored water for prolonged periods of [[drought]] and enabled the city to prosper from its sale.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nabataea.net/waterw.html |title=Petra: Water Works |publisher=Nabataea.net |accessdate=2011-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Lisa Pinsker |url=http://www.agiweb.org/geotimes/june04/feature_petra.html |title=Geotimes – June 2004 – Petra: An Eroding Ancient City |publisher=Agiweb.org |date=2001-09-11 |accessdate=2011-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[image:Petra-Roman-Aqueduct.jpg|thumb|left|The narrow passage ([[Siq]]) that leads to Petra]]

===Access routes===
In ancient times, Petra might have been approached from the south on a track leading across the plain of Petra, around Jabal Haroun (&quot;Aaron's Mountain&quot;), the location of the [[Tomb of Aaron]], said to be the burial place of [[Aaron]], brother of [[Moses]]. Another approach was possibly from the high plateau to the north. Today, most modern visitors approach the site from the east. The impressive eastern entrance leads steeply down through a dark, narrow gorge, in places only {{convert|3|–|4|m|0|abbr=on}} wide, called the ''[[Siq]]'' (&quot;shaft&quot;), a natural geological feature formed from a deep split in the [[sandstone]] rocks and serving as a waterway flowing into [[Wadi Musa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fulford97&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.robertfulford.com/petra.html |title= Robert Fulford's column about Petra, Jordan |publisher= Robertfulford.com |date= 1997-06-18 |access-date=2014-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===City centre===
At the end of the narrow gorge, the Siq, stands Petra's most elaborate ruin, popularly known as [[Al Khazneh]] (&quot;the Treasury&quot;), hewn into the sandstone cliff. While remaining in remarkably preserved condition, the face of the structure is marked by hundreds of bullet holes made by the local Bedouin tribes that hoped to dislodge riches that were once rumoured to be hidden within it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fulford97&quot;/&gt; A little further from the Treasury, at the foot of the mountain called ''en-Nejr'', is a massive [[theatre]], positioned so as to bring the greatest number of [[tomb]]s within view. At the point where the valley opens out into the plain, the site of the city is revealed with striking effect. The theatre has been cut into the hillside and into several of the tombs during its construction. Rectangular gaps in the seating are still visible. Almost enclosing it on three sides are rose-coloured mountain walls, divided into groups by deep fissures and lined with knobs cut from the rock in the form of towers.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;

===Huge structure discovered in 2016===
In 2016, archaeologists using [[satellite imagery]] and [[Unmanned aerial vehicle|drones]] have discovered a very large, previously unknown monumental structure whose beginnings were tentatively dated to about 150 BCE, the time when the Nabataeans initiated their public building programme. It is located outside the main area of the city, at the foot of Jabal an-Nmayr and about half a mile (800 metres) south of the city centre, but is facing east, not towards the city, and has no visible relationship to it. The structure consists of a huge, 184-by-161-foot (c. 56-by-49-metre) platform, with a truly monumental staircase all along its eastern side. The large platform enclosed a slightly smaller one, topped with a comparatively small building (28-by-28-foot or 8.5-by-8.5-metre), which was facing east toward the staircase. The structure, second in size only to the Monastery complex, probably had a ceremonial function of which not even a speculative explanation has yet been offered by the researchers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1= Parcak |first1= Sarah |last2= Tuttle |first2= Christopher A. |title= Hiding in Plain Sight: The Discovery of a New Monumental Structure at Petra, Jordan, Using WorldView-1 and WorldView-2 Satellite Imagery |journal= Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research |volume= 375 |date= May 2016 |issue= 375 |pages= 35–51 |jstor= 10.5615/bullamerschoorie.375.0035 |issn= 0003-097X |doi= 10.5615/bullamerschoorie.375.0035}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Archaeologists discover massive Petra monument that could be 2,150 years old |url= https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jun/09/petra-buried-monument-discovered-jordan |access-date=10 June 2016 |work= The Guardian |date=10 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Massive New Monument Found in Petra |url= http://news.nationalgeographic.com/2016/06/space-archaeology-satellite-petra-ancient-city-discovery-jordan-monument/ |access-date=10 June 2016 |work= National Geographic |date=8 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Climate==
In Petra, there is a semi-arid climate. Most rain falls in the winter. The Köppen-Geiger climate classification is BSk. The average annual temperature in Petra is {{convert|15.5|°C|1}}. About {{convert|193|mm|2|abbr=on}} of precipitation falls annually.

{{Weather box|location = Petra
|metric first = Y
|single line = Y

|Jan high C = 11.0											
|Feb high C = 13.1
|Mar high C = 16.6
|Apr high C = 20.9
|May high C = 25.1
|Jun high C = 28.6
|Jul high C = 29.8
|Aug high C = 30.0
|Sep high C = 28.1
|Oct high C = 24.6
|Nov high C = 18.2
|Dec high C = 13.4

|Jan low C =  2.2								 				
|Feb low C =  2.8
|Mar low C =  5.6
|Apr low C =  8.7
|May low C = 11.7
|Jun low C = 14.1
|Jul low C = 16.1
|Aug low C = 16.5
|Sep low C = 14.2
|Oct low C = 11.2
|Nov low C =  7.1
|Dec low C =  3.4

|Jan precipitation mm = 45												
|Feb precipitation mm = 38
|Mar precipitation mm = 36
|Apr precipitation mm = 12
|May precipitation mm = 4
|Jun precipitation mm = 0
|Jul precipitation mm = 0
|Aug precipitation mm = 0
|Sep precipitation mm = 0
|Oct precipitation mm = 2
|Nov precipitation mm = 15
|Dec precipitation mm = 41
|year precipitation mm= 193

|source = Climate-Data.org,Climate data
|date=17 January 2018}}

==History==
Though the city was founded relatively late, a sanctuary has existed there since very ancient times{{when|date=December 2019}}.{{cn|date=December 2019}}

===Neolithic===
{{History of the Arab States}}

By 7000 BCE, some of the earliest recorded farmers had settled in [[Beidha (archaeological site)|Beidha]], a [[Pre-Pottery Neolithic]] settlement just north of Petra.&lt;ref name=&quot;PNF&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=A Short History|url=http://www.petranationalfoundation.org/history.html|publisher=Petra National Foundation|accessdate=13 February 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171204141534/http://www.petranationalfoundation.org/history.html|archive-date=4 December 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bronze Age===
Petra{{dubious|There was no Petra in that time. Maybe the mountain, or the region. SOURCE!!!|date=December 2019}} is listed in Egyptian campaign accounts and the [[Amarna letters]] as ''Pel'', ''Sela'' or ''Seir''.{{cn|date=December 2019}}

===Iron Age Edom===
The Edomite site excavated at the top of the Umm el-Biyara mountain at Petra was established not earlier than the seventh century BCE (Iron II).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/citedby/10.1179/007589192790220919?scroll=top&amp;needAccess=true Bienkowski, P. (1992). The beginning of the Iron Age in Edom: A reply to Finkelstein. ''Levant'', ''24''(1), 167–169]&lt;/ref&gt;

===The emergence of Rekem/Petra===
The [[Nabataeans]] were one among several nomadic Bedouin tribes that roamed the [[Arabian Desert]] and moved with their herds to wherever they could find pasture and water.&lt;ref name=&quot;lost kingdom&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FcAoBq4_EnEC|title=Petra and the Lost Kingdom of the Nabataeans |first= Taylor |last= Jane |pages= 14, 17, 30, 31 |year= 2001 |publisher=[[I.B.Tauris]] |location= London, United Kingdom |access-date=8 July 2016 |isbn= 9781860645082}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Nabataeans were initially embedded in Aramaic culture, theories about them having [[Aramean]] roots are rejected by modern scholars. Instead, archaeological, religious and linguistic evidence confirm that they are a northern [[Tribes of Arabia|Arabian tribe]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=A0BdsFRX55cC |title= Arabs in the Shadow of Israel: The Unfolding of God's Prophetic Plan for Ishmael's Line |access-date=8 July 2016 |publisher= Kregel Academic |first= Tony |last= Maalouf |year= 2003 |isbn= 9780825493638}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Petra as &quot;Rekem&quot;====
Historian [[Josephus]] (ca. 37–100) writes that the region as inhabited by the [[Midianites]] during the time of [[Moses]], and that they were ruled by five kings, one of whom was Rekem. Josephus mentions that the city, called Petra by the Greeks, &quot;ranks highest in the land of the Arabs&quot; and was still called '''Rekeme''' by all the Arabs of his time, after its royal founder (Antiquities iv. 7, 1; 4, 7).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url= http://www.loebclassics.com/view/josephus-jewish_antiquities/1930/pb_LCL490.79.xml?mainRsKey=zBRKmE&amp;result=1&amp;rskey=O69i4Z |doi=10.4159/DLCL.josephus-jewish_antiquities.1930 |title=Jewish Antiquities |year=1930 |last1=Josephus |via=[[Loeb Classical Library]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:RekemInscription.jpg|thumb|The Rekem Inscription before it was buried by the bridge abutments]] 

The name '''Rekem''' was inscribed in the rock wall of the Wadi Musa opposite the entrance to the Siq.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |author= Iain Browning |title= Petra |publisher= Chatto &amp; Windus |year= 1974 |page= 109}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Jordan built a bridge over the wadi and this inscription was buried beneath tons of concrete.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=History of Petra|url=http://www.terhaal.com/history-petra|publisher=Terhaal Adventures|accessdate=2015-09-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Petra as &quot;Sela&quot;====
{{see also|Sela (Edom)#Confusion with Petra}}
An old theory held that Petra might be identified with a place called ''sela'' in the [[Hebrew Bible]]. Encyclopædia Britannica of 1911 states that the [[Semitic languages|Semitic]] name of the city, if not Sela, would remain unknown. It nevertheless cautioned that ''sela'' simply means &quot;rock&quot; in Hebrew, and thence might not be identified with a city where it occurs in the biblical text.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;

The passage in [[Diodorus Siculus]] (xix. 94–97) which describes the expeditions which [[Antigonus I Monophthalmus|Antigonus]] sent against the Nabataeans in 312 BCE, was understood by some researchers-and not so by others-to throw some light upon the history of Petra, but the &quot;petra&quot; (Greek for rock) referred to as a natural fortress and place of refuge cannot be a proper name, and the description implies that there was no town in existence there at the time.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Diodorus Siculus]]' account of Antigonus' expedition to Arabia, xix, [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Diodorus_Siculus/19E*.html#93 section 95 (note 79)].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Roman period===
[[image:Petra-5.JPG|thumb|General view]]
[[File:Great Temple, Petra, Jordan4.jpg|thumb|Ancient columns of the Great Temple]]

In AD 106, when [[Aulus Cornelius Palma Frontonianus|Cornelius Palma]] was governor of [[Roman Syria|Syria]], the part of [[Arabian Peninsula|Arabia]] under the rule of Petra was absorbed into the [[Roman Empire]] as part of ''Arabia Petraea'', and Petra became its capital.&lt;ref&gt;Dio Cassius, LXVII. 14, 5.&lt;/ref&gt; The native dynasty came to an end but the city continued to flourish under Roman rule. It was around this time that the [[Petra Roman Road]]{{dubious|It links back to Petra article. Never defined. What is it?|date=December 2019}} was built. A century later, in the time of [[Alexander Severus]], when the city was at the height of its splendor, the issue of coinage comes to an end. There is no more building of sumptuous tombs, owing apparently to some sudden catastrophe, such as an invasion by the neo-[[Iran|Persian]] power under the [[Sassanid Empire]].&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;

Meanwhile, as [[Palmyra]] ([[floruit|fl.]] 130–270) grew in importance and attracted the Arabian trade away from Petra, the latter declined. It appears, however, to have lingered on as a religious centre. Another [[Petra Roman Road|Roman road]] was constructed at the site. [[Epiphanius of Salamis]] (c.315–403) writes that in his time a feast was held there on December 25 in honour of the virgin [[Khaabou]] (Chaabou) and her offspring [[Dushara]].&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; Dushara and al-Uzza were two of the main deities of the city, which otherwise included many idols from other Nabatean deities such as Allat and Manat.&lt;ref&gt;''The Religious Life of Nabataea'', Chapter Two, 2013, Peter Alpass&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 111 and 114, Trajan built the [[Via Traiana Nova]], running from the Syrian border to the Red Sea through Petra. This road followed the old routes of Nabataean caravans. In the shadow of the [[Pax Romana]], this route revived trade between Arabia, Syria, and Mediterranean harbors. In 125 AD, one of Emperor [[Hadrian]]'s administrators left marks{{dubious|Meaning what?|date=December 2019}} in Petra, pointed out by documents found at the [[Dead Sea]]. In 130 AD, Hadrian visited the former Nabataean capital, giving it the name of ''Hadriane Petra Metropolis'', imprinted on his coins. His visit, however, did not lead to any boom in architectural development and new buildings as it did in [[Jerash]]. The province's governor, Sextius Florentinus, erected a monumental [[mausoleum]] for his son near the end of the al-Hubta (King's Wall) tombs, which had been generally reserved during the Nabataean period for the royal family.

The interest that Roman emperors showed for the city in the 3rd century suggests that Petra and its environs remained highly esteemed for a long time. An inscription to [[Liber Pater]], a god revered by Emperor [[Septimius Severus]], was found in the ''[[temenos]]'' of the temple known as [[Qasr al-Bint]], and Nabataean tombs contained silver coins with the Emperor's portrait, as well as pottery from his reign. Emperor [[Elagabalus]] declared Petra to be a &quot;Roman colony&quot; when he reorganised the Roman Empire towards the end of the 3rd century.&lt;ref&gt;jordantourspetra.com. [http://www.jordantourspetra.com/en/petra-jordan.html ''Petra Jordan''].&lt;/ref&gt; The area from Petra to [[Wadi Mujib]], the [[Negev]], and the [[Sinai Peninsula]] were annexed into the province of [[Palaestina Salutaris]]. Petra may be seen on the mosaic map of [[Madaba]] from the reign of Emperor [[Justinian]].

===Byzantine period===
Petra declined rapidly under Roman rule, in large part from the revision of sea-based trade routes. In [[Galilee earthquake of 363|363 an earthquake]] destroyed many buildings, and crippled the vital water management system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E3DF143EF934A25753C1A9659C8B63 | work=The New York Times | title=ART REVIEW; Rose-Red City Carved From the Rock | first=Grace | last=Glueck | date=2003-10-17 | accessdate=2010-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The old city of Petra was the capital of the Byzantine province of [[Palaestina Salutaris|Palaestina III]] and many churches were excavated in and around Petra from the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine period]]. In one of them, 140 papyri were discovered, which contained mainly contracts, dated from 537 to 593, establishing that the city was still flourishing in the sixth century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Encyclopedia of Ancient History|last=Frösén|first=Jaakko|publisher=Blackwell Publishing Ltd.|year=2012|doi=10.1002/9781444338386.wbeah06244|chapter = Petra papyri|isbn = 9781444338386}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Crusaders and Mamluks===
In the 12th century, the [[Kingdom of Jerusalem|Crusaders]] built fortresses, but were forced to abandon Petra after a while. As a result, the location of Petra was lost for the Western world until the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://nabataea.net/crusades.html|title=Nabataea: The Crusades|website=nabataea.net|access-date=2018-12-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/reconstructing-petra-155444564/|title=Reconstructing Petra|last=Lawler|first=Andrew|website=Smithsonian|language=en|access-date=2018-12-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ruins of Petra were an object of curiosity during the [[Middle Ages]] and were visited by [[Baibars]], one of the first [[Mamluk Sultanate (Cairo)|Mamluk sultans of Egypt]], towards the end of the 13th century.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;

===19th century===
[[File:Gravkammare 2.jpg|thumb|View of the Royal Tombs in Petra]]
The first European to describe them was Swiss traveller [[Johann Ludwig Burckhardt]] during his travels in 1812.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Burckhardt1822&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=John Lewis Burckhardt|title=Travels in Syria and the Holy Land|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=R9N70FsNRNYC|year=1822|publisher=J. Murray}}&lt;/ref&gt; At that time, the [[Greek Orthodox Church of Jerusalem|Greek Church of Jerusalem]] operated a diocese in [[Al Karak]] named Battra (باطره in Arabic, and Πέτρας in Greek) and it was the opinion among the clergy of Jerusalem that Kerak was the ancient city of Petra.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burckhardt1822&quot;/&gt;

The Scottish painter [[David Roberts (painter)|David Roberts]] visited Petra in 1839 and returned to England with sketches and stories of the encounter with local tribes, published in ''[[The Holy Land, Syria, Idumea, Arabia, Egypt, and Nubia]]''. The archaeologist Philip Hammond from the [[University of Utah]], USA, has visited Petra for nearly 40 years. He explains that the local folklore says it was created by the wand of [[Moses]], when he struck the rock to bring forth water for the [[Israelites]]. Hammond believes the carved channels deep within the walls and ground were made from ceramic pipes that once fed water for the city, from rock-cut systems on the canyon rim.&lt;ref&gt;National Geographic documentary : Forbidden Archaeology of Petra and Nazca, 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;

Because the structures weakened with age, many of the tombs became vulnerable to thieves, and many treasures were stolen. In 1929, a four-person team, consisting of British archaeologists [[Agnes Conway]] and [[George Horsfield]], Palestinian physician and folklore expert Dr
[[Tawfiq Canaan]] and Dr Ditlef Nielsen, a Danish scholar, excavated and surveyed Petra.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last1=Conway |first1=A. |last2=Horsfield |first2=G. |year=1930 |title=Historical and Topographical Notes on Edom: with an account of the first excavations at Petra |publisher=The Geographical Journal |volume=76 |issue=5 |pages=369–390}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Numerous scrolls in Greek and dating to the [[Byzantine]] period were discovered in an excavated church near the Winged Lion Temple in Petra in December 1993.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalgeographic.com/archaeology-and-history/archaeology/lost-city-petra/ Petra-National Geographic]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Comparative Petra siq.jpg|thumb|Petra siq in 1947 (left) compared with the same location in 2013]]

==UNESCO listing of ancient Petra and Bedouin heritage==
[[File:Al khazneh.jpg|thumb|Petra at night]]
[[file:Petra-7.JPG |thumb|Tourist attraction]]
The Bidoul/Bidul or Petra Bedouin were forcibly resettled from their cave dwellings in Petra to Umm Sayhoun/Um Seihun by the Jordanian government in 1985, prior to the UNESCO designation process. Here, they were provided with block-built housing with some infrastructure including in particular a sewage and drainage system. Among the six communities in the Petra Region, Umm Sayhoun is one of the smaller communities. The village of Wadi Musa is the largest in the area, inhabited largely by the Layathnah Bedouin, and is now the closest settlement to the visitor centre, the main entrance via the Siq and the archaeological site generally. Umm Sayhoun gives access to the 'back route' into the site, the Wadi Turkmaniyeh pedestrian route.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.go2petra.com/guide_inside_clickmap.htm|title=Map of the area from the go2petra website|access-date=2015-06-04|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180313061923/http://www.go2petra.com/guide_inside_clickmap.htm|archive-date=2018-03-13|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 6, 1985, Petra was designated a [[World Heritage Site]]. In a popular poll in 2007, it was also named one of the [[New7Wonders of the World]]. The&amp;nbsp; PAP (Petra Archaeological Park) became an autonomous legal entity over the management of this site in August 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://visitpetra.jo/Pages/viewpage.aspx?pageID=129|title=Archeological Park - Visit Petra|website=visitpetra.jo|access-date=2018-12-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Bidouls belong to one of the Bedouin tribes whose cultural heritage and traditional skills were proclaimed by UNESCO on the [[UNESCO Intangible Cultural Heritage Lists|Intangible Cultural Heritage List]] in 2005 and inscribed&lt;ref name=bedu&gt;{{cite web| title= The Cultural Space of the Bedu in Petra and Wadi Rum |url= http://www.unesco.org/culture/ich/index.php?lg=en&amp;pg=00011&amp;RL=00122 |publisher=UNESCO Culture Sector |accessdate=2015-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 2008.

In 2011, following an 11-month project planning phase, the Petra Development and Tourism Region Authority in Association with DesignWorkshop and JCP s.r.l published a Strategic Master Plan that guides planned development of the Petra Region. This is intended to guide planned development of the Petra Region in an efficient, balanced and sustainable way over the next 20 years for the benefit of the local population and of Jordan in general. As part of this, a Strategic Plan was developed for Umm Sayhoun and surrounding areas.&lt;!-- &lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.pdtra.gov.jo/SchemeFiles/English/communities%2520master%2520plans/Umm%2520Sayhoun%2520Strategy.pdf&amp;rct=j&amp;frm=1&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;sa=U&amp;ei=hUxsVY_FLsuNsgHv7aHoAw&amp;ved=0CBQQFjAA&amp;usg=AFQjCNHSZAz2PGlfOtLIHYBNhXxtIjoPTA Petra |work=Development and Tourism Region Authority in Association with DesignWorkshop and JCP s.r.l. |title=Strategic Plan for Umm Sayhoun and surrounding areas |dead-link=yes |date=February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.pdtra.gov.jo/UploadedFiles/PDETRA_Folder/English/communities%20master%20plans/Umm%20Sayhoun%20Strategy.pdf |work=Petra Development and Tourism Region Authority in Association with DesignWorkshop and JCP s.r.l. |title=Strategic Plan for Umm Sayhoun and surrounding areas |access-date=8 April 2017 }}{{Dead link|date=July 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The process of developing the Strategic Plan considered the area's needs from five points of view:
*a socio-economic perspective
*the perspective of Petra Archaeological Park
*the perspective of Petra's tourism product
*a land use perspective
*an environmental perspective

==Issues==
The site suffers from a host of threats, including collapse of ancient structures, erosion from flooding and improper rainwater drainage, weathering from salt upwelling,&lt;ref&gt;Heinrichs, K., Azzam, R.: &quot;Investigation of salt weathering on stone monuments by use of a modern wireless sensor network exemplified for the rock-cut monuments in Petra / Jordan – a research project '' International Journal of Heritage in the Digital Era'', Volume 1, Nr. 2 / Juni 2012, S. 191–216&lt;/ref&gt; improper restoration of ancient structures and unsustainable tourism.&lt;!-- &lt;ref name = ICOMOS2004&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20051018040549/http://www.international.icomos.org/risk/2004/jordan2004.pdf Icomos.org]Heritage at Risk 2004/2005: Petra&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icomos.org/risk/2004/jordan2004.pdf Heritage at Risk 2004/2005: Petra, at icomos.org] Accessed 27 March 2017&lt;/ref&gt; The last has increased substantially, especially since the site received widespread media coverage in 2007 during the [[New Seven Wonders of the World]] Internet and cellphone campaign.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2007-11/03/content_7006318.htm |title=Heritage Conservation Grips Jordan's Petra Amid Booming Tourism |publisher=[[Xinhua News Agency]] |date=November 3, 2007 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090918212011/http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2007-11/03/content_7006318.htm |archive-date=September 18, 2009 |df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an attempt to reduce the impact of these threats, the [[Petra National Trust]] (PNT) was established in 1989. It has worked with numerous local and international organisations on projects that promote the protection, conservation, and preservation of the Petra site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.petranationaltrust.org/UI/ShowContent.aspx?ContentId=1 |title=Petra National Trust-About |publisher=Petranationaltrust.org |accessdate=2011-12-05 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111228122554/http://petranationaltrust.org/ui/ShowContent.aspx?ContentId=1 |archivedate=2011-12-28 |df= }}&lt;!-- Live again 30 March 2017 --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, UNESCO and ICOMOS recently collaborated to publish their first book on human and natural threats to the sensitive World Heritage sites. They chose Petra as its first
and the most important example of threatened landscapes. A book released in 2012, ''Tourism and Archaeological Heritage Management at Petra: Driver to Development or Destruction?'', was the first in a series of important books to address the very nature of these deteriorating buildings, cities, sites, and regions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://openarchive.icomos.org/1208/1/III-1-Article2_Comer_Willems.pdf |author= Comer and Willems |title= Tourism and Archaeological Heritage Management at Petra: Driver to Development or Destruction? |accessdate=2015-09-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next books in the series of deteriorating UNESCO World Heritage Sites will include [[Machu Picchu]], [[Angkor Wat]], and [[Pompeii]].
 
[[People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals]] (PETA) released a video in 2018 highlighting abuse against working animals in Petra. PETA claimed that animals are forced to carry tourists or pull carriages every day. The video showed handlers beating and whipping working animals, with beatings intensifying when animals faltered. PETA also revealed some wounded animals, including camels with fly-infested, open wounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-42692743 |title=Jordan urged to end animal mistreatment at Petra site |last=Usher |first=Sebastian |date=January 16, 2018 |newspaper=[[BBC News]] |access-date=February 28, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Jordanian authority running the site responded by opening up a veterinarian clinic, and by spreading awareness among animal handlers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jordantimes.com/news/local/stakeholders-take-steps-address-animal-abuse-petra|title=Stakeholders take steps to address animal abuse in Petra|work=Saeb Rawashdeh|publisher=The Jordan Times|accessdate=19 April 2018|date=5 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{wide image|Koenigsgraeber.jpg|1000px|align-cap=center|Tombs in the southern part of the city}}

==Religion==
{{see also|Nabataean art}}
{{multiple image |align=right |direction=vertical |width=
 |image1=PetraAmphitheatre.jpg |caption1=The Theatre
 |image2=The Monastery, Petra, Jordan8.jpg |caption2=El Deir (&quot;The Monastery&quot;)
 |image3=Great Temple of Petra 02.jpg |caption3=The Great Temple of Petra
}}
The Nabataeans worshipped [[Arab mythology|Arab gods]] and [[goddess]]es during the [[Pre-Islamic Arabia|pre-Islamic]] era as well as a few of their [[Apotheosis|deified]] kings. One, [[Obodas I]], was deified after his death. [[Dushara]] was the primary male god accompanied by his three female deities: [[Al-‘Uzzá]], [[Allat]] and [[Manāt]]. Many statues carved in the rock depict these gods and goddesses. New evidence indicates that broader [[Edom]]ite, and Nabataean theology had strong links to Earth-Sun relationships, often manifested in the orientation of prominent Petra structures to equinox and solstice sunrises and sunsets.&lt;ref&gt;Paradise T.R. &amp; Angel C.C. 2015, [http://www.esri.com/esri-news/arcuser/winter-2015/nabataean-architecture-and-the-sun Nabatean Architecture and the Sun, ArcUser (Winter)].&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[stele]] dedicated to Qos-Allah 'Qos is Allah' or 'Qos the god', by Qosmilk (melech – king) is found at Petra (Glueck 516). Qos is identifiable with Kaush (Qaush) the God of the older Edomites. The stele is horned and the seal from the Edomite Tawilan near Petra identified with Kaush displays a [[star and crescent]] (Browning 28), both consistent with a moon deity. It is conceivable that the latter could have resulted from trade with [[Harran]] (Bartlett 194). There is continuing debate about the nature of Qos (qaus – bow) who has been identified both with a hunting bow (hunting god) and a rainbow (weather god) although the crescent above the stele is also a bow.{{citation needed|date=February 2019}}

Nabatean inscriptions in Sinai and other places display widespread references to names including Allah, El and Allat (god and goddess), with regional references to al-Uzza, [[Baal]] and Manutu (Manat) (Negev 11). Allat is also found in Sinai in South Arabian language. Allah occurs particularly as Garm-'allahi – god decided (Greek Garamelos) and Aush-allahi – 'gods covenant' (Greek Ausallos). We find both Shalm-lahi 'Allah is peace' and Shalm-allat, 'the peace of the goddess'. We also find Amat-allahi 'she-servant of god' and Halaf-llahi 'the successor of Allah'.&lt;ref&gt;Negev 11&lt;/ref&gt;

Recently, Petra has been put forward as the original 'Mecca' by some in the [[revisionist school of Islamic studies]], owing to claims of large numbers of independent pieces of evidence, namely that the early original mosques faced Petra, not Jerusalem or Mecca, as the direction of Muslim prayer, the qibla.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Gibson |first1=Dan |title=Early Islamic Qiblas: A survey of mosques built between 1AH/622 C.E. and 263 AH/876 C.E. |isbn=978-1927581223|year=2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, others have challenged the notion of comparing modern readings of Qiblah directions to early mosques’ Qiblahs as they claim early Muslims could not accurately calculate the direction of the Qiblah to Mecca and so the apparent pinpointing of Petra by some early mosques may well be coincidental.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=King |first1=David A. |title=The Petra Fallacy |url=https://www.academia.edu/37957366}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Monastery, Petra's largest monument, dates from the 1st century BC. It was dedicated to Obodas I and is believed to be the symposium of Obodas the god. This information is inscribed on the ruins of the Monastery (the name is the translation of the Arabic &quot;''[[Ad Deir]]''&quot;).{{citation needed|date=February 2019}}

[[Christianity]] found its way to Petra in the 4th century AD, nearly 500 years after the establishment of Petra as a trade centre. [[Athanasius of Alexandria|Athanasius]] mentions a bishop of Petra (Anhioch. 10) named [[Asterius of Petra|Asterius]]. At least one of the tombs (the &quot;tomb with the urn&quot;?) was used as a church. An inscription in red paint records its consecration &quot;in the time of the most holy bishop Jason&quot; (447). After the [[Islam]]ic conquest of 629–632, Christianity in Petra, as of most of Arabia, gave way to Islam. During the [[First Crusade]] Petra was occupied by [[Baldwin I of Jerusalem|Baldwin I]] of the [[Kingdom of Jerusalem]] and formed the second [[fief]] of the [[feudal barony|barony]] of [[Al Karak]] (in the lordship of [[Oultrejordain]]) with the title ''Château de la Valée de Moyse'' or Sela. It remained in the hands of the [[Franks]] until 1189.&lt;ref name=EB1911&gt;{{EB1911 |wstitle=Petra |volume=21 |pages=309–310 |first=George Albert |last=Cooke|inline=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is still a [[titular see]] of the [[Catholic Church]].&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy|wstitle=Petra}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two Crusader-period castles are known in and around Petra. The first is al-Wu'ayra and is situated just north of Wadi Musa. It can be viewed from the road to &quot;Little Petra&quot;. It is the castle of Valle Moise which was seized by a band of Turks with the help of local Muslims and only recovered by the Crusaders after they began to destroy the olive trees of Wadi Musa. The potential loss of livelihood led the locals to negotiate surrender. The second is on the summit of el-Habis in the heart of Petra and can be accessed from the West side of the Qasr al-Bint.

According to Arab tradition, Petra is the spot where [[Islamic view of Moses|Musa]] ([[Moses]]) struck a rock with his staff and water came forth, and where Moses' brother, [[Islamic view of Aaron|Harun]] ([[Aaron]]), is [[Tomb of Aaron|buried]], at [[Mount Hor]], known today as Jabal Haroun or Mount Aaron. The Wadi Musa or &quot;Wadi of Moses&quot; is the Arab name for the narrow valley at the head of which Petra is sited. A mountaintop shrine of Moses' sister [[Miriam]] was still shown to pilgrims at the time of [[Jerome]] in the 4th century, but its location has not been identified since.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sacredsites.com/middle_east/jordan/petra_ruins.htm |title=Petra |publisher=Sacred Sites |accessdate=2011-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
[[File:20100925 petra213.JPG|thumb|The Hadrian Gate also known as the Temenos Gate and the [[Decumanus Maximus]] in Petra&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Colonnade Street, Petra. |url=http://madainproject.com/decumanus_(petra) |website=Madain Project |accessdate=7 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

===Literature===
*Petra appeared in the novels ''[[The Remnant (novel)|Left Behind Series]]''; ''[[Appointment with Death]]''; ''[[Eagle Series|The Eagle in the Sand]]''; ''[[The Red Sea Sharks]]'', the nineteenth book in ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'' series; and in Kingsbury's ''[[The Moon Goddess and the Son]]''. It played a prominent role in the [[Marcus Didius Falco]] mystery novel ''[[Last Act in Palmyra]]''. In [[Blue Balliett]]'s novel, ''[[Chasing Vermeer]]'', the character Petra Andalee is named after the site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Balliett|first=Blue|title=Chasing Vermeer: ''Afterwords by Leslie Budnick: Author Q&amp;A''|year=2004|publisher=Scholastic|isbn=978-0-439-37294-7|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/chasingvermeer000ball}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 1979 Marguerite van Geldermalsen from New Zealand married Mohammed Abdullah, a Bedouin in Petra.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geldermalsen|first=Marguerite|title=Married to a Bedouin|year=2010|publisher=Virago UK|isbn=978-1844082209|url=http://marriedtoabedouin.com/}}&lt;/ref&gt; They lived in a cave in Petra until the death of her husband. She authored the book ''Married to a Bedouin''. Van Geldermalsen is the only western woman who has ever lived in a Petra cave.
*An Englishwoman, Joan Ward, wrote ''Living With Arabs: Nine Years with the Petra Bedouin''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ward|first=Joan|title=Living With Arabs: Nine Years with the Petra Bedouin|year=2014|publisher=UM Peter Publishing|isbn=978-1502564917}}&lt;/ref&gt; documenting her experiences while living in Umm Sayhoun with the Petra Bedouin, covering the period 2004-2013.

===Plays===
*Playwright John Yarbrough's [[tragicomedy]], ''Petra'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OcMb53MqYEA|title=John Yarbrough's ''Petra'' on Youtube}}&lt;/ref&gt; debuted at the Manhattan Repertory Theatre in 2014&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://manhattanrep.com/fall-one-act-competition-2014/|title=Manhattan Repertory Theatre fall one act competition 2014 including John Yarbrough's ''Petra''|accessdate=2015-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was followed by award-winning performances at the [[Hudson Guild]] in New York in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.broadwayworld.com/off-off-broadway/article/Playwright-John-Yarbrough-Wins-Strawberry-One-Act-Festival-20150308|title=Broadwayworld, Off-Off-Broadway, article: 'Playwright John Yarbrough Wins Strawberry One Act Festival'|accessdate=2015-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was selected for the ''Best American Short Plays 2014-2015'' anthology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.broadwayworld.com/article/THE-BEST-AMERICAN-SHORT-PLAYS-2014-15-Hits-the-Shelves-20160718|title=Broadwayworld, Off-Off-Broadway, article: 'The Best American Short Plays 2014-15 Hits the Shelves'}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Films===
*The site appeared in [[film]]s such as: ''[[Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade]]'', ''[[Arabian Nights (1942 film)|Arabian Nights]]'', ''[[Passion in the Desert]]'', ''[[Mortal Kombat: Annihilation]]'', ''[[Sinbad and the Eye of the Tiger]]'', ''[[The Mummy Returns]]'', ''[[Transformers: Revenge of the Fallen]]'', ''[[Samsara (2011 film)|Samsara]]'' and ''[[Kajraare]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Mourby |first1=Adrian |title=Can Jordan's 'Indiana Jones' city survive? |url=https://www.cnn.com/travel/article/jordan-petra-tourism/index.html |website=CNN Travel |language=en |date=16 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Television===
*Petra appeared in episode 20 of ''[[Misaeng (TV series)|Misaeng]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jordantimes.com/scenes-for-tv-drama-series-misaeng-shot-around-kingdom |title=Scenes for TV drama series 'Misaeng' shot around Kingdom.The Jordan Times |publisher=The Jordan Times |date=2014-09-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dramabeans.com/2014/12/misaeng-episode-20-final/ |title=Misaeng Episode 20 Final |publisher=dramabeans.com|date=2014-12-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Petra appeared in an episode of ''Time Scanners'', made for [[National Geographic (U.S. TV channel)|National Geographic]], where six ancient structures were laser scanned, with the results built into 3D models.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.atlanticproductions.tv/productions/time-scanners/#readmore Time Scanners] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150928045932/http://www.atlanticproductions.tv/productions/time-scanners/ |date=2015-09-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Examining the model of Petra revealed insights into how the structure was built.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.sciencefocus.com/science/time-scanners-how-was-petra-built/|title=Time Scanners: How was Petra built?|website=Science Focus - BBC Focus Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Petra was the focus of an American [[PBS]] ''[[Nova (American TV series)|Nova]]'' special, &quot;Petra: Lost City of Stone&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/ancient/building-wonders.html#petra-lost-city|title=Petra-Lost City in building-wonders at pbs.org|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; which premiered in the US and Europe in February 2015.

===Music and musical videos===
*Six months after a deadly hike by two Israelis in 1958, [[Haim Hefer]] wrote the lyrics for a ballad called Ha-Sela ha-Adom (“The Red Rock”)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.degruyter.com/downloadpdf/j/tra.2015.13.issue-2/tra-2015-0011/tra-2015-0011.pdf|title=Melody of a Myth: The Legacy of Haim Hefers Red Rock Song}} by Dominik Peters, 2015&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1971/01/17/archives/the-ballad-of-red-rock.html|title=The Ballad of Red Rock|newspaper=The New York Times|date=1971-01-17}} New York Times, Jan. 17, 1971&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 1977, the Lebanese Rahbani brothers wrote the musical ''Petra'' as a response to the Lebanese Civil War.&lt;ref&gt;Stone, Christopher. Popular Culture and Nationalism in Lebanon.&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[The Sisters of Mercy|Sisters of Mercy]] filmed their music video for &quot;Dominion/Mother Russia&quot; in and around [[Al-Khazneh]] (&quot;The Treasury&quot;) in February 1988.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/name/nm3538960/|title=The Sisters of Mercy|website=IMDb}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 1994 Petra appeared in the video to the [[Urban Species]] single &quot;Spiritual Love&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121109005109/http://www.nme.com/musicvideos/urban-species-spiritual-love/234768|title=Spiritual Love - NMETV Latest Music Videos and Clips - - NME.COM|date=9 November 2012|website=web.archive.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jukebo.com/urban-species/music-clip,spiritual-love,rs0qq.html  Urban Species Spiritual Love music video (similar to video formerly at nme.com) at jukebo.com] Accessed 30 March 2017&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[power metal]] band [[Helloween]] mentions this city in their song [[Nabataea (song)]] which appear in their 2013 album [[Straight Out Of Hell]]

===Videogames===
*Petra is featured in ''[[Sid Meier's Civilization V]]'' and ''[[Sid Meier's Civilization VI]]'' as a buildable Wonder in a player's cities and as an illustration for ''Civilization V''&lt;nowiki/&gt;'s loading screens. In ''Civilization V'', the in-game encyclopedia, the Civilopedia, erroneously states that Petra was constructed in 1000 BC. This error was corrected in the Civilopedia for ''Civilization VI.''
*Petra is featured as a location in the online multiplayer game ''[[Overwatch (video game)|Overwatch]]''.
*The stage Shamar in the game ''[[Sonic Unleashed]]'' is heavily inspired by Petra.

==See also==
{{Portal|Asia|History|Architecture|Jordan|Christianity}}
* [[List of colossal sculpture in situ]]
* [[List of modern names for biblical place names]]
* [[List of World Heritage Sites in Jordan]]
* [[Mada'in Saleh]]
* [[Negev incense route]]
* [[UNESCO Intangible Cultural Heritage Lists]]
: '''Petra monuments, findings, and nearby related sites''' (see also &quot;Petra&quot; category below)
* [[Ad Deir]], &quot;the Monastery&quot;
* [[Al-Khazneh]], &quot;the Treasury&quot;
* [[Beidha (archaeological site)]], nearby site, best known for Neolithic and Early Muslim period findings
* [[Byzantine Church (Petra)]]
* [[Great Temple (Petra)]], in the city centre
* [[Jebel al-Madhbah]], the &quot;Altar Mountain&quot; towering over the city centre
* [[Little Petra]], nearby site, best known for Nabataean findings
* [[Palace Tomb]], monumental tomb in the city centre
* [[Petra papyri]], found in the Byzantine Church
* [[Petra Pool and Garden Complex]], in the city centre
* [[Qasr al-Bint]], temple in the city centre
* [[Siq]], narrow canyon and one of the city's access routes
* [[Temple of the Winged Lions]], in the city centre
* [[Tomb of the Roman Soldier]], funerary complex in a side valley

==References==
'''Notes'''
{{Reflist|30em}}

'''Bibliography'''
*{{cite book|last=Bedal|first=Leigh-Ann|title=The Petra Pool-Complex: A Hellenistic Paradeisos in the Nabataean Capital|publisher=[[Gorgias Press]]|location=[[Piscataway Township, New Jersey|Piscataway]], [[New Jersey|NJ]]|year=2004|isbn=978-1-59333-120-7}}
* [[Brown University]]. [http://www.brown.edu/Departments/Joukowsky_Institute/Petra/excavations/history.html &quot;The Petra Great Temple; History&quot;] Accessed April 19, 2013. 
*Glueck, Nelson (1959). ''Rivers in the Desert: A History of the Negev''. New York: Farrar, Straus &amp; Cudahy/London: Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson
*{{cite web|url=http://www.digitaljournalist.org/issue0607/petra.html|title=The Bedouin Tribes of Petra Photographs: 1986–2003|last=Harty|first=Rosemary|accessdate=2008-07-17}}
*{{cite book|last=Hill|first=John E.|title=The Peoples of the West from the Weilue 魏略 by Yu Huan 魚豢 : A Third Century Chinese Account Composed between 239 and 265 CE|year=2004|quote=Draft annotated English translation where Petra is referred to as the Kingdom of Sifu.|url=http://depts.washington.edu/silkroad/texts/weilue/weilue.html}}
*[[Judith McKenzie|McKenzie, Judith]] (1990). ''The Architecture of Petra.'' (Oxford University Press)
*Mouton, Michael and Schmid, Stephen G. (2013) &quot;Men on the Rocks: The Formation of Nabataean Petra&quot;
*Paradise, T. R. (2011). &quot;Architecture and Deterioration in Petra: Issues, trends and warnings&quot; in Archaeological Heritage at Petra: Drive to Development or Destruction?&quot; (Doug Comer, editor), ICOMOS-ICAHM Publications through Springer-Verlag NYC: 87–119.
*Paradise, T. R. (2005). &quot;Weathering of sandstone architecture in Petra, Jordan: influences and rates&quot; in GSA Special Paper 390: Stone Decay in the Architectural Environment: 39–49.
*Paradise, T. R. and Angel, C. C. (2015). [http://www.esri.com/esri-news/arcuser/winter-2015/nabataean-architecture-and-the-sun.html Nabataean Architecture and the Sun: A landmark discovery using GIS in Petra, Jordan]. ArcUser Journal, Winter 2015: 16-19pp.
*{{cite book|last=Reid|first=Sara Karz|title=The Small Temple|publisher=[[Gorgias Press]]|location=[[Piscataway Township, New Jersey|Piscataway]], [[New Jersey|NJ]]|year=2006|isbn=978-1-59333-339-3|quote=Reid explores the nature of the small temple at Petra and concludes it is from the Roman era.}}
*[[UNESCO World Heritage Centre]]. [https://whc.unesco.org/en/list/326 &quot;Petra&quot;] Accessed April 19, 2013.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Petra, Jordan}}
{{Wikivoyage}}
*[http://www.jordantourspetra.com/en/petra-jordan.html/ Petra Jordan]
*[http://visitpetra.jo/ Petra Archaeological Park]
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=heIU6d15bb0 Video overview of Petra]
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VSY_HZmaYiw Petra In The Early 1800s]
*[http://3dtour.ua/tours/2011/petra/index.php?id=62 3D-tour on Petra (Russian)]
&lt;!--*[https://web.archive.org/web/20110809180607/http://geosciences.uark.edu/217.php University of Arkansas Petra Project] --&gt;
*[http://fulbright.uark.edu/departments/geosciences/research/petraproject.php University of Arkansas Petra Project, Accessed 27 March 2017]
*[http://www.smartedaleel.com/allaboutjordan/interactive-jordan/79-interactive-map-of-petra.html Smart e Guide], interactive map of Petra
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20181010174301/https://opencontext.org/projects/A5DDBEA2-B3C8-43F9-8151-33343CBDC857 Open Context], &quot;Petra Great Temple Excavations (Archaeological Data)&quot;, Open Context Publication of Archaeological Data from the 1993–2006 [[Brown University]] Excavations at the Great Temple of Petra, Jordan
*[http://www.iconicarchive.ch/sites/overview.php?source=52&amp;term=petra Petra iconicarchive], photo gallery
&lt;!--*[https://web.archive.org/web/20111012172220/http://www.lahistoriaconmapas.com:80/2011/10/petra-la-capital-del-reino-nabateo.html Petra History and Photo Gallery] History with Maps --&gt;
*[http://www.lahistoriaconmapas.com/imperios-reinos/reino-nabateo/petra-la-capital-del-reino-nabateo-nabatean-kingdom-capital/ Petra History and Photo Gallery, Accessed 27 March 2017] History with Maps
*Parker, S., R. Talbert, T. Elliott, S. Gillies, S. Gillies, J. Becker. &quot;Places: 697725 (Petra)&quot;. Pleiades. &lt;http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/697725&gt; [Accessed: March 7, 2012 4:18 pm]
*[http://www.kotipetripaavola.com/Bible_Petra.html Pictures on Petra]
*[http://www.pbase.com/dosseman_jordan/petra Almost 800 pictures with captions, some panoramas]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20181010060847/http://www.doa.gov.jo/En/inside.php?src=sublinks&amp;SlID=5194&amp;MlID=5024 Jordanian Ministry of Tourism and Antiquities]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20180109235501/https://www.check123.com/videos/13303-petra-abandonment Why was Petra abandoned by its inhabitants?] | Check123 Video Encyclopedia

{{Jordan topics}}
{{Cliff dwellings}}
{{World Heritage Sites in Jordan}}
{{Roman colonies in ancient Levant}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Petra| 01]]
[[Category:Nabataean architecture]]
[[Category:Arabic architecture]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites in Jordan]]
[[Category:Cliff dwellings]]
[[Category:Former populated places in Jordan]]
[[Category:Levant]]
[[Category:Nabataea]]
[[Category:Nabataean sites in Jordan]]
[[Category:Populated places along the Silk Road]]
[[Category:Protected areas established in 1985]]
[[Category:Rock cut architecture]]
[[Category:Rock-cut tombs]]
[[Category:Roman towns and cities in Jordan]]
[[Category:Sandstone buildings]]
[[Category:Subterranea (geography)]]
[[Category:Tourism in Jordan]]
[[Category:World Heritage Sites in Jordan]]</text>
      <sha1>ioxguw1e01afu33y1irfg42xvzsws08</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
