  <page>
    <title>Poohsticks</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>750623</id>
    <revision>
      <id>920751159</id>
      <parentid>920751075</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-11T16:45:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Unreal7</username>
        <id>12374079</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Magdalen College Pooh Sticks Society */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2017}}
{{Use British English|date=May 2017}}
{{For|the band|The Pooh Sticks}}
[[File:Pooh sticks bridge.jpg|right|thumb|200px|Poohsticks Bridge in Ashdown Forest ({{coord|51.085459|0.097783|display=inline|format=dms}})]]
'''Poohsticks''' is a [[game]] first mentioned in ''[[The House at Pooh Corner]]'', a [[Winnie-the-Pooh]] book by [[A. A. Milne]]. It is a simple game which may be played on any [[bridge]] over running water; each player drops a [[branch|stick]] on the upstream side of a bridge and the one whose stick first appears on the downstream side is the winner. The annual World Poohsticks Championships have been held at [[Day's Lock]] on the [[River Thames]] in the UK since 1984.&lt;ref name=23rd/&gt;

==History==
Poohsticks was invented by English author A. A. Milne for his son [[Christopher Robin Milne]].&lt;ref name=Chris/&gt; The game first came to prominence when it was described in the author's book ''The House at Pooh Corner''&lt;ref&gt;[[A. A. Milne]]. (1928) ''[[The House at Pooh Corner]]'', London: Methuen. {{ISBN|0-7497-0116-1}}.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as in the [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]] animated featurette ''[[Winnie the Pooh and a Day for Eeyore]]''. [[Winnie-the-Pooh]], the [[protagonist]] of the book, accidentally drops a [[pine cone]] into a river from a bridge and, after observing how it appeared on the other side of the bridge, devises the rules for Poohsticks. Pooh continues to play the game with the other characters, [[Christopher Robin]], [[Tigger]] and [[Eeyore]].&lt;ref name=BBC1&gt;{{cite news |title=New 'pooh-sticks' World Champion |publisher=[[BBC]] |date=2003-03-16 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/2853091.stm |accessdate=2008-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Davies/&gt;

The game was first played at a bridge located in [[Ashdown Forest]], close to the village of [[Upper Hartfield]], [[East Sussex]], England. Built in 1907 and originally called Posingford Bridge, it is considered to be the bridge on which Milne and his son first played the game.&lt;ref name=Davies/&gt;&lt;ref name=Disney&gt;{{cite news |title=Disney to save Pooh Bridge |publisher=[[BBC]] |date=1999-09-11 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/444815.stm |accessdate=2008-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is uncertain whether the game was first played at the bridge and then written into the story, or vice versa.&lt;ref name=Chris/&gt; The bridge maintained the public's interest and a campaign to rebuild it in the late seventies was considered important enough to feature on the [[BBC]] ''Nine&amp;nbsp;O'Clock News''. The bridge was subsequently reopened by Christopher Robin Milne and officially renamed as ''Poohsticks Bridge''.&lt;ref name=PC&gt;{{cite web |title=A Short History of Pooh and Winnie |publisher=PoohCorner |url=http://www.poohcorner.com/A-Short-History-of-Pooh-and-Winnie.html |accessdate=2008-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The site was so popular that in 1999 the East Sussex county council made an appeal to Disney as the old wooden bridge had been worn down by an overwhelming number of visitors.&lt;ref name=Bridge&gt;{{cite news |title=Appeal to save Winnie the Pooh's bridge  |publisher=[[BBC]] |date=1999-08-10 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/416892.stm |accessdate=2008-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company provided a substantial donation towards the estimated £30,000 needed to replace the bridge. Partly rebuilt in 1979, the donations from Disney, building firms and members of the public funded its complete reconstruction. The newly built and modernised bridge retained its precursor's original style.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Halstead |first=Robin |title=Great escapes: Days out with a difference |newspaper=[[The Independent]] |date=2008-03-21 |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/great-escapes-days-out-with-a-difference-798923.html |accessdate=2008-11-03 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; A plaque was also placed to commemorate the occasion and thank those who financially contributed to the project.&lt;ref name=Disney/&gt; The game can still be played in Ashdown Forest to this day and the site regularly attracts tourists from as far afield as the United States and Japan.&lt;ref name=Bridge/&gt; However, visitors are now advised to bring their own sticks, as previous visitors have caused damage to the trees in the vicinity.&lt;ref name=Chris/&gt;&lt;ref name=Marsh&gt;{{cite news |last=Marsh |first=Stephanie |title=Want to win at Pooh Sticks? It’s all in the throw |newspaper=[[The Times]] |date=2004-10-19 |url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/article496177.ece |accessdate=2008-11-04 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rules and strategy==
A game for two players or more, in the traditional version of poohsticks the participants must drop a stick simultaneously on the upstream side of a bridge and run to the other side. The winner is the player whose stick first appears on the other side of the bridge.&lt;ref name=23rd/&gt; Alternatively, players may decide upon a starting point on a [[river]] and a finish line farther downstream. The winner is the player whose stick first passes the finishing point.&lt;ref name=BBC1/&gt;

It is generally agreed that the stick must be made of organic materials, preferably [[willow]], and not of any artificial materials.&lt;ref name=Marsh/&gt; All participants must drop their sticks at the same time, usually after a referee shouts &quot;drop&quot;, &quot;twitch&quot; or any other agreed keyword. Additionally, no advantage may be gained through either dismantling the bridge or the use of any self-propelling stick devices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Barritt |first=Owen |title=The Official Poohsticks Rules Of The Pembroke College Winnie-The-Pooh Society |publisher=The Pembroke College Winnie-The-Pooh Society 2000-2007 |date=2003-03-21 |url=http://www.poohsoc.org.uk/sticks/rules.html |accessdate=2008-11-04 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080725094128/http://www.poohsoc.org.uk/sticks/rules.html |archivedate=25 July 2008 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The stick must be dropped, not thrown, into the water and any player who is deemed to have thrown their stick is disqualified.&lt;ref name=Marsh/&gt;

Poohsticks is considered to be a game of chance yet some players claim skill is involved. Some strategies involve the way in which the stick is held before it is dropped and trying to find the fastest route in the river.&lt;ref name=Davies/&gt; Author [[Ben Schott]] outlined a throwing method as a winning strategy in his third book, ''[[Schott’s Sporting, Gaming and Idling Miscellany]]'', but his method was dismissed as cheating by competition organisers.&lt;ref name=Marsh/&gt; In any event, the [[turbulence]] around the bridge supports make the path of the stick very difficult to predict and may vary according to the season.

The traditional game has inspired filmmakers and screenwriters and has been portrayed in the 1998 film ''[[Into My Heart]]'' with [[Rob Morrow]] and [[Claire Forlani]], BBC sitcom ''[[To the Manor Born]]'' and also in a [[Marks &amp; Spencer]] clothes advert where models, including [[Twiggy]] and [[Myleene Klass]], played the game. The popularity of the game was underlined when it featured as a question on long-running British quiz series ''[[University Challenge]]''.&lt;ref name=Davies/&gt;

==World Poohsticks Championships==
[[File:LittleWitBr01.JPG|left|thumb|Little Wittenham Bridge with the lock keeper's house beyond]]
Following the closure of the short-lived Oxford University Poohsticks Society,{{Citation needed|date=November 2013}} Poohsticks was brought to a larger audience by the annual World Poohsticks Championships. Originally these took place at Day's Lock on the River Thames near [[Dorchester-on-Thames]], [[Oxfordshire]]. but were later moved to Langel Common in [[Witney]], also in Oxfordshire, and have attracted over 1,500 visitors, including many from overseas.&lt;ref name=BBC1/&gt; The championships features an individual event and a four-person team event.&lt;ref name=Chris&gt;{{cite website |title=Pooh, Piglet, Tigger and You |publisher=BBC |date=1998-03-13 |url=http://pooh-sticks.com/ |accessdate=2017-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Players come from a wide variety of countries including the United States, Japan, Kenya, Australia and England.&lt;ref name=BBC1/&gt;&lt;ref name=Davies/&gt;&lt;ref name=PoohTime&gt;{{cite web |last= |first= |title=It's Pooh Sticks Time! |publisher=BBC |date=2007-12-23 |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/oxford/content/articles/2007/03/12/world_poohsticks.shtml |accessdate=2008-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before its move to Witney, the event took place from [[Little Wittenham Bridge]] but now uses a bridge over the [[River Windrush]] near [[Cogges Manor Farm]].

The sporting event was started at Little Wittenham Bridge in 1984 by the [[lockkeeper]], Lynn David, as a fund-raising event for the [[Royal National Lifeboat Institution]] (RNLI).&lt;ref name=Chris/&gt; He noticed that people occasionally snapped sticks from nearby hedges to play the game and he then came up with the idea of a competition to aid the charity. He put out a box of sticks and a collection box and it soon became an annual event.&lt;ref name=Davies/&gt; In this championship version of the game, a finish line is set up farther downstream and the winner is the first to pass this point.&lt;ref name=Czech&gt;{{cite news |title=Czech team takes Pooh-sticks gold |publisher=[[BBC]] |date=2004-03-29 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/oxfordshire/3578055.stm |accessdate=2008-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The competition originally took place every January, but it was moved to March due to icy weather in 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Thaw to bring wave of misery |newspaper=[[The Independent]] |date=1997-01-04 |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/thaw-to-bring-wave-of-misery-1281491.html |accessdate=2013-05-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:DaysLock04.JPG|right|thumb|upright|Day's Lock from [[Wittenham Clumps]] (or Sinodun Hills) in summer]]
The event proved popular with the local community and even attracted the attention of the foreign media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Pooh's Pastime Noted In a Village on Thames |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=1987-01-06 |url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DF153CF935A35752C0A961948260 |accessdate=2008-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Lynn David's retirement, the running of the event was taken over by the former [[Rotary Club]] of Sinodun, based in nearby [[Wallingford, Oxfordshire|Wallingford]].&lt;ref name=Davies&gt;{{cite news |last=Davies |first=Caroline |title=Poohsticks fans club together to save the game |newspaper=[[The Observer]] |date=2008-11-02 |url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2008/nov/02/uk-news |accessdate=2008-11-03 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, the funds raised were divided between the RNLI and charitable projects supported by the Rotary Club.&lt;ref name=Czech/&gt; Twenty years after its first edition, the event had grown in popularity, attracting visitors from across the globe, and had been broadcast on television in countries including Russia, Japan and Czech Republic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Townsend |first=Ian |title=Oxford rotary club steps in to save Pooh Sticks championship previously run by a Wallingford rotary club |publisher=Herald Series |date=2008-10-27 |url=http://www.heraldseries.co.uk/search/3793580.print/ |accessdate=2008-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, [[VisitBritain]], the official British tourist board, named it as a highlight in its collection of &quot;Quirky British Events&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Quirky British Events For 2008 |publisher=[[VisitBritain]] |year=2008 |url=http://www.visitbritain.us/Images/quirky_events_2008_tcm20-119321.pdf |accessdate=2008-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout its existence, it has raised around £30,000 for the RNLI.&lt;ref name=Oxford&gt;{{cite web |title=Pooh sticks championships return |publisher=thisisoxfordshire |date=2002-03-01 |url=http://archive.thisisoxfordshire.co.uk/2002/3/1/43157.html |accessdate=2008-11-03 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=http://archive.wikiwix.com/cache/20081104141540/http://archive.thisisoxfordshire.co.uk/2002/3/1/43157.html |archivedate=4 November 2008 |df=dmy-all }} &lt;/ref&gt;

The Championships were at risk of decline when in 2008 the Rotary Club declared that its members were simply too old to stage an annual event of its size. The Sinodun president, David Caswell, stated: &quot;The trouble is there is a lot of heavy work staging the event. Some of our members are over 70, and it was just getting too much&quot;. However, the Rotary Club of Oxford Spires declared that its members would continue hosting the event, thus preserving the competition for future generations. The President of Oxford Spires for 2008–2009, Liz Williamson, stressed that it should continue as the event was popular locally and demonstrated quirky English nature to a worldwide audience.&lt;ref name=Davies/&gt;

The organisers announced in January 2015 that they had decided that the [[Little Wittenham]] site was no longer suitable, citing increasing logistical difficulties as the event had become more popular and the use of the land had changed. In June the World Championships were held at their new home, one of the cycle-track bridges over the [[River Windrush]] on Langel Common, near the Cogges Manor Farm Museum in Witney, Oxfordshire. The new location still retains a rural atmosphere but is a few minutes' walk from Witney town centre with its convenient public transport links to [[Oxford]]. Car parking is also much closer than at the original venue, a factor that influenced the choice of venue. For the first year at the new location, the organizers decided not to hold the 2015 team games,&lt;ref name=&quot;name=Rotary Club of Oxford Spires&quot;&gt;name=Rotary Club of Oxford Spires&lt;/ref&gt; but team games were restored in 2016. The move to the new venue also allowed the event to move to June when the weather is likely to be better.

===Winners===

The winners of both the individual and team events receive a trophy, and the second- and third-placed individuals and teams also receive a smaller trophy. Despite claims that the game involves skill more than luck, no team or individual has ever won the competition more than once. The individual competition usually involves winning three rounds of matches before receiving an entry to the final.&lt;ref name=Davies/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
|-
! Year !! Edition !! Date !! Individual event !! Team event
|-
| 1984 ||1st Annual Championships || || ? || ?
|-
| 1985 ||2nd Annual Championships || || ? || ?
|-
| 1986 ||3rd Annual Championships || || ? || ?
|-
| 1987 ||4th Annual Championships || || ? || ?
|-
| 1988 ||5th Annual Championships || || ? || ?
|-
| 1989 ||6th Annual Championships || || ? || ?
|- 
| 1990 ||7th Annual Championships || || ? || ? 
|-
| 1991 ||8th Annual Championships || || ? || ?
|-
| 1992 ||9th Annual Championships || || Sue Rayner, Wootton{{Citation needed|date=November 2013}} || ?
|-
| 1993 ||10th Annual Championships || || ? || ?
|-
| 1994 ||11th Annual Championships || || ? || ?
|-
| 1995 ||12th Annual Championships || || ? || ?
|-
| 1996 ||13th Annual Championships || || Théo Welch-King, a five-year-old from [[Abingdon, Oxfordshire|Abingdon]]{{Citation needed|date=May 2015}} || ?
|-
| 1997 ||14th Annual Championships || || ? || ?
|-
| 1998 ||15th Annual Championships || || ? || ?
|-
| 1999 ||16th Annual Championships || || Daisy || ?
|-
| 2000 ||17th Annual Championships || || Blair DeBart, 18, from Brixton{{Citation needed|date=November 2013}} || ?
|-
| 2001 ||18th Annual Championships || || colspan=2 |Cancelled&lt;ref name=&quot;Ellery&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.oxfordmail.co.uk/news/headlines/5199094.Health_and_safety_fears_scupper_Pooh_sticks_race/|title=Health and safety fears scupper Pooh sticks race|last=Ellery|first=Ben|date=28 March 2010|work=[[Oxford Mail]] |accessdate=24 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2002 ||19th Annual Championships || || Rachel Banham (age 11) [[Wantage]]&lt;ref name=BBC1/&gt; || ?
|-
| 2003 ||20th Annual Championships || || Becky Aram (age 10) [[Wantage]]&lt;ref name=BBC1/&gt; || [[Australia]]&lt;ref name=BBC1/&gt;
|-
| 2004 ||21st Annual Championships || || Susan Young from [[Didcot]], [[Oxfordshire]]&lt;ref name=Czech/&gt; || [[Czech Republic]]&lt;ref name=Czech/&gt;
|-
| 2005 ||22nd Annual Championships ||  || Callum Alexander (age 9) || [[Japan]]&lt;ref name=23rd&gt;{{cite news |title=23rd world Pooh-sticks race held  |publisher=[[BBC]] |date=2006-03-27 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/oxfordshire/4845136.stm |accessdate=2008-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2006 ||23rd Annual Championships ||25–26 March 2006 || Harry Norton Shaw, an eight-year-old from near [[Abingdon, Oxfordshire|Abingdon]]&lt;ref name=23rd/&gt; || Team Natural Colour Cotton from [[Milton Keynes]]&lt;ref name=23rd/&gt;&lt;ref name=UKAEA&gt;{{cite web|title=Successful return for Pooh Sticks |publisher=[[United Kingdom Atomic Energy Authority]] |date=2007-03-29 |url=http://www.ukaea.org.uk/news/2007/29-03-07.shtml |accessdate=2008-11-03 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090614132821/http://www.ukaea.org.uk/news/2007/29-03-07.shtml |archivedate=14 June 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2007 ||24th Annual Championships || ||Bob Jones of [[Carterton, Oxfordshire|Carterton]]&lt;ref name=PoohTime/&gt; || Bears for Life from [[United Kingdom]]&lt;ref name=UKAEA/&gt;
|-
| 2008 ||25th Annual Championships || || Lydia Leece, aged ten&lt;ref name=25th/&gt; || Sticking to the Prize&lt;ref name=25th&gt;[http://www.rotary-ribi.org/clubs/committee.asp?ClubCtteeID=3134&amp;ClubID=568 2008 World Pooh Sticks Championships Results] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110727223958/http://www.rotary-ribi.org/clubs/committee.asp?ClubCtteeID=3134&amp;ClubID=568 |date=27 July 2011 }}. The Rotary Club of Sinodun. Retrieved on 2009-03-30.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2009 ||26th Annual Championships || || Phil Davies&lt;ref name=26th/&gt; || Cytoarchitechno (from [[Oxford]])&lt;ref name=26th&gt;[http://scotlandonsunday.scotsman.com/latest-south-east-news/Crowds-enjoy-pooh-sticks-championships.5119756.jp Crowds enjoy pooh sticks championships]{{dead link|date=December 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}. ''Scotland on Sunday'' (2009-03-29). Retrieved on 2009-03-30.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2010 ||27th Annual Championships || ||colspan=2 |Cancelled - the flow was too heavy&lt;ref name=27th&gt;{{cite news |title=Pooh sticks event cancelled |first=Ben |last=Ellery |url=http://www.oxfordmail.co.uk/news/headlines/5198542.Pooh_sticks_event_cancelled/ |newspaper=[[Oxford Mail]] |publisher=Newsquest Media Group |location=Oxford |date=27 March 2010 |accessdate=27 March 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2011 ||28th Annual Championships || 27 March 2011 || Saffron Sollit, aged nine&lt;ref name =BBC2011&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-oxfordshire-12874674|title=Girl wins Oxfordshire World Pooh Sticks Championships|work=[[BBC Online]]|accessdate=27 March 2011|date=2011-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; || Team Kelly&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC2011&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 2012 ||29th Annual Championships || 25 March 2012 || Aidan Eltham{{Citation needed|date=November 2013}} || The Tiglets{{Citation needed|date=November 2013}} 
|-
| 2013 ||30th Annual Championships || 13 October 2013 (after high river levels forced cancellation on 24 March)&lt;ref name=&quot;2013 Delay&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Pooh Sticks World Championships 2013 |publisher=Rotary Club of Oxford Spires |url=http://www.pooh-sticks.com/node/366 |accessdate=2014-04-28 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140429044659/http://www.pooh-sticks.com/node/366 |archivedate=2014-04-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =BBC2013Cancel&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-oxfordshire-21896847|title=World Pooh Sticks Championship hit by high river levels|work=[[BBC Online]]|accessdate=28 April 2014|date=2013-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; || Alex Marshall (aged 30) of [[Mornington, Victoria|Mornington]], [[Australia]]&lt;ref name =BBC2013&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-oxfordshire-24516717|title=Australian Alex Marshall is World Pooh Sticks Champion|work=[[BBC Online]]|accessdate=28 April 2014|date=2013-10-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; || We don't spell love we feel it (from [[Oxford]]) &lt;ref name =OxfordMailTeam&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.oxfordmail.co.uk/news/10735871.Pooh_Sticks_contest_braves_the_downpour/?ref=rss|title=Pooh Sticks contest braves the downpour|work=[[Oxford Mail]]|accessdate=28 April 2014|date=2013-10-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2014 ||31st Annual Championships || 30 March 2014 || Simon Critchley &lt;ref name=LocalHeroes&gt;{{cite news |title=Local heroes claim honours at Pooh Sticks competition |newspaper=[[Oxford Mail]] |date=2014-03-31 |url=http://www.oxfordmail.co.uk/news/11113179.Local_heroes_claim_honours_at_Pooh_Sticks_competition/ |accessdate=2014-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; || Blantz Family&lt;ref name=&quot;LocalHeroes&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 2015 ||32nd Annual Championships || 7 June 2015 || James Smith &lt;ref name=DreamComeTrue&gt;{{cite news |title=Fan\'s visit to \'land of Winnie the Pooh\' dream come true |newspaper=[[Oxford Mail]] |date=2015-06-08 |url=http://www.oxfordtimes.co.uk/news/13317769.Video__Fan___s_visit_to____land_of_Winnie_the_Pooh____dream_come_true/}}&lt;/ref&gt; || ''No team games this year'' 
|-
| 2016 ||33rd Annual Championships || 5 June 2016 || Charlie Roman || Hundred Acre Edwards
|-
| 2017 ||34th Annual Championships || 4 June 2017 || Daniel Gooding (age 6) from [[Oxford]]&lt;ref name=OxTimes17&gt;{{cite news |title=Ready, steady, go! Pooh Sticks World Championships 2017 at Witney's Langel Common |newspaper=[[Oxford Times]] |date=2017-06-04 |url=http://www.oxfordtimes.co.uk/news/15327258.Ready__steady__go__Pooh_Sticks_World_Championships_2017/ |accessdate=2017-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; || Kanga Roo Pooh from East Hanney &lt;ref name=OxTimes17&gt;{{cite news |title=Ready, steady, go! Pooh Sticks World Championships 2017 at Witney's Langel Common |newspaper=[[Oxford Times]] |date=2017-06-04 |url=http://www.oxfordtimes.co.uk/news/15327258.Ready__steady__go__Pooh_Sticks_World_Championships_2017/ |accessdate=2017-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2018 ||35rd Annual Championships || 3 June 2018 || Innes Turnbull&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oxfordmail.co.uk/news/16266638.PIC_GALLERY__Hundreds_compete_in_World_Poohsticks_Championships/|title=PIC GALLERY: Hundreds compete in World Poohsticks Championships|website=Oxford Mail|language=en|access-date=2018-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; || Kids 4 Us&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;
|}

== Notable Poohsticks societies ==

=== Rotary Club of Oxford Spires ===

Although not a Poohsticks Society as such, the Rotary Club of Oxford Spires&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford Spires Rotary&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=The Oxford Spires Rotary Club |publisher=Rotary Club of Oxford Spires |url=http://www.oxfordspiresrotary.org.uk |accessdate=2014-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; is responsible for the World Pooh Sticks Championships held annually since 1983 at Days Lock on the River Thames then in Witney since 2015.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC2011&quot; /&gt; The Championships were voted 'Britain's Favourite Quirky Event' by ''Countryfile'' magazine readers in 2012&lt;ref name=&quot;CountryFile Awards&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=CountryFile Awards at Poohsticks.com |publisher=Rotary Club of Oxford Spires |url=http://www.pooh-sticks.com/node/219 |accessdate=2014-04-12 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140407091312/http://www.pooh-sticks.com/node/219 |archivedate=2014-04-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and are carried out with the aim of raising money for a variety of charities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Championships Information&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=All you need to know for 2014 at Poohsticks.com |publisher=Rotary Club of Oxford Spires |url=http://www.pooh-sticks.com/content/all-you-need-know-2014 |accessdate=2014-04-12 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140407091325/http://www.pooh-sticks.com/content/all-you-need-know-2014 |archivedate=2014-04-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:MCPSSLogo.jpeg|thumbnail|100px|right|The logo of the MCPSS, circa 2013]]

=== Magdalen College Pooh Sticks Society ===

Revival of the Oxford University Pooh Sticks Society has begun thanks to students in Magdalen College, Oxford, with the creation of the Magdalen College Pooh Sticks Society (MCPSS) founded in April 2013 which mixes classic Pooh Sticks games with commentary and rules in the style of radio programme ''[[I'm Sorry I Haven't a Clue]]''. Of late the club has become increasingly well known inside the University and is no longer restricted solely to members of Magdalen College.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Oxford Student&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Pooh Sticks Society a Winnie-er |publisher=[[The Oxford Student]] |date=2014-02-13 |url=http://oxfordstudent.com/2014/02/13/pooh-stick-society-a-winnie-er/ |accessdate=2014-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Pembroke College Winnie the Pooh Society ===

Founded in 1993, students of Pembroke College, Cambridge, pay homage to the works of A. A. Milne in a variety of ways, including playing games of Poohsticks alongside events such as visits to the 'real-life' Hundred Acre Wood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pembroke College&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=The Poohsticks Cam Bridge Crawl |publisher=Pembroke College Winnie the Pooh Society |url=http://pooh.soc.srcf.net/sticks/ |archive-url=https://archive.is/20140407012316/http://pooh.soc.srcf.net/sticks/ |url-status=dead |archive-date=2014-04-07 |accessdate=2014-04-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Society has gained significant fame at the University of Cambridge and claims Her Majesty the Queen as an honorary member.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Daily Mail&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Happy 90th birthday, Winnie the Pooh: The bear of very little brain (but VERY big bank balance) |newspaper=[[The Daily Mail]] |date=2012-06-11 |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2002613/Winnie-Pooh-The-bear-little-brain-VERY-big-bank-balance.html |accessdate=2014-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Elsewhere in popular culture==

[[Terry Pratchett]] mentioned the game in ''[[Thud!]]'' (2005) as a popular children's game played in the gutters during Sam Vimes' childhood in Ankh-Morpork, originally called &quot;turd races&quot; before renaming it &quot;poohsticks&quot; to take the game upmarket.

[[Julia Donaldson]] mentioned the game in her children's book ''[[Stick Man]]'' (2008) when the protagonist, Stickman, is used by a girl in a game of Poohsticks.

In Season 14, Episode 2 (2010) of ''[[Midsomer Murders]]'' a group of children play Poohsticks, as [[Chief inspector|DCI]] John Barnaby and [[Detective Sergeant|DS]] Ben Jones drive by. Jones instructs children not to play on the road, Barnaby explains the game to Jones and recommends him to hang on to childhood poetry. The still-playing children later find a dead body floating in the stream.

In Season 5, Episode 7 (2014) of ''[[Downton Abbey]]'', Tom Branson and young Sybil play a game of Poohsticks, without referencing the game by name, while he is telling her of his idea to leave Downton and move them to Boston.

The partly fictitious 1980s Swansea power pop band [[The Pooh Sticks]] was named as both a homage to the game, and as a description of the factual or habitual sticky qualities of lowercase pooh.{{cn|date=July 2018}}

The song &quot;[[Twydale's Lament]]&quot; by British band [[Half Man Half Biscuit]], on their 2005 album ''[[Achtung Bono]]'', includes the line, &quot;I saw a young professional couple playing poohsticks on a Cotswold bridge&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://halfmanhalfbiscuit.uk/achtung-bono-2005/twydales-lament/ |title=Twydale's Lament |website=halfmanhalfbiscuit.uk |accessdate=1 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.pooh-sticks.com/ World Pooh Sticks Championships Home Page]
*[http://www.rotary-ribi.org/clubs/homepage.asp?ClubID=568 The Rotary Club of Sinodun]
*[http://www.oxfordspiresrotary.org.uk The Rotary Club of Oxford Spires]
* Map and aerial photo sources for [[british national grid reference system|grid reference]]:
** {{mmukscaled|TQ470338|25|TQ 470 338}} — Poohsticks Bridge near [[Hartfield]] — marked on the [[Ordnance Survey]] &quot;25k&quot; map
** {{mmukscaled|SU567934|25|SU 567 934}} — Day's Lock and the [[Sinodun Hills]]
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20051119234953/http://geoimages.berkeley.edu/wwp904/html/BruceHemming.html Bruce Hemming's page about the Poohsticks Bridge] with QuickTime panorama — note that the coordinates given are in error by 25&amp;nbsp;km

{{Winnie-the-Pooh}}

{{good article}}

[[Category:Outdoor games]]
[[Category:Winnie-the-Pooh]]
[[Category:Bridges in the United Kingdom|*]]
[[Category:Culture associated with the River Thames]]
[[Category:Fictional games]]</text>
      <sha1>a65g4indr6c3d1cayfmq5seu68mg033</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
