  <page>
    <title>Propertarianism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2838370</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937816977</id>
      <parentid>932069191</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-27T11:47:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{libertarianism in the United States sidebar}}
{{anarcho-capitalism sidebar}}
'''Propertarianism''', or '''proprietarianism''',&lt;ref&gt;Ralf M. Bader, John Meadowcroft (eds.), ''The Cambridge Companion to Nozick's Anarchy, State, and Utopia'', Cambridge University Press, 2011, p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt; is an [[ethical philosophy]] that advocates [[Labor theory of property|Lockean sticky property norms]], where an owner keeps his property more or less until he consents to gift or sell it, rejecting the [[Lockean proviso]].

Closely related to and overlapping with [[right-libertarianism]], it is also often accompanied with the idea that state monopoly law should be replaced by market-generated law centered on contractual relationships. Propertarian ideals are most commonly cited to advocate for an [[anarcho-capitalist]] or [[minarchist]] society with governance systems limited to enforcing [[contracts]] and [[private property]].

According to its advocates, propertarianism is synonymous with [[capitalism]].&lt;ref&gt;Ayn Rand, Nathaniel Branden, Alan Greenspan, Robert Hessen (1967). ''Capitalism: The Unknown Ideal''. New York City: Signet.&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The term appears to have been coined by Edward Cain in 1963: &lt;blockquote&gt;Since [libertarians' in the United States] use of the word &quot;[[liberty]]&quot; refers almost exclusively to [[property]], it would be helpful if we had some other word, such as &quot;propertarian,&quot; to describe them. [...] Novelist Ayn Rand is not a conservative at all but claims to be very relevant. She is a radical capitalist, and is the closest to what I mean by a propertarian.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Edward Cain|title=They'd Rather Be Right: Youth and the Conservative Movement|publisher=Macmillan|pages=32–36|year=1963|asin=B0000CLYF9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Marcus Cunliffe]] defined propertarianism in his 1973 lectures as &quot;characteristic values of American history&quot; in regard to property.&lt;ref&gt;Hans Joachim Morgenthau, (Kenneth W. Thompson, Robert John Myers, Editors), ''Truth and tragedy: a tribute to Hans J. Morgenthau'', Transaction Publishers, [https://books.google.com/books?id=4ejXvbBV0ocC&amp;pg=PA174&amp;lpg=PA174&amp;dq=%22propertarianism%22+is+Cunliffe%27s&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Qjcman0_5R&amp;sig=EihLq_efZHLVE46c0oGGBBTTTi0&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=M-qWSo3-LIu_lAesr5yzDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2#v=onepage&amp;q=cunliffe&amp;f=false p. 165], 1984 {{ISBN|0-87855-866-7}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marcus Cunliffe, ''The right to property: a theme in American history, Sir George Watson lecture delivered in the University of Leicester, 4 May 1973, Leicester University Press, 1974 {{ISBN|0-7185-1129-8}}, {{ISBN|978-0-7185-1129-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rob Kroes, ''Them and us: questions of citizenship in a globalizing world'', University of Illinois Press, [https://books.google.com/books?id=QQ0ysmUUjFYC&amp;pg=PA208&amp;lpg=PA208&amp;dq=%22propertarianism%22+is+Cunliffe%27s&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=w-Rrj300FH&amp;sig=aVdr9OKfekMLwCzd_ejUm2aMnSk&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=M-qWSo3-LIu_lAesr5yzDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false p. 208], 2000 {{ISBN|0-252-06909-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marcus Cunliffe, ''In search of America: transatlantic essays, 1951–1990'', p. 307, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; [[David Boaz]] writes that the &quot;propertarian approach to privacy&quot;, both morally and legally, has ensured Americans' privacy rights.&lt;ref&gt;David Boaz, Cato Institute, ''Toward liberty: the idea that is changing the world : 25 years of public policy from the Cato Institute'', Cato Institute, [https://books.google.com/books?id=81to23W3wB0C&amp;pg=PA386&amp;dq=Propertarian&amp;lr=&amp;ei=ni-XSsmiJ57CzQSwh-XbDg#v=onepage&amp;q=Propertarian&amp;f=false p. 386], 2002 {{ISBN|1-930865-27-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Markus Verhaegh states that Rothbardian [[anarcho-capitalism]] advocates the neo-[[Lockean]] idea that property only legitimately originates from labor and may then only legitimately change hands by trade or gift.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Verhaegh|first=Marcus|year=2006|title=Rothbard as a Political Philosopher|url=http://mises.org/journals/jls/20_4/20_4_1.pdf|journal=[[Journal of Libertarian Studies]]|volume=20|issue=4|page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Brian Doherty (journalist)|Brian Doherty]] describes [[Murray Rothbard]]'s form of [[Right-libertarianism|libertarianism]] as propertarian because he &quot;reduced all human rights to rights of property, beginning with the natural right of self-ownership&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|last=Doherty|first=Brian|authorlink=Brian Doherty (journalist)|editor-first=Ronald|editor-last=Hamowy|editor-link=Ronald Hamowy|encyclopedia=The Encyclopedia of Libertarianism|title=Rothbard, Murray (1926–1995)|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yxNgXs3TkJYC|year=2008|publisher=[[SAGE Publications|SAGE]]; [[Cato Institute]]|location=Thousand Oaks, CA|doi=10.4135/9781412965811.n271|isbn=978-1-4129-6580-4|oclc=750831024|lccn=2008009151|page=442–445|quote=|ref=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[L. Neil Smith]] describes propertarianism as a positive libertarian philosophy in his [[alternate history]] novels ''[[The Probability Broach]]'' (1980) and ''The American Zone'' (2002).&lt;ref&gt;L. Neil Smith, ''The American Zone'', p. 167, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John J. Pierce, ''When world views collide: a study in imagination and evolution'', p. 163, 1989.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Alternative meanings ==
[[Hans Morgenthau]] used propertarianism to characterize the connection between property and suffrage.&lt;ref&gt;Hans Morgenthua, [https://books.google.com/books?id=4ejXvbBV0ocC&amp;pg=PA174&amp;lpg=PA174&amp;dq=%22propertarianism%22+is+Cunliffe%27s&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Qjcman0_5R&amp;sig=EihLq_efZHLVE46c0oGGBBTTTi0&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=M-qWSo3-LIu_lAesr5yzDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2#v=onepage&amp;q=cunliffe&amp;f=false p. 174].&lt;/ref&gt; 

Since 2013, Curt Doolittle has used propertarianism in an expanded sense to include all socially demonstrated interests instead of scarce resources. He considers it a subset of [[natural law]] defining rules of [[Reciprocity (social psychology)|reciprocity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.counter-currents.com/2015/06/interview-with-curt-doolittle/|title=Counter-Currents Radio: Interview with Curt Doolittle|work=Counter-Currents Publishing|accessdate=June 12, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{better source needed|date=June 2019}}

== Criticism ==
In the [[science fiction]] novel ''[[The Dispossessed]]'' (1974), [[Left-libertarianism|left-libertarian]] [[Ursula K. Le Guin]] contrasted a propertarian statist society with an anarchist anti-propertarian society&lt;ref&gt;Ursela K. Le Guin, ''The dispossessed: a novel'', HarperCollins, [https://books.google.com/books?id=k1Smynbdy_IC&amp;pg=PA326&amp;dq=Ursula+K.+Le+Guin+propertarian&amp;ei=2CmXSraWMIiqzQS31ejwDg#v=onepage&amp;q=propertarian&amp;f=false various pages], 2003 {{ISBN|0-06-051275-X}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John P. Reeder, ''Source, sanction, and salvation: religion and morality in Judaic and Christian traditions'', [https://archive.org/details/sourcesanctionsa00reed &lt;!-- quote=nonpropertarian. --&gt; p. 113], 1988. Reeder uses phrase &quot;nonpropertarian&quot; to describe Le Guin's views.&lt;/ref&gt; in an attempt to show that property and state objectified human beings.&lt;ref&gt;Laurence Davis, Peter G. Stillman, ''The new utopian politics of Ursula K. Le Guin's The dispossessed'', Lexington Books, [https://books.google.com/books?id=9goKmJQaMzEC&amp;pg=PR17&amp;dq=Ursula+K.+Le+Guin+propertarian&amp;ei=2CmXSraWMIiqzQS31ejwDg#v=onepage&amp;q=Ursula%20K.%20Le%20Guin%20propertarian&amp;f=false p. xvii], 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.depauw.edu/sfs/interviews/delany52interview.htm On Triton and Other Matters: An Interview with Samuel R. Delany],  Science Fiction Studies, November 1990.&lt;/ref&gt; A book presenting the dual opposite of this scenario is Robert Heinlein's ''[[The Moon is a Harsh Mistress]]'' which contrasts a propertarian, stateless society on the moon with a statist anti-propertarian society on earth. Other left-libertarian non-propertarians like [[Murray Bookchin]] have been called anti-propertarians.{{Citation needed|reason=No one on the right uses the word propertarian, and so it's unlikely he was ever called anti-propertarian|date=September 2019}} Bookchin objected to propertarians even calling themselves libertarian, arguing: &lt;blockquote&gt;We have permitted cynical political reactionaries and the spokesmen of large corporations to pre-empt these basic libertarian American ideals. We have permitted them not only to become the specious voice of these ideals such that individualism has been used to justify egotism; the pursuit of happiness to justify greed, and even our emphasis on local and regional autonomy has been used to justify parochialism, insularism, and exclusivity – often against ethnic minorities and so-called deviant individuals. We have even permitted these reactionaries to stake out a claim to the word libertarian, a word, in fact, that was literally devised in the 1890s in France by Elisée Reclus as a substitute for the word anarchist, which the government had rendered an illegal expression for identifying one's views. The propertarians, in effect – acolytes of Ayn Rand, the earth mother of greed, egotism, and the virtues of property – have appropriated expressions and traditions that should have been expressed by radicals but were willfully neglected because of the lure of European and Asian traditions of socialism, socialisms that are now entering into decline in the very countries in which they originated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bookchin&quot;&gt;Murray Bookchin, ''The Greening of Politics: Toward a New Kind of Political Practice,'' Green Perspectives: Newsletter of the Green Program Project, No. 1 January 1986 [http://dwardmac.pitzer.edu/Anarchist_Archives/bookchin/gp/perspectives1.html].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Bookchin described three concepts of possession, namely property itself, possession and [[usufruct]], i.e. appropriation of resources by virtue of use.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clement&amp;Oppenheim&quot;&gt;Ellie Clement and Charles Oppenheim, Department of Information Science, Loughborough University, Loughborough, Leics Great Britain, [http://www.lwbooks.co.uk/journals/anarchiststudies/articles/ClementOppenheim.pdf Anarchism, Alternative Publishers and Copyright], [http://www.lwbooks.co.uk/journals/anarchiststudies/ Journal of Anarchist Studies], undated.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{cols}}
* [[Anarcho-capitalism]]
* [[Capitalism]]
* [[Creative disruption]]
* [[Private law society]]
* [[Private property]]
* [[Privatism]]
* [[Privatization]]
* [[Producerism]]
* [[Right-libertarianism]]
{{colend}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}
{{anarcho-capitalism}}
{{libertarianism}}
[[Category:Anarcho-capitalism]]
[[Category:Libertarian theory]]
[[Category:Political theories]]</text>
      <sha1>asq4mntbibwx7txpli4ypro2l7x89b5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
