  <page>
    <title>Qualimetry</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5468371</id>
    <revision>
      <id>795358551</id>
      <parentid>544408262</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-08-13T18:55:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Trey314159</username>
        <id>1818005</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fix homographs: Мoscow</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Qualimetry''' is a scientific discipline which concerns itself with the methods and problems of quantification of the quality of any object: things or processes, whether natural or man-made, products of labour or nature, whether living or inanimate,  etc.&lt;ref&gt;Azgaldov, G. G. (1982), Theory and Practice of Product  Quality Assessment: Fundamentals of Qualimetry, Ekonomika,  Moscow (in Russian).&lt;/ref&gt;

It is a scientific theory of the quantitative determination of quality developed in the former USSR by G.G.Azgaldov&lt;ref&gt;Azgaldov, G.G. (1981), &quot;Development of the theoretical basis of qualimetry&quot;, doctoral dissertation, Kuibyshev Military Engineering Academy, Moscow (in Russian).&lt;/ref&gt; and currently used in development of Russian standards&lt;ref&gt;Product Quality (1979), Product Quality: Terms and Definitions. -  GOST 15467 – 79.&lt;/ref&gt; ([[GOST]]),  etc.

==Discussion==
&quot;The term qualimetry (from the Latin [[quale]], “of what kind”), which designates a scientific discipline studying the methodology and problems of quantitative assessment of the quality of any kind of object (primarily, products), was first used in 1968.  That this initiative was timely and justifiable was borne out by a series of international scholarly conferences fully or partly devoted to issues of qualimetry, e.g., in [[Moscow]], [[Oslo]], [[Varna]], [[Yerevan]], [[Madrid]] or [[Tallinn]]. 
The term qualimetry is being gradually admitted into the scientific and engineering vocabularies of many countries. According to Google, tens of thousands of references to publications in 32 languages contain this term. &quot; &lt;ref&gt;Azgaldov, G.G. and Kostin, A.V. (2011), &quot;Applied Qualimetry: its Origins, Errors and Misconceptions&quot;, Benchmarking: An International Journal, Vol. 18 Iss: 3, pp.428 – 444.&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Standards]]
[[Category:Quality]]
[[Category:Metrology]]


{{Sci-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>9us8f2bj5z5h3kn3t7lsa70mobp59ka</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
