  <page>
    <title>Randonneuring</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2704903</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934366929</id>
      <parentid>922405555</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-06T04:06:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kaltenmeyer</username>
        <id>14703151</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>clean up, [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: 60 hour → 60-hour, upto → up to (2), 1000 Km → 1000&amp;nbsp;km</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
{{More citations needed|date=March 2009}}
{{Globalize |date=March 2016 |discuss=Talk:Randonneuring#Globalize }}
}}

[[File:Cyclists riding a randonneuring event..JPG|thumb|A group of cyclists riding a 200 km randonneuring event]]
'''Randonneuring''' (also known as '''[[Audax (cycling)|Audax]]''' in the UK, Australia and Brazil) is a long-distance [[cycling]] sport with its origins in audax cycling.  In randonneuring, riders attempt courses of 200&amp;nbsp;km or more, passing through predetermined &quot;controls&quot; (checkpoints) every few tens of kilometres.  Riders aim to complete the course within specified time limits, and receive equal recognition regardless of their finishing order.  Riders may travel in groups or alone as they wish, and are expected to be self-sufficient between controls.   A randonneuring event is called a '''randonnée''' or '''brevet,''' and a rider who has completed a 200&amp;nbsp;km event is called a '''randonneur'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Randonneurs USA | work=Randonneuring | url=http://www.rusa.org | date=May 15, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = Seray
  | first = Jacques|editorn-last=
  |editor1-last= Krausz
  |editor1-first= John
  |editor2-last= Krausz
  |editor2-first= Vera van der Reis
  | title = The Bicycling Book
  | publisher = The Dial Press
  | year = 1982
  | location = New York
  | pages = 89
  | isbn = 0-385-27666-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The international governing body for randonneuring is [[Audax Club Parisien|Audax Club Parisien (ACP)]], which works with other randonneuring organisations worldwide through [[Les Randonneurs Mondiaux|Les Randonneurs Mondiaux (RM)]].  Randonneuring is popular in France, and has a following in the [[Netherlands]], Belgium, United Kingdom, Italy, Australia, United States, Canada, [[Brazil]], Ireland, India, Japan and Malaysia.

==History==
In the late nineteenth century Italy, day-long &quot;challenge&quot; sports became popular.  Participants aimed to cover as much distance as possible and prove themselves ''audax'' (&quot;audacious&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ctc.org.uk/DesktopDefault.aspx?TabID=3931 &quot;What is Audax?&quot;]. [[Cyclists' Touring Club|CTC - The UK's National Cyclists' Organisation]].  Retrieved 2011-02-20.&lt;/ref&gt;  The first recorded audax cycling event took place on June 12, 1897, when twelve Italian cyclists attempted the challenge of cycling from [[Rome]] to [[Naples]], a distance of {{convert|230|km}}, during daylight hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;BQ - 8 - 3&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Heine|first=Jan|title=The History of Randonneuring , Part 1: Vélocio, the Audax and Paris-Brest-Paris|journal=Bicycle Quarterly|year=2010|volume=8|issue=3|pages=54|url=http://www.bikequarterly.com/contents.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;   Similar events became popular elsewhere, and in 1904 French journalist [[Henri Desgrange]] produced '''Audax regulations''', which belonged to his ''Auto'' newspaper.  Under the Audax regulations, riders rode as a group.  Successful riders were awarded a certificate called a '''Brevet d'Audax'''.  A group of successful audax cyclists formed the '''Audax Club Parisien (ACP)''', which took over the organisation of Audax events on Desgrange's behalf.   In 1920, there was a disagreement between Desgrange and the ACP.  Desgrange withdrew ACP's permission to organise events under his Audax regulations, and ACP created its own '''allure libre''' (free-paced) version of the sport, where successful riders were awarded certificates called '''Brevets des Randonneurs'''.  This style is now popularly known as &quot;randonneuring&quot;.

Desgrange continued to promote the original Audax rules, and on July 14, 1921 the Union of Parisian Audax Cyclistes (UACP) was formed, which became the Union of French Audax in January 1956, and later simply [[Union des Audax]].  The original style is still popular in France and neighbouring countries.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Origins and History of Audax UK&quot;, [http://www.aukweb.net/handbook/handbook.pdf ''Audax UK Handbook 2011''].  [[Audax UK]].  Retrieved 2011-02-20.&lt;/ref&gt;  In [[Great Britain]] where the original audax style does not exist, and in [[Brazil]] where it is not common, the term '''audax''' is used interchangeably with '''randonneuring''', reflecting the sport's origins with [[Audax Club Parisien]].

Randonneuring has much in common with cyclotouring, the founding-father of which is often said to be the journalist [[Paul de Vivie|Velocio (Paul de Vivie)]], also credited with making derailleur gears popular.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  |last = Durry
  |first = J
  |editor1-last= Wadley
  |editor1-first= JB
  |title = The Guinness Guide to BICYCLING
  |publisher = Guinness Superlatives LTD
  |location = Enfield, Middlesex, England
  |page = 91
  |year = 1976
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rules and process==
[[File:20110312 Brevet Card.jpg|thumb|right|A completed brevet card from a {{convert|100|km}} 'populaire'. The pink stamps are from controllers and the rider has written in the answers at the information controls.]]
The majority of randonneuring events are classified as &quot;brevets des randonneurs&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;def&quot;&gt;{{cite book |editor1-last= Wise |editor1-first= Jennifer |title = Randonneurs USA Members Handbook |publisher = Randonneurs USA  |location = Santa Cruz, CA, USA  |page = 10 |year = 2009 |isbn = 0-900424-62-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In such events, riders follow a course through a series of predetermined checkpoints called &quot;controls&quot;; these are typically a few tens of kilometres apart.  Each rider carries a &quot;brevet card&quot; which must be stamped at each control to prove completion.  In some events, riders will be asked to supplement this by collecting till receipts in certain places and by answering questions about their surroundings at &quot;information controls&quot;, such as recording a distance from a milepost.  At the end of the event, the brevet card is handed in to the organisers who will then check and certify the results.  Riders are expected to keep within minimum and maximum average speed limits.  For a typical {{convert|200|km|adj=on}} brevet, the minimum speed is around {{convert|15|km/h}} and the maximum is {{convert|30|km/h}}.  Riders who arrive early at controls will be made to wait before they can carry on. Riders can stop to eat and rest at controls, though no extra time is allowed for doing so.  Riders are free to ride individually or in groups as they wish.  A brevet is not a race, and no completion order is published.  Riders are expected to be fully self-sufficient between controls and must carry food, water, spare clothing and tools to meet their requirements.

In addition to brevets appearing on a calendar date, there are &quot;permanent&quot; (or &quot;raid&quot;) brevets which may be ridden on any date by prior arrangement with the organiser, and &quot;DIY permanents&quot; where a rider proposes a specific route.  In these events, the &quot;controls&quot; are predesignated places where a rider will stop and collect evidence of passage such as a shop receipt.

In addition to {{convert|200|km|adj=on}} events, there are brevets of {{convert|300|,|400|,|600|km}} and more.  These will typically involve an element of night-riding.  There are also shorter events: in a &quot;brevet populaire&quot; (or simply &quot;populaire&quot;), riders follow a course of {{convert|50|,|100|,|150|km}}.  These brevets are seen as a good introduction to the full-blown &quot;randonneur&quot; events, and also as a manageable distance for riders who want to maintain regular participation in the sport over a sustained period of time.

There are variations on the brevet theme including team events such as the &quot;[[Flèche (cycling)|Flèche]]&quot; or &quot;Arrow&quot;, which usually converge on a single end point from many starts, and {{convert|200|km}} per day &quot;Dart&quot; events.

==Bicycles and equipment==
[[File:20110312 Audax Bikes.png|thumb|right|Typical bicycles at a randonneuring event in the United Kingdom.]]

Randonneuring bicycles are not subject to the UCI regulations for road-racing: a cycle is acceptable for randonneuring if it is solely human powered, uses wheels, and is no more than a metre wide.{{Citation needed|date=April 2012}}  Tricycles and [[recumbent bicycles|recumbents]], therefore, are allowed.

Authors such as Simon Doughty describe a 'typical' randonneuring bike as being somewhere between a dedicated [[racing bicycle|road-racing bike]] and a [[touring bike]].&lt;ref&gt;Doughty, Simon (2004).  ''The Long Distance Cyclists' Handbook'', 2nd. ed.  London: A &amp; C Black&lt;/ref&gt;  Such bicycles usually have lightweight steel frames, drop handlebars, relaxed (i.e. comfortable) frame geometry, medium-width tyres, triple chainsets, moderately low gearing, and the capacity to carry lightweight luggage.  Mudguards and lighting systems are also common, and may be required for some events.

As of 2019, modern lighting (LED &amp; Lithium Ion batteries), paired with a dynamo hubs are more prevailent; as well as a mix between equipment designed for bikepacking (aerodynamic, lightweight); or more traditional pannier systems particularly for longer distance events.

Randonneurs are expected to be self-sufficient between controls except in the event of real emergency.  Riders are therefore expected to carry food, water, tools, etc.  Some events specifically require riders to carry specific equipment (e.g. lights, spare bulbs, reflective clothing), though this varies depending on the organiser.

==Famous brevets==
The majority of brevets are relatively small and locally organised, making for a busy calendar of events for enthusiasts.  However, there are also some particularly well-known and prestigious events which attract participants from all over the world.

===Paris–Brest–Paris===
Sometimes regarded as the [[Blue Riband]] ''randonnée'', [[Paris–Brest–Paris]] (PBP) is an approximately {{convert|1200|km}} event held on an out-and-back course between [[Paris]] and [[Brest, France|Brest]] every four years. Begun in 1891, it is the oldest bicycling event still regularly run. It began as a race for professional cyclists, but is now a non-competitive endurance challenge. To qualify, a cyclist must complete a series of ''brevets'' within the same year. The series can be completed in any order ({{convert|200|,|300|,|400|and|600|km}} is traditional), and any brevet may be replaced with a longer randonnée.

The PBP was the first popular long distance race, initiated in 1891. After 1931 the riders were separated into three groups: professional cyclists, and two non-professional groups known as the [[Allure libre]] club and the [[Audax (cycling)|Audax]] club. Allure Libre consisted of individuals riding alone in the spirit of self-sufficiency, while Audax riders rode as a group and maintained a steady pace.  As interest in long distance cycling had waned in favour of stage events like the [[Tour de France]], the professional race part of the PBP was lost in 1951, leaving only the randonneuring part of the event.

The Randonneuring part of the PBP had been governed by Audax Club Parisien (ACP) since the 1930s. In 1975 the Audax and Allure libre groups split up and formed two different PBP events. Now the ACP runs the event every four years in their Allure Libre format, and the Union des Audax runs it every five years in their Audax format.

The most recent Paris-Brest-Paris was held in 2019 on August 18. In order to qualify for the event a randonneur needed to do a super randonee series of brevets ({{convert|200|,|300|,|400|and|600|km}}) in the qualifying year i.e. by July 2019.

===London–Edinburgh–London===
[[London–Edinburgh–London]] is a 1400&amp;nbsp;km event that takes place in the United Kingdom every four years. The event typically starts in north [[London]], taking a route through the east of England, to [[Edinburgh]], usually returning along the same route.

The event last took place in July 2017.

===Boston–Montreal–Boston===
[[Boston–Montreal–Boston]] (BMB) is also a {{convert|1200|km}} out-and-back between [[Boston]] and [[Montreal]]. BMB is sometimes regarded as the North American equivalent of PBP.  It was held every year except when Paris–Brest–Paris was held.

'''Other 1000&amp;nbsp;km brevets across globe'''
* Kittur Express 1000&amp;nbsp;km (Bangalore, India)
* Celtic Knot 1000&amp;nbsp;km (Offaly, Ireland)
* Jog Falls 1000&amp;nbsp;km (Bangalore, India)
* Noida Dasuya Noida 1000&amp;nbsp;km (India)
* Deccan Queen – CCD start finish 1000&amp;nbsp;km (India)
* Brevet LOC (India)
* TN 1000 (India)
* BRM Ek Hazaar (Lucknow, India)
'''Other 1200&amp;nbsp;km brevets across globe'''
* Granite Anvil 1200&amp;nbsp;km brevet (Canada)
* Herentals – Cosne s/Loire – Herentals 1200&amp;nbsp;km (Belgium)
* Mumbai–Indore–Mumbai 1200&amp;nbsp;km (India)
* BGB (Bangalore–Goa–Bangalore) 1200&amp;nbsp;km (Bangalore, India)
* Bliss In The Hills 1200&amp;nbsp;km (Bangalore, India)
* Big Tour of Bavaria 1200&amp;nbsp;km (Germany)
* Big Wild Ride 1200&amp;nbsp;km (Alaska, USA)
* BMB Boston–Montreal–Boston 1200k (USA)
* Cascade 1200 (USA)
* Colorado High Country 1200&amp;nbsp;km Randonnée (USA)
* Coulee Challenge 1200 Brevet (Minnesota/Wisconsin USA)
* Gates of Heaven 1200&amp;nbsp;km (Bangalore, India)
* Gold Rush Randonnée (USA) 1200&amp;nbsp;km
* Great Southern Randonnee (Australia) 1200&amp;nbsp;km
* Korea Grande Randonnee 1200 (Korea)
* Last Chance 1200&amp;nbsp;km Randonnée (USA)
* Lowlands 1200&amp;nbsp;km (Netherlands)
* Madrid–Gijon–Madrid 1200&amp;nbsp;km (Spain)
* Míle Fáilte 1200 (Ireland)
* Perth–Albany–Perth (Australia) 1200&amp;nbsp;km
* Rocky Mountain 1200 (Canada)
* Sofia–Varna–Sofia 1200&amp;nbsp;km (Bulgaria)
* Super Brevet Scandinavia 1200&amp;nbsp;km (Denmark, Norway, Sweden)
* Sydney-Melbourne (Australia) 1200&amp;nbsp;km
* Texas Rando Stampede (USA) 1200&amp;nbsp;km
* Taste of Carolina 1200k (USA)
* VanIsle 1200 (Canada)
* Ultimate Island Explorer 2000&amp;nbsp;km (Canada)
* Vologda–Onega–Ladoga (Russia) 1200&amp;nbsp;km
* Silk Route (Uzbekistan) 1200&amp;nbsp;km
* 1200&amp;nbsp;km BRM across Rajasthan, Mahro Rajasthan By Delhi Randonneurs (India)
* 1200 Chuiski tract (Russia)
* BRM Tour of Hungary – BRM 1200 (Hungary)
* Lviv–Karpaty–Lviv, 1200&amp;nbsp;km (Ukraine)
* Noida–Jammu–Noida 1200&amp;nbsp;km – Jammu Express by Noida Randonneurs (India)
* Hokkaido 1200&amp;nbsp;km (Japan)
* Tapi to Aravalli 1200&amp;nbsp;km (India)
* Ranbanka Ride BRM1200 v2 (India)
* KODANAD – 1200&amp;nbsp;km (India)
* Rivers–Mountains–Beaches 1200 (India)
* BRM-1200 (Power it Up) MUM–MAHBLESWR–MUM–DHULE–MUM (India)
* Goa 2 Kanyakumari 1200&amp;nbsp;km (India)
* Psyclepath 1200 – Kochi–Bangalore–Kochi (India)
'''Other 1400&amp;nbsp;km brevets across globe'''
* Dalhousie 1400&amp;nbsp;km Noida Dalhousie Noida by Noida Randonneurs (India)
* Danube Road Randonneur 1440&amp;nbsp;km (Romania)
* Bangkok–Phrae–Bangkok 1400&amp;nbsp;km (Thailand)
* Dutch Capitals Tour 1400&amp;nbsp;km (Netherlands)	
* Giro Central Greece 1400&amp;nbsp;km (Greece)
'''Other 1400 plus km brevets across globe''' 
* Hamburg–Berlin–Cologne–Hamburg 1500&amp;nbsp;km (Germany)
* 1001 Miglia 1630k (Italy)
* Wild Atlantic Way, 2100&amp;nbsp;km (Ireland)
* Sverigetempot 2100&amp;nbsp;km (Sweden)
* Maraton Rowerowy Dookoła Polski 3130&amp;nbsp;km (Poland)

==Awards==
[[File:Sr- Medal-2017.jpg|thumb|Super Randonneur medal]]
A rider who has successfully completed a {{convert|200|km|adj=on}} brevet is called a randonneur.  This is a lifelong title.

Riders completing successful events receive awards, either from Audax Club Parisien or another randonneuring organisation.  Examples of these are:

* Brevet Medal{{spaced endash}}for completing any single brevet of {{convert|200|,|300|,|400|,|600|or|1000|km}}.
* Super Randonneur{{spaced endash}}for completing a series of {{convert|200|,|300|,|400|and|600|km|adj=on}} brevets within the same season.
* Randonneur 5000{{spaced endash}}for completing the full series of {{convert|200|,|300|,|400|,|600|and|1000|km|adj=on}} brevets, the Paris–Brest–Paris and a Flèche Vélocio (in which at least three riders must start, and at least three must finish). Other BRM, LRM, or ACP homologated events up to a balance of 5000&amp;nbsp;km total, all within 4 years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.audax-club-parisien.com/EN/382.html Randonneur 5000 rules on Audax Club Parisien website]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Randonneur 10000{{spaced endash}}for completing two full series of {{convert|200|,|300|,|400|,|600|and|1000|km|adj=on}} brevets, the Paris–Brest–Paris, another 1200&amp;nbsp;km event homologated by LRM, a Flèche Vélocio (in which at least three riders must start, and at least three must finish), and a 1 Super Randonee (a permanent of 600&amp;nbsp;km and at least 10,000&amp;nbsp;m (32.800&amp;nbsp;ft) of climbing, within a 60-hour time limit, homologated by the Audax Club Parisien). Other BRM, LRM, or ACP homologated events up to a balance of 10000&amp;nbsp;km total, all within 4 years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.audax-club-parisien.com/EN/462.html Randonneur 10000 rules on Audax Club Parisien website]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Paris–Brest–Paris{{spaced endash}}for completion of the PBP within the 90-hour time.
* Many others{{spaced endash}}for example, BMB, RUSA specific Super Randonneur.

==Time limits==
Randonneuring events must be undertaken within set time limits based on a set average speed.  There is some regional variation in these, but the following list is typical:
*{{convert|200|km}}{{spaced endash}}13.5 hours (15&amp;nbsp;km/h)
*{{convert|300|km}}{{spaced endash}}20 hours (15&amp;nbsp;km/h)
*{{convert|400|km}}{{spaced endash}}27 hours (15&amp;nbsp;km/h)
*{{convert|600|km}}{{spaced endash}}40 hours (15&amp;nbsp;km/h)
*{{convert|1000|km}}{{spaced endash}}75 hours (13.3&amp;nbsp;km/h)
*{{convert|1200|km}}{{spaced endash}}90 hours (13.3&amp;nbsp;km/h)
*{{convert|1400|km}}{{spaced endash}}116:40 hours (12&amp;nbsp;km/h)
*{{convert|2200|km}}{{spaced endash}}220 hours (10&amp;nbsp;km/h)

Organisers are usually free to reduce the maximum speed. This sometimes makes it easier to man controls at particularly hilly events.
To emphasise that Randonneuring events are not a race, many events also have a maximum speed equal to double the minimum speed (i.e. 30&amp;nbsp;km/h for a 600&amp;nbsp;km event).

==See also==
*[[Challenge riding]]
*[[Cyclosportive]]
*[[Race Across America]]
*[[Reliability trial]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Cycling}}

[[Category:Cycle sport]]
[[Category:Ultra-distance cycling]]</text>
      <sha1>nxi1x6v7i8m32e6hfcmxpm65n4xaas2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
