  <page>
    <title>Salona</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>494183</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932570951</id>
      <parentid>927898454</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-26T21:57:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Further reading */HTTP → HTTPS for [[Open Library]], replaced: http://openlibrary.org/ → https://openlibrary.org/ (2)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Destroyed city on the Dalmatian coast}}
{{About|the ancient Roman city}}
{{Infobox ancient site
  |name = Salona
  |native_name = Σάλωνα
  |alternate_name = Salon
  |image = Roman ruins at Salona, Croatia.jpg
  |alt = 
  |caption = The ruins of Salona
  |map_type = Croatia
  |map_alt = 
  |map_size= 
  |coordinates = {{coord|43|32|22|N|16|28|59|E|display=inline,title}}
  |location = Near [[Solin, Croatia]]
  |region = [[Dalmatia]]
  |type = Settlement
  |part_of = 
  |length = 
  |width = 
  |area = 
  |height = 
  |builder = 
  |material = 
  |built = 
  |abandoned = 7th century
  |epochs = 
  |cultures = Illyrian, Greek, Roman
  |dependency_of = 
  |occupants = 
  |event = 
  |excavations = 
  |archaeologists = 
  |condition = In ruins
  |ownership = 
  |management = 
  |public_access = 
  |website = &lt;!-- {{URL|example.com}} --&gt;
  |notes = 
}}
[[File:Salona - amphitheatre - panorama.jpg|thumb|Salona - amphitheatre]]
'''Salona''' ({{lang-grc|Σάλωνα}}) was an ancient city and the capital of the [[Roman Empire|Roman]] province of [[Dalmatia (Roman province)|Dalmatia]]. The name Salona preserves the language of the early inhabitants of this area whom the Romans called the [[Dalmatae]], considered to be part of a larger group called the [[Illyrians]].&lt;ref&gt;John J. Wilkes. ''Dalmatia''. 1969&lt;/ref&gt; Salona (or '''Salon''') is situated in today's town of [[Solin]], right next to [[Split (city)|Split]], in modern-day [[Croatia]].

==History==
The first mention of the name Salon originates about 7th century BC as an Illyrian settlement near the spring of river Jadro {{Citation needed|reason=Where was it mentioned in the 7th century bc and by whom|date=April 2019}}. 
It is the largest archaeological park in Croatia, whose size is attested by the monumental ramparts with towers and gates, a forum with temples, an amphitheater and cemeteries with Salonian martyrs (Manastirine, Kapljuč, Marusinac). Salona was a town with over [https://visitsplit.com/en/520/salona 60 000 inhabitants] and, according to the legend, the birthplace of [[Diocletian|Emperor Diocletian]]. 
In the first millennium BC&lt;ref&gt;[http://w3.mrki.info/split/solin.html Solin early history]&lt;/ref&gt; the Greeks set up an ''[[Emporium (antiquity)|emporion]]'' (marketplace) there.&lt;ref&gt;Excavations at Salona, Yugoslavia, 1969-1972: conducted for the Department of Classics, Douglass College, Rutg, by Christoph W. Clairmont, 1975, {{ISBN|0-8155-5040-5}}, page 4, &quot;If we are correct in our interpretation of the earliest finds from Salona, the emporion, even if very small, was a settlement in a strategic position&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
After the conquest by the [[Roman Empire|Romans]], Salona became the capital of the [[Roman province of Dalmatia]]&lt;ref&gt;John Everett-Heath. &quot;Dalmatia.&quot; ''Concise Dictionary of World Place-Names''. Oxford University Press. 2005. Encyclopedia.com&lt;/ref&gt; because it sided with the future Roman emperor Gaius Julius Caesar in the civil war against Pompeius and Marcus Licinius Crassus of the first Triumvirate.
Martia Iulia Valeria Salona Felix (the full name of the ancient city) was founded probably after the Roman civil wars under [[Julius Caesar]]. The early Roman city encompassed the area around the Forum and Theatre, with an entrance, the Porta Caesarea, on the north-east side, The walls were fortified with towers during the reign of [[Augustus]].&lt;ref&gt;Jasna Jeličić-Radonić and Ana Sedlar. &quot;Topografija antičke Salone (I) Salonitanska Urbs vetus.&quot; ''Tusculum 2.''&lt;/ref&gt;
The early trapezoidal shape of the city was transformed by eastern and western expansion of the city.
The city quickly acquired Roman characteristics: walls; a [[Forum (Roman)|forum]]; a [[Roman theatre (structure)|theatre]]; an [[Roman amphitheatre|amphitheatre]] {{ndash}} the most conspicuous above-ground remains today; [[Thermae|public baths]]; and an [[Roman aqueduct|aqueduct]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.romanaqueducts.info/aquasite/salona/index.html&lt;/ref&gt; Many inscriptions in both Latin and Greek have been found both inside the walls and in the cemeteries outside, since Romans forbade burials inside the city boundaries. A number of fine marble [[Ancient Roman sarcophagi|sarcophagi]] from those cemeteries are now in the [http://www.mdc.hr/split-arheoloski/nj/index.html Archaeological Museum of Split]. All this archaeological evidence attests to the city's prosperity and integration into the [[Roman Empire]].

[[File:Aqueduct of Salona.JPG|thumb|Aqueduct of Salona]]
Salona had a mint that was connected with the mint in [[Sirmium]] and silver mines in the [[Dinaric Alps]] through [[Via Argentaria]]. When the [[Roman Emperor]] [[Diocletian]] retired, he erected a monumental palace nearby. This massive structure, known as [[Diocletian's Palace]], became the core of the modern city of [[Split, Croatia|Split]].

Salona's continuing prosperity resulted in extensive church building in the fourth and fifth centuries, including an episcopal [[basilica]] and a neighboring church and [[baptistery]] inside the walls, and several shrines honoring martyrs outside. These have made it a major site for studying the development of Christian [[sacred architecture]].&lt;ref&gt;Ejnar Dyggve.  History of Salonitan Christianity. 1951. (Summary of most important buildings and possible interpretations); see now A. M. Yasin. &quot;Reassessing Salona's Churches: Martyrium Evolution in Question,&quot; ''Journal of Early Christian Studies'' 20:1 (2012): 59–112 and [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zLd34zb3lXs%20 recent excavations]&lt;/ref&gt;

Salona was largely destroyed in the invasions of the [[Pannonian Avars|Avars]] and [[Croats]] in the seventh century AD, though the exact year of the destruction still remains an open subject between archaeologists. Refugees from Salona settled inside Diocletian's Palace.&lt;ref&gt;Charles George Herbermann, ''The Catholic Encyclopedia: An International Work of Reference'' (1913) see also Constantine VII Porphyrogenitus. 1967, ''De administrando imperio''; Greek text edited by Gy. Moravcsik; English translation by R. J. H. Jenkins.rev.ed. : Dumbarton Oaks Center for Byzantine Studies, 1967, 1985 and Thomae Archidiaconi. 2006. ''Spalatensis Historia Salonitanorum atque Spalatinorum pontificum'' – Archdeacon Thomas of Split: ''History of the Bishops of Salona and Split''. Damir Karbić, Mirjana Matijević Sokol, Olga Perić and James Ross Sweeney,eds. Budapest: CEU Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Salona is one of the largest archeological sites of the Roman Empire, the park is underutilized and is not preserved, and few visitors know that Salona was one of the largest cities of the Roman Empire. Also, the site is not being guarded and thefts have been [https://www.24sata.hr/news/velika-steta-s-anticke-salone-lopovi-ukrali-arheoloski-kamen-474769 reported], but recently renovations and new excavations have commenced.

==City walls==
The construction of the Salonitan city walls took several centuries. The earliest part of the city was surrounded by walls as early as the second century BC. During the [[Pax Romana]] the city expanded to both east and west. 

During the reign of Emperor [[Marcus Aurelius]] around 170 A.D., under constant threat of Germanic tribes the east and west suburbs were included in the  walls which were fortified with at least 90 towers. Some parts of existing buildings were used in the extensions to the walls thus making them an integral part. Total circumference of the elliptical shape of the walls was approximately 4 km, with varying width from 1.9 to 2.5 metres. 

During the reign of Emperor [[Theodosius II]] in the early fifth century all the towers were reconstructed, as witnessed by an inscription on the walls. Furthermore, in the first half of the sixth century, in order to improve city's security and defence system, triangular shaped endings were added to some square-shaped towers. Such examples are visible today on the northern side of the Urbs orientalis.
Best preserved part of the oldest part of the city (Urbs vetus) is eastern wall and Porta Caesarea with two octagonal towers and three passages; one for cart traffic and two for pedestrians on each side of the wider passage. Central passage was probably equipped with a movable grid, as indicated by grooves on side pylons. Porta Caesarea was constructed using large regular stones primarily for fortification purposes. After eastern and western expansion had occurred, the gate lost their primary purpose and became carrying construction of the aqueduct. According to Kähler reconstruction, the gate had two floors, of which the top one was very elaborately decorated with half columns, composite capitals, and window openings. Within the gate there was small courtyard for defence purposes.

==Thermae==
The [[thermae]] were typical buildings of Roman civilisation and indispensable part of Roman urban life. Although the city of Salona at the time had multiple baths, best preserved and largest one are those in the eastern part of the city called the Great Thermae, built in the second or beginning of third century A.D. This building is rectangular in shape with three symmetrically arranged apses in the north and one in the west. To the north there was an adjoining elongated spacious room, housing a semicircular pool, the piscina, filled with cold water, the [[frigidarium]]. To the left there were two dressing rooms, with benches for sitting and openings in the wall for clothes. The room to the west was also used as a massage room, the unctorium. The room ending with an apse served both as a lounge and an exercise room. To the right there were hot baths and sauna: [[caldarium]], [[tepidarium]] and [[sudatorium]].

==Bridge of Five Arches==
In the eastern suburb of Salona five arches spanned the western-most backwater of the Jadro river (the ancient Salon river). The bridge carried one extension of [[Decumanus Maximus]] which branched into two roads, one of which led north-east to the Porta Andetria gate, while the other one led across the bridge to Epetium, today's city of Stobreč.

==Amphitheatre==
At the westernmost point of Salona, in the Urbs occidentalis, in the second half of the second century A.D. under the influence of Flavian architectural style a monumental building was erected. It is one of the most recognizable buildings of Roman architecture. The remains of Roman amphitheatre indicate that gladiator fights were held in the city of Salona just as in any part of Roman empire, until the fifth century when they were finally banned. The building was ellipsoidal in shape, with three floors on the south side and one floor on the north side, which was conveniently laid down on a natural hillside. Despite its relatively small size (125 by 100 meters outer shell and 65 by 40 meters the arena), Salonitan amphitheatre could have been occupied by 15,000 up to 18,000 spectators. The auditorium was divided into three tiers, the lower two with seats and the upper one for standing. In Diocletian's time the top tier was covered with a porch. By means of poles attached to the outer shell of the building the whole arena could be covered with canvas, giving protection from the sun and rain. On the south side there was a state box for the Province governor and opposite it [[seat of honor|seats of honor]] for the city magistrates. In the centre of arena there was an opening which led into an underground corridor whose purpose was disposal of dead gladiators' bodies. On the south side of the amphitheatre, beneath the auditorium, there were two vaulted rooms, where gladiators worshipped Nemesis, the goddess of revenge and destiny. During Diocletian's persecutions of Christians, the amphitheatre was used as a site of executions.

Only parts of substructures of this monumental building, as well as some fragments of architectural decoration and stone sculpture have been preserved. The amphitheatre was most severely damaged during the wars against the Turks in the 17th century when Venetians had it demolished for strategic reasons.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
{{commons category}}
* {{Citation |publisher = J. Murray |publication-place = London |author = R. Lambert Playfair |author-link = Lambert Playfair |url = https://openlibrary.org/books/OL16538259M/Handbook_to_the_Mediterranean |title = Handbook to the Mediterranean |edition=3rd |publication-date = 1892 |chapterurl= https://archive.org/stream/handbooktomedit01firgoog#page/n41/mode/2up |chapter= Salona }}
* {{Citation |publisher = Sturgis &amp; Walton Company |publication-place = New York |title = Roman Cities in Italy and Dalmatia |url = https://openlibrary.org/books/OL7027058M/Roman_cities_in_Italy_and_Dalmatia. |author = Arthur L. Frothingham |publication-date = 1910 |chapterurl = https://archive.org/stream/romancitiesinita00frotuoft#page/266/mode/2up |chapter = Salona }}

== Literature ==
* ''Buovac, Marin Buovac Amphitheatres in the Republic of Croatia, 13th Annual Meeting of the European Association of Archaeologists, Sveučilište u Zadru, Zadar 2007.''
* [https://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=101834 Buovac, Marin: ''O sudbini kamena s rimskih amfiteatara na prostoru istočnojadranske obale'', Klesarstvo i graditeljstvo, Vol.XXII No.1-2, 2011., str. 53 - 69.]
* [http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=136639 Buovac, Marin: O natpisnoj građi rimskih amfteatara na prostoru istočnojadranske obale / On the inscriptions of Roman amphitheatres in the Eastern Adriatic seaboard, Vjesnik za arheologiju i povijest dalmatinsku, Vol. 105, No. 1, 2012.]
* [https://www.academia.edu/35711422/Marin_Buovac_Rimski_amfiteatri_na_tlu_isto%C4%8Dnog_Jadrana_i_zaobalja_R%C3%B6mische_Amphitheater_auf_dem_ostadriatischen_Gebiet Buovac, Marin: ''Rimski amfiteatri na tlu istočnog Jadrana i zaobalja / Römische Amphitheater auf dem ostadriatischen Gebiet und Hinterland'', Histria Antiqua, vol. 22, Pula, 2013., str. 129 - 156.]
* [https://www.academia.edu/8495563/The_destiny_significance_and_role_of_the_amphitheatre_of_Salona_in_Late_Antiquity_Middle_Ages_and_Modern_Times_O_sudbini_zna%C4%8Daju_i_ulozi_salonitanskog_amfiteatra_u_razdoblju_kasne_antike_srednjega_i_novoga_vijeka Buovac, Marin: ''O sudbini, značaju i ulozi salonitanskog amfiteatra u razdoblju kasne antike, srednjega i novoga vijeka / The destiny, significance and role of the amphitheatre of Salona in Late Antiquity, Middle Ages and Modern Times'', Zbornik radova &quot;Lucius&quot; - god. XII., sv. 18.-19., Zagreb 2013, str. 61 - 70.]
[[Category:Former populated places in the Balkans]]
[[Category:Greek colonies in Illyria]]
[[Category:Byzantine Dalmatia]]
[[Category:Tourist attractions in Croatia]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites in Croatia]]
[[Category:Roman towns and cities in Croatia]]</text>
      <sha1>bmhilfn9mqlw1npecygdc7qdd4oenwq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
