  <page>
    <title>Sandboarding</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>930074</id>
    <revision>
      <id>930027772</id>
      <parentid>930027760</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-09T19:30:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>911ChickenCop</username>
        <id>33166191</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/168.102.136.25|168.102.136.25]] ([[User talk:168.102.136.25|talk]]) to last revision by ClueBot NG ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Sandboarding in Dubai.jpg|right|thumb|Sandboarding in [[Dubai]], [[United Arab Emirates]]]]
[[Image:Sandboarding.jpg|thumb|right|A sandboarder does a jump on [[Fortaleza]] dunes in Brazil.]]
[[File:Sandboarding in maldives.jpg|thumb|right|A boy sandboarding in [[Fuvahmulah]], [[Maldives]]]]
[[Image:Ladybirdsandboarding.jpg|thumb|right|Woman sandboarding at [[Atlantis, Western Cape|Atlantis]] Dunes in South Africa.]]
[[File:Sandboarding in San Pedro de Atacama.jpg|thumb|Sandboarding in San Pedro de Atacama, Chile.]]
[[File:Sandboarding in Israel.jpg|thumb|Israel Sandboarding at DrorBamidbar]]
[[File:Sandboarding with DrorBamidbar.webm|thumb|Sandboarding with DrorBamidbar at the Negev Desert in Israel]]
'''Sandboarding''' is a [[boardsport]] and [[extreme sport]]{{cn|date=November 2018}} similar to [[snowboarding]] that involves riding across or down a [[sand dune]] while standing on a board, either with both feet strapped in or while standing loose, without bindings. Sandboarding can also be practised sitting down or lying on the belly or the back. It typically involves a [[sandboard]], although it is also possible to use [[Sledding|sleds]], [[Surfboard|surfboards]], a [[skateboard]] deck, or [[Snowboard|snowboards]].

Sandboarding has adherents throughout the world, but is most prevalent in desert areas or coastal areas with beach dunes. It is less popular than snowboarding, partly because it is very difficult to build a mechanised [[ski lift]] on a sand dune, meaning participants must walk or ride a [[dune buggy]] or [[all-terrain vehicle]] back to the top of the dune. On the other hand, dunes are normally available year-round as opposed to [[ski resorts]], which are seasonal.

==Equipment==
The sandboard base is much harder than a snowboard, and is built mostly out of [[formica (plastic)|formica]] or laminex with special base materials now being made for this sport. To glide in the sand, the board bottom is often waxed, usually with a [[Paraffin wax|paraffin]]-based sandboard wax, before a run. Afterwards, the bottom of the board may have a lightly sanded look to it, while 'Race Base' tends to polish smoother and glossier with use. Most terrain sandboards are composed of hardwood ply, while 'full-size' sandboards are a wood, fiber glass, and plastic composite. However, a snowboarding base will sometimes work on steeper dunes.

==Worldwide==
===Sandboarding in Israel===
Drorbamidbar has sandboarding in Israel at [[Negev Desert]] not far from [[Ashalim]] in the [[Ramat Negev]].

===Sandboarding in Australia===
[[Little Sahara (Kangaroo Island)|Little Sahara]] on [[Kangaroo Island]] in [[South Australia]] is a sand dune system roughly covering two square kilometres. The highest dune is approximately 70 metres above sea level.

Lucky Bay, about 30&amp;nbsp;km south of [[Kalbarri]], in Western Australia, is another sandboarding hotspot. Sandboarding Tours are offered in the area.

The Stockton dunes, 2.3 hours north from Sydney. Stockton Bight Sand Dunes system is up to one kilometre wide, 32 kilometres long, and covers an area of over 4,200 hectares. The massive sand dunes climb up to 40 metres high. Located only minutes from the centre of Nelson Bay, it is the largest sand dune system in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.portstephens.org.au/TheSandDunes.aspx |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2011-03-24 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110216080726/http://www.portstephens.org.au/TheSandDunes.aspx |archivedate=16 February 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sandboarding in Africa===
Sandboarding sites in [[Egypt]] include the Great Sand Sea near Siwa Oasis واحة سيوة in Egypt's Western Desert, the Qattaniya القطانية sand dunes (1.5 hr drive on/off-road from Cairo), El Safra الصفراء and Hadudah هدودة dunes midway between Dahab and St. Catherine in Sinai. 

[[Namibia]] features [[sand-skiing]], which is similar to sandboarding, performed with skis instead of a board. Most of the sand-skiing is performed in the [[Namib]] desert dunes around [[Swakopmund]] and [[Walvis Bay]]. With a special permit it is sometimes possible to sand-ski at the world's highest dunes in [[Sossusvlei]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.xtremespots.com/board-sports/sandboarding/swakopmund-erongo-district-namibia/|title = Xtreme Spots|date = |accessdate = 26 August 2015|website = Xtreme Spots|publisher = |last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Henrik May, a German living in Namibia for some 10 years, set a Guinness World Record in speed sand-skiing on 6 June 2010. He reached a speed of 92.12&amp;nbsp;km/h.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.ski-namibia.com/?id=1001 The World Record]&quot;, Ski Namibia, Retrieved 5 January 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

After some pioneers like Derek Bredenkamp who boarded Swakopmund around 1974, commercial operators in [[South Africa]] began offering sandboarding to tourists in 1994.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.downhilladventures.com/activities/full-half-day-adventures/sandboarding/&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000 the Sandboarding South Africa league was established. 
Between 2002 and 2004 the South African Sandboarding League held competitions on the Matterhorn Dune located between Swakopmund and Walvis bay. Competition events included dual slalom, boarder cross and big air events. In 2005 and 2006 Alter Action held sandboarding competitions at Matterhorn but the competitions no longer formed part of the South African Sandboarding League during those years. The league collapsed, then the sport was revived again in 2007 with weekly sandboarding sessions in and around Cape Town and Gauteng. 

===Sandboarding in the U.S.===
Sand Master Park, located in [[Florence, Oregon]] USA is a sandboard park with {{convert|40|acre|m2}} of private sculpted sand dunes and a full-time pro shop. Dune Riders International is the governing body for competitive sandboarding worldwide and sanctions three events each season at Sand Master Park.

[[Great Sand Dunes National Park and Preserve]] near [[Alamosa, Colorado]] has sandboarding on what it calls the tallest dunes in North America. &lt;ref&gt;https://www.nps.gov/grsa/index.htm. US National Park Service. Retrieved 05 January 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Sandboarding and skiing are permitted anywhere on the dunefield away from vegetated areas. &lt;ref&gt;https://www.nps.gov/grsa/planyourvisit/sandboardingsandsledding.htm. US National Park Service. Retrieved 05 January 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Sandboarding in South America===
[[Peru]] is known for having large sand dunes in [[Ica Province|Ica]], some reaching up to 2&amp;nbsp;km. Duna Grande in Ica is the largest sand dune in the world. The ''Copa Sandboarding Perú'' (Peru – Sandboarding Cup) has been held near Paracas every year since 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;copa&quot;&gt;[http://www.livinginperu.com/news/13616 Peru's top sandboarders compete tomorrow in Paracas], Living Peru. Sports. 26-11-2010. Retrieved 11-26-2010&lt;/ref&gt; There are also great dunes near the capital city (Lima) in Chilca.

In [[Chile]], sandboarding is practiced throughout the north of the country, including the Medanoso dunes in Copiapo (where the Dakar rally takes place), Puerto Viejo beach in Caldera, excellent dunes in Iquique, and some near Viña del Mar.

===Sandboarding in Central America===
[[Nicaragua]] is home to [[Cerro Negro]], the youngest volcano in Central America. Since it has steep slopes and volcanic sand, it is possible to sandboard down this active volcano.

===Sandboarding in Europe===
[[File:Sanboardinggreece.jpg|thumb|Sandboarding in Greece]]
A rather small sand mountain is the [[Monte Kaolino]] in [[Hirschau]], [[Germany]]. Being equipped with a lift to the 120m top it is also the host of the annual Sandboarding World Championships. 

Amothines is a small desert five kilometres from Katalakkos village in [[Limnos]], [[Greece]]. There are many sand dunes there, where people can practice sandboarding.

===Sandboarding in the United Kingdom===
[[File:Sand Dunes at Holywell Bay, November 2018.jpg|thumb|Sand dunes at Holywell, England]]
[[Wales]] is home to the village of [[Merthyr Mawr]] that is 2½ from the town of [[Bridgend]], the village is close to a beach and it is home to the &quot;Big Dipper&quot;, the second largest sand dune in [[Europe]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.countryliving.com/uk/wildlife/countryside/news/a2092/merthyr-mawrth-europes-second-largest-sand-dune-big-dipper/|title=A sleepy village in Wales is home to the second largest sand dune in Europe |accessdate=2019-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Holywell, Cornwall]] is also home to a beach with a complex of sand dunes; in the summer and during peak times, local shops that cater for beach goers also sell sandboards.

The [[Braunton Burrows]] sand dunes on the Devon coast, was the filming location for where Alex Bird became the first sandboarder to be towed by a car on British shores.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.menswearstyle.co.uk/2017/02/27/jeep-renegade-desert-hawk-sandboard-stunt/7582|title=JEEP RENEGADE DESERT HAWK SANDBOARDING STUNT |accessdate=2019-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[North East England|North East region]] of the [[United Kingdom]], there is a small beach at [[Seaton Sluice]] where people can sandboard. This is a good alternative to [[sledding]], as there is insufficient [[snow]] to support sledding there, even though the UK has a cold climate, with cold winters and cool summers.

==Events==
* Sandboarding World Championship – The SWC was held annually in Hirschau (until 2007), Germany at Monte Kaolino, currently also the site of Europe’s largest sand hill. Riders can board down dunes over {{convert|300|ft|m}} tall, riding into a water landing site at the base of the hill. It has a sand lift, the only one in the world. Events include slalom (akin to snowboarding's [[parallel giant slalom]]), freestyle (similar to [[freestyle snowboarding]]) and sandboard cross (cf. [[snowboard cross]]).
* Sand Master Jam – Annual sandboarding event that takes place in [[Florence, Oregon]] at Sand Master Park. This event occurs in late spring or early summer. The Sand Master Jam has been held since 1996.
* Pan-American Sandboarding Challenge – This event takes place in July in Aquiraz, Ceara, Brazil at Prainha’s Beach. It features amateurs and professionals who wish to compete in freestyle and jump events.
* Sand Sports Super Show – Annual outdoor event for all sand sports, including sandboarding. This three-day event takes place in September in [[Costa Mesa, California]] at the Orange County Fair and Expo Center.
* Sand Spirit - Annual event that takes place at [[Monte Kaolino]], [[Germany]].

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Sandboarding}}
* [http://www.sandboarding.org 2009 Sandboarding World Championships, Monte Kaolino, Germany]
* [http://www.gilimag.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=62:sandboardingfly-over-the-sand&amp;catid=48:tourism&amp;Itemid=55 Kareem Hossam...the flyer over the sand]

{{Extreme sports}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2011}}

[[Category:Sandboarding| ]]
[[Category:Racing]]
[[Category:Boardsports]]
[[Category:Sand]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Games and sports introduced in the 1970s]]</text>
      <sha1>e0gjqikikkejqiutu3c2ga01qo7mvyo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
