  <page>
    <title>Shujabad</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23023839</id>
    <revision>
      <id>926811411</id>
      <parentid>926805773</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-18T21:16:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MB</username>
        <id>26021349</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>convert units</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
| name                    = Shujabad
| official_name           =
| native_name             = {{Nastaliq|شُجاع آباد}}
| native_name_lang        = ur
| other_name              = Shujaabad
| settlement_type         = City
| image_skyline           =  
| imagesize               =  240px
| image_alt               = 
| image_caption           = 
| image_map               = 
| mapsize                 = 150 px
| map_alt                 = 
| map_caption             = 
| coordinates             = {{Coord|29|52|45|N|71|18|10|E|type:city_region:PK|display=inline,title}}
| pushpin_map             = Pakistan
| pushpin_label_position  = &lt;!-- left, right, top, bottom, none --&gt;
| pushpin_map_alt         = 
| pushpin_mapsize         = 
| pushpin_map_caption     =  
| subdivision_type        = [[Country]]
| subdivision_name        = {{flag|Pakistan}}
| subdivision_type1       = [[Subdivisions of Pakistan|Province]]
| subdivision_name1       = [[Punjab (Pakistan)]]
| population_total        = 
| population_as_of        = 1998
| population_est          = 
| pop_est_as_of           = 
| population_footnotes    = 
| area_total_km2          = 
| elevation_m             = 152
| elevation_m_min         = 
| elevation_m_max         = 
| population_density_km2  = 
| leader_title            = 
| leader_name             = 
| leader_title1           = 
| leader_name1            = 
| area_code               = 
| area_code_type          = [[List of dialling codes of Pakistan|Calling code]]
| timezone1               = [[Pakistan Standard Time|PST]]
| utc_offset1             = +5
| website                 = 
| footnotes               = 
}}

'''Shujaabad'''  ({{lang-ur|{{Nastaliq|'''شُجاع آباد'''}}}}) is a city and the capital of [[Shujabad Tehsil]] of [[Multan District]] in the [[Punjab (Pakistan)|Punjab]] province of [[Pakistan]]. It is located about {{cvt|45|km}} in south from [[Multan]]. [[Chenab River]] is situated in the west of city. Neighbouring settlements include [[Jalalpur Pirwala]], [[Multan]] and [[Lodhran]]. Its population is about 600,000.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.multan.gov.pk/dt_shujabad/index.php&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
Shujabad is a historical city. The name of Shujabad is on his ruler's name(Nawab Shuja Khan Sadozae سدوزئی) Nawab Shuja Khan, the second son of Nawab Zahid khan Sadozae (سدوزئی)twice remained the governor (Subedar) of [[Multan]] under Ahmad Shah Durrani's rule(also known as Ahmad Shah Abdali). He founded the Shujabad city in 1750 and built the fortification wall between 1767 and 1772. He left [[Multan]] and came to Shujabad in 1772 to save his life after he was badly defeated by bhangu Sikhs of [[Bhangi Misl]]. He hid himself in the fort to save himself from Lehna Singh bhangi the new ruler of Multan and died in 1775 Ad and was buried outside the city in a locality known as Basti Khairpur.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dawn.com/2008/01/07/nat39.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Old city of Shujabad was protected and made secured against the invaders with the huge and high wall all around the city by the Nawab Shuja Khan. Though the condition of the wall is deteriorating yet it is still in its original position. It is very much planned city at that time. The arrangement of old city is symmetrical. There are four Bazaars within the walled city i.e. Multani Bazaar, Rasheed Shah Bazaar, Rail Bazaar and Chotaka Bazaar on the names of its four respective doors (Railway Gate (open towards railway station), Multani Gate (open towards Multan), Rasheed Shah Gate (having the tomb of Rasheed Shah), Chutaka Gate (as Chutaka means crossing of four roads, four roads going on different directions from this gate). Chandni Chowk is the center of all Bazaars. In the ancient time all the gates were locked at night. Only little outlets were being used for in coming and out going. Shujabad is also very famous due to the presence of saints.

== Political representation ==
'''National Assembly Constituencies'''
* NA-158
* Candidates for Elections 2018.
Syed Yousuf Raza Gilani (PPP)
Syed Javed Ali Shah (PMLN)
Ibrahim Khan (PTI)
Allah Nawaz Wains (Pakistan Saraiki Party)
'''Provincial Assembly Constituencies '''
* PP-219
* PP-220
* PP-221
* PP-222

== Geography and climate ==
The city is located in southern [[Punjab (Pakistan)|Punjab]] at almost the exact center of Pakistan. The area around the city is flat, fertile land. The very hot weather of this region makes it ideal for agriculture. There are many canals providing water for cultivation in the region for the growth of crops such as cotton, wheat and mangoes. The average temperature, during summer, is about {{Convert|44|C}}, and in the winter about {{Convert|3|C}}. Dusty winds blow in the summer. Mango trees, palms / cotton / wheat / simplicity / near to nature lifestyle / is a very important quality.

== Demographics ==
The majority of residents speak [[Saraiki language|Saraiki]], [[Haryanvi]], [[Mewati]], [[Punjabi language|Punjabi]] and [[Urdu]].

== Economy ==
[[File:Govt_High_School_Shujabad.jpg|right|250px|thumb|Govt High School Shujabad]]
Shujabad is an agricultural city due to its hot weather, flat land and irrigation system. The hot weather in the region make it ideal for the growth of crops like cotton, wheat, dates and mangoes. There is one civil hospital and other private hospitals in city. The city has a Court, Police Station, Rescue (1122) and Fire Brigade office.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*https://www.facebook.com/National-Press-Club-Shujabad-1107368982734921/

{{Neighbourhoods of Multan}}
[[Category:Populated places in Multan District]]
[[Category:1750 establishments in India]]
[[Category:Tehsils of Punjab, Pakistan]]</text>
      <sha1>juxzia1clldb93i9ijdsj2vd4uonnij</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
