  <page>
    <title>Siena</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27856145</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937579739</id>
      <parentid>932493760</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-25T22:52:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RL0919</username>
        <id>327763</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Removing link(s): [[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/List of English exonyms for Italian toponyms]] closed as delete ([[WP:XFDC|XFDcloser]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Distinguish|sienna}}
{{other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2019}}
{{Use British English|date=June 2013}}
{{Infobox Italian comune
| name                = Siena
| official_name       = Comune di Siena
| native_name         =
| image_skyline       = PiazzadelCampoSiena.jpg
| imagesize           =
| image_alt           =
| image_caption       = View of Piazza del Campo (Campo Square), the Mangia Tower ([[Torre del Mangia]]) and [[Santa Maria in Provenzano, Siena|Santa Maria in Provenzano Church]]
| image_shield        = Siena-Stemma.png
| shield_alt          =
| image_map           = Map - IT - Siena - Siena.svg
| map_alt             =
| map_caption         =
| pushpin_label_position =
| pushpin_map         = Italy#Tuscany#Europe
| pushpin_map_alt     =
| coordinates         = {{coord|43|19|07|N|11|19|50|E|type:region:IT_type:city (53893)|display=inline,title}}
| coordinates_footnotes =
| region              = [[Tuscany]]
| province            = [[province of Siena|Siena]] (SI)
| frazioni            = Costalpino, Isola d'Arbia, Taverne d'Arbia, San Miniato, Vignano, Ruffolo
| mayor_party         = 
| mayor               = [[Luigi De Mossi]]
| area_footnotes      =
| area_total_km2      = 118
| population_footnotes =
| population_total    = 53901
| population_as_of    = 31 December 2017&lt;ref&gt;Data from [[National Institute of Statistics (Italy)|Istat]]&lt;/ref&gt;
| pop_density_footnotes =
| population_demonym  = Senese
| elevation_footnotes =
| elevation_m         = 322
| twin1               =
| twin1_country       =
| saint               = [[Ansanus|St. Ansanus]]/&lt;br&gt;[[Ambrose of Siena]]
| day                 = 1 December/&lt;br&gt;8 October
| postal_code         = 53100, 53010
| area_code           = 0577
| website             = {{Official website|http://www.comune.siena.it/}}
| footnotes           = {{Infobox UNESCO World Heritage Site
| child         = yes
| official_name =
| criteria      = {{UNESCO WHS type|(i)(ii)(iv)}}(i)(ii)(iv)
| ID            = 717
| year          = 1995
| area          = {{convert|170|ha|acre|abbr=on}}
| buffer_zone   = {{convert|9907|ha|acre|abbr=on}}
}}
}}
[[File:02 Sienne vue de San Clemente.jpg|thumb]]
[[File:Siena5.jpg|thumb]]
'''Siena''' ({{IPAc-en|s|i|ˈ|ɛ|n|ə}} {{respell|see|EN|ə}}, {{IPA-it|ˈsjɛːna|lang|It-Siena.ogg}}; in English sometimes spelled '''Sienna'''; {{lang-lat|Sena Iulia}}) is a [[city]] in [[Tuscany]], Italy. It is the capital of the [[province of Siena]].

The historic centre of Siena has been declared by [[UNESCO]] a [[World Heritage Site]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://whc.unesco.org/en/list/717 |title=Historic Centre of Siena  |publisher=UNESCO World Heritage Centre |date=3 December 2009 |accessdate=19 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is one of the nation's most visited tourist attractions, with over 163,000 international arrivals in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.euromonitor.com/_Euromonitor_Internationals_Top_City_Destinations_Ranking |title=Euromonitor Internationals Top City Destinations Ranking &gt; Euromonitor archive |publisher=Euromonitor.com |date=12 December 2008 |accessdate=9 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Siena is famous for its [[cuisine]], [[art]], [[museums]], medieval cityscape and the [[Palio di Siena|Palio]], a horse race held twice a year.

==History==
[[File:Capitoline Wolf at Siena Duomo.jpg|thumbnail|Capitoline Wolf at [[Siena Duomo]]. According to a legend Siena was founded by [[Senius and Aschius]], two sons of Remus. When they fled [[Rome]], they took the statue of the She-wolf to Siena, which became a symbol of the town.]]
{{See also|Republic of Siena|Timeline of Siena}}
Siena, like other [[Tuscany|Tuscan]] hill towns, was first settled in the time of the [[Etruscan civilization|Etruscans]] (c. 900–400&amp;nbsp;BC) when it was inhabited by a tribe called the Saina. The Etruscans were a tribe of advanced people who changed the face of central Italy through their use of [[irrigation]] to reclaim previously unfarmable land, and their custom of building their settlements in well-defended [[hill fort]]s. A [[Roman Empire|Roman]] town called ''Saena Julia'' was founded at the site in the time of the Emperor [[Augustus]]. Some [[archaeologists]] assert that Siena was controlled for a period by a [[Gaul]]ish tribe called the [[Senones]]. {{citation needed|date=May 2017}}

According to local legend, Siena was founded by [[Senius and Aschius]], two sons of [[Remus]] and thus nephews of [[Romulus]], after whom Rome was named. Supposedly after their father's murder by Romulus, they fled Rome, taking with them the statue of the she-wolf suckling the infants ([[Capitoline Wolf]]), thus appropriating that symbol for the town. {{Citation needed|date=May 2017}} Additionally they rode white and black horses, giving rise to the ''Balzana'', or coat of arms of Siena with a white band atop a dark band. Some claim the name Siena derives from Senius. Other etymologies derive the name from the Etruscan family name ''Saina'', the Roman family name ''Saenii'', or the [[Latin]] word ''senex'' &quot;old&quot; or its derived form ''seneo'' &quot;to be old&quot;.

Siena did not prosper under Roman rule. It was not sited near any major roads and lacked opportunities for trade. Its insular status meant that Christianity did not penetrate until the 4th century AD, and it was not until the [[Lombards]] invaded Siena and the surrounding territory that it knew prosperity. {{Citation needed|date=May 2017}} After the Lombard occupation, the old [[Roman road]]s of [[Via Aurelia]] and the [[Via Cassia]] passed through areas exposed to [[Byzantine Raids in Italy|Byzantine raids]], so the Lombards rerouted much of their trade between the Lombards' northern possessions and Rome along a more secure road through Siena. Siena prospered as a trading post, and the constant streams of [[pilgrim]]s passing to and from Rome provided a valuable source of income in the centuries to come. {{Citation needed|date=May 2017}}

The oldest [[aristocracy (class)|aristocratic]] families in Siena date their line to the Lombards' surrender in 774 to [[Charlemagne]]. At this point, the city was inundated with a swarm of [[Franks|Frankish]] overseers who married into the existing Sienese nobility and left a legacy that can be seen in the abbeys they founded throughout Sienese territory. {{Citation needed|date=May 2017}} [[Feudal]] power waned, however, and by the death of [[Matilda of Tuscany|Countess Matilda]] in 1115 the border territory of the [[March of Tuscany]] which had been under the control of her family, the Canossa, broke up into several autonomous regions. This ultimately resulted in the creation of the [[Republic of Siena]].

The Republic existed for over four hundred years, from the 12th century until the year 1555. During the golden age of Siena before the [[Black Death]] in 1348, the city was home to 50,000 people.&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Art as Politics in Late Medieval and Renaissance Siena|author1=Smith, T.B.|author2=Steinhoff, J.B.|date=2012|publisher=Ashgate Publishing Company|isbn=9781409400660|url=https://books.google.dk/books?id=gKyxJL2f88gC&amp;pg=PA77|page=77|accessdate=14 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Italian War of 1551–1559|Italian War of 1551–59]], the republic was defeated by the rival [[Duchy of Florence]] in alliance with the Spanish crown. After 18 months of resistance, Siena surrendered to [[Spain]] on 17 April 1555, marking the end of the republic.

The new [[Kingdom of Spain|Spanish]] [[Philip II of Spain|King Felipe II]], owing huge sums to the [[Medici]], ceded it (apart from a series of coastal fortress annexed to the [[State of Presidi]]) to the [[Grand Duchy of Tuscany]], to which it belonged until the unification of Italy in the 19th century.

A Republican government of 700 Sienese families in [[Montalcino]] resisted until 1559. {{Citation needed|date=May 2017}}

==Geography==
Siena is located in the central part of [[Tuscany]], in the middle of a vast hilly landscape between the [[Arbia]] river valley (south), the [[Merse (river)|Merse]] valley (south-west), the Elsa valley (north), the [[Chianti]] hills (north-east), the Montagnola Senese (west) and the [[Crete Senesi]] (south-east). The city lies at 322&amp;nbsp;m above sea level.

===Climate===
Siena has a typical inland Mediterranean climate. Average rainfall is {{convert|750|mm|1|abbr=on}}, with the maximum in November and the minimum in July. July is the hottest month, with an average temperature of {{convert|22.2|C|1|abbr=on}}, and January the coldest.&lt;ref name=enea/&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:80%;&quot;&gt;
{{Weather box
|location= [[University of Siena]] &lt;small&gt;(altitude: 348&amp;nbsp;m sl)&lt;/small&gt;
|metric first= yes
|single line= yes
|Jan high C= 8.0
|Feb high C= 9.1
|Mar high C= 11.9
|Apr high C= 16.0
|May high C= 20.4
|Jun high C= 24.6
|Jul high C= 27.9
|Aug high C= 27.4
|Sep high C= 23.4
|Oct high C= 18.0
|Nov high C= 12.5
|Dec high C= 9.0
|year high C= 17.4
|Jan mean C= 5.0
|Feb mean C= 5.7
|Mar mean C= 8.1
|Apr mean C= 11.7
|May mean C= 15.5
|Jun mean C= 19.4
|Jul mean C= 22.2
|Aug mean C= 22.0
|Sep mean C= 18.7
|Oct mean C= 14.0
|Nov mean C= 9.5
|Dec mean C= 6.3
|year mean C= 13.2
|Jan low C= 2.0
|Feb low C= 2.3
|Mar low C= 4.2
|Apr low C= 7.3
|May low C= 10.5
|Jun low C= 14.1
|Jul low C= 16.6
|Aug low C= 16.6
|Sep low C= 14.1
|Oct low C= 10.0
|Nov low C= 6.6
|Dec low C= 3.5
|year low C= 9.0
|Jan precipitation mm= 65
|Feb precipitation mm= 64
|Mar precipitation mm= 61
|Apr precipitation mm= 67
|May precipitation mm= 55
|Jun precipitation mm= 58
|Jul precipitation mm= 31
|Aug precipitation mm= 51
|Sep precipitation mm= 56
|Oct precipitation mm= 93
|Nov precipitation mm= 78
|Dec precipitation mm= 71
|year precipitation mm= 750
|Jan precipitation days= 8
|Feb precipitation days= 11
|Mar precipitation days= 8
|Apr precipitation days= 10
|May precipitation days= 6
|Jun precipitation days= 7
|Jul precipitation days= 4
|Aug precipitation days= 4
|Sep precipitation days= 5
|Oct precipitation days= 8
|Nov precipitation days= 8
|Dec precipitation days= 8
|year precipitation days= 87
|unit precipitation days = 1&amp;nbsp;mm
|source 1= Archivio Climatico ENEA&lt;ref name=enea&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://clisun.casaccia.enea.it/Profili/tabelle/350%20%5BSiena%5D%20capoluogo.Txt
 |title=Climate Data from the University of Siena's Meteorological Station (1961–1990) – Achivio Climatico ENEA
 |accessdate=15 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|date=September 2015}}
&lt;/div&gt;

==Government==
{{See also|List of mayors of Siena}}

==Main sights==
[[File:Duomo di Siena - panoramio.jpg|thumb|[[Siena Cathedral]]]]
[[File:Siena Cathedral.jpg|thumb|Interior of the Siena Cathedral.]]
[[File:Siena Palazzo Pubblico 20030813-349.jpg|thumb|Façade of the [[Palazzo Pubblico]] (town hall) during the [[Palio di Siena|Palio]] days.]]
[[File:The oldest surviving bank in the world. Siena, Italy. (23117920029).jpg|thumb|Piazza Salimbeni.]]
[[File:Strsiena.JPG|thumb|Streets of old Siena.]]
[[File:San Domenico church in Siena, Italy.jpg|thumb|[[Basilica of San Domenico (Siena)|Basilica of San Domenico]].]]
[[File:201105 Toscane Sienne.jpg|thumb|View from the Campanile del Mangia.]]
The '''[[Siena Cathedral]]''' (''[[Duomo]]''), begun in the 12th century, is a masterpiece of Italian [[Romanesque architecture|Romanesque]]–[[Gothic architecture]]. Its main façade was completed in 1380 with a nave oriented northeast-southwest. A proposed expansion of the eastern transept would have transformed the church into an ambitiously massive basilica, the largest then in the world, with an east-west nave. However, the scarcity of funds, in part due to war and the Black Death, truncated the project. Two walls of this expanded eastern transept remain; through an internal staircase, visitors can climb for a grand view of the city.

The [[Siena Cathedral Pulpit]] is an octagonal 13th-century masterpiece sculpted by [[Nicola Pisano]] with lion pedestals and biblical bas-relief panels. The inlaid marble mosaic floor of the cathedral, designed and labored on by many artists, is among the most elaborate in Italy. The Sacristy and Piccolomini library have well preserved [[Renaissance art|Renaissance]] frescos by [[Domenico Ghirlandaio|Ghirlandaio]] and [[Pinturicchio]] respectively. Other sculptors active in the church and in the subterranean [[Battistero di San Giovanni (Siena)|baptistry]] are [[Donatello]], [[Lorenzo Ghiberti]], [[Jacopo della Quercia]] and others. The Museo dell'Opera del Duomo contains Duccio's famous ''[[Maestà (Duccio)|Maestà]]'' (1308–11) and various other works by Sienese masters. More Sienese paintings are to be found in the Pinacoteca, e.g. 13th-century works by [[Dietisalvi di Speme]].

The '''[[Piazza del Campo]]''', the shell-shaped town square, unfurls before the [[Palazzo Pubblico]] with its tall [[Torre del Mangia]]. This is part of the site for the ''Palio'' horse race. The Palazzo Pubblico, itself a great work of architecture, houses yet another important art museum. Included within the museum is [[Ambrogio Lorenzetti]]'s frescoes depicting the ''Allegory and Effects of Good and Bad Government'' and also some of the finest frescoes of [[Simone Martini]] and [[Pietro Lorenzetti]].

The '''[[Palazzo Salimbeni]]''', located in a piazza of the same name, was the original headquarters and remains in possession of the [[Monte dei Paschi di Siena]], one of the oldest banks in continuous existence in Europe.

Housed in the notable [[gothic architecture|Gothic]] [[Palazzo Chigi-Saracini]] on Via di Città is the [[Accademia Musicale Chigiana]], Siena's [[music school|conservatory of music]].

Other churches in the city include:
* [[Basilica dell'Osservanza]]
* [[Santa Maria dei Servi, Siena|Santa Maria dei Servi]]
* [[San Domenico, Siena|San Domenico]]
* [[San Francesco, Siena|San Francesco]]
* [[Santo Spirito, Siena|Santo Spirito]]
* [[San Martino, Siena|San Martino]]
* Sanctuary of ''Santa Caterina'', incorporating the old house of [[St. Catherine of Siena]]. It houses the miraculous ''Crucifix'' (late 12th century) from which the saint received her [[stigmata]], and a 15th-century statue of St. Catherine.

The historic [[Siena synagogue]] is also preserved and open to visitors.

The city's gardens include the [[Orto Botanico dell'Università di Siena]], a [[botanical garden]] maintained by the [[University of Siena]].

The [[Fortezza Medicea (Siena)|Medicean Fortress]] houses the [[Enoteca|Enoteca Italiana]] and the Siena Jazz School, with courses and concerts throughout the year, and a festival during the International Siena Jazz Masterclasses.

In the neighbourhood are numerous patrician villas, some of which are attributed to [[Baldassarre Peruzzi]]:
* [[Villa Chigi, Siena|Villa Chigi]]
* [[Castle of Belcaro, Siena|Castle of Belcaro]]
* [[Villa Celsa, Siena|Villa Celsa]]
* [[Villa Cetinale, Siena|Villa Cetinale]]
* [[Villa Volte Alte, Siena|Villa Volte Alte]]

{{Wide image|Siena Panorama from Torre del Mangia 01.jpg|1200|A view of Siena from the Torre del Mangia}}

==Culture==

===Contrade===
{{Main|Contrade di Siena}}
Siena retains a ward-centric culture from medieval times. Each ward (''contrada'') is represented by an animal or mascot, and has its own boundary and distinct identity. Ward rivalries are most rampant during the annual [[horse race]] (Palio) in the Piazza del Campo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Huppert|first= George|title=After the Black Death: A Social History of Early Modern Europe|publisher=[[Indiana University Press]]|year= 1998|page= 36|edition=Second}}&lt;/ref&gt;There are 17 wards (contrada): Aquila, Bruco, Chiocciola, Civetta, Drago, Giraffa, Istrice, Leocorno, Lupa, Nicchio, Oca, Onda, Pantera, Selva, Tartuca, Torre, Valdimontone.

===The Palio===
{{Main|Palio di Siena}}
The [[Palio di Siena]] is a traditional medieval [[horse race]] run around the Piazza del Campo twice each year, on 2 July and 16 August. The event is attended by large crowds, and is widely televised. 10 randomly selected from Seventeen [[Contrade of Siena|Contrade]] (which are city neighbourhoods originally formed as [[battalion]]s for the city's defence) vie for the trophy: a painted banner, or ''[[:wiktionary:palio|Palio]]'' bearing an image of the [[Blessed Virgin Mary]].

===Art===
[[File:Duccio.The-Madonna-and-Child-with-Saints-149.jpg|thumb|''Madonna and Child with saints polyptych'' by [[Duccio]] (1311–18).]]
[[File:Institution-of-the-eucharist--Sassetta--Siena Pinacoteca.jpg|thumb|[[Sassetta]], ''Institution of the Eucharist'' (1430–32), Pinacoteca di Siena.]]

Over the centuries, Siena has had a rich tradition of arts and artists. The list of artists from the [[Sienese School]] include [[Duccio]] and his student [[Simone Martini]], [[Pietro Lorenzetti]] and [[Martino di Bartolomeo]]. A number of well-known works of [[Renaissance]] and [[High Renaissance]] art still remain in galleries or churches in Siena.

The Church of '' San Domenico''   contains art by [[Guido da Siena]], dating to the mid-13th century. Duccio's [[Maestà (Duccio)|''Maestà'']], which was commissioned by the City of Siena in 1308, was instrumental in leading Italian painting away from the hieratic representations of [[Byzantine art]] and directing it towards more direct presentations of reality. And his [[Madonna and Child with saints polyptych (Duccio)|''Madonna and Child with Saints'' polyptych]], painted between 1311 and 1318, remains at the city's [[Pinacoteca Nazionale (Siena)|''Pinacoteca Nazionale'']].

The Pinacoteca also includes several works by [[Domenico Beccafumi]], as well as art by [[Lorenzo Lotto]], [[Domenico di Bartolo]] and [[Fra Bartolomeo]].

==Economy==
The main activities are tourism, services, agriculture, handicrafts and light industry.

===Agriculture===
Agriculture constitutes Siena's primary industry. {{As of|2009}}, Siena's agricultural workforce comprises 919 companies with a total area of {{convert|10.755|km2|mi2}} for a UAA (usable agricultural area) of {{convert|6.954|km2|mi2}} or about 1/30 of the total municipal area (data [[National Institute of Statistics (Italy)|ISTAT]] for the 2000 Agriculture Census ''V'').

===Industry and manufacturing===
The industrial sector of the Sienese economy is not very developed. However, the area has seen recent growth in important core manufacturing enterprises.

The [[confectionery]] industry is one of the most important of the traditional sectors of the secondary industry, because of the many local specialties. Among the best known are [[Panforte]], a precursor to modern fruitcake, Ricciarelli biscuits, made out of almond paste, and the well-known [[gingerbread]], and the horses. Also renowned is Noto, a sweet made out of honey, almonds and pepper. The area known for making these delicacies ranges between Tuscany and [[Umbria]]. Other seasonal specialties are the chestnut and the ''pan de 'Santi'' (or ''Pan co' Santi'') traditionally prepared in the weeks preceding the Festival of [[Saints]], 1 November.
All are marketed both industrial and artisan bakeries in different cities.

The area has also seen a growth in [[biotechnology]]. The Centenary Institute Sieroterapico Achille Sclavo used to be Swiss-owned, operating under the company name, [[Novartis]] Vaccines. Novartis developed and produced vaccines and employed about a thousand people. In 2015, the research plant in Siena became part of [[Glaxo Smith Kline]], as part of a deal between [[Novartis]] and this firm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.corriere.it/economia/15_gennaio_28/novartis-stabilimenti-siena-fcbee832-a6d3-11e4-93fc-9b9679dd4aa0.shtml?refresh_ce-cp |title=Novartis, gli stabilimenti di Siena passano a Glaxo entro marzo. E attacca il governo sulla maxi-multa|publisher=Corriere|date=28 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2017}}

===Service industry, financial and light commerce===
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2017}}
In this area, the most important financial activities are those related to the bank [[Monte dei Paschi di Siena]], the oldest bank still in existence, headquartered in Siena, which has been operating continuously since 1472.

There are also important appearances of the university and the hospital, which employ thousands of people and serves a catchment area much wider than the already large territory [[Province of Siena|province]]. In the territory there is a dense network of micro-enterprises (less than 10,000) active in trade and tourism.

In the last ten years {{which|date=May 2017}}, Siena has been completely wired with [[fibre optic]] cable. This distinction makes Siena the first city in Italy to complete Telecom's ''Socrates Project (Progetto Socrate)''. As a result, the town can claim that almost every house is wired for cable. The wiring, built by private companies in partnership with the city, helped to create a civic public station (Channel Civic Sienese) cable that transmits information and local news and gives access to [[Internet]] [[broadband]]. In 2007, however, the station was privatised, separating the TV from the Internet. The wiring is currently extending to major centres of the province through another company set up ad hoc (earth cable).

==Sports==
Siena has enjoyed a long tradition in sports. [[Basketball]] and [[football (soccer)|football]] are perhaps the most popular in Siena, but other sports such as [[rugby union|rugby]] and [[Athletics (sport)|athletics]] are also practised.

===Professional sports===
[[File:Siena artemio franchi.jpg|thumb|[[Stadio Artemio Franchi – Montepaschi Arena]]]]
[[A.C. Siena|Associazione Calcio Siena]] ([[football (soccer)|football]]) was founded in 1904 and fully established in 1908. It was first promoted to Italy's top league, [[Serie A]], for the 2003–04 season and stayed in this serie for 9 seasons. After the club's bankruptcy in 2014, a new club named [[S.S. Robur Siena|Società Sportiva Robur Siena]] took its place and had to restart from [[Serie D]]. Currently it is in [[Lega Pro]] league. The club hosts its games at the [[Stadio Artemio Franchi (Siena)|Stadio Artemio Franchi]].

The premier society of men's basketball in Siena was called [[Mens Sana Basket]] (also referred to by its [[Monte dei Paschi di Siena|sponsored]] name of ''Montepaschi Siena''). It is also the oldest sports society in Siena. Mens Sana Basket participated in the highest level of play in Italy, [[Lega Basket Serie A]], and it has won the national championship eight times, with a streak of seven (2004 and 2007–13). The team host their home games at [[Palasport Mens Sana|PalaEstra]] indoor arena. Like the local football team, the club went through financial issues in 2014, and its place was taken by the new club [[Mens Sana 1871 Basket|Mens Sana 1871]], currently in the [[Serie A2 Basket|Serie A2]] league. The city co-hosted the [[EuroBasket 1979]].

[[File:Strade Bianche 2014 (13504915215).jpg|thumb|right|The [[Strade Bianche]] cycling race starts and finishes in Siena]]
Siena hosts the start and finish of the [[Strade Bianche]], a professional [[Road bicycle racing|cycling race]] famous for its historic white gravel roads, called ''strade bianche'' or ''sterrati'' in Italian.&lt;ref name=&quot;CN 2016&quot; &gt;{{cite web|title=Siena start for Strade Bianche in 2016|url=http://www.cyclingnews.com/news/siena-start-for-strade-bianche-in-2016/|website=[[Cycling News]]|accessdate=6 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; More than {{convert|50|km|0|abbr=off}} of the race is run over dirt roads, usually country lanes and farm tracks twisting through the hills and vineyards of the Chianti region. The finish is on the [[Piazza del Campo]], after a steep and narrow climb on the roughly-paved Via Santa Caterina leading into the center of the medieval city.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Brown|first1=Gregor|title=Preview: Strade Bianche promises to be a strongman's race|url=http://velonews.competitor.com/2015/03/news/preview-strade-bianche-promises-strongmans-race_362232|website=Velo News|accessdate=29 November 2015|date=6 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015 the [[volleyball]] team [[Emma Villas]], based in [[Chiusi]] (a small town in the [[Province of Siena|Siena Province]]) was promoted in Serie A2 and decided to move to Siena, aiming at a wider audience, hosting its games at [[Palasport Mens Sana|PalaEstra]].

===Amateur sports===

Siena is home to several amateur basketball teams: these include the Associazione Sportiva Costone Basket and Virtus Siena.

There exist several female university sports teams organised under the CUS (Centro Universitario Sportivo). These include such sports as fencing, [[volleyball]] and rugby, and a basketball team composed exclusively by students of the University of Siena.

==Transport==
The nearest international airports to Siena are [[Peretola Airport]] in [[Florence]] and [[Galileo Galilei International Airport]] in [[Pisa]]. There are two to three buses daily (Sena line) between Siena and [[Bologna Airport]] as well.

Siena can be reached by train from both Pisa and Florence, changing at [[Empoli]]. [[Siena railway station]] is located at the bottom of a long hill outside the city walls. A series of escalators connects the train station with the old city on top of hill.

Buses leave from Piazza Gramsci, located within the city walls. Buses are available directly to and from Florence, a one-hour trip, as well as from [[Rome]] (three hours), [[Milan]] (four and a half hours), and from various other towns in Tuscany and beyond.

===Road===
By road, Siena is linked to [[Florence]] by a &quot;superstrada&quot; (the ''Raccordo Autostradale RA03 – Siena-Firenze''), a form of toll free [[autostrada]]. The superstrada to Florence is indicated on some road signs with the letters SI-FI, referring to [[Provinces of Italy|province abbreviations]]. A continuation of the same four lane road to the south east
will facilitate the drive towards [[Perugia]] and to Rome by the [[Autostrada A1 (Italy)|A1 highway]].

Almost no automobile traffic is permitted within the city centre. Several large car parks are located immediately outside the city walls. The &quot;La Fortezza&quot; and &quot;Il Campo&quot; car parks are closest to the centre; free parking areas are further out (near Porta Romana). Commercial traffic is permitted within the city only during morning hours.

==Twin towns==
{{See also|List of twin towns and sister cities in Italy}}
Siena is [[Twin towns and sister cities|twinned]] with:
* {{flagicon|FRA}} [[Avignon]], France&lt;ref name=&quot;Avignon jumelages&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.avignon.fr/fr/pratique/jumelage/ville.php|title=Jumelages et Relations Internationales – Avignon|accessdate=13 July 2013|work=Avignon.fr|language=French|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130716104225/http://www.avignon.fr/fr/pratique/jumelage/ville.php|archivedate=16 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Avignon Ministère&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cncd.fr/frontoffice/bdd-recherche-resultat.asp?searchField=avignon&amp;x=70&amp;y=21|title=Atlas français de la coopération décentralisée et des autres actions extérieures|accessdate=13 July 2013|work=Ministère des affaires étrangères|language=French|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130226021826/http://www.cncd.fr/frontoffice/bdd-recherche-resultat.asp?searchField=avignon&amp;x=70&amp;y=21|archivedate=26 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|USA}} [[Concord, North Carolina]], US, since 2016
* {{flagicon|GER}} [[Weimar]], Germany, since 1994
* {{flagicon|GER}} [[Wetzlar]], Germany, since 1987

== Image gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Siena Palazzo-Pubblico-Duomo-JBU01.jpg|Siena, Campanile Palazzo Pubblico &amp; Duomo
File:Siena Palazzo-Pubblico-Campanile-JBU02.jpg|Siena, Campanile, Torre del Mangia (Palazzo Pubblico)
File:Siena Duomo JBU03.jpg|Siena, Duomo
File:Interior of the dome, Duomo, Siena, Italy.jpg|The interior of the dome in the Siena cathedral
File:Interior of the dome, Siena Cathedral, Italy.jpg|Interior of the dome at the duomo, Siena
File:Siena panorama.jpg|Panorama of Siena
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
{{See also|Timeline of Siena#Bibliography|l1=Bibliography of the history of Siena}}
* ''A Medieval Italian Commune: Siena under the Nine, 1287–1355''  by Professor [[William M. Bowsky]] (1982)
* McIntyre, Anthony Osler. ''Medieval Tuscany and Umbria'' (1992) {{ISBN|0-670-83525-0}}
* {{Cite book|last=Nevola|first=Fabrizio   |title=Siena: Constructing the Renaissance city|url=https://books.google.com/?id=U5v2KrFA32YC|accessdate=1 March 2010|edition=second|year=2007|publisher=[[Yale University Press]]|isbn=978-0-300-12678-5|ref=Nevola69}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links}}
* {{Wikivoyage-inline}}

{{Siena landmarks}}
{{Province of Siena}}
{{World Heritage Sites in Italy}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Siena| ]]
[[Category:Populated places established in the 1st millennium BC]]
[[Category:Roman sites of Tuscany]]
[[Category:World Heritage Sites in Italy]]
[[Category:1st-millennium BC establishments]]
[[Category:University towns in Italy]]</text>
      <sha1>e0aa0e8qu4awcs1m7k87f7uyxckkohy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
