  <page>
    <title>Sumo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>51814</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936960733</id>
      <parentid>936577642</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-22T02:24:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Artanisen</username>
        <id>1099904</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Edo period (1603–1867) */ increased thumbnail size to 300px</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Sumo (disambiguation)}}
{{More citations needed|date=March 2014}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2011}}
{{infobox martial art
| logo         =
| logocaption  =
| logosize     =
| image        = Asashoryu fight Jan08.JPG
| imagecaption = A sumo match (''tori-kumi'') between ''yokozuna'' [[Asashōryū Akinori|Asashōryū]] (left) and ''komusubi'' [[Kotoshōgiku Kazuhiro|Kotoshōgiku]] in January 2008.
| imagesize    = 300px
| name         = Sumo wrestling (相撲)
| aka          =
| focus        = [[Grappling]]
| hardness = Full contact
| country      = [[Japan]]
| creator      =
| parenthood   =
| famous_pract =
| olympic      = No, but [[Association of IOC Recognised International Sports Federations|recognized]] by the [[International Olympic Committee|IOC]]
| website      = {{url|http://www.sumo.or.jp/en/index}}
}}
{{Infobox sport
| name       = Sumo
| image      = 
| imagesize  = 220px
| caption    = 
| union      = International Sumo Federation (Amateur) / Japan Sumo Association (Professional)
| first      = Japan, mid-16th century ([[dohyō]])
| firstlabel =
| country/region = 
| registered =
| clubs      =
| contact    = Yes
| team       = No
| mgender    = Yes (Amateur) No (Professional)
| category   = Grappling sport
| equipment  =
| venue      =
| obsolete   =
| olympic    = No
| paralympic =
| IWGA       = [[2001 World Games|2001]] (invitational); [[2005 World Games|2005]]{{snds}}[[2017 World Games|2017]]
}}
{{infobox Chinese
|pic=Sumo (Chinese characters).svg
|piccap=&quot;Sumo&quot; in ''[[kanji]]''
|picupright=0.4
|kanji=相撲
|romaji=sumō
}}

{{Nihongo|'''Sumo'''|相撲|sumō|{{IPA-ja|sɯmoː}}, lit. &quot;striking one another&quot;}} is a form of competitive full-contact [[wrestling]] where a ''[[rikishi]]'' (wrestler) attempts to force his opponent out of a circular ring (''[[dohyō]]'') or into touching the ground with any body part other than the soles of his feet (usually by throwing, shoving or pushing him down).

The sport originated in Japan, the only country where it is practiced professionally. It is considered a ''[[gendai budō]]'', which refers to modern [[Japanese martial art]], but the sport has a history spanning many centuries. Many ancient traditions have been preserved in sumo, and even today the sport includes many ritual elements, such as the use of salt purification, from [[Shinto]].

Life as a wrestler is highly regimented, with rules regulated by the [[Japan Sumo Association]]. Most sumo wrestlers are required to live in communal sumo training stables, known in Japanese as ''[[Heya (sumo)|heya]]'', where all aspects of their daily lives—from meals to their manner of dress—are dictated by strict tradition.

From 2008 to 2017, a number of high-profile [[Controversies in professional sumo|controversies and scandals]] rocked the sumo world, with an associated effect on its reputation and ticket sales. These have also affected the sport's ability to attract recruits.&lt;ref name=&quot;Decline in sumo&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Decline in apprentices threatens future of national sport |newspaper=Asahi Shimbun |url=http://ajw.asahi.com/article/sports/sumo/AJ201209070047 |access-date=June 23, 2013 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130628045756/http://ajw.asahi.com/article/sports/sumo/AJ201209070047 |archive-date=June 28, 2013 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this setback, sumo's popularity and general attendance has rebounded due to having multiple ''[[yokozuna]]'' (or grand champions) for the first time in a number of years and other high-profile wrestlers such as [[Endō Shōta|Endō]] and [[Ichinojō Takashi|Ichinojō]] grabbing the public's attention.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sumo revival&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Revival of sumo's popularity |publisher=Saga Shinbun |url=http://www.saga-s.co.jp/column/ariakesyou/124367|language=Japanese |accessdate=December 8, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Somagahana Fuchiemon restored.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Sumo wrestler Somagahana Fuchiemon, {{c.|1850|lk=on}}]]
===Antiquity (pre-1185)===
Prehistoric wall paintings indicate that sumo originated from an agricultural [[ritual dance]] performed in prayer for a good harvest.&lt;ref name=&quot;USADojo&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.usadojo.com/history-of-sumo/ |title=History of Sumo |last=Sharnoff |first=Lora |date=August 13, 2013 |website=USA Dojo |accessdate=December 29, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first mention of sumo can be found in a ''[[Kojiki]]'' manuscript dating back to 712, which describes how possession of the Japanese islands was decided in a wrestling match between the ''[[kami]]'' Takemikazuchi and Takeminakata. The ''[[Nihon Shoki]]'', published in 720, dates the first sumo match between mortals to the year 23 BC, when a man named Nomi-no-Sukune fought against Taima-no-Kuehaya at the request of [[Emperor Suinin]] and eventually killed him, making him the mythological ancestor of sumo.&lt;ref name=&quot;USADojo&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kokugakuin&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://k-amc.kokugakuin.ac.jp/DM/detail.do?class_name=col_eos&amp;data_id=23231 |title=Encyclopedia of Shinto: Sumō |author=Shigeru Takayama |date= |publisher=Kokugakuin University |accessdate=December 29, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Until the Japanese Middle Ages, this unregulated form of wrestling was often fought to the death of one of the fighters.&lt;ref name=&quot;USADojo&quot;/&gt; The first historically-attested sumo fights were held in 642 at the court of [[Empress Kōgyoku]] to entertain a [[Korea]]n legation. In the centuries that followed, the popularity of sumo within the court increased its ceremonial and religious significance. Regular events at the Emperor's court, the ''sumai no sechie'', and the establishment of the first set of rules for sumo fall into the cultural heyday of the [[Heian period]].

===Japanese Middle Ages (1185–1603)===
With the collapse of the Emperor's central authority, sumo lost its importance in the court; during the [[Kamakura period]], sumo was repurposed from a ceremonial struggle to a form of military combat training among ''[[samurai]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;USADojo&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kokugakuin&quot;/&gt; By the [[Muromachi period]], sumo had fully left the seclusion of the court and became a popular event for the masses, and among the ''[[daimyō]]'' it became common to sponsor wrestlers. ''Sumotori'' who successfully fought for a ''daimyō'''s favor were given generous support and ''samurai'' status. [[Oda Nobunaga]], a particularly avid fan of the sport, held a tournament of 1,500 wrestlers in February 1578. Because several bouts were to be held simultaneously within Nobunaga's castle, circular arenas were delimited to hasten the proceedings and to maintain the safety of the spectators. This event marks the invention of the ''[[dohyō]]'', which would be developed into its current form up until the 18th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;USADojo&quot;/&gt;

===Edo period (1603–1867)===
[[Image:Kunisada sumo 1851.jpg|thumb|300px|Sumo wrestling scene {{c.|1851}}]]
Because sumo had become a nuisance due to wild fighting on the streets, particularly in Edo, sumo was temporarily banned in the city during the [[Edo period]]. In 1684, sumo was permitted to be held for charity events on the property of Shinto shrines, as was common in [[Kyoto]] and [[Osaka]]. The first sanctioned tournament took place in the [[Tomioka Hachiman Shrine]] at this time. An official sumo organization was developed, consisting of professional wrestlers at the disposal of the Edo administration. Many elements date from this period, such as the ''[[Glossary of sumo terms#dohyō-iri|dohyō-iri]]'', the ''[[Heya (sumo)|heya]]'' system, the ''[[gyōji]]'' and the ''[[mawashi]]''. The 18th century brought forth several notable wrestlers such as [[Raiden Tameemon]], [[Onogawa Kisaburō]] and [[Tanikaze Kajinosuke]], the first historical ''[[yokozuna]]''.

===Since 1868===
The [[Meiji Restoration]] of 1868 brought about the end of the feudal system, and with it the wealthy ''daimyō'' as sponsors. Due to a new fixation on [[Western culture]], sumo had come to be seen as an embarrassing and backward relic, and internal disputes split the central association. The popularity of sumo was restored when [[Emperor Meiji]] organized a tournament in 1884; his example would make sumo a national symbol and contribute to nationalist sentiment following military successes against Korea and China. The Japan Sumo Association reunited in 1926 and increased the number of annual tournaments from two to four, and then to six in 1958. The length of tournaments was extended from ten to fifteen days in 1949.

==Winning a sumo bout==
The winner of a sumo bout is generally either the first wrestler to force his opponent to step out of the ring, or the first wrestler to force his opponent to touch the ground with any part of his body other than the bottom of his feet. Also, a number of other less common rules can be used to determine the winner. For example, a wrestler using an illegal technique (''[[kinjite]]'') automatically loses, as does one whose ''[[mawashi]]'' (belt) comes completely undone. A wrestler failing to show up for his bout (even if due to prior injury) also automatically loses (''[[fusensho|fusenpai]]'').

The initial crouch and charge are crucial. Upon positioning themselves opposite each other, the wrestlers perform a deep squat; without taking their feet off the ground, they then move forwards into a head-first crouched position, whilst also resting on one or two fists. This position is important because it allows them to adopt a more efficient posture to charge from and also [[Isometric exercise#Isometric presses as preparation for explosive power movements|isometrically preloads]] their muscles: this enables them to spring up and charge their opponents more powerfully when the referee signals the bout to begin.  A successful charge is usually a powerful charge and is often a key determining factor in who wins the bout.

Bouts consist solely of a single round and often last only a few seconds, as usually one wrestler is quickly ousted from the circle or thrown to the ground. However, they can occasionally last for several minutes. Each match is preceded by an elaborate ceremonial ritual. Traditionally, sumo wrestlers are renowned for their great girth and body mass, which is often a winning factor in sumo. No weight divisions are used in professional sumo; a wrestler can sometimes face an opponent twice his own weight. However, with superior technique, smaller wrestlers can control and defeat much larger opponents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Rules of Sumo |work=Beginner's Guide of Sumo |publisher=[[Japan Sumo Association]] |url=http://sumo.goo.ne.jp/eng/ozumo_joho_kyoku/shiru/kiso_chishiki/beginners_guide/rules.html |access-date=June 26, 2007 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070601161839/http://sumo.goo.ne.jp/eng/ozumo_joho_kyoku/shiru/kiso_chishiki/beginners_guide/rules.html |archive-date=June 1, 2007 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The average weight of top division wrestlers has continued to increase, from {{convert|125|kg}} in 1969 to over {{convert|150|kg}} by 1991, and was a record {{convert|166|kg}} as of January 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.asahi.com/ajw/articles/AJ201902190008.html|title=SUMO/ Heavier wrestlers blamed for increase in serious injuries|date=19 February 2019|newspaper=Asahi Shimbun|accessdate=8 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In some situations, a review of the [[gyōji]]'s decision may be needed.  The judges outside the ring, who sit at eye level (the ''[[Judge (sumo)|shimpan]]'') may convene a conference in the middle of the ring, called a ''[[mono-ii]]''.  This is done if the judges decide that the decision over who won the bout needs to be reviewed; for example, if both [[sumotori]] appear to touch the ground or step out of the ring at the same time.  In these cases, sometimes video is reviewed to see what happened.  Once a decision is made, the chief judge will announce the decision to the spectators and the wrestlers alike.  They may order a bout to be restarted, or leave the decision as given by the gyōji. Occasionally the shimpan will overrule the gyōji and give the bout to the other wrestler.

After the winner is declared, an off-stage ''gyōji'' (referee) determines the ''[[kimarite]]'' (or winning technique) used in the bout, which is then announced to the audience. The Japan Sumo Association recognizes 82 different ''kimarite'' and 5 different ''hiwaza'' (or non-technique) in a win.  

On rare occasions the referee or judges may award the win to the wrestler who touched the ground first. This happens if both wrestlers touch the ground at nearly the same time and it is decided that the wrestler who touched the ground second had no chance of winning, his opponent's superior ''sumo'' having put him in an irrecoverable position. The losing wrestler is referred to as being ''[[shini-tai]]'' (&quot;dead body&quot;) in this case.

==Wrestling ring (''dohyō'')==
{{Main|dohyō}}

Sumo matches take place in a ''[[dohyō]]'' (土俵): a ring, {{convert|4.55|m|ft|abbr=on}} in diameter and {{convert|16.26|m2|ft2|abbr=on}} in area, of rice-straw bales on top of a platform made of clay mixed with sand. A new ''dohyō'' is built for each tournament by the bout callers (or ''[[yobidashi]]''). At the center are two white lines, the ''[[Glossary of sumo terms#shikiri-sen|shikiri-sen]]'', behind which the wrestlers position themselves at the start of the bout.&lt;ref name=BBOS&gt;{{cite book |last= Hall |first= Mina |title= The Big Book of Sumo: History, Practice, Ritual, Fight |publisher= Stone Bridge Press |year= 1997 |isbn= 1-880656-28-0 |url-access= registration |url= https://archive.org/details/bigbookofsumohis00hall }}&lt;/ref&gt; A roof resembling that of a [[Shinto shrine]] may be suspended over the ''dohyō''. Women are traditionally forbidden from entering or touching the ring.&lt;ref&gt;
http://www.msn.com/en-us/news/world/female-medics-rushed-to-help-a-man-who-collapsed-on-a-sumo
-ring-they-were-promptly-told-to-leave/ar-AAvuhSO?li=BBnb7Kz&amp;ocid=ASUDHP&lt;/ref&gt;

==Professional sumo==
[[File:Sumo ceremony.jpg|right|thumb|350px|Sumo wrestlers gather in a circle around the ''[[gyōji]]'' (referee) in the ''[[dohyō-iri]]'' (ring-entering ceremony).]]

Professional sumo is organized by the Japan Sumo Association.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharnoff&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |author=Sharnoff, Lora |title=Grand Sumo|publisher=Weatherhill |year=1993 |isbn=0-8348-0283-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; The members of the association, called ''[[oyakata]]'', are all former wrestlers, and are the only people entitled to train new wrestlers. Most practicing wrestlers are members of a training stable  (or [[heya (sumo)|''heya'']]) run by one of the ''oyakata'', who is the stablemaster for the wrestlers under him. In 2007, 43 training stables hosted 660 wrestlers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Sumo Beya Guide| publisher=[[Japan Sumo Association]]| url=http://sumo.goo.ne.jp/eng/ozumo_meikan/sumo_beya/index.html| access-date=July 8, 2007| url-status=dead| archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070715230032/http://sumo.goo.ne.jp/eng/ozumo_meikan/sumo_beya/index.html| archive-date=July 15, 2007| df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

All sumo wrestlers take wrestling names called {{nihongo|''[[shikona]]''|四股名}}, which may or may not be related to their real names. Often, wrestlers have little choice in their names, which are given to them by their trainers (or stablemasters), or by a supporter or family member who encouraged them into the sport. This is particularly true of foreign-born wrestlers. A wrestler may change his wrestling name during his career, with some wrestlers changing theirs several times.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharnoff&quot;/&gt;

Sumo wrestling is a strict hierarchy based on sporting merit. The wrestlers are ranked according to a system that dates back to the Edo period. Wrestlers are promoted or demoted according to their performance in six official tournaments held throughout the year. A carefully prepared ''[[banzuke]]'' listing the full hierarchy is published two weeks prior to each sumo tournament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Kamiya, Setsuko|url=http://www.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20100216i1.html|title=Steeped in tradition, Shinto, sumo is also scandal-stained|newspaper=[[Japan Times]]|date=February 19, 2010|accessdate=August 16, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to the professional tournaments, exhibition competitions are held at regular intervals every year in Japan, and roughly once every two years, the top-ranked wrestlers visit a foreign country for such exhibitions. None of these displays is taken into account in determining a wrestler's future rank. Rank is determined only by performance in grand sumo tournaments (or ''[[honbasho]]'').&lt;ref name=BBOS/&gt;

===Sumo divisions===
{{Main|Professional sumo divisions}}
[[File:Foreigner and Wrestler at Yokohama 1861.jpg|thumb|upright|Foreigner and sumo wrestler, 1861]]

The six divisions in sumo, in descending order of prestige, are:

* ''[[makuuchi]]'' (幕内). Maximum 42 wrestlers; Further divided into five ranks

* ''[[jūryō]]'' (十両). Fixed at 28 wrestlers

* ''[[makushita]]'' (幕下). Fixed at 120 wrestlers

* ''[[sandanme]]'' (三段目). Fixed at 200 wrestlers

* ''[[jonidan]]'' (序二段). About 200 wrestlers

* ''[[jonokuchi]]'' (序ノ口 or 序の口). Around 50 wrestlers

Wrestlers enter sumo in the lowest ''jonokuchi'' division and, ability permitting, work their way up to the top division. A broad demarcation in the sumo world can be seen between the wrestlers in the top two divisions known as ''[[sekitori]]'' (関取) and those in the four lower divisions, known commonly by the more generic term ''[[rikishi]]'' (力士).  The ranks receive different levels of compensation, privileges, and status.&lt;ref name=&quot;banzuke&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Banzuke |work=Beginner's Guide of Sumo |publisher=[[Japan Sumo Association]] |url=http://sumo.goo.ne.jp/eng/ozumo_joho_kyoku/shiru/kiso_chishiki/beginners_guide/banzuke.html |access-date=June 27, 2007 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070630033048/http://sumo.goo.ne.jp/eng/ozumo_joho_kyoku/shiru/kiso_chishiki/beginners_guide/banzuke.html |archive-date=June 30, 2007 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The topmost ''makuuchi'' division receives the most attention from fans and has the most complex hierarchy. The majority of wrestlers are ''[[maegashira]]'' (前頭) and are ranked from the highest level 1 down to about 16 or 17. In each rank are two wrestlers, the higher rank is designated as &quot;east&quot; and the lower as &quot;west&quot;, so the list goes #1 east, #1 west, #2 east, #2 west, etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scgroup.com/sumo/faq/faq4.html|title=Sumo FAQ - Professional rankings: The Banzuke|work=scgroup.com|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121001032019/http://www.scgroup.com/sumo/faq/faq4.html|archive-date=October 1, 2012|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Above the ''maegashira'' are the three champion or titleholder ranks, called the ''[[makuuchi#Overview|san'yaku]]'', which are not numbered. These are, in ascending order, ''[[komusubi]]'' (小結), ''[[sekiwake]]'' (関脇), and ''[[ōzeki]]'' (大関). At the pinnacle of the ranking system is the rank of ''[[Yokozuna (sumo)|yokozuna]]'' (横綱).&lt;ref name=banzuke /&gt;

''Yokozuna'', or grand champions, are generally expected to compete for and to win the top division tournament title on a regular basis, hence the promotion criteria for ''yokozuna'' are very strict. In general, an ''ōzeki'' must win the championship for two consecutive tournaments or an &quot;equivalent performance&quot; to be considered for promotion to ''yokozuna''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharnoff&quot;/&gt; More than one wrestler can hold the rank of ''yokozuna'' at the same time.

In antiquity, sumo was solely a Japanese sport. Since the 1900s, however, the number of foreign-born sumo wrestlers has gradually increased.  In the beginning of this period, these few foreign wrestlers were listed as Japanese, but particularly since the 1960s, a number of high-profile [[Rikishi#Foreign-born rikishi|foreign-born wrestlers]] became well-known, and in more recent years have even come to dominate in the highest ranks.  Half of the last six wrestlers promoted to ''ōzeki'' have been foreign-born, and a Japanese had not been named ''yokozuna'' from 1998 until the promotion of [[Kisenosato Yutaka]] in 2017.  This and other issues eventually led the Sumo Association to limit the number of foreigners allowed to one in each stable.

===Women and sumo===
{{main|Controversies in professional sumo#Women and sumo}}
Women are not allowed to compete in professional sumo. They are also not allowed to enter the wrestling ring (''[[dohyō]]''), a tradition stemming from Shinto and Buddhist beliefs that women are &quot;impure&quot; because of menstrual blood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Yoshida |first1=Reiji |title=Banning women from the sumo ring: centuries-old tradition, straight-up sexism or something more complex? |url=https://www.japantimes.co.jp/news/2018/04/30/national/social-issues/banning-women-sumo-ring-sexism-centuries-old-cultural-tradition/ |accessdate=11 December 2019 |work=The Japan Times |date=30 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Professional sumo tournaments==
{{Main|Honbasho}}
[[File:Sumo-hall-angle.jpg|thumb|left|The sumo hall of [[Ryōgoku]] in Tokyo during the May, 2001 tournament]]

Since 1958, six Grand Sumo tournaments (Japanese: ''honbasho'') have been held each year: three at the Sumo Hall (or [[Ryōgoku Kokugikan]]) in [[Ryōgoku]], Tokyo (January, May, and September), and one each in [[Osaka]] (March), [[Nagoya]] (July), and [[Fukuoka, Fukuoka|Fukuoka]] (November). Each tournament begins on a Sunday and runs for 15 days, ending also on a Sunday.&lt;ref&gt;An exception to this rule occurred when [[Hirohito]], the former [[Emperor of Japan]], died on Saturday, January 7, 1989. The tournament that was to start on the following day was postponed to start on Monday, January 9 and finish on Monday, January 24.&lt;/ref&gt; Each wrestler in the top two divisions (''sekitori'') has one match per day, while the lower-ranked wrestlers compete in seven bouts, about one every two days.

Each day is structured so that the highest-ranked contestants compete at the end of the day. Thus, wrestling starts in the morning with the ''[[jonokuchi]]'' wrestlers and ends at around six o'clock in the evening with bouts involving the ''yokozuna''. The wrestler who wins the most matches over the 15 days wins the tournament championship (''[[yūshō]]'') for his division. If two wrestlers are tied for the top, they wrestle each other and the winner takes the title. Three-way ties for a championship are rare, at least in the top division. In these cases, the three wrestle each other in pairs with the first to win two in a row take the tournament. More complex systems for championship playoffs involving four or more wrestlers also exist, but these are usually only seen in determining the winner of one of the lower divisions.

[[File:Sumo Nobori flags.jpg|thumb|right|Sumo [[nobori]] flags]]
The matchups for each day of the tournament are announced a day in advance. They are determined by the sumo elders who are members of the judging division of the [[Japan Sumo Association|Sumo Association]]. As many more wrestlers are in each division than matchups during the tournament, each wrestler only competes against a selection of opponents from the same division, though small overlaps can occur between two divisions. With the exception of the ''[[makuuchi#Overview|san'yaku]]''-ranked wrestlers, the first bouts tend to be between wrestlers who are within a few ranks of each other. Afterwards, the selection of opponents takes into account a wrestler's prior performance. For example, in the lower divisions, wrestlers with the same record in a tournament are generally matched up with each other and the last matchups often involve undefeated wrestlers competing against each other, even if they are from opposite ends of the division. In the top division, in the last few days, wrestlers with exceptional records often have matches against much more highly ranked opponents, including ''san'yaku'' wrestlers, especially if they are still in the running for the top division championship. Similarly, more highly ranked wrestlers with very poor records may find themselves fighting wrestlers much further down the division. For the ''yokozuna'' and ''ōzeki'', the first week and a half of the tournament tends to be taken up with bouts against the top ''[[maegashira]]'', ''komusubi'', and ''sekiwake'', with the bouts within these ranks being concentrated into the last five days or so of the tournament (depending on the number of top-ranked wrestlers competing). Traditionally, on the final day, the last three bouts of the tournament are between the top six ranked wrestlers, with the top two competing in the final matchup, unless injuries during the tournament prevent this.

Certain match-ups are prohibited in regular tournament play. Wrestlers who are from the same training stable cannot compete against each other, nor can wrestlers who are brothers, even if they join different stables. The one exception to this rule is that training stable partners and brothers can face each other in a championship-deciding playoff match.

The last day of the tournament is called ''senshūraku'', which literally means &quot;the pleasure of a thousand autumns&quot;. This colorful name for the culmination of the tournament echoes the words of the playwright [[Zeami Motokiyo|Zeami]] to represent the excitement of the decisive bouts and the celebration of the victor. The Emperor's Cup is presented to the wrestler who wins the top-division ''makuuchi'' championship. Numerous other (mostly sponsored) prizes are also awarded to him. These prizes are often rather elaborate, ornate gifts, such as giant cups, decorative plates, and statuettes. Others are quite commercial, such as one trophy shaped like a giant Coca-Cola bottle.

Promotion and relegation for the next tournament are determined by a wrestler's score over the 15 days. In the top division, the term ''[[kachikoshi]]'' means a score of 8–7 or better, as opposed to ''[[makekoshi]]'', which indicates a score of 7–8 or worse. A wrestler who achieves ''kachikoshi'' almost always is promoted further up the ladder, the level of promotion being higher for better scores. See the ''[[makuuchi]]'' article for more details on promotion and relegation.

A top-division wrestler who is not an ''ōzeki'' or ''yokozuna'' and who finishes the tournament with ''kachikoshi'' is also eligible to be considered for one of the three prizes awarded for &quot;technique&quot;, &quot;fighting spirit&quot;, and defeating the most ''[[Yokozuna (sumo)|yokozuna]]'' and ''ōzeki'' the &quot;outstanding performance&quot; prize.  For more information see ''[[sanshō (sumo)|sanshō]].

For the list of upper divisions champions since 1909, refer to the [[list of sumo tournament top division champions|list of top division champions]] and [[list of sumo tournament second division champions|the list of second division champions]].

===A professional sumo bout===
[[File:2006 March Grand Sumo Tournament in Osaka.jpg|thumb|Sumo wrestlers at the Grand Tournament in [[Osaka]], March 2006]]
At the initial charge, both wrestlers must jump up from the [[sumo squat|crouch]] simultaneously after touching the surface of the ring with two fists at the start of the bout. The referee (''gyōji'') can restart the bout if this simultaneous touch does not occur. Upon completion of the bout, the referee must immediately designate his decision by pointing his ''[[gunbai]]'' or war-fan towards the winning side. The winning technique (''[[kimarite]]'') used by the winner would then be announced to the audience. The referee's decision is not final and may be disputed by the five [[judge (sumo)|judges]] seated around the ring. If this happens, they meet in the center of the ring to hold a ''mono-ii'' (a talk about things). After reaching a consensus, they can uphold or reverse the referee's decision or order a rematch, known as a ''[[torinaoshi]]''. The wrestlers then return to their starting positions and bow to each other before retiring. A winning wrestler in the top division may receive additional prize money in envelopes from the referee if the matchup has been sponsored. If a ''yokozuna ''is defeated by a lower-ranked wrestler, it is common and expected for audience members to throw their seat cushions into the ring (and onto the wrestlers), though this practice is technically prohibited.

[[File:Sumoclip-may242007-tokyo.ogv|left|thumb|thumbtime=9|300px|A short video clip of a ''sandanme'' division bout between 萬華城 (Mankajō, left) and 剛天佑 (Gōtenyū, right): Mankajō was the eventual winner of this unusually long match on day 12 of the 2007 May ''honbasho''.]]
In contrast to the time in bout preparation, bouts are typically very short, usually less than a minute (most of the time only a few seconds). Extremely rarely, a bout can go on for several minutes. If a bout lasts up to four minutes, the referee or one of the judges sitting around the ring may call a ''mizu-iri'' or &quot;[[water break]]&quot;. The wrestlers are carefully separated, have a brief break, and then return to the exact position they left, as determined by the referee. If after four more minutes, they are still deadlocked, they may have a second break, after which they start from the beginning. Further deadlock with no end of the bout in sight can lead to a draw (''hikiwake''), an extremely rare result in modern sumo. The last draw in the top division was in September 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharnoff&quot;/&gt;

==Life as a professional sumo wrestler==
[[File:Sumoworkout.JPG|right|thumb|Young low-ranking sumo wrestlers at the [[Tomozuna stable|Tomozuna Stable]] in Tokyo end their daily workout routine with a footwork drill.]]
A sumo wrestler leads a highly regimented way of life. The Sumo Association prescribes the behavior of its wrestlers in some detail. For example, the association prohibits wrestlers from driving cars, although this is partly out of necessity as many wrestlers are too big to fit behind a steering wheel.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-42178483|title=Inside the scandal-hit world of sumo|last=Seales|first=Rebecca|date=2017-12-01|work=BBC News|access-date=2018-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Breaking the rules can result in fines and/or suspension for both the offending wrestler and his stablemaster.

On entering sumo, they are expected to grow their hair long to form a topknot, or ''[[chonmage]]'', similar to the ''samurai'' hairstyles of the Edo period. Furthermore, they are expected to wear the ''chonmage'' and traditional Japanese dress when in public, allowing them to be identified immediately as wrestlers.

The type and quality of the dress depends on the wrestler's rank. ''Rikishi'' in ''[[jonidan]]'' and below are allowed to wear only a thin cotton robe called a ''[[yukata]]'', even in winter. Furthermore, when outside, they must wear a form of wooden sandal called ''[[geta (footwear)|geta]]''. Wrestlers in the ''[[makushita]]'' and ''[[sandanme]]'' divisions can wear a form of traditional short overcoat over their ''yukata'' and are allowed to wear straw sandals, called ''[[zōri]]''. The higher-ranked ''[[sekitori]]'' can wear silk robes of their own choice, and the quality of the garb is significantly improved. They also are expected to wear a more elaborate form of topknot called an ''ōichō'' (big [[Ginkgo biloba|ginkgo]] leaf) on formal occasions.

Similar distinctions are made in stable life. The junior wrestlers must get up earliest, around 5&amp;nbsp;am, for training, whereas the ''sekitori'' may start around 7&amp;nbsp;am. When the ''sekitori'' are training, the junior wrestlers may have chores to do, such as assisting in cooking the lunch, cleaning, and preparing the bath,  holding a ''sekitori'''s towel, or wiping the sweat from him. The ranking hierarchy is preserved for the order of precedence in bathing after training, and in eating lunch.

Wrestlers are not normally allowed to eat breakfast and are expected to have a ''[[siesta]]''-like nap after a large lunch. The most common type of lunch served is the traditional sumo meal of ''[[chankonabe]]'', which consists of a simmering stew of various fish, meat, and vegetables cooked at the table. It is usually eaten with rice and washed down with beer. This regimen of no breakfast and a large lunch followed by a sleep is intended to help wrestlers put on a lot of weight so as to compete more effectively.

In the afternoon, the junior wrestlers again usually have cleaning or other chores, while their ''sekitori'' counterparts may relax, or deal with work issues related to their fan clubs. Younger wrestlers also attend classes, although their education differs from the typical curriculum of their non-sumo peers. In the evening, ''sekitori'' may go out with their sponsors, while the junior wrestlers generally stay at home in the stable, unless they are to accompany the stablemaster or a ''sekitori'' as his ''tsukebito'' (manservant) when he is out. Becoming a ''tsukebito'' for a senior member of the stable is a typical duty. A ''sekitori'' has a number of ''tsukebito'', depending on the size of the stable or in some cases depending on the size of the ''sekitori''.  The junior wrestlers are given the most mundane tasks such as cleaning the stable, running errands, and even washing or massaging the exceptionally large ''sekitori'' while only the senior ''tsukebito'' accompany the ''sekitori'' when he goes out.

The ''sekitori'' are given their own room in the stable, or may live in their own apartments, as do married wrestlers; the junior wrestlers sleep in communal dormitories. Thus, the world of the sumo wrestler is split broadly between the junior wrestlers, who serve, and the ''sekitori'', who are served. Life is especially harsh for recruits, to whom the worst jobs tend to be allocated, and the dropout rate at this stage is high.

The negative health effects of the sumo lifestyle can become apparent later in life. Sumo wrestlers have a [[life expectancy]] between 60 and 65, more than 10 years shorter than the average Japanese male, as the diet and sport take a toll on the wrestler's body. Many develop [[type 2 diabetes]] or [[high blood pressure]], and they are prone to heart attacks due to the enormous amount of body mass and fat that they accumulate. The excessive intake of [[alcoholic beverage|alcohol]] can lead to [[Alcoholic liver disease|liver problems]] and the stress on their joints due to their excess weight can cause [[arthritis]]. Recently, the standards of weight gain are becoming less strict, in an effort to improve the overall health of the wrestlers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Becoming a Sumo Wrestler | work=Sumo East and West | publisher=[[Discovery Channel]] | url=http://www.discoverychannelasia.com/sumo/become_a_sumo_wrestler/index.shtml | access-date=November 18, 2005 | url-status=dead | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050831220303/http://discoverychannelasia.com/sumo/become_a_sumo_wrestler/index.shtml | archive-date=August 31, 2005 | df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=United Nations Statistics Division – Demographic and Social Statistics | url=http://unstats.un.org/unsd/demographic/products/dyb/dyb2.htm | accessdate=November 18, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Minimum height requirement==
Some sumo organizations have minimum height requirements for their competitors. In 1994, the Japanese Sumo Association required that all sumo wrestlers be a minimum 173&amp;nbsp;cm (5 feet 8 inches) in height. This prompted 16-year-old Takeji Harada of Japan (who had failed six previous eligibility tests) to have four separate cosmetic surgeries over a period of 12 months to add an extra 15&amp;nbsp;cm (6 inches) of silicone to his scalp, which created a large, protruding bulge on his head.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://community.seattletimes.nwsource.com/archive/?date=19940707&amp;slug=1919134|title=Wrestlers Go Great Lengths To Qualify|last=Ashmun|first=Chuck|year=1994|newspaper=Seattle Times|accessdate=15 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response to this, the Japanese Sumo Association stated that they would no longer accept aspiring wrestlers who surgically enhanced their height, citing health concerns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1994-07-07/news/mn-13018_1_minimum-height|title=Silicone Raises Sumo Hopeful to New Heights|first=|last=|date=July 7, 1994|publisher=|via=LA Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Salary and payment==
{{as of|2018}}, the monthly salary figures for ''[[makuuchi]]'' (in [[Japanese yen]]) were:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Rikishi Salaries | language=Japanese |  url=https://www.sankei.com/sports/news/181129/spo1811290026-n1.html | accessdate=December 3, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:YokozunaJmills74.jpg|right|thumb|''Yokozuna'' Asashoryu performing the distinctive ''[[dohyō-iri]]'' of his rank]]
*''[[Yokozuna (sumo)|yokozuna]]'': 3,000,000, about US$26,500
*''[[ōzeki]]'': 2,500,000, about US$22,000
*''[[makuuchi#Overview|san'yaku]]'': 1,800,000, about US$16,000
*''[[maegashira]]'': 1,400,000 or about US$12,500
*''[[jūryō]]'': 1,100,000, about US$9,500

Wrestlers lower than the second division, who are considered trainees, receive only a fairly small allowance instead of a salary.

In addition to the basic salary, ''sekitori'' wrestlers also receive additional bonus income, called ''[[mochikyūkin]]'', six times a year (once every tournament, or ''basho'') based on the cumulative performance in their career to date. This bonus increases every time the wrestler scores a ''[[kachikoshi]]'' (with larger ''kachikoshi'' giving larger raises). Special increases in this bonus are also awarded for winning the top division championship (with an extra large increase for a &quot;perfect&quot; championship victory with no losses), and also for scoring a gold star or ''[[kinboshi]]'' (an upset of a ''yokozuna'' by a ''[[makuuchi#|maegashira]]'').

''San'yaku'' wrestlers also receive a relatively small additional tournament allowance, depending on their rank, and ''yokozuna'' receive an additional allowance every second tournament, associated with the making of a new ''tsuna'' belt worn in their ring entering ceremony.

Also, prize money is given to the winner of each divisional championship, which increases from 100,000 yen for a ''[[jonokuchi]]'' victory up to 10,000,000 yen for winning the top division. In addition to prizes for a championship, wrestlers in the top division giving an exceptional performance in the eyes of a judging panel can also receive one or more of three special prizes (the ''[[Sanshō (sumo)|sanshō]]''), which are worth 2,000,000 yen each.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Sumo Questions | url=http://www.sumotalk.com/sumofaq.htm | accessdate=November 18, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Individual top division matches can also be sponsored by companies. In such cases, the winner of the bout typically receives around 30,000 yen net per sponsor (out of the sponsors' contribution of 60,000 yen—much of the remainder goes in paying the wrestler's tax on the prize). These bout prizes are called ''kenshōkin''. For bouts involving ''yokozuna'' and ''ōzeki'', the number of sponsors of the matchup can be quite large, whereas for lower-ranked matchups, no bout sponsors may be active at all unless one of the wrestlers is particularly popular, or unless a company has a policy of sponsoring all his matchups. No bout prize money is awarded for a bout decided by a ''[[glossary of sumo terms#fusenshō|fusenshō]]'' or forfeit victory.

==Amateur sumo==
[[File:Bulgarian-sumists.jpg|thumb|right|[[Bulgaria]]n amateurs – on the right is the national coach Hristo Hristov]]
Sumo is also practised as an amateur sport, with participants in college, high school, and grade school in Japan. In addition to college and school tournaments, open amateur tournaments are also held. The sport at this level is stripped of most of the ceremony. The most successful amateur wrestlers in Japan (usually college champions) can be allowed to enter professional sumo at ''[[makushita]]'' (third division) rather than from the very bottom of the ladder. This rank is called ''[[makushita tsukedashi]]'', and is currently ''makushita'' 10 or 15 depending on the level of amateur success achieved. Many of the current top division wrestlers entered professional sumo by this route. All amateur athletes entering the professional ranks must be under 23 to satisfy the entry, except those who qualify for ''[[makushita tsukedashi]]'', who may be up to 25.

The [[International Sumo Federation]] was established to encourage the sport's development worldwide, including holding international championships. A key aim of the federation is to have sumo recognized as an [[Olympic sports|Olympic sport]]. Accordingly, amateur tournaments are divided into weight classes (men: Lightweight up to {{Convert|85|kg|abbr=on}}, Middleweight up to {{Convert|115|kg|abbr=on}}, Heavyweight over {{Convert|115|kg|abbr=on}}, and Open Weight (unrestricted entry), and include competitions for female wrestlers (Lightweight up to {{Convert|65|kg|abbr=on}}, Middleweight up to {{Convert|80|kg|abbr=on}}, Heavyweight over {{Convert|80|kg|abbr=on}}, and Open Weight).

Amateur sumo clubs are gaining in popularity in the United States, with competitions regularly being held in major cities across the country. The US Sumo Open, for example, was held in the Los Angeles Convention Center in 2007 with an audience of 3,000.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.amazon.com/My-First-Date-Sumo-ebook/dp/B0061BMG0O My First Date With Sumo (2007) Gould, Chris]  {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120928012736/http://www.amazon.com/My-First-Date-Sumo-ebook/dp/B0061BMG0O |date=September 28, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The sport has long been popular on the West Coast and in Hawaii, where it has played a part in the festivals of the Japanese ethnic communities. Now, however, the sport has grown beyond the sphere of [[Japanese diaspora]] and athletes come from a variety of ethnic, cultural, and sporting backgrounds.

Amateur sumo is particularly strong in Europe. Many athletes come to the sport from a background in [[judo]], [[freestyle wrestling]], or other [[grappling]] sports such as [[Sambo (martial art)|sambo]]. Some Eastern European athletes have been successful enough to be scouted into professional sumo in Japan, much like their Japanese amateur counterparts. The most notable of these to date is the Bulgarian [[Kotoōshū Katsunori|Kotoōshū]], who is the highest-ranking foreign wrestler who was formerly an amateur sumo athlete.

Brazil is another center of amateur sumo, introduced by Japanese immigrants who arrived during the first half of the twentieth century. The first Brazilian sumo tournament was held in 1914.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/27/world/americas/brazils-japanese-preserve-sumo-and-share-it-with-others.html?_r=0|title=Brazil's Japanese Preserve Sumo and Share It With Others|last=Benson|first=Todd|date=January 27, 2005|work=The New York Times|access-date=November 21, 2016|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Sumo took root in immigrant centers in southern Brazil, especially São Paulo, which is now home to the only purpose-built sumo training facility outside Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/world/brazil-female-sumo-wrestlers-1.3703178|title='Sumo feminino': How Brazil's female sumo wrestlers are knocking down gender barriers|last=Kwok|first=Matt|date=August 2, 2016|work=CBC News|access-date=November 21, 2016|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Beginning in the 1990s, Brazilian sumo organizations made an effort to interest Brazilians without Japanese ancestry in the sport, and by the mid-2000s an estimated 70% of participants came from outside the Japanese-Brazilian community.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;  Brazil is also a center for women's sumo.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;  A small number of Brazilian wrestlers have made the transition to professional sumo in Japan, including [[Ryūkō Gō]] and [[Kaisei Ichirō]].

== Clothing ==
Sumo wrestlers wear Mawashi which is essentially a thick 30-foot-long belt, that they tie in knots in the back.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.usasumo.com/shop/sumo-equipment/|title=Sumo Equipment|last=|first=|date=|website=|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; They have an official thickness and strength requirement. During matches, the wrestler will grab onto the other wrestler's Mawashi and use it to help them and make moves during a match.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.livestrong.com/article/483679-what-do-sumo-wrestlers-wear-during-a-match/|title=What Do Sumo Wrestlers Wear During a Match?|last=|first=|website=LIVESTRONG.COM|language=en|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-10-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Muwashi they wear practicing versus in a tournament is essentially the same except for the material. The different Mawashi that the wrestlers wear differentiate their rank. Top rated wrestlers wear different colors of silk Mawashi during tournament, while lower rated wrestlers are limited to just black cotton. Sumo wrestlers wear Mawashi because there are fewer ways to cheat when you wear one.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

Their hair is put in what they call a topknot, and they use wax to get it to stay. Wax is applied to sumo wrestlers' hair daily by sumo hairdressers ([[Tokoyama|Tokoyama).]]&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.japantimes.co.jp/sports/2018/09/14/sumo/sumo-101-topknot/#.XdhQkZNKhAZ|title=The Topknot|last=|first=|date=|website=Sportsrec|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The topknot is a type of [[Samurai]] hairstyle which was once popular in Japan during the [[Edo period]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; The topknot is hard for some foreigner's hair because their hair is not as coarse and straight as Japanese hair. Once a wrestler joins a stable, they are required to grow out their hair in order to form a topknot.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;

Outside of tournaments and practices, in daily life, sumo wrestlers are required to wear traditional Japanese clothes&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.insidejapantours.com/blog/2014/09/16/11-amazing-things-you-probably-never-knew-about-sumo-wrestling/|title=Things You Didn't Know About Sumo Wrestlers|last=|first=|date=|website=|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;. They must wear these traditional clothes all the time in public. What you can wear in public is also determined by rank. Lower rated wrestlers must wear a [[Yukata]] at all times, even in winter, where higher rated wrestlers have more choice in what they wear.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;

== Image gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Sumo May09 Tochinoshin.jpg|Initial [[full squat]] with heels up.
File:Sumo-Japan.jpg|[[Partial squat]] before engaging.
File:Yumitori shiki.ogv|Yumitori-shiki
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Japan|Society|Martial arts}}
*[[Controversies in professional sumo]]
*[[Culture of Japan]]
*[[Glossary of sumo terms]]
*''[[Kimarite]]'', list of winning moves in sumo
*[[List of active sumo wrestlers]]
*[[List of past sumo wrestlers]]
*[[List of sumo stables]]
*[[List of sumo record holders]]
*[[List of sumo tournament top division champions]]
*[[List of sumo tournament second division champions]]
*[[List of years in sumo]]
*[[List of yokozuna]]
*[[Lists of sumo wrestlers]]
*''[[Sumo East and West]]'', documentary on sumo

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite book | last = Benjamin | first = David | year = 1991 | title = The Joy of Sumo: A Fan's Notes | publisher=Charles E. Tuttle Company | location = Rutland, Vermont, U.S.A. &amp; Tokyo, Japan | isbn = 0-8048-1679-4 }}
*{{cite book | last = Gould | first = Chris | year = 2011 | title = Sumo Through the Wrestlers' Eyes | publisher=Amazon | asin = B006C1I5K8}}
*{{cite book | last = Gould | first = Chris | origyear = 2007|year=2011 | title = My First Date With Sumo | publisher=Amazon | asin = B0061BMG0O}}
*{{cite book | last = Schilling | first = Mark | year = 1994 | title = Sumo: A Fan's Guide | publisher=The Japan Times, Ltd. | location = Tokyo, Japan | isbn = 4-7890-0725-1 }}
*{{cite book | last = Shapiro | first = David | year = 1995 | title = Sumo: A Pocket Guide | publisher=Charles E. Tuttle Company | location = Rutland, Vermont, U.S.A. &amp; Tokyo, Japan | isbn = 0-8048-2014-7 }}
*Sharnoff, Lora (1993). Grand Sumo. Weatherhill. {{ISBN|0-8348-0283-X}}.
*{{cite book | last = Tablero | first = Fco. Javier | year = 2002 | title = Parentesco y organización del sumo en Japón | publisher=Universidad Complutense de Madrid | location = Madrid | isbn = 84-8466-257-8 }}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons and category|Professional sumo|Sumo}}
*[http://www.sumo.or.jp/en/index Nihon Sumo Kyokai Official Grand Sumo Home Page]
*[http://www.sumoforum.net The Sumo Forum]
*[https://www.nhk.or.jp/nhkworld/en/tv/sumo/ Live-Stream and Video-on-Demand from Grand Sumo Tournament on NHK Japan (english)]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20141223143125/http://www.scgroup.com/sumo/faq/ Sumo FAQ]
*[http://www.sumoreference.com Searchable Sumo Database]
*[http://www.sumotalk.com Sumo News and Analysis]
*[https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1258123/ A Matter of Size], an Israeli fictional film on Amateur Sumo (2009)

{{Grappling}}
{{folk wrestling}}
{{Japanese martial arts}}
{{Martial arts}}
{{Sports of the World Games program}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Sumo| ]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Combat sports]]
[[Category:Sports originating in Japan]]
[[Category:Partial squatting position]]</text>
      <sha1>b36zr31zlopxx72sc5e5eqnf30jtphz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
