  <page>
    <title>Surr</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33081648</id>
    <revision>
      <id>908460232</id>
      <parentid>860869567</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-07-29T21:26:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Akld guy</username>
        <id>3122361</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Digits only if 10 or more. Rmv duplicate word</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Surr.svg|thumb|right|300px|Surr is played on a rectangular ground divided into four equal quadrants. Two perpendicular lines of defense run in the middle of the ground. Team A gathers in one of the quadrants, while Team B gathers along the lines of defense bordering the quadrant.]]
'''Surr''' ({{lang-hi|सुर्र}}) is a sport played in the areas around [[Ayodhya]] in northern [[India]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.jagran.com/uttar-pradesh/faizabad-up-faizabad-news-11491492.html |title=विलुप्त हो गए सावन के खेल सुर्र और सिकड़ी |newspaper=Jagran |date=2014-07-20 |language=Hindi }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news &lt;!-- | url = http://www.dainikbhaskarnet.com/%E0%A4%96%E0%A4%A4%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%AE-%E0%A4%B9%E0%A5%8B%E0%A4%A4%E0%A5%87-%E0%A4%96%E0%A4%B2%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%B9%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%A8 --&gt; | title = खत्म होते खलिहान | author = Jagadish Sahay | newspaper = Dainik Bhaskar | date = 2012-06-17 | accessdate = 2012-10-23 | language = Hindi }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Surr is played between two teams, each of which needs to have a minimum of four players. A rectangular ground is divided into four equal quadrants. One team gathers in the first quadrant, while the other team gathers along the lines of defence at the borders of the adjoining quadrant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:PeopleAreKnowledge_Sur_Interview1.ogg
 | title = People Are Knowledge - Sur Interview 1
 | date = April 2011
 | publisher = Wikimedia Commons
 | accessdate = 2011-09-14
}} ([[:meta:Research:Oral Citations|oral citation]])&lt;/ref&gt;

== Rules ==

Surr is organised by a set of tightly defined rules:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:PeopleAreKnowledge_Sur_Interview2.ogg
 | title = People Are Knowledge - Sur Interview 2
 | date = April 2011
 | publisher = Wikimedia Commons
 | accessdate = 2011-09-14
}} ([[:meta:Research:Oral Citations|oral citation]])&lt;/ref&gt;

# There are two teams in a game. Each game has at least four members. Both teams should have an equal number of players.
# Surr is played on a rectangular ground, which is divided into four equal quadrants. Two perpendicular lines of defence run through the middle of the ground, as illustrated in the accompanying picture.
# At the beginning of the game, Team A gathers in the first quadrant, while Team B gathers along the lines of defence bordering the adjoining quadrant.
# The objective of Team A is to enter the other three quadrants without being touched by any player of Team B. The aim of Team B is to stop Team A from doing so by touching them. Any Team A player who gets touched by a Team B player has to step out of the game.
# The surviving Team A players have to enter each quadrant one at a time, and then be together in that quadrant before entering the next quadrant.
# Once all the surviving Team A players gather in a new quadrant, they shout &quot;Bol Den Goivan Surr!&quot; together.
# If Team A members survive and reach the final quadrant, then Team A wins the game. Otherwise Team B wins.

== References ==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Traditional sports of India]]
[[Category:Sports originating in India]]</text>
      <sha1>fkg3f52jvsl5wkiopep2ahrzdy30hzx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
