  <page>
    <title>TAFISA</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>41225059</id>
    <revision>
      <id>892893863</id>
      <parentid>883786920</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-04-17T15:11:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Colonies Chris</username>
        <id>577301</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Primary sources|date=August 2016}}
{{Infobox organization
| name                = The Association For International Sport for All
| image               = TAFISA 2012 - 04.jpg
| image_border        = 
| size                = 200px
| alt                 = &lt;!-- alt text; see [[WP:ALT]] --&gt;
| caption             = TAFISA World Games in [[Šiauliai]], [[Lithuania]] 2012
| map                 = 
| msize               =
| malt                = &lt;!-- map alt text --&gt;
| mcaption            = 
| abbreviation        = TAFISA
| motto               = For an Active World
| formation           = 1991
| extinction          = &lt;!-- date of extinction, optional --&gt;
| type                = 
| status              = International, non-profit organisation
| purpose             = &lt;!-- focus as e.g. humanitarian, peacekeeping, etc --&gt;
| headquarters        = [[Frankfurt]], {{flag|Germany}}
| coords              = 
| region_served       = All Continents
| membership          = 301 members
| language            = 
| leader_title        = President
| leader_name         = Pr. Ju-Ho Chang
| main_organ          = General Assembly, Board of Directors
| parent_organization = &lt;!-- if one --&gt;
| affiliations        = TAFISA Europe, ASFAA, TAFISA Africa, PASFAF
| num_staff           = 
| num_volunteers      = 
| budget              = 
| website             = {{URL|http://www.tafisa.org//}}
| remarks             = 
}}

'''The Association For International Sport for All''' ('''TAFISA''') is the leading international Sport for All{{vague|date=November 2018}} organisation. With more than 270 members from over 150 countries on all continents, TAFISA aims to achieve an Active World by globally promoting and facilitating access for every person to Sport for All and physical activity.

==History==
TAFISA began in the 1960s as the semi regular gathering of international but individual personalities and leaders interested and working in the field of Sport for All, under the title ‘Trim and Fitness’.  At the time, Sport for All was a little known concept.

In 1991, the organisation TAFISA, Trim And Fitness International Sport for All Association, was officially formed and its statues registered with the law courts of Frankfurt, Germany.

In 2005, TAFISA became professional with the opening of its office, also in Frankfurt, Germany. In addition, TAFISA has full-time employees working in the office of the President in Seoul, South Korea.

In 2009, TAFISA officially changed its name to ‘The Association For International Sport for All’ to more accurately describe its activities and its position as the leading international Sport for All association.

The TAFISA General Assembly is composed of TAFISA National Members and is the supreme governing body of TAFISA.  The General Assembly meets every two years at TAFISA World Congresses to discuss and decide the future direction of TAFISA, including election of the Board of Directors every four years.

The most recent TAFISA General Assembly took place on October 25, 2013, as part of the 23rd TAFISA World Congress in Enschede, Netherlands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tafisa.org/ |title=Home |website=Tafisa.org |date=2016-07-21 |accessdate=2016-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Board of directors==
The TAFISA Board of Directors is elected by the General Assembly every four years for a four-year term. The last election was held on 25 October 2013 in Enschede, Netherlands.

The board of directors consists of the president, four vice-presidents, the treasurer, the secretary general and up to five other members.

At least two members of the board of directors are to be female, and two are to be male. The four vice-presidents are to come from different continents (Americas – Asia/Oceania – Africa – Europe).

The 2013–2017 elected board of directors is composed of the following members:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Position !! Name !! Country
|-
| President || Prof. Ju-Ho Chang || South Korea
|-
| Vice president || Mr. Jianzhong Feng || China
|-
| Vice president || Ms. Catherine Forde || Trinidad &amp; Tobago
|-
| Vice president || Mr. Peter Barendse || Netherlands
|-
| Vice president || Mr. Leonard Thadeo || Tanzania
|-
| Treasurer || Mr. Herzel Hagay || Israel
|-
| Secretary general || Mr. Wolfgang Baumann || Germany
|-
| Board Member || Dr. Mitra Rouhi Dehkordi || Iran
|-
| Board Member || Prof. Erdal Zorba || Turkey
|-
| Board Member || Prof. Yasuo Yamaguchi || Japan
|-
| Board Member || Mr. Attila Czene || Hungary
|-
| Board Member || Mr. Dionysios Karakasis || Greece
|}&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20141016063722/http://www.tafisa.org/index.php?option=com_steckbriefe&amp;view=category&amp;catid=61&amp;Itemid=68]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Programs and events==
To encourage as many people around the world as possible to become involved in Sport for All and physical activity, TAFISA has developed a wide range of programs and events, that range for single day physical activity events to targeted, education programs. TAFISA programs and events include:

===TAFISA World Games===

* '''TAFISA World Sport for All Games''' (in short : '''TAFISA World Games'''):
Held every four years since 1992, the week-long festival aims to safeguard and promote traditional sports and games. The most successful events, held in Busan, South Korea, in 2008 and Siauliai, Lithuania, in 2012, both gathered more than 8 000 participants from the entire world. The 6th TAFISA World Sport for All Games 2016 will be hosted by TAFISA member Indonesian Sport for All Association (FORMI) and take place in Jakarta, Indonesia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tafisagames2016.com/ |title=TAFISA Games 2016 |publisher=TAFISA Games 2016 |date= |accessdate=2016-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2016 TAFISA World Sports Games 12,000 athletes from 87 countries in 62 sports participated in the competition.&lt;ref&gt;https://idf64.org/2016/results-of-the-vi-tafisa-world-sports-games/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jagranjosh.com/current-affairs/indian-wrestlers-bagged-four-medals-at-2016-tafisa-world-games-1476759453-1&lt;/ref&gt;

{|class=wikitable
!Edition ||Year ||Host 
|-
|align=center |1 ||[[1992 TAFISA World Games|1992]] ||{{flag|Germany}}, [[Bonn]] 
|-
|align=center |2 ||[[1996 TAFISA World Games|1996]] ||{{flag|Thailand}}, [[Bangkok]]  
|-
|align=center |3 ||[[2000 TAFISA World Games|2000]] ||{{flag|Germany}}, [[Hannover]] 
|-
|align=center |4 ||[[2008 TAFISA World Games|2008]] ||{{flag|South Korea}}, [[Busan]] 
|-
|align=center |5 ||[[2012 TAFISA World Games|2012]] ||{{flag|Lithuania}}, [[Siauliai]] 
|-
|align=center |6 ||[[2016 TAFISA World Games|2016]] ||{{flag|Indonesia}}, [[Jakarta]] 
|-
|align=center |7 ||[[2020 TAFISA World Games|2020]] ||{{flag|Portugal}}, [[Lisbon]] 
|}
http://www.tafisa.org/tafisa-world-sport-for-all-games

* '''TAFISA World Martial Arts Games'''

See : [[World Martial Arts Games]]
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Number
!Year
!Host City
!Country
|-
|align=center |1||[[2014 TAFISA World Martial Arts Games|2014]] || [[Richmond, British Columbia|Richmond]] || {{CAN}} 
|}

Richmond, Canada – September 3 to 7 (8th World Martial Arts Games  &amp;  1st TAFISA World Martial Arts Games)

* '''Traditional Sports And Games (TSG)'''

In the purest sense, they are the games and movements that are traditional to our cultures, from dances to ball games and water sports. But they are more than that. TSG form a significant part of our history and help make us, and our variety of cultures, what we, and they, are today. TSG tell the story of our past, and span genders, generations and individual differences like little else can.

http://www.tafisa.org/traditional-sports-and-games

* '''TAFISA European Games'''

2018 will see the 1st TAFISA European Sport for All Games, to be held in Fryslân, Netherlands, on August 3–7. Following the same concept as the World Sport for All Games, the European Games will gather delegations from all over Europe.&lt;ref&gt;http://esfag2018.eu/&lt;/ref&gt;

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Number
!Year
!Host City
!Country
|-
|align=center |1||[[2018 TAFISA European Games|2018]] || [[Fryslân]] || {{NED}} 
|}
http://esfag2018.eu/

===TAFISA World Congresses===
'''TAFISA World Congresses''': A number one event held every two years, that gathers world's experts in Sport for All and physical activity over 4 to 5 days. The 24th TAFISA World Congress 2015 will be hosted by TAFISA member the Hungarian Leisure Sports Association and take place in Budapest, Hungary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tafisaworldcongressbudapest.com |title=24th TAFISA World Congress 2015|website=Tafisaworldcongressbudapest |date=2015-10-18 |accessdate=2016-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===TAFISA World Challenge Day===
'''TAFISA World Challenge Day''': a friendly international competition in Sport for All and physical activity where communities of similar sizes from around the world compete against each other to motivate as many people as possible be physically active for only 15 minutes on a single day.  The event, held every year on the last Wednesday of May, is a fun day that creates awareness and enthusiasm for fitness and active living in the participating communities. World Challenge Day is open to communities of any size from any country, and since its beginning in 1991, has been growing rapidly every year, with more than 48 million participants from over 40 countries in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20120411164540/http://tafisa.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=71&amp;Itemid=56 ]&lt;/ref&gt;

===TAFISA World Walking Day===
'''TAFISA World Walking Day''': held on the first weekend of October every year since 1991 and over the full month of October for the first time in 2014, TAFISA World Walking Day is open to citizens of all ages, backgrounds, abilities and genders. It aims to integrate physical activity into the everyday lives by promoting the benefits of walking.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20141016063720/http://www.tafisa.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=48&amp;Itemid=55 ]&lt;/ref&gt;

===TAFISA Certified Leadership Courses in Sport for All===
'''TAFISA Certified Leadership Courses in Sport for All''': A three- to five-day training that aims to qualify national Sport for All leaders around the globe.  Since their inception in 2007 and 2011 respectively, more than 30 International and National TAFISA CLCs have been successfully held all across the world.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20120411163913/http://tafisa.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=72&amp;Itemid=75 ]&lt;/ref&gt;

===TAFISA Reach Out Program===
'''TAFISA Reach Out Program''': an initiative that aims to build awareness, cooperation and strategic development of local and national Sport for All movements, particularly less developed countries.  The program creates synergies between governors and practitioners of Sport for All delivery, to enable communities and citizens around the world to benefit from the myriad benefits that Sport for All can bring.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20141016064043/http://www.tafisa.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=350&amp;Itemid=110 ]&lt;/ref&gt;

===TAFISA Triple AC Program===
'''TAFISA Triple AC Program''': The TAFISA &quot;Active Cities, Active Communities, Active Citizens&quot; Program believes in the dramatic role and importance municipalities have in increasing Sport for All and physical activity participation. It aims to support them in their work by collecting and disseminating good practices, as well as providing practical tools and advice to build an Active City strategy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.triple-ac.net/ |title=3AC - Active Cities, Active Communities, Active Citizens |website=Triple-ac.net |date= |accessdate=2016-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{International multi-sport events}}

[[Category:Multi-sport events]]
[[Category:International sports organizations]]
[[Category:International organisations based in Germany]]</text>
      <sha1>kulkschmint8nag9aprmr3yop32j620</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
