  <page>
    <title>Torball</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12850291</id>
    <revision>
      <id>852493389</id>
      <parentid>849037660</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-29T10:36:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BlackcurrantTea</username>
        <id>13756482</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>copy editing, convert template</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Torball Moldova.JPG|thumb|M.E.A.N. team at the European Torball Cup, Paris, 2007]]
'''Torball''' ([[German language|German]]: ''goal ball'') is a sport for the [[blindness|blind]] and visually impaired. It is played by two teams on opposite sides of an indoor [[playing field]]. Each team consists of three players. In the middle part of the field, there are three cords stretched across the entire width. On each end of the playing field is a goal that also stretches the entire width ({{convert|7|m|ft|abbr=on}}) of the field. The playing ball is similar to a soccer ball with bells inside so that it can be heard when it is rolling across the playing field.

==Description==
The object of the game is to score as many goals as possible by rolling the ball under the three cords into the goal of the opposing team. The three-player teams are both attackers and defenders during the two five-minute periods. If the ball touches one of the three cords, a penalty is called, where one player leaves the field and the remaining two players must try to defend their goal for one ‘throw’ by the opposing team.

==Official IBSA Torball rules==
The current official rules for Torball can be downloaded from the [[International Blind Sports Federation]] website.

==See also==
* [[Goalball]]

== External links ==
{{Commonscat|Torball}}
* [http://www.torball.org Official website of Torball]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090329190049/http://www.ibsa.es/eng/deportes/torball/reglamento.htm 2006 - 2009 Official Torball Rules]
* [http://www.ibsa.es International Blind Sport Federation (IBSA)]
* [http://www.blindensport.at Austrian Sport Organization for the Blind]
* [http://www.plusport.ch Swiss Association for the Impaired People]

{{Team Sport}}

[[Category:Team sports]]
[[Category:Blind sports]]</text>
      <sha1>3oxgom45jq0m4v1s96l95gsf0cr8ibk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
