  <page>
    <title>Varde</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20645394</id>
    <revision>
      <id>921534973</id>
      <parentid>921534295</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-16T09:03:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>80.62.117.123</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=October 2015}}

{{Infobox settlement
|name = Varde
|image_skyline = Varde Kirke1.jpg
|image_caption = Church of Sct. Jacob in Varde
|image_shield = Coat of arms of Varde.svg
|image_seal = Vardes segl.jpg
|motto = ''Varde, town of commerce'' or ''We in nature''
|image_map = Map DK Varde.PNG
|coordinates = {{coord|55|37|N|8|29|E|display=inline}}
|subdivision_type = Denmark|subdivision_type1 = Region of Southern Denmark
|leader_title = Mayor
|leader_name = Erik Buhl Nielsen
|website = www.vardekommune.dk
|established_date = Approx. 1100
|timezone1 = +1
|population_total =13989&lt;ref&gt;[https://m.statbank.dk/TableInfo/BY3?lang=en BY3: Population 1 January, by urban areas] The Mobile Statbank from [[Statistics Denmark]]&lt;/ref&gt;
|population_as_of = 2019
|seal_size = 150px
|shield_size = 150px
|mapsize = 250px
|seal_alt = Seal
|shield_alt = Coat of arms
|postal_code = 6800 Varde
|area_blank1_km2 = 1240
|population_blank1 = 50122
|area_blank1_title = Municipality of Varde
|population_blank1_title = Municipality of Varde
}}

'''Varde'''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://dendigitalebyport.byhistorie.dk/koebstaeder/by.aspx?koebstadID=66|title = Dansk Center for Byhistorie|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Danmarks Købstæder: Varde|publisher = Dansk Center for Byhistorie|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; is a Danish city in southwestern [[Jutland]] and is the primary city in the municipality of Varde, in [[Region of Southern Denmark]]. In 2015 municipality changed its motto to &quot;We in nature&quot; to emphasize its rural atmosphere.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.viinaturen.dk/|title = Vi i naturen/Municipality of Varde|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Vi skaber bevægelse i naturen|publisher = Varde Kommune|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; The town has an old market environment and is located by [[Varde River|Varde stream/river]] and is a short distance away from the beaches by the [[North Sea]]. These features make it a tourist destination. The age of Varde is not known precisely, but it is mentioned in written sources from 1107 A.D. and is therefore thought have been founded sometime in the early [[Middle Ages]].

== The history of Varde ==

Early on the name of Varde is presented in 2 different versions &quot;Warwath&quot; and &quot;Warwik.&quot; War is identical in both and is believed to mean [[grassland]], maybe [[beach]] or in other ways uncultivated area. The [[suffix]]es &quot;wath&quot; and &quot;wick&quot; are believed to mean respectively [[Ford (crossing)|ford]] and [[inlet]]. The differing versions of the name occur quite naturally, depending on where you are located &quot;on ground&quot; or &quot;on water&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx|title = Municipality of Varde|accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = NaturKulturKanon - Varde Kommune|publisher = Varde Kommune|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151001034407/http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx|archive-date = 2015-10-01|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; As with other older Danish towns, Varde is located, where the countryside in different ways favors human settlement and other human activity. The town was founded near a stream allowing a convenient port for ships near a place, where north and south bound traffic by land had an important ford/crossing, which was later replaced with a bridge. Varde was from olden times protected against sudden attacks from outsiders, partly because of its distance from the shore and partly because of its neighbourship with the built royal castle/fortress/fort/estate (Vardehus). Vardehus was the administrative center of the district and from this base of power a royal official governed the shire of Varde a sizeable area corresponding to the former [[Ribe County|Ribe Amt]]. On the greater scale Varde has never been a big town, but the fact that Varde already in the early Middle Ages had 2 churches, means that it had some status.

=== Royal castles by the stream/river ===
[[File:Varde - Rathaus.jpg|thumb|Varde - The old town hall, with the black pearl in front]]
Written sources from the [[12th century]] repeatedly mention the [[Official|royal official]]/[[Caretaker government|caretaker]] in Varde. In his capacity of being the representative of the king in the shire of Varde, this high level official must have resided in the local royal estate/castle – Vardehus. The oldest castle lay to the vest of the town, by the stream/river of Varde.

Around the beginning of the [[14th century]] Vardehus was moved to an islet in the stream/river near the southern edge of the town. During an uprising in 1439 this new Vardehus II was stormed, pillaged and destroyed by rebel farmers. Later that same year the council of the state retaliated by burning down the town of Varde. Lesser excavations have been made on both sites, and the findings are kept in Varde museum. It is also known, that during the Viking ages there was a camp near the school of [[Saint Jacob|Sct. Jacob]].

=== Borough/Market town 1442 ===

The [[borough]] sigil of Varde is the oldest town arms in Denmark. It depicts a blue shield with a walking golden leopard with a red tongue. It looks somewhat like a lion, but golden leopard is the official denomination.

From the beginning, commerce together with arts and crafts have been closely linked to being a town and when [[Christopher of Bavaria]] in August 1442 awarded Varde its first borough/market town privileges, it had already functioned as a borough/market town for a long time. Most importantly this meant, that peasants trading goods in country stores was outlawed, but at the same time, that the merchants of the town were now officially recognized as having exclusive rights to conducting trade in the town. Although the royal letter of privilege from 1442 has been long lost, the text is known from a transcript from 1648.

=== The town square of Varde ===

By the town square of Varde lays amongst others the Church of Sct. Jacob from the 12th century, Sillasens house from 1797, the old town hall from 1872 and Den Schultzske Gaard 1796/97.

Around 1900 there was a livestock market on the town square, and for a period in the middle of the [[20th century]] a bus station. 2014/2015 the town square was renovated/renewed as it also was in 2003. 2003 landscape architect Charlotte Horn was inspired by the stream/river of Varde and the characteristic Varde clam with the black pearl, when reshaping the town square. In front of the old town hall of Varde is a basin with a big black round rock symbolizing the Varde pearl. From here a stream symbolizing the [[Varde River|stream/river of Varde]] runs through a part of the town square. The webcam of the library of Varde takes pictures of the square around the clock and here the &quot;stream&quot; is visible.

== The municipality of Varde ==
[[File:Tyrrestrup painting at night at Varde kommune.jpg|thumb|Tyrrestrup painting at night at the new town hall of Varde]]
The current [[Varde Municipality|municipality of Varde]] was formed in 2007, following structural reforms in Denmark, which meant that the old municipality of Varde was merged with the municipalities of [[Blaabjerg]], [[Blåvandshuk]], Helle and [[Ølgod]], which together formed fifth biggest municipality in Denmark measuring in square kilometres, with {{convert|1240|km2}}.

Varde is the main town in the [[Varde Municipality|municipality of Varde]] and is with its 13,771 inhabitants the biggest town in the municipality, followed by [[Ølgod]] and [[Oksbøl]] with respectively 3853 and 2852 inhabitants. All in all there are 50.122 inhabitants with permanent residence in the municipality of Varde. These are, in vacation periods, supplemented by large quantities of tourists visiting the [[Coast|coastal region]] of Varde, especially in and around the towns of [[Blåvand]](Oksby), [[Henne Strand]] and [[Vejers]] Strand, that grow accordingly.

The town hall of the municipality of Varde&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.vardekommune.dk/|title = Municipality of Varde|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Forside - Varde Kommune|publisher = Varde Kommune|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; is at home at Bytoften 2 in Varde, where the new town hall opened its doors in the summer of 2015. During the opening of the new facilities the municipality received a work of art from local artist [[Hans Tyrrestrup]], which it had commissioned, consisting of one poem and three paintings under the title &quot;Sonate for sol,&quot; which means &quot;Sonata for the sun.&quot; This work of art now adorns the council chamber of the town hall.

== Geography ==
[[File:Red Deer in Varde nature.jpg|thumb|left|Red Deer in Varde nature]]
[[File:Vejers-Strand-140625-001.JPG|thumb|Vejers beach]]
[[File:Tirpitz position.jpg|thumb|Tirpitz position]]
Varde stretches from [[Ansager]] in the east to [[Blåvandshuk|Blåvands Huk]] in the west and from [[Skallingen]] in the south to [[Nymindegab]]/[[Ølgod]] in the north.  A variety of different types of landscape types are thus at home in Varde, partly due to the size of the municipality.

Following the vision/motto &quot;We in nature&quot; the eyes have again been opened to the possibilities in the diverseness and the unspoiledness of Varde nature. This has opened for investments to make the nature accessible to visitors, both permanent residents and vacationers.

At the municipality of Varde &quot;[[Wadden Sea National Park, Denmark|Wadden Sea National park]],&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://nationalparkvadehavet.dk/|title = Nationalpark Vadehavet|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Nationalpark Vadehavet|publisher = Nationalpark Vadehavet/Naturstyrelsen|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; which in June 2014, together with areas of the [[Wadden Sea]] in Germany and the Netherlands, was declared [[World Heritage Site|world heritage]] by [[UNESCO]], meets &quot;Naturpark Vesterhavet,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.naturparkvesterhavet.dk/|title = Naturpark Vesterhavet|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Naturpark Vesterhavet|publisher = Naturpark Vesterhavet|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; which stretches across an area of 22.500 hectares between Blåvands Huk and Nymindegab. The parks along the western shores of Varde offer an array of different types of landscapes&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx|title = Municipality of Varde|accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = NaturKulturKanon - Varde|publisher = Varde Kommune|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151001034407/http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx|archive-date = 2015-10-01|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; e.g. [[dune]] landscapes, [[heath]], dune plantations, [[Coastal geography|coastal lakes]], and for the wadden sea, vast areas of [[Mudflat|mud flats]], where the guest can experience the exposed seabed.

Where [[Wadden Sea National Park, Denmark|national park]] meets nature park you can also experience the western tip of Denmark, adorned by the [[Blåvand Lighthouse|lighthouse of Blåvand]], with the purpose of guiding ships past [[Horns Rev]], where the [[Shoal|sandbank]](s) stretch far out into the ocean. If you peer across the ocean from the lighthouse you can often see the wind farms of Horns Rev.

Sizeable areas along the coast of Varde are laid out as training areas for the Danish military, but as long as the red signal has not been hoisted,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://forsvaret.dk/oksbl/skydninger/Pages/default.aspx|title = Information to the public about live firing on Kallesmærsk hede.|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = forsvaret.dk/oksbl/skydninger|publisher = Forsvaret.dk|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; it is accessible to visitors of all types. There are 3 military barracks in the municipality of Varde which can be found in Varde, Oksbøl and Nymindegab. The [[barracks]] of Nymindegab&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx#23520|title = Municipality of Varde|accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = NaturKulturKanon - Varde Kommune|publisher = Varde Kommune|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151001034407/http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx#23520|archive-date = 2015-10-01|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; look differently from other Danish barracks in general, as it was built in 1941 by the [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German Wehrmacht]] as a school for anti-aircraft personnel. The barracks were meant to look like a small village, in order not to be bombed by the allied or British bombers, which it never was.

Just near the barracks of Nymindegab lay the [[Atlantic Wall]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx#23520|title = Municipality of Varde|accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = NaturKulturKanon - Varde Kommune|publisher = Varde Kommune|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151001034407/http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx#23520|archive-date = 2015-10-01|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; stretching from [[Nordkapp|Nordkap]] in Norway to the [[Pyrenees]] by the Spanish border. Because of this [[bunker]]s lay along the coast as a constant reminder of [[World War II|WW2]]. Among these the Tirpitz-position (in German: Batterie Vogelsnest), which was being built (but never finished) in order to protect the port of [[Esbjerg]].

Following the Second World War it was necessary to demine the westcoast of Jutland, as the Wehrmacht had mined the coast to stop allied forces from attacking. The demining of the Danish Westcoast was in 2015 problematized in the Danish movie &quot;[[Land of Mine]]&quot;, in which the conditions for the German soldiers, who demined the Danish westcoast following WW2 were described. More German soldiers died in Denmark demining the beaches following WW2, than during the invasion and the occupation of Denmark from 1940-45.

== Tourist places in and around Varde ==
[[File:Lighthouse in Blåvand(Varde).jpg|thumb|Lighthouse in Blåvand(Varde)]]
[[File:Filsø under gendannelse.jpg|thumb|Filsø recovering]]
*The Museum of Varde town and municipality operates as an umbrella for the museums in the municipality of Varde, among these are e.g. Varde Museum, the Tirpitz-position, Nymindegab museum, the Danish amber museum in Oksbøl and more.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://vardemuseum.dk/|title = Museet for Varde by og omegn|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Museet for Varde by og omegn|publisher = Museet for Varde by og omegn|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.swiflet.com/VardeEogT/guide2015/1/1/|title = VisitWestDenmark|accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Guide 2015|publisher = VisitWestDenmark|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151001142318/http://www.swiflet.com/VardeEogT/guide2015/1/1/|archive-date = 2015-10-01|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Tirpitz Museum (Denmark)|Tirpitz Museum]], a museum built in an old bunker complex and holds exhibitions about the [[Atlantic Wall]], life on the western coast of Denmark and an [[amber]] collection.
*Varde Minitown* in the Arnbjergparken in Varde is a miniature of Varde anno 1866 in the scale 1:10, which is maintained and built by 12 voluntary &quot;mini-masons,&quot; whose work, making the miniature houses, you can observe from May to October at their workshop in Varde.
*[[Blåvandshuk|Blåvands Huk]]/ [[Blåvand Lighthouse|The lighthouse of Blåvand]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx#23520|title = Municipality of Varde|accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = NaturKulturKanon - Varde Kommune|publisher = Varde Kommune|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151001034407/http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx#23520|archive-date = 2015-10-01|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; the western tip of Denmark, overlooking the wind farms of [[Horns Rev]].
*The beaches along the shore(s) of Varde are among the top crowd pullers/attractions in Varde and a big part of why Varde is a tourist destination.{{fact|date=March 2019}} Among these are the broad white beaches of [[Blåvandshuk|Blåvand]], [[Vejers Strand]] and [[Henne Strand]], strand meaning beach in Danish.
*Filsø was once the second largest lake in Denmark, until it, in the middle of the 18th century, was contained and used for agricultural purposes. In 2010 the area was bought up by the nature fund of &quot;Aage W. Jensen Filsø Avlsgods&quot; with the purpose of restoring Filsø to its original state.
*Varde Sommerspil in Varde is held by and performed by the biggest amateur theatre group in Denmark, named &quot;7-kanten&quot; and has for many years been a crowd puller in the summer months.
*Nationalpark Vadehavet ([[Wadden Sea National Park, Denmark|Wadden Sea National park]], [[World Heritage Site|UNESCO world heritage]]). [[Mudflat|Mud flats]] from Varde in the north to the Netherlands in the south.
*Naturpark Vesterhavet (Vesterhavet/North Sea Nature Park) – 22.500 hectares of nature park between [[Blåvandshuk|Blåvands Huk]] and Nymindegab.
*[[Skallingen]] – [[Land of Mine|the demining of the Westcoast]] - Skallingen is a relatively newly formed landmass, which was created by/after a storm surge in 1634, by sediment left behind by the retracting ocean. It is still under transformation and was home to the last minefield in Denmark. Post 2000 the area was demined and opened to the public.
* The [[Oksbøl Refugee Camp]] museum and cemetery, Oksbøl housed up to 37,000 German Refugees in Denmark after World War II.

== Arts and building style ==
[[File:Spejlinger - Reflections.jpg|thumb|left|Reflections - by Otto William Frello]]
[[File:Nymindegab (Laurits Tuxen).jpg|thumb|Nymindegab (Laurits Tuxen)]]
[[Otto Frello|Otto William Frello]] (died 2015), local artist with permanent exhibition at Varde Museum.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://vardemuseum.dk/dk.php/udstillinger/tema/view/ottofrello|title = Museet for Varde by og omegn|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Otto Frello - Udstillinger|publisher = Museet for Varde by og omegn|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Frello is known for his surreal, but at the same time very realistic and detailed paintings.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.ottofrello.dk/malerier.htm|title = Otto Frello.dk|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Otto Frellos Malerier|publisher = Varde Museum|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Laurits Tuxen]] is known as one of the &quot;[[Skagen Painters|Skagensmalerne]] –[[Skagen Painters|painters of Skagen]],&quot; but already in 1879 visited Nymindegab, where he was one of the founding fathers of the painter colony ''Nymindegabmalerne''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://vardemuseum.dk/dk.php/udstillinger/tema/nymindegabmalerne/ukendt_malerkoloni_i_nymindegab|title = Museet for Varde by og omegn|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Nymindegab - en malermesters pensel værdig|publisher = Museet for Varde by og omegn|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the summer months the painters rented rooms at the Nymindegab Inn, where they sketched drawings/drafts for paintings, which were finished when they returned to [[Copenhagen]] for the winter. Some of Tuxens paintings can be seen at Nymindegab Museum.

Vestjyllands Kunstmuseum (''Janus Bygningen'') – The Art Museum of western Jutland (The Janus Building)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx#23520|title = Municipality of Varde|accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = NaturKulturKanon - Varde Kommune|publisher = Varde Kommune|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151001034407/http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx#23520|archive-date = 2015-10-01|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; in Tistrup, between Varde and Ølgod, is home to a collection of 2000 works, primarily contemporary art and varying temporary exhibitions.

=== Varde classicism ===
As Varde has burned several times many of the buildings were built in the late [[18th century]] and in the beginning of the [[19th century]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://www.dr.dk/tv/se/guld-i-koebstaederne/guld-i-koebstaederne-varde-2-10/|title = Danmarks Radio/Holger Grumme|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = DR-tv|publisher = DR-tv|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Among these we find Sillasens Hus (Sillasens house) adjacent to the town square and the Kampmannske Gaard (Kampmannske estate). The Danish classicism dictated that house walls were to be plastered, but this was not done in Varde, as a breakthrough in the mass production of bricks and tiles had been made at the time. Instead details were more prominently highlighted, which resulted in red walls, red tiles and an abundance of details.

== Businesses and Industry ==
The Businesses and Industries in Varde can somewhat be divided into 5 pillars, where 4 categories according to Kontur 2014&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://detgodeliv.regionsyddanmark.dk/publikation/kontur-2014-varde/|title = Region Syddanmark|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Kontur 2014 Varde|publisher = Region Syddanmark|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; is above the national average. These are the production of food products/[[agriculture]], [[furniture]]/[[clothing]], [[tourism]] and [[construction]]/[[housing (residential)|housing]].

=== Larger businesses ===
Among the larger businesses in the municipality of Varde we find [[Nobia]], owner of e.g. the kitchen brands HTH and Invita with about 2000 employees in Denmark. [[BoConcept]], furniture and accessories business. The Danish part of BoConcepts production is located in [[Ølgod]]. Fibervisions, global leader in the area of [[bicomponent fiber]]s, used in everything from tea bags to fibreboards. Titan Europe, producer of turbine towers, subcontractor to [[Titan Wind Energy]].

=== Tourism ===
Varde is one of the largest tourism municipalities&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.visitwestdenmark.com/|title = VisitWestDenmark|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = VisitWestDenmark|publisher = VisitWestDenmark|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; in Denmark, which also means that it encompasses a few/several larger tourism related businesses. Within this category we find Hvidbjerg Strand Feriepark (''Blåvand Badeland''), number 42 on the most visited attraction list of 2013 from VisitDenmark, the cottage rental agencies, Dayz Seawest in Nymindegab and businesses who supplement these and cater to tourists visiting the area.

=== Gastronomy ===
Following the business development project ''Naturen til bords'' a community of interests was formed named ''Sydvestjyske Smagsoplevelser''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.sydvestjyskesmagsoplevelser.dk/da/velkommen/|title = Sydvestjyske Smagsoplevelser|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Sydvestjyske Smagsoplevelser|publisher = Destination Sydvestjylland|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; – Taste experiences of South-western Jutland(roughly translated) in order to carry forward and promote the project after release of the cooking book ''Naturen til bords''. Stakeholders in the community include Varde ådal lam(lamb), Hr. Skov in Blåvand(delicacies and restaurant), Henne Kirkeby Inn(prominent restaurant), NaturKulturVarde(NatureCultureVarde) and many more.

=== Danish army ===
The Danish army has 3-4 [[garrison]]s in the [[Varde Municipality|municipality of Varde]], specifically Varde, Oksbøl and Nymindegab. Following the &quot;Military/Defense- settlement of 2013&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://forsvaret.dk/HST/Nyt%20og%20Presse/forlig2013-17/Pages/TostorecentreogsergentskolensamlesiVestjylland.aspx|title = Forsvaret.dk|accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = To store centre og sergeantskolen samles i Vestjylland|publisher = Forsvaret.dk|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151220182142/http://forsvaret.dk/HST/Nyt%20og%20Presse/forlig2013-17/Pages/TostorecentreogsergentskolensamlesiVestjylland.aspx|archive-date = 2015-12-20|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ''Hærens Sergeantskole'' moved from Sønderborg to the barracks in Varde, which means that ''Hærens Sergeantskole'', ''Hærens Efterretningscenter'' and the ''Hærens Kamp- og Ildstøttecenter'' are at home in the municipality of Varde. In addition to this the ''Hjemmeværnsskolen'' is located in Nymindegab.

== Tourism ==
[[File:Family having fun on the beach at Varde.jpg|thumb|OTB in Varde]]
[[File:Sunset in coastal region of Varde(kommune).jpg|thumb|left|Sunset in coastal region of Varde(kommune)]]
With a long and broad high quality beach stretching from [[Skallingen]] in the south to [[Nymindegab]] in the north and with its characteristic look, the coastal area of Varde in the beginning primarily attracted artists, who found inspiration in the landscape and thereby were among the first, together with the [[bourgeoisie]], to initiate the building of [[cottage]]s for [[recreation]]al purposes along the coast of Varde. In Denmark in the 1920s the common worker was awarded 2 weeks of vacation, which put the building of cottages along the coast in motion and made the [[Tourism|tourism industry]] in Varde what it is today. A target destination could have been the Henne Mølleå Badehotel (seaside hotel), designed by [[Poul Henningsen]] in 1935.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx|title = Municipality of Varde|accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = NaturKulturKanon - Varde kommune|publisher = Municipality of Varde|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151001034407/http://www.vardekommune.dk/Borger/Kultur-og-fritid/Natur/NaturKulturKanon.aspx|archive-date = 2015-10-01|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Varde municipality is the largest coastal tourism municipality&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.vardekommune.dk/Nyheder-og-presse/Nyhedsarkiv/Varde-vil-lokke-flere-turister-til.aspx|title = Municipality of Varde|accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Varde vil lokke flere turister til|publisher = Varde Kommune|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150930233051/http://www.vardekommune.dk/Nyheder-og-presse/Nyhedsarkiv/Varde-vil-lokke-flere-turister-til.aspx|archive-date = 2015-09-30|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; in Denmark and especially attracts tourists to the coastal destinations of [[Blåvandshuk|Blåvand]], [[Vejers Strand]] and [[Henne Strand]]. The tourists who stay in [[Varde Municipality|Varde municipality]] primarily stay in seaside cottages and among these tourists the [[Germany|German]] segment is by far the biggest, although there has also been reported a rise in the number of guests from [[Norway]] and the [[Danes]] themselves.

== Transport and Infrastructure ==

=== Automobile ===
Most traffic from and to Varde goes via primary route 11, which starts in [[Tønder]], and goes via Varde all the way to [[Aalborg]] in northern [[Jutland]]. Primary route 11 crosses the E20 (the Esbjerg highway) near Korskro, from where there is approximately {{convert|10|km|mi}} to Varde via primary route 11.

=== Train ===
It is possible to reach Varde via [[Esbjerg]] or [[Skjern, Denmark|Skjern]]. Apart from that the &quot;Vestbanen&quot; connects Varde with [[Oksbøl]] in the western and [[Nørre Nebel]] in the north-western part of the municipality.

=== Bicycle ===
In recent years the municipality of Varde has widened/expanded its net of [[Bicycle routes in denmark|bicycle roads]] significantly,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.visitwestdenmark.dk/sydjylland/cykelture/cykelruter-i-varde-kommune|title = Cykelruter i Vare Kommune|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Cykelruter i Vare Kommune|publisher = VisitWestDenmark|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; in large degree through the goodwill of citizens and landowners, whereby the municipality has been able to build {{convert|20|km|mi}} of bicycle road between Varde and Nørre Nebel and about {{convert|10|km|mi}} between Varde and [[Næsbjerg]]. This means that you´re now able to reach almost all corners of Varde by bike as there was already about {{convert|25|km|mi}} of bicycle road between Varde and Blåvand via Oksbøl and approximately 20&amp;nbsp;km of bicycle road between Varde and Esbjerg.

=== Hiking ===
If you enjoy hiking, the [[North Sea Trail|North Sea trail]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.northseatrail.org/|title = North Sea Trail|accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = North Sea Trail|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160101042324/http://www.northseatrail.org/|archive-date = 2016-01-01|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; goes through the municipality of Varde, the bicoastal &quot;kyst til kyst stien&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.kyst-kyststien.dk/english/index.htm|title = Doesn´t say|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = The Coast to Coast trail|publisher = |last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; goes from Blåvand in the west to Vejle in the east and along with these a variety of local hiking trails.

== Sports ==
[[File:Mountainbiking in Varde.jpg|thumb|Mountainbiking in Varde]]
Speedway is generally a sport that is more prominent in the municipality of Varde, than in most other Danish municipalities.{{fact|date=March 2019}}

Furthermore, the nature in and around Varde favours outdoor sports like cycling, mountainbiking, beach related sports, fishing, golf, hunting, and [[Parachuting|skydiving]] at Varde Faldskærmsklub.{{fact|date=March 2019}}

== Festivals and annual events ==
[[File:Varde Open Air.jpg|thumb|140px|Varde Open Air]]
[[File:Varde Sommerspil.jpg|thumb|140px|Varde Sommerspil]]
*Varde Open Air – Music festival
*Varde Sommerspil – Musical taking place in July
*Day of the forest, lake, sea and stream/river
*[[Red deer]] festival in Vejers
*The amber festival
*The lamb festival
*The Wadden Sea festival
*The sheep market in Ho
*The elf/goblin triathlon
*Eventcalendar&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://detsker.vardekommune.dk/perl/arrlist/type-varde?Genre=Sport%7CMusik%7CUdstilling%7CB%F8rn%7CForedrag%7CTeater%7CNatur%7CDiverse&amp;Area=Varde-storkommune&amp;periode=|title = Det sker - Varde Kommune|date = |accessdate = 2015-10-19|website = Det sker - Varde Kommune|publisher = Varde Kommune|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notable people ==
[[File:Marie Luplau by Laurberg cropped.jpg|thumb|150px|Marie Luplau, 1910]]
* [[Ludvig Verner Helms]] (1825–1918) a trader and merchant with [[Borneo Company Limited]] in [[Sarawak]]
* [[Marie Luplau]] (1848–1925) a Danish artist and educator, active in the women's movement
* [[Johanne Hesbeck]] (1873–1927) a Danish photographer, ran a portrait studio in [[Holte]] 1915-1927
* [[Peder Oluf Pedersen]] (1874 in Sig – 1941) a Danish engineer and physicist
* [[Johannes Nicolaus Brønsted]] (1879–1947) a Danish [[physical chemist]]
* [[Hans Christian Adamson]] (1890–1968) a Danish-born American writer, who survived adrift for 24 days in the Pacific Ocean in 1942.
* [[Henning Karmark]] (1907–1989) a Danish film producer. 
* [[John Nielsen (racing driver)|John Nielsen]] (born 1956) a Danish former racing driver. He won the [[24 Hours of Le Mans]] in 1990
* [[Uiloq Slettemark]] (born 1965) a Greenlandic biathlete
* [[Jakob Poulsen]] (born 1983) a Danish professional football player, 370 pro appearances
* [[Jesper Jørgensen]] (born 1984) a Danish professional footballer, 340 pro appearances

==Sister cities==
Varde has a single [[town twinning|sister city]], as designated by the Sister Cities International, Inc.:&lt;ref&gt;Sister Cities information obtained from the [http://www.sister-cities.org/interactive-map/San%20Mateo,%20California Sister Cities International, Inc. (SCI)] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160225072056/http://www.sister-cities.org/interactive-map/San%20Mateo,%20California |date=2016-02-25 }}. Retrieved on May 17, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{flagicon|USA}} [[San Mateo, California|San Mateo]], USA (since November 17, 1969)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sister-cities.org/sites/default/files/San%20Mateo%2C%20CA-Varde%2C%20Denmark.pdf San Mateo City Council resolution] to adopt Varde as a sister city. November 17, 1969. Retrieved on May 17, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Varde Museum.jpg|Varde Museum
File:Varde - Det Gamle Rådhus.jpg|The old City Hall
File:Jugendhuset Varde.jpg|Jugendhuset – The Art Nouveau House
File:Varde Kaserne.jpg|Varde Barracks
File:Henne Strand 06.JPG|Henne Strand
File:Henne Strand10.jpg|Henne Strand
File:Henne Strand5.jpg|Cottages at Henne Strand
File:Blåvandshuk4.jpg|Blåvandshuk lighthouse and part of the atlantic wall
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

=== Sources ===
* Varde 1920–1990, Fra købstad til storkommune bind II, Varde kommune 1992 {{ISBN|87-984163-0-8}}
* Varde i 1950érne, Varde Lokalhistoriske Arkiv {{ISBN|87-988172-6-4}}

== External links ==
{{commons-inline|Category:Varde|Varde}}

{{Coord|55|38|N| 08|29|E|region:DK_type:city|display=title}}

These external links are Danish, but may have English translations.
* [http://www.visitwestdenmark.com/ Varde Turistbureau] – Varde Tourist agency.
* [http://www.varde.dk/ Varde byportal] Official homepage of the municipality
* [http://www.vardehistorie.dk/Varde_MapKort.html På værtshus i Varde 1901] title: Visiting a bar in Varde in 1901
* [http://detsker.vardekommune.dk/ Det sker i Varde Kommune] Event calendar for the municipality of Varde
* [http://www.mitarriva.dk/ MitArriva.dk] Train in and around Varde
* [http://forsvaret.dk/oksbl/skydninger/Pages/default.aspx Øvelsesområde og oplysninger om skydninger], Forsvaret. Information about the military training area.

{{Municipal seats of Denmark}}

[[Category:Municipal seats of the Region of Southern Denmark]]
[[Category:Municipal seats of Denmark]]
[[Category:Cities and towns in the Region of Southern Denmark]]
[[Category:Varde Municipality]]</text>
      <sha1>ktcnwtsoyrqnajq8ea5yb8r1ikowtg9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
