  <page>
    <title>Vinkensport</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11489722</id>
    <revision>
      <id>918033314</id>
      <parentid>900149733</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-26T17:53:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Monkbot</username>
        <id>20483999</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* History and practices */[[User:Monkbot/task 16: remove replace deprecated dead-url params|Task 16]]: replaced (1×) / removed (0×) deprecated |dead-url= and |deadurl= with |url-status=;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Good article}}
{{Infobox sport
| image                 = File:Vinkensport, Deinze 03.JPG
| imagesize             = 200px
| caption               = Vinkensport in [[Deinze]]. The long black rod is used for counting.
| nickname              = vinkenzetting, finching
| first                 = 1596, [[Flanders]]
| clubs                 = yes
| contact               = none
| mgender               = yes
| category              = Animal sport
}}

'''''Vinkensport''''' ([[Dutch language|Dutch]] for ''&quot;finch sport&quot;'') is a competitive [[animal sport]] in which male [[common chaffinch]]es are made to compete for the highest number of [[bird calls]] in an hour. Also called '''''vinkenzetting''''' (&quot;finch sitting&quot;), it is primarily active in the Dutch-speaking region of [[Flanders]] in [[Belgium]].

Vinkensport traces its origins to competitions held by [[Flemish people|Flemish]] merchants in 1596, and is considered part of traditional Flemish culture. As of 2007, it was estimated that there are over 13,000 enthusiasts, called ''vinkeniers'' (&quot;finchers&quot;), breeding 10,000 birds every year. [[Animal rights activist]]s have opposed the sport for much of its history.

==Description==
In a contest, a row of small cages, each housing a single male finch, is lined up approximately six feet apart along a street. The proximity of the cages increases the number of calls, as the birds sing for mates and to establish territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Bilefsky |last=Dan |title= One-Ounce Belgian Idols Vie for Most Tweets per Hour |work=[[The New York Times]] |publisher=The New York Times Company |date= May 21, 2007 |accessdate=2007-05-23 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/21/world/europe/21finch.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[timekeeper]] begins and ends the contest with a red flag. Every time a bird sings a correct terminating flourish to their call&amp;mdash;most often transcribed as ''susk-e-wiet''&amp;mdash;a [[tally mark]] in [[chalk]] is made on a long wooden stick. The bird singing its song the most times during one hour wins the contest. Champion finches regularly sing hundreds of calls in contests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;/&gt;

== History and practices ==
The earliest known records of vinkeniers are from 1596 (with some sources advocating a slightly earlier 1593 origin) with Flemish merchants competing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;/&gt; By the late nineteenth century, vinkenzetting's popularity had diminished significantly, but it saw a resurgence after the [[First World War]]. As of 2007, it was estimated that there are over 13,000 ''vinkeniers'' breeding 10,000 birds every year. However, the popularity of this [[Folk culture|folk]] sport is waning in the 21st century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;/&gt; There is also a museum of the sport (''Nationaal Volkssportmuseum Vinkensport'') in the village of [[Hulste]] in the [[Harelbeke]] municipality of Belgium.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Weird Europe: A Guide to Bizarre, Macabre, and Just Plain Weird Sights | publisher=Macmillan | author=Lawson, Kristan | year=1999 | isbn=978-0-312-19873-2 | pages=32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Vinkeniers use a variety of methods to increase the number of calls in their birds. Techniques to develop singing aptitude include [[selective breeding]] programs, [[high-protein diet]]s, and stimulating them with music and recordings of bird song. As wild finches generally begin singing during the spring mating season, keepers may also use artificial lights placed in [[aviaries]] to encourage increased song.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;/&gt;

Some vinkeniers claim that finches from the different regions of Belgium sing in different [[dialect]]s; with birds from the Dutch-speaking Flanders singing &quot;in Dutch&quot; and those from the [[French language|French]]-speaking [[Wallonia]] singing undesirably &quot;in French&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;/&gt; The use of &quot;Dutch&quot; and &quot;Walloon&quot; to describe these two supposed types of finches has been suggested to refer to a simple difference in calling not literally linked to either the Flemish or Walloon communities of Belgium, and some linguists even suggest that &quot;Walloon&quot; simply means &quot;foreign&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last=Liberman| first=Mark| title=Dialect variation in the terminal flourishes of Flemish chaffinches| work=Language Log| accessdate=2007-05-29|url= http://itre.cis.upenn.edu/~myl/languagelog/archives/004526.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; While minute regional differences (a.k.a. dialects) in [[bird song|song]] have been observed in the chaffinch (also within Belgium), the differences have only been reliably distinguishable by the use of [[Spectrogram|sonograms]].&lt;ref&gt;Alström, P. &amp; Ranft, R. 2003. The use of sounds in avian systematics, and the importance of bird sound archives. Bulletin of the British Ornithologists' Club Supplement 123A: 114–135.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/nature/wildfacts/factfiles/250.shtml |title=Chaffinch |accessdate=2008-03-26 |publisher=[[BBC]] |work=Science &amp; Nature:Animals |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080429125218/http://www.bbc.co.uk/nature/wildfacts/factfiles/250.shtml |archive-date=2008-04-29 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Taxonomically, there are no officially recognized subspecies of chaffinch within Belgium.

===Caribbean and South American-based contests===
Speed-singing contests for finches are also a common event in Guyana, Trinidad, Suriname and Brazil. The male finches are placed in cages on poles about one foot apart. The first finch to reach 50 songs wins. The illegal importation of these finches from immigrants of these countries has challenged authorities in New York City.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/08/02/nyregion/tiny-birds-big-drama-inside-the-world-of-the-birdmen-of-queens.html|title=Tiny Birds, Big Drama: Inside the World of the Birdmen of Queens|work=www.nytimes.com|first=Emily S.|last=Rueb|date=July 31, 2015|accessdate=December 12, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thesmokinggun.com/buster/finches/bird-smuggle-thwarted-496015|title=Feds: Air Traveler Caught Trying To Smuggle 70 Birds Into U.S.|work=www.thesmokinggun.com|date=December 12, 2018|accessdate=December 12, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cheating incidents===
As with other sports, vinkensport has had its cheating scandals, as well as accusations of artificial enhancement. One finch sang a record 1,278 susk-e-weits in one hour, and the owner was later accused of [[Doping (sport)|doping]] the bird with [[testosterone]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;/&gt; After one contestant sang exactly the same number of calls in three rounds, the box was opened and a mini [[CD player]] was discovered within.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;/&gt;

=== Opposition to the sport ===
{{rquote|right|&lt;poem&gt;...Blinded ere yet a-wing
By the red-hot needle thou,
I stand and wonder how,
So zestfully thou canst sing!
Resenting not such wrong,
Thy grievous pain forgot,
Eternal dark thy lot,
Groping thy whole life long;
After that stab of fire;
Enjailed in pitiless wire...&lt;/poem&gt;|''The Blinded Bird'' [[Thomas Hardy]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ray&quot;/&gt;}}
Throughout much of its history, certain attributes of the sport have garnered criticism. Early proponents of the sport would [[Blindness|blind]] birds with hot needles in order to reduce visual distractions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;/&gt; [[Thomas Hardy]]&amp;mdash;the celebrated English author and poet who was also an [[Vivisection|antivivisectionist]] and member of the [[RSPCA]]&amp;mdash;is said to have written his poem &quot;[[The Blinded Bird]]&quot; as a protest against the practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;ray&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Thomas Hardy Remembered |last=Ray |first=Martin  |year=2007 |publisher=Ashgate Publishing, Ltd |isbn=0-7546-3973-8 }} pg. 193&lt;/ref&gt; In 1920, a campaign by blind [[World War I]] veterans banned the practice, and today the birds are kept in small wooden boxes that let air in but keep distractions out.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;/&gt;

Modern [[animal rights]] activists, such as those from the Flemish Bird Protection Society, accuse trainers of &quot;[[brainwashing]]&quot; birds into singing more than is natural or healthy by playing looped recordings of finch calls, and that caging birds in the intentionally small and dark contest boxes is cruel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;/&gt; The finch is a popular [[aviary]] bird in many countries and it is forbidden in the [[European Union]] to catch birds in the wild, despite vinkeniers purporting that wild birds sing better than captive ones.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;/&gt; Though chaffinch populations are currently not considered to be threatened, a 2002 court case at the [[Belgian Constitutional Court]] upheld a 1979 [[European Union|EU]] law banning the capture of wild finches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belgian Idols&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;/&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Animals in sport]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://audioblog.sonatura.com/?p=121 Chaffinch dialects in Belgium]
* [http://www.vildaphoto.net/photo/3024 Photo of a contest]

[[Category:Sport in Belgium]]
[[Category:Animals in sport]]
[[Category:Fringilla]]
[[Category:Bird sounds]]
[[Category:Sport in Brazil by sport]]
[[Category:Sport in Suriname by sport]]
[[Category:Sport in Trinidad and Tobago by sport]]
[[Category:Birds]]
[[Category:Sport in Guyana by sport]]</text>
      <sha1>szj9k7jmhajy5m09m241qo4gyk32vh5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
