  <page>
    <title>Wakeboarding</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33623</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936376648</id>
      <parentid>930302136</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-18T12:57:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Praxidicae</username>
        <id>28040267</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>spam</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
{{More citations needed|date=July 2019}}
{{Original research|date=July 2019}}
}}
{{short description|Surface water sport}}
{{distinguish|Water skiing}}
[[File:Wakeboard logan.jpg|thumb|An athlete practicing the sport of wakeboarding.]]
[[Wakeboarding]] is a water sport in which the rider, standing on a wakeboard (a short board with foot bindings), is towed behind a motorboat across its wake and especially up off the crest in order to perform aerial maneuvers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/wakeboard|title=Definition of WAKEBOARD|website=www.merriam-webster.com|language=en|access-date=2019-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; A hallmark of wakeboarding is the attempted performance of midair tricks.

The rider is usually towed by a rope behind a boat, but can also be towed by cable systems and winches, and be pulled by other motorized vehicles like personal watercraft, cars, trucks, and all-terrain vehicles. The gear and [[wakeboard boat]] used are often personalized to each rider's liking.

Wakeboarding is done for pleasure and competition, ranging from freestyle wakeboarding and wakeboard parks to wakeboard competitions at the [[X Games]], WWA Wakeboard World Championships, or similar events.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.fise.fr/fr/wakeboard-pro-top-5-fise-montpellier-2019|title=Wakeboard Pro Top 5 {{!}} FISE Montpellier 2019 {{!}} FISE|website=www.fise.fr|access-date=2019-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
==History==
The sport that would later become wakeboarding began as [[wakesurfing]], which was invented by [[surfer]]s who were looking for an alternative to surfing when the sea was calm. Wakesurfing began picking up traction around 1964, where it was seen as an &quot;exciting new sport that's soon going to sweep the waterways.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Borden|first=Dick|date=April 1964|title=Make the most of your wake... ride it|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=P6A9j6aZAo8C&amp;lpg=PP5&amp;pg=PA100-IA106#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|magazine=Popular Boating|publisher=Ziff-Davis Publishing Company|access-date=October 1, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although surfboards were originally used, boards without straps or bindings were first seen in New Zealand with boards called &quot;skurfboards&quot;.{{cn|date=October 2019}} Eventually, wakeboards with bindings or straps were sold in Australia under the name &quot;McSkis&quot;. Later, another company called &quot;Skurfer&quot; was founded by Tony Finn in 1985,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://unleashedwakemag.com/tony-finn-inventor-wakeboarding/|title=TONY FINN {{!}} Inventor of wakeboarding {{!}}|date=2016-12-11|website=Unleashed Wake Mag|language=en-US|access-date=2019-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; named as such due to the board being a cross of a surfboard and a [[Water skiing|water ski]]. The first board made in the early 1990s was the Hyperlite board by the O’Brien company,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://obrien.com/obrien-wakeboards/|title=O'Brien Wakeboards|website=O'Brien Watersports - Our World Is Water|language=en-US|access-date=2019-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{better source|date=October 2019}} a water ski manufacturer who marketed the board as a “compression-molded neutral-buoyancy wakeboard.”&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.usawaterski.org/pages/divisions/wakeboard/WakeboardHistory.htm|title=Wakeboard|website=www.usawaterski.org|access-date=2019-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was followed by a variety of boards that are curvier and more compact, creating a smoother ride.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

The wakeboard rope has advanced over the years with improvements in the material makeup. When wakeboarding first started, wakeboarders used ski rope, which was made with stretchy cloth or plastic ropes. The latter soon grew in popularity, and a braided rope made out of [[polypropylene]] was eventually introduced. A few years later{{when|date=October 2019}}, a rope that was less stretchy was invented that gave the rider a more consistent pull on the rope, though they were heavier and larger in diameter. Modern ropes are coated with Spectra and Dyneema, which decrease the stretch and drag of the rope.

==Equipment==
[[File:Wakeboarding - Box End Park September 2009 (3916745528).jpg|thumb|Wakeboarding - Box End Park September 2009]]
When wakeboarding, a wide variety of safety equipment is used. These include life vests or other buoyancy aids which prevent water-related injuries and deaths, as they keep the wearer buoyant until they are picked up. These vests especially help in situations where the rider is knocked unconscious or cannot tread water.&lt;ref name=&quot;beginner-gear&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://mpora.com/wakeboarding/wakeboarding-beginners-gear|title=What Essential Wakeboarding Gear Do I Need?|website=Mpora|language=en-US|access-date=2019-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, wakeboarders use water-resistant helmets that are able to ventilate water so that the helmets do not fill up with water.&lt;ref name=&quot;beginner-gear&quot;/&gt; Even the length of a wakeboarder's rope is important in providing safety; if the rope is too long, a wakeboarder will land on the flat part of the wake instead of the downside, and their knees will buckle.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://culture.evo.com/2013/05/wakeboard-boating-tips-towing-speed-rope-length-weighting-your-boat-properly/|title=Wakeboard Boating Tips: Towing Speed, Rope length &amp; Weighting|date=2013-05-15|website=evo Culture, Community, Cause|language=en-US|access-date=2019-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Wakeboarding.jpg|thumb|Guy Robinson - Wakeboarding Method grab]]
[[File:Wakeboarding Jump (Unsplash).jpg|thumb|Wakeboarding Jump (Unsplash)]]

At the same time, the length of a wakeboarding rope will vary based on the rider's preferences. A longer rope may allow for more preparation and momentum before performing tricks,&lt;ref name=&quot;:32&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://humanoidwake.com/wakeboard-rope/|title=Adjusting your wakeboard rope is the best kept secret to crush your trick list.|date=2018-08-15|website=Humanoid Wakeboards|language=en-US|access-date=2019-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; whereas a shorter rope may require less speed and height to travel between wakes.&lt;ref name=&quot;:32&quot; /&gt;
==Tricks==
{{expand section|date=October 2019}}
When wakeboarding, a variety of tricks may be attempted. Most of these stem from the wakeboarder adjusting their posture, edge, and distribution of weight so as to fly into the air upon hitting the wake.&lt;ref name=&quot;:52&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.wakeboarder.com/display.phtml?a=59|title=Learn The Progressive Toeside Edge - Wakeboarder.com Wakeboarding News|website=www.wakeboarder.com|access-date=2019-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Various tricks include the toeside edge,&lt;ref name=&quot;:52&quot; /&gt; the heelside edge,&lt;ref name=&quot;:62&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.wakeboarder.com/display.phtml?a=50|title=Learn the Progressive Heelside Edge - Wakeboarder.com Wakeboarding News|website=www.wakeboarder.com|access-date=2019-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ride switch,&lt;ref name=&quot;:7&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.wakeboarder.com/display.phtml?a=35|title=Learning To Ride Switch - Wakeboarder.com Wakeboarding News|website=www.wakeboarder.com|access-date=2019-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the 180° spin.&lt;ref name=&quot;:8&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.wakeboarder.com/display.phtml?a=33|title=Progressive Steps to Learn 180s - Wakeboarder.com Wakeboarding News|website=www.wakeboarder.com|access-date=2019-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;
==External links==
*[http://www.unholy3-618th-engineers.org/v3/albums/New-Guinea/WWII_NG_waterski_1.sized.jpg Wakeboarding in 1944]

[[Category:Water sports]]</text>
      <sha1>b2d9a2y3a57s6umsgif3cdj7mcoxjf4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
