  <page>
    <title>Waveski</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2061592</id>
    <revision>
      <id>921174428</id>
      <parentid>920377710</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-14T10:33:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>121.222.224.158</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Waveski By Macski South Africa.JPG|thumb|A waveski at Carlsbad, California USA 2007]]

{{Multiple issues|
{{Unreferenced|date=January 2016}}
{{Advert|date=January 2016}}
}}

'''Waveskis''' (also known as &quot;Sit on top surf kayaks, or SOTs) also known as &quot;Paddle Ski&quot; are a type of surf kayak that allows the rider to 'sit on top' instead of having to sit in it. Waveski surfing is a dynamic sport combining the paddle power of a [[sit on top kayak]] with the manoeuvrability and performance of a [[surfboard]]. A Waveski resembles a larger surfboard, with the addition of a seat, fins, foot straps, and seat belt, enabling the rider to '[[eskimo roll]]' if overturned.  The waveski rider or waveski surfer uses a double ended [[kayak paddle]] for motion while seated in the waveski. To turn the rider uses his paddle to bring himself up the wave.

==History==
The origins are obscure, but waveskis have been around for over forty years.  [[Danny Broadhurst]], a [[Long Island]], New York, surfer created some early waveskis in the 1970s, although these were heavy, bulky and not particularly manoeuvrable{{Citation needed|date=January 2016}}. The sport experienced its major growth in the 1980s with manufactures like [[Macski &amp; Kola Ski]] being a dominant force in the market exporting worldwide to countries such as Australia, USA as well as into Europe. Original boards had wooden frames covered in glass fibre then became foam injected and soon custom hand made boards were being shaped and glassed out of polystyrene foam and epoxy resins. Contemporary boards are shaped in precision CNC machines and weigh around {{Convert|6|kg}} when completed. 
throughout the 80's the sport Thrived, but as the 90's approached so did other developments in the Sport of surfing, and so Kola Ski closed its doors &amp; the Waveski Sport faded away losing numbers &amp; intensity,however with the comeback of the sport with New Manufacturers,combining passion and enthusiasm these new manufacturers of the 20th  century have been growing the sport! 
these manufacturers being:
(RD Waveski's / Viking Waveski's / Bless Waveski's / KS Waveski's) it's thanks to these manufacturers that the sport is on the incline.{{Citation needed|date=January 2016}}.

==Description==
Many of the manoeuvres waveskiers have been performing since the 1980s are only now becoming mainstream moves in surfing, where they were mocked in days gone by surfers, maneuvers such as aerials, flip aerials and various other radical moves one can do on a wave. The sport is experiencing a resurgence in countries such as Brazil and France tying in with the river and [[sea kayak]] sports and holding joint competitions as they share a common functionality{{Citation needed|date=January 2016}}. More junior riders and sponsors are needed to see larger coverage of this sport{{according to whom|date=January 2016}}. Competitions are similar to stand up surfing ones and are judged on the performance of the rider on the waves within a 20-minute heat.

==Equipment==
There are several kinds of waveskis, including the shorter and &quot;fatter&quot; Australian style ski, used for high performance &quot;slash and burn&quot; surfing, and American style waveskis perhaps epitomized by Steve Boehne's Infinity Surf Shop skis.  There are also skegless skis for performing tricks, and even tandem skis. The &quot;Jbay&quot; wave ski shape has become the predominant shape of a ski nowadays with riders positioned further back on the ski for better maneuverability. High performance skis weigh {{Convert|6-8|kg}} and are custom made, using [[epoxy]] resin and EPS foam, which makes the waveski light and strong{{Citation needed|date=January 2016}}. The sport provides fun and exercise for beginners through to advanced riders. A waveski is not to be confused with a [[surf ski]].  Waveskis are designed for surfing ocean waves and surf skis are designed for racing in open water, as seen in [[Magnum P.I.]], the Tom Selleck TV series.

== See also ==
* [[Kayak]]
* [[Surf Kayaking]]
* [[Surfing|Surf]]

== External links ==
* [http://uswaveski.com/ United States Waveski Surfing Association]
* [http://www.waveski-reunion.com/ Website for the Reunion island]

[[Category:Human-powered vehicles]]
[[Category:Kayaks]]</text>
      <sha1>advw8gksf7yk4k0v5wc8phn7v2v450z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
