  <page>
    <title>Zorbing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>357158</id>
    <revision>
      <id>935348167</id>
      <parentid>935348121</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-12T02:29:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hog Farm</username>
        <id>37763213</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 935348121 by [[Special:Contributions/72.93.238.164|72.93.238.164]] ([[User talk:72.93.238.164|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
{{More citations needed|date=September 2011}}
{{Cleanup|date=September 2015|reason=informal style and tone}}
}}
{{Infobox sport
| image         = Zorbing.jpg
| imagesize     = 225px
| caption       = Zorbs in [[Rotorua]]
| union         = ZORB Limited
| nickname      =
| first         = 1994, [[Stien Vermeiren]], [[Bay of Plenty]], [[New Zealand]]
| registered    =
| category      = Indoor or Outdoor and extreme
| ball          = Zorb
}}

'''Zorbing''' ('''globe-riding''', '''sphereing''', '''orbing''') is the recreation or sport of rolling downhill inside an orb, generally made of transparent plastic.  Zorbing is generally performed on a gentle slope, but can also be done on a level surface, permitting more rider control.  In the absence of hills some operators have constructed inflatable, wooden, or metal ramps. Due to the buoyant nature of the orbs, Zorbing can also be carried out on water, provided the orb is inflated properly and sealed once the rider is inside. &quot;Water walking&quot; using such orbs has become popular in theme parks across the UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ncHSmCXErI0|title=Noah in Aqua Zorb, Chessington 25June12|first=|last=bersmythuk|date=25 June 2012|publisher=|via=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{failed verification|date=June 2016}} There are two types of orbs, harnessed and non-harnessed. Non-harness orbs carry up to three riders, while the harness orbs are constructed for one to two riders. Double-harness spheres have different slope requirements, and must only be operated in specific locations.  The longer runs are approximately {{convert|1/2|mi|m|order=flip|abbr=on}}. The first zorbing site was established in [[Rotorua]], New Zealand, by ZORB Ltd.

==History==
[[File:Zorbs at the Chew Stoke Harvest Home 2010.jpg|thumb|Zorbing at the [[Chew Stoke]] Harvest Home September 2010]]
[[Hamster ball]]s, hard plastic single layer spheres made for small rodent pets, have been manufactured and sold since at least the 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.gillesebersolt.com/tel/ballulegb.pdf
 |title=A History of the Ballule
 |first=Gilles
 |last=Ebersolt
 |date=April 2008
 |format=PDF
 |accessdate=August 18, 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Russian article on the Zorb mentions a similar device having debuted in 1973.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.newizv.ru/inset/2005-05-01/23482-kogo-ne-berut-v-kosmonavty-tot-stanovitsja-zorbonavtom.html
 |accessdate=August 18, 2009
 |date=March 1, 2005
 |first=Марина
 |last=БАЗЫЛЮК
 |script-title=ru:Новые Известия / Кого не берут в космонавты, тот становится зорбонавтом.
|language=Russian
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the early 1980s, the [[Dangerous Sports Club]] constructed a giant [[sphere]] (reportedly {{convert|23|m|0|disp=or}} across) with a [[gimbal]] arrangement supporting two [[deck chair]]s inside.  This device was eventually cut up for scrap, with some of the plastic remnants used to cover a compost heap.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.extremedreams.co.uk/index.php/Extremedreams/zorb/xsid/59
 |title=What on earth is a zorb?
 |accessdate=August 18, 2009
 |publisher=ExtremeDreams
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Human spheres have been depicted in mass media since 1990, when the [[gladiators (television franchise)|Gladiators]] event &quot;Atlaspheres&quot; first aired, albeit with steel balls. The 1991 film ''[[Armour of God II: Operation Condor]]'' features a scene in which [[Jackie Chan]] appears to roll down a mountainside in a flexible plastic orb very similar to the Zorb, except with only one entrance/exit tunnel, and with more space between the inner and outer orbs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mI7vz9Bd664|title=Operation Condor - Zorb ball scene - YouTube|date=2007-01-19|accessdate=2016-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1994, three investors created the firm ZORB Limited in New Zealand to create suitable spheres and commercialize sphereing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=READ |first1=ELLEN |title=Zorb inventors rolling in it |url=https://www.nzherald.co.nz/business/news/article.cfm?c_id=3&amp;objectid=3518104 |accessdate=11 July 2019 |issue=14 Aug 2003 |publisher=New Zealand Herald |date=14 Aug 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Their business model was to develop the activity via a [[franchising|franchise]] system.

Zorbing entered the Concise [[Oxford English Dictionary]] in 2001 where it was defined as: &quot;a sport in which a participant is secured inside an inner capsule in a large, transparent ball which is then rolled along the ground or down hills&quot;.

==Construction==
The orb is double-sectioned, with one ball inside the other with an air layer in between (unlike the [[water walking ball]], which is usually a single thin-walled ball). This acts as a [[shock absorber]] for the rider, damping bumps while traveling. Orbs are lightweight and made of flexible plastic, as opposed to the rigid plastic, for example, of a [[hamster ball]]. Many orbs have straps to hold the rider in place, while others leave the rider free to walk the orb around or be tossed about freely by the rolling motion. A typical orb is about {{convert|3|m|0}} in diameter, with an inner orb size of about {{convert|2|m|0}}, leaving a 50–60&amp;nbsp;centimetre (20–24&amp;nbsp;in) air cushion around the riders.  The plastic is approximately {{convert|0.8|mm|2}} thick.{{citation needed|date=January 2013}} The inner and outer orbs are connected by numerous (often hundreds of) small nylon strings. Orbs have one or two tunnel-like entrances.

==Facilities==
Zorbing is performed at commercial locations, where prospective riders pay a fee for each ride or for a whole day's activity. 'Hill-Rolling' or 'Globe riding' (the generic name for this activity) is practised in the United Kingdom, [[New Zealand]], the middle of [[Sweden]], [[Estonia]], Canada, the [[Czech Republic]], [[Poland]], the [[Slovak Republic]], [[Switzerland]], Japan, [[Kochi]] in India, Phuket in [[Thailand]], and [[Slovenia]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} In the United States, there are facilities in [[Pigeon Forge, Tennessee]] near the Great Smoky Mountains National Park), [[Wisconsin Dells, Wisconsin]], [[Amesbury, Massachusetts]], and Roundtop Mountain Resort, Lewisberry, Pennsylvania (near [[Hershey, Pennsylvania|Hershey]]).{{Citation needed|date=November 2017}}

==Records==
The [[Guinness World Records|Guinness Book of World Records]] recognises four sphereing records:
*Longest distance travelled in a single roll held by Steve Camp who travelled {{convert|570|m|0}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/greatest-distance-zorbing |title= Greatest Distance Zorbing |publisher=Guinness World Records |accessdate=November 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Fastest sphereing ride held by Rebecca Mazonson who reached a speed of {{convert|52|km/h|0}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/travel/news/2006-11-09-guinness-world-records-day_x.htm |title=World's fastest 'zorbanaut' kicks off Guinness World Records Day |publisher=USA TODAY |accessdate=November 9, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Longest time spent zorbing - 3:49:06. Held by Rebecca Mazonson.
*Fastest {{convert|100|m}} in a Zorb – 23.21 seconds. Held by James Duggan,Dunmanway,Co.Cork,Ireland who broke the record during the Sam Maguire Harvest Festival on the 8th September 2019.

==Injuries and deaths==
Although the cushioning design of the orbs prevent many serious injuries, light injuries such as bruises and grazes can often be sustained by colliding with objects or tripping whilst the orb is rolling down an incline. Even though severe injury is rare, there have been cases of children passing out due to lack of air, and even some deaths. The [[U.S. Consumer Product Safety Commission]] has urged consumers to stop using water walking balls &quot;due to the potential risks of suffocation and drowning&quot;, and reports that several states have banned their use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Consumer Alert: CPSC Warns of Deadly Danger with Water Walking Balls|url=http://www.cpsc.gov/en/Newsroom/News-Releases/2011/Consumer-Alert-CPSC-Warns-of-Deadly-Danger-with-Water-Walking-Balls/|publisher=U.S. Consumer Product Safety Commission|accessdate=1 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2009 a teacher died and a pupil was severely injured in the Czech Republic while trying zorbing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= http://www.news.com.au/top-stories/teacher-killed-in-zorbing-accident/story-e6frfkp9-1225722279320 | work= News.com.au | title= Teacher killed in zorbing accident | date=June 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2013, at a ski resort in [[Dombay, Russia]], a man died from a broken neck and another was badly injured when the Zorb he was in rolled out of control down a mountain, hitting rocks and eventually coming to a stop a kilometre away on a frozen lake.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= https://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2013/01/09/168943032/zorbing-death-brings-call-for-safety-rules-fatal-ride-captured-on-video|work=[[NPR]] | title= 'Zorbing' Death Brings Call For Safety Rules; Fatal Ride Captured On Video| date=January 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= http://www.3news.co.nz/VIDEO-Zorb-death-at-Russian-ski-resort/tabid/313/articleID/282433/Default.aspx |work=3 News NZ | title= Fatal Zorb accident at ski resort| date=January 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= https://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/11/world/europe/zorbing-accident-kills-1-man-and-injures-another-in-russia.html |work=[[New York Times]] | title= Man in Plastic Ball Dies on Russian Ski Slope| date=January 11, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The incident was caught on camera and uploaded to the Internet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.mreporter.ru/reports/125474|title=VIDEO: Zorb death at Russian ski resort|last=|first=|date=January 4, 2013|work=Mobile Reporter (RU)|access-date=|archive-url=|archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the incident made international headlines, Russian authorities called for tougher safety laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= http://www.3news.co.nz/Russia-probes-Zorb-death/tabid/417/articleID/282548/Default.aspx |work=3 News NZ | title= Russia probes Zorb death| date=January 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Water ball]]
*[[Hamster ball]]
*[[Bubble bump football]]
*[[Bubbleball in the United States]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

{{Spoken Wikipedia|En-Zorbing.ogg|2013-05-27}}

[[Category:Hybrid sports]]
[[Category:Games and sports introduced in the 1990s]]</text>
      <sha1>guam0e43oc6iy7k162pxtxu27255chc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
